<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<cookbook type="famous" class1="breadsweets" class2="generalfood" region="general" bookID="1909choc" chefschool="Maria Parloa">
<meta>
<dcTitle>Chocolate and Cocoa Recipes by Miss Parloa and Home Made Candy Recipes by Mrs. Janet McKenzie Hill.</dcTitle>
<dcCreator>Parloa, Maria</dcCreator>
<dcCreator>Hill, Janet McKenzie</dcCreator>
<dcSubject>Chocolate. Cocoa. Confectionery.</dcSubject>
<dcDescription>Sample recipes: Plain Chocolate. Chocolate, Vienna Style. Breakfast Cocoa. Chocolate Layer Cake. Chocolate Cake.</dcDescription>
<dcPublisher>Dorchester, Mass.: Walter Baker &#38; Co., Ltd.</dcPublisher>
<dcContributor>Electronic edition created by Digital &#38; Multimedia Center, Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003.</dcContributor>
<dcContributor>Supplementary material by Jan Longone, Anne-Marie Rachman, Peter Berg, Yvonne Lockwood, and Val Berryman</dcContributor>
<dcDate>1909</dcDate>
<dcType>Text</dcType>
<dcFormat>xml-external-parsed-entity</dcFormat>
<dcFormat>jpeg</dcFormat>
<dcFormat>quicktime</dcFormat>
<dcIdentifier>http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/chocolate/choc.xml</dcIdentifier>
<dcSource>OCLC 4273967</dcSource>
<dcLanguage>en</dcLanguage>
<dcRelation>Digitized as part of "Feeding America: The Historic American Cookbook Project." Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003. http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/</dcRelation>
<dcCoverage>United States</dcCoverage>
<dcCoverage>Twentieth century</dcCoverage>
<dcRights>The book digitized here was published in the United States before 1923 and is in the public domain according to U.S. copyright law. The digital version and supplementary materials are made available for all educational uses.</dcRights></meta>
<front>
<div type="frontcover">
 
<pb n="front cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=1"/>
<illustration><description>A border of illustrated flowering plants.</description></illustration>
<p align="center" rend="ornate" size="larger">Chocolate<lb/>and<lb/>Cocoa<lb/>Recipes<lb/>By Miss Parloa<lb/>and<lb/>Home Made<lb/>Candy<lb/>Recipes<lb/>By Mrs Janet McKenzie Hill</p>
<p align="center" rend="ornate">Compliments of<lb/>Walter Baker &#38; Co., Ltd.</p>
<p rend="bold">ESTABLISHED<lb/>
1780</p>
<p rend="bold">DORCHESTER<lb/>MASS</p>
</div>
<div type="other">
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=2"/>
</div>
<div type="titlepage">
 
<pb n="title page" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=3"/>
<p>Lillie Mackenland</p>
<ednote>Handwritten inscription.</ednote>
<doctitle align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">CHOCOLATE AND<lb/>COCOA RECIPES</doctitle>
<docauthor align="center" rend="bold">BY<lb/>MISS PARLOA</docauthor>
<doctitle align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">and Home Made<lb/>Candy Recipes</doctitle>
<docauthor align="center" rend="bold">BY<lb/>Mrs. Janet McKenzie Hill</docauthor>
<illustration><description>A fruiting plant with a cross section of one of the "fruits."</description></illustration>
<docimprint align="center" rend="bold">Compliments of<lb/>WALTER BAKER &#38; CO., LTD.<lb/>
ESTABLISHED 1780<lb/>DORCHESTER, MASS.</docimprint>
</div>
<div type="copyrightstmt">
<p align="center" size="smaller">Copyright, 1909, by<lb/>WALTER BAKER &#38; CO., Ltd.</p>
</div>
<div type="illustration">
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=4"/>
<illustration><caption>BIRD'S-EYE VIEW OF WALTER BAKER &#38; CO.'S MILLS, DORCHESTER AND MILTON, MASS. FLOOR SPACE, 350,000 SQUARE FEET.</caption><description>A city with factories around the area.</description></illustration>
</div>
<div type="introduction">
 
<pb n="3" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=5"/>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">Cocoa and Chocolate</hd>
<p>THE term "Cocoa," a corruption of "Cacao," is almost universally used in English-speaking countries to designate the seeds of the small tropical tree known to botanists as THEOBROMA CACAO, from which a great variety of preparations under the name of cocoa and chocolate for eating and drinking are made. The name "Chocolatl" is nearly the same in most European languages, and is taken from the Mexican name of the drink, "Chocolate" or "Cacahuatl." The Spaniards found chocolate in common use among the Mexicans at the time of the invasion under Cortez in 1519, and it was introduced into Spain immediately after. The Mexicans not only used chocolate as a staple article of food, but they used the seeds of the cacao tree as a medium of exchange.</p>
<p>No better evidence could be offered of the great advance which has been made in recent years in the knowledge of dietetics than the remarkable increase in the consumption of cocoa and chocolate in this country. The amount retained for home consumption in 1860 was only 1,181,054 pounds--about 3-5 of an ounce for each inhabitant. The amount retained for home consumption for the year ending Dec. 31, 1908, was 93,956,721 pounds--over 16 ounces for each inhabitant.</p>
<p>Although there was a marked increase in the consumption of tea and coffee during the same period, the ratio of increase fell far below that of cocoa. It is evident that the coming American is going to be less of a tea and coffee drinker, and more of a cocoa and chocolate drinker. This is the natural result of a better knowledge of the laws of health, and of the food value of a beverage which nourishes the body while it also stimulates the brain.</p>
<p>Baron von Liebig, one of the best-known writers on dietetics, says:</p>
<p>"It is a perfect food, as wholesome as delicious, a beneficient restorer of exhausted power; but its quality must be good and it must be carefully prepared. It is highly nourishing and easily digested, and is fitted to repair wasted strength, preserve health, and prolong life. It agrees with dry temperaments and convalescents; with mothers who nurse their children; with those whose occupations oblige them to undergo severe mental strains; with public speakers, and with all those who give to work a portion of the time needed for sleep. It soothes both stomach and brain, and for this reason, as well as for others, it is the best friend of those engaged in literary pursuits."</p>
<p>M. Brillat-Savarin, in his entertaining and valuable work, <emph rend="italic">Physiologie du Go&#219;t,</emph> says: "Chocolate came over the mountains 
 
<pb n="4" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=6"/>
[from Spain to France] with Anne of Austria, daughter of Philip III and queen of Louis XIII. The Spanish monks also spread the knowledge of it by the presents they made to their brothers in France. It is well known that Linn&#230;;us called the fruit of the cocoa tree <emph rend="italic">theobroma,</emph> 'food for the gods.' The cause of this emphatic qualification has been sought, and attributed by some to the fact that he was extravagantly fond of chocolate; by others to his desire to please his confessor; and by others to his gallantry, a queen having first introduced it into France.</p>
<p>"The Spanish ladies of the New World, it is said, carried their love for chocolate to such a degree that, not content with partaking of it several times a day, they had it sometimes carried after them to church. This favoring of the senses often drew upon them the censures of the bishop; but the Reverend Father Escobar, whose metaphysics were as subtle as his morality was accommodating, declared, formally, that a fast was not broken by chocolate prepared with water; thus wire-drawing, in favor of his penitents, the ancient adage, <emph rend="italic">'Liquidum non frangit jejunium.'</emph></p>
<p>"Time and experience," he says further, "have shown that chocolate, carefully prepared, is an article of food as wholesome as it is agreeable; that it is nourishing, easy of digestion, and does not possess those qualities injurious to beauty with which coffee has been reproached; that it is excellently adapted to persons who are obliged to a great concentration of intellect; in the toils of the pulpit or the bar, and especially to travellers; that it suits the most feeble stomach; that excellent effects have been produced by it in chronic complaints, and that it is a last resource in affections of the pylorus.</p>
<p>"Some persons complain of being unable to digest chocolate; others, on the contrary, pretend that it has not sufficient nourishment, and that the effect disappears too soon. It is probable that the former have only themselves to blame, and that the chocolate which they use is of bad quality or badly made; for good and well-made chocolate must suit every stomach which retains the slightest digestive power.</p>
<p>"In regard to the others, the remedy is an easy one: they should reinforce their breakfast with a <emph rend="italic">p&#226;t&#233;,</emph> a cutlet, or a kidney, moisten the whole with a good draught of soconusco chocolate, and thank God for a stomach of such superior activity.</p>
<p>"This gives me an opportunity to make an observation whose accuracy may be depended upon.</p>
<p>"After a good, complete, and copious breakfast, if we take, in addition, a cup of well-made chocolate, digestion will be perfectly accomplished in three hours, and we may dine whenever we like. Out of zeal for science, and by dint of eloquence,
 
<pb n="5" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=7"/>
I have induced many ladies to try this experiment. They all declared, in the beginning, that it would kill them; but they have all thriven on it and have not failed to glorify their teacher.</p>
<p>"The people who make constant use of chocolate are the ones who enjoy the most steady health, and are the least subject to a multitude of little ailments which destroy the comfort of life; their plumpness is also more equal. These are two advantages which every one may verify among his own friends, and wherever the practice is in use."</p>
<p>In corroboration of M. Brillat-Savarin's statement as to the value of chocolate as an aid to digestion, we may quote from one of Mme. de S&#233;vign&#233;'s letters to her daughter:</p>
<p>"I took chocolate night before last to digest my dinner, in order to have a good supper. I took some yesterday for nourishment, so as to be able to fast until night. What I consider amusing about chocolate is that it acts according to the wishes of the one who takes it."</p>
<p>Chocolate appears to have been highly valued as a remedial agent by the leading physicians of that day. Christopher Ludwig Hoffman wrote a treatise entitled, "Potus Chocolate," in which he recommended it in many diseases, and instanced the case of Cardinal Richelieu, who, he stated, was cured of general atrophy by its use.</p>
<p>A French officer who served in the West Indies for a period of fifteen years, during the early part of the last century, wrote, as the result of his personal observations, a treatise on "The Natural History of Chocolate, Being a distinct and Particular Account of the Cacao Tree, its Growth and Culture, and the Preparation, Excellent Properties, and Medicinal Virtues of its Fruit," which received the approbation of the Regent of the Faculty of Medicine at Paris, and which was translated and published in London, in 1730. After describing the different methods of raising and curing the fruit and preparing it for food (which it is not worth while to reproduce here, as the methods have essentially changed since that time), he goes on to demonstrate, as the result of actual experiment, that chocolate is a substance "very temperate, very nourishing, and of easy digestion; very proper to repair the exhausted spirits and decayed strength; and very suitable to preserve the health and prolong the lives of old men....</p>
<p>"I could produce several instances," he says, "in favor of this excellent nourishment; but I shall content myself with two only, equally certain and decisive, in proof of its goodness. The first is an experiment of chocolate's being taken for the only nourishment--made by a surgeon's wife of Martinico. She had lost, by a very deplorable accident, her lower jaw, which reduced her to such a condition that she did not know 
 
<pb n="6" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=8"/>
how to subsist. She was not capable of taking anything solid, and not rich enough to live upon jellies and nourishing broths. In this strait she determined to take three dishes of chocolate, prepared after the manner of the country, one in the morning, one at noon, and one at night. There chocolate is nothing else but cocoa kernels dissolved in hot water, with sugar, and seasoned with a bit of cinnamon. This new way of life succeeded so well that she has lived a long while since, more lively and robust than before this accident.</p>
<p>"I had the second relation from a gentleman of Martinico, and one of my friends not capable of a falsity. He assured me that in his neighborhood an infant of four months old unfortunately lost his nurse, and its parents not being able to put it to another, resolved, through necessity, to feed it with chocolate. The success was very happy, for the infant came on to a miracle, and was neither less healthy nor less vigorous than those who are brought up by the best nurses.</p>
<p>"Before chocolate was known in Europe, good old wine was called the milk of old men; but this title is now applied with greater reason to chocolate, since its use has become so common that it has been perceived that chocolate is, with respect to them, what milk is to infants. In reality, if one examines the nature of chocolate a little, with respect to the constitution of aged persons, it seems as though the one was made on purpose to remedy the defects of the other, and that it is truly the panacea of old age."</p>
<p>The three associated beverages, cocoa, tea, and coffee are known to the French as <emph rend="italic">aromatic</emph> drinks. Each of these has its characteristic aroma. The fragrance and flavor are so marked that they cannot be imitated by any artificial products, although numerous attempts have been made in regard to all three. Hence the detection of adulteration is not a difficult matter. Designing persons, aware of the extreme difficulty of imitating these substances, have undertaken to employ lower grades, and, by manipulation, copy, as far as may be, the higher sorts. Every one knows how readily tea, and coffee, for that matter, will take up odors and flavors from substances placed near them. This is abundantly exemplified in the country grocery or general store, where the teas and coffees share in the pervasive fragrance of the cheese and kerosine. But perhaps it is not so widely understood that some of these very teas and coffees had been artificially flavored or corrected before they reached their destination in this country.</p>
<p>Cacao lends itself very readily to such preliminary treatment. In a first-class article, the beans should be of the highest excellence; they should be carefully grown on the plantation and there prepared with great skill, arriving in the factory in good condition. In the factory they should simply receive the
 
<pb n="7" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=9"/>
mechanical treatment requisite to develop their high and attractive natural flavor and fragrance. They should be most carefully shelled after roasting and finely ground without concealed additions. This is the process in all honest manufactories of the cacao products.</p>
<p>Now, as a matter of fact, in the preparation of many of the cacao products on the market, a wholly different course has been pursued. Beans of poor quality are used, because of their cheapness, and in some instances they are only imperfectly, if at all, shelled before grinding. Chemical treatment is relied on to correct in part the odor and taste of such inferior goods, and artificial flavors, other than the time-honored natural vanilla and the like, are added freely. The detection of such imposition is easy enough to the expert, but is difficult to the novice; therefore the public is largely unable to discriminate between the good and the inferior, and it is perforce compelled to depend almost entirely on the character and reputation of the manufacturer.</p>
<p>A distinguished London Physician, in giving some hints concerning the proper preparation of cocoa, says:</p>
<p>"Start with a pure cocoa of undoubted quality and excellence of manufacturer, and which bears the name of a respectable firm. This point is important, for there are many cocoas on the market which have been doctored by the addition of alkali, starch, malt, kola, hops, etc."</p>
<p>Baker's Breakfast Cocoa is absolutely pure, and, being ground to an extraordinary degree of fineness, is highly soluble. The analyst of the Massachusetts State Board of Health states in his recent valuable work on "Food Inspection and Analysis," that the treatment of cocoa with alkali for the purpose of producing a more perfect emulsion is objectionable, even if not considered as a form of adulteration. Cocoa thus treated is generally darker in color than the pure article. The legitimate means, he says, for making it as soluble as possible is to pulverize it very fine, so that particles remain in even suspension and form a smooth paste.</p>
<p>That is the way the Baker Cocoa is treated. It has received the Grand Prize--the highest award ever given in this country, and altogether 52 highest awards in Europe and America.</p>
</div>
</front>
<body>
<chapter class1="breadsweets" class2="generalfood">
 
<pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=10"/>
<illustration><description>A decorative banner with the words "choice recipes" written on it. Two branches form a border around the banner and the rest of the chapter's title.</description></illustration>
<hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">Choice Recipes<lb/>by<lb/>Miss Maria Parloa<lb/>SPECIALLY PREPARED FOR<lb/>WALTER BAKER &#38; CO LTD.</hd>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE</purpose>
For six people, use one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> one tablespoonful of <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient></p>
<p>Mix the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> with one gill of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put the remainder of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on to heat in the 
<implement>double-boiler.</implement> When the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> comes to the boiling point, stir in the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> and cook for ten minutes. Have the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> cut in fine bits, and put it in a <implement>small iron</implement> or <implement>granite-ware pan;</implement> add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and place the pan over a hot fire. Stir constantly until the mixture is smooth and glossy. Add this to the hot <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and beat the mixture with a <implement>whisk</implement> until it is frothy. Or, the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> may be poured back and forth from the <implement>boiler</implement> to a pitcher, holding high the vessel from which you pour. This will give a thick froth. Serve at once.</p>
<p><variation>If you prefer not to have the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> thick, omit the cornstarch.</variation> <variation>If <ingredient>condensed milk</ingredient> is used, substitute <ingredient>water</ingredient> for the milk named above and add three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>condensed milk</ingredient> when the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is added.</variation></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE, VIENNA STYLE</purpose>
Use four ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Vanilla Chocolate,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
<p>Cut the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in fine bits. Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on the stove in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and when it has been heated to the boiling point, put the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> in a <implement>small iron</implement> or <implement>granite-ware pan,</implement> and stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy. Stir this mixture into the hot <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and beat well with a <implement>whisk.</implement> Serve at once, putting a tablespoonful of <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> in each cup and then filling up with the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient></p>
<p><variation>The <ingredient>plain chocolate</ingredient> may be used instead of the <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> but in that case use a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract</ingredient> and three generous tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> instead of one.</variation></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="9" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=11"/>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BREAKFAST COCOA</purpose>
<ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co,'s Breakfast Cocoa</ingredient> is powdered so fine that it can be dissolved by pouring <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> on it. For this reason it is often prepared at the table. A small teaspoonful of the powder is put in the cup with a teaspoonful of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> on this is poured two-thirds of a cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is added to suit the individual taste. This is very convenient; but cocoa is not nearly so good when prepared in this manner as when it is boiled.</p>
<p>For six cupfuls of <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> use two tablespoonfuls of the powder, two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and a pint and a half of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on the stove in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Put the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a saucepan, and gradually pour the <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> upon them, stirring all the time. Place the saucepan on the fire and stir until the contents boil. Let this mixture boil for five minutes; then add the boiling <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and serve.</p>
<p>A gill of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is a great addition to this <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient></p>
<p><variation><ingredient>Scalded milk</ingredient> may be used in place of boiled milk, if preferred.</variation> For flavoring, a few grains of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract</ingredient> may be added.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE LAYER CAKE</purpose>
Beat half a cupful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and gradually beat into it one cupful of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> When this is light, beat in half a cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a little at a time, and one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>whites of six eggs</ingredient> to a stiff froth. Mix half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> with two scant cupfuls of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites of eggs</ingredient> alternately into the mixture. Have three deep tin plates well buttered, and spread two-thirds of the batter in two of them.</p>
<p>Into the remaining batter stir one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co,'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> melted, and spread this batter in the third plate. Bake the cakes in a moderate oven for about twenty minutes. Put a layer of white cake on a large plate, and spread with <ingredient>white icing</ingredient>. Put the dark cake on this, and also spread with <ingredient>white icing</ingredient>. On this put the third cake. Spread with <ingredient>chocolate icing.</ingredient></p>
<p>TO MAKE THE ICING. Put into a <implement>granite-ware saucepan</implement> two gills of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and boil gently until bubbles begin to come from the bottom--say, about five minutes. Take from the fire instantly. Do not stir or shake the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> while it is cooking. Pour the hot <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> in a thin stream into the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> that have been beaten to a stiff froth, beating the mixture all the time. Continue to beat until the icing is thick. Flavor with one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Use two-thirds of this as a <ingredient>white icing</ingredient>, and to the remaining third add one ounce of melted <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> To melt the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> shave it fine and put in a cup, which is then to be placed in a pan of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="10" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=12"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CAKE</purpose>
For two sheets of cake, use three ounces of  <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1Chocolate,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one cupful and three-fourths of sifted <ingredient>pastry flour,</ingredient> one cupful and three-fourths of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> one teaspoonful and a half of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient></p>
<p>Grate the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and gradually beat in the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Beat in the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> then the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (already well beaten), next the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and finally the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in which the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> should be mixed. Pour into two well buttered shallow cake pans. Bake for twenty-five minutes in a moderate oven. Frost or not, as you like.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">CHOCOLATE MARBLE CAKE</purpose>
Put one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a cup, and set this in a pan of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Beat to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and one cupful of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Gradually beat in half a cupful of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Now add the <ingredient>whites of six eggs</ingredient> beaten to a stiff froth, one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and a cupful and a half of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in which is mixed one teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Put about one-third of this mixture into another bowl, and stir the melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> into it. Drop the <ingredient>white-and-brown mixture</ingredient> in spoonfuls into a well buttered deep cake pan, and bake in a moderate oven for about forty-five minutes; or, the cake can be baked in a sheet and iced with a <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> or <ingredient>white icing.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE GLAC&#201; CAKE</purpose>
Beat to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> a generous half cupful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and gradually beat into this one cupful of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co's Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> melted; also two unbeaten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Beat vigorously for five minutes; then stir in half a cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and lastly, one cupful and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with which has been mixed one generous teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Flavor with one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Pour into a buttered, shallow cake pan, and bake for half an hour in a moderate oven. When cool, spread with glac&#233; frosting.</p>
<p>GLAC&#201; FROSTING. Put half a cupful of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> in a small saucepan. Stir over the fire until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is nearly melted. Take the spoon from the pan before the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> really begins to boil, because it would spoil the icing if the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> were stirred after it begins to boil. After boiling gently for four minutes, add half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> but do not stir; then set away to
 
<pb n="11" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=13"/>
cool. When the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is about blood warm, beat it with a wooden spoon until thick and <ingredient>white.</ingredient> Now put the saucepan in another with <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir until the icing is thin enough to pour. Spread quickly on the cake.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE GLAC&#201;</purpose>
After making a glac&#233; frosting, dissolve one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate</ingredient> in a cup, and put it with the frosting, adding also a tablespoonful of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE BISCUIT</purpose>
Cover three large <implement>baking pans</implement> with paper that has been well oiled with washed <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Over these dredge <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient> Melt in a cup one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate.</ingredient> Separate the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks of four eggs.</ingredient> Add to the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> a generous half cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and beat until light and firm. Add the melted <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and beat a few minutes longer. Beat the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> to a stiff, dry froth. Measure out three-fourths of a cupful of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and stir it and the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> into the <ingredient>yolks.</ingredient> The <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> must be cut in as lightly as possible, and with very little stirring. Drop the mixture in teaspoonfuls on the buttered paper. Sprinkle <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> over the cakes, and bake in a slow oven for about fourteen or fifteen minutes. The mixture can be shaped like lady fingers, if preferred.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE WAFERS</purpose>
Grate four ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No.1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and mix with it two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and one-fourth of a teaspoonful each of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> and <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Separate six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Add one cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> to the <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> and beat until very light; then add the grated <ingredient>yellow rind</ingredient> and the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of half a <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and beat five minutes longer. Now add the dry mixture, and with a spoon lightly cut in the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> which are first to be beaten to a stiff froth. Pour the mixture into buttered shallow pans, having it about half an inch thick. Bake in a moderate oven for half an hour. When the cake is cool, spread a thin layer of <ingredient>currant jelly</ingredient> over one sheet, and place the other sheet on this. Ice with <ingredient>vanilla icing</ingredient>; and when this hardens, cut in squares. It is particularly nice to serve with <ingredient>ice-cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CINDERELLA CAKES</purpose>
Use two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one cupful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one cupful and a quarter of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> one tablespoonful of <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> half a <implement>tumbler</implement> of any kind of <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate icing</ingredient> the same as for &#233;clairs.</p>
 
<pb n="12" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=14"/>
<p>Separate the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and beat the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together until light. Beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> until light, and then beat them with <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>grated chocolate.</ingredient> Next beat in the <ingredient>lemon juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and finally the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in which the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> should be mixed. Beat for three minutes, and then pour the batter into two pans, and bake in a moderate oven for about eighteen minutes. When done, spread one sheet of cake with the <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> and press the other sheet over it; and when cold, cut into little squares and triangular pieces. Stick a wooden toothpick into each of these pieces and dip each one into the <ingredient>hot icing</ingredient>, afterwards removing the toothpick, of course.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE &#201;CLAIRS</purpose>
Into a <implement>granite-ware saucepan</implement> put half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two well-rounded tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and place on the stove. When this boils up, add half a pint of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and cook for two minutes, beating well with a wooden spoon. It will be smooth and velvety at the end of that time. Set away to cool; and when cool, beat in four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one at a time. Beat vigorously for about fifteen minutes. Try a small bit of the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> in the oven; and if it rises in the form of a hollow ball, the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is beaten enough; whereas, if it does not, beat a little longer. Have tin sheets or shallow pans slightly buttered. Have ready, also, a tapering tin tube, with the smaller opening about three-quarters of an inch in diameter. Place this in the small end of a conical cotton pastry bag. Put the mixture in the bag, and press out on buttered pans, having each &#233;clair nearly three inches long. There should be eighteen, and they must be at least two inches apart, as they swell in cooking. Bake in a moderately hot oven for about twenty-five minutes. Take from the oven, and while they are still warm coat them with <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> When cold, cut open on the side, and fill with either of the following described preparations:--</p>
<p>FILLING NO. 1--Mix in a bowl half a pint of <ingredient>rich cream,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Place the bowl in a pan of <ingredient>ice-water,</ingredient> and beat the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> until light and firm, using either an <ingredient>egg</ingredient>-beater or a <implement>whisk.</implement></p>
<p>FILLING NO. 2--Put half a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> into a <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and place on the fire. Beat together until very light one level tablespoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and one <ingredient>egg.</ingredient> When the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> boils, stir in this mixture. Add one eighth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and cook for fifteen minutes, stirring often. When cold, flavor with one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>
<p><variation><purpose>ICING FOR &#201;CLAIRS.</purpose>
--Put in a small <implement>granite-ware pan</implement> half a pint of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and five tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Stir until
 
<pb n="13" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=15"/>
the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is partially melted, and then place on the stove, stirring for half a minute. Take out the spoon, and watch the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> closely. As soon as it boils, take instantly from the fire and pour upon a meat-platter. Let this stand for eight minutes. Meantime, shave into a cup one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it on the fire in a pan of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> At the end of eight minutes stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with a wooden spoon until it begins to grow white and to thicken. Add the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> quickly, and continue stirring until the mixture is thick. Put it in a small saucepan, and place on the fire in another pan of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir until so soft that it will pour freely. Stick a <implement>skewer</implement> into the side of an &#233;clair, and dip the top in the <ingredient>hot chocolate.</ingredient> Place on a plate, and continue until all the &#233;clairs are "glac&#233;d." They will dry quickly. Do not stir the sugar after the first half minute, and do not scrape the sugar from the saucepan into the platter. All the directions must be strictly followed.</variation></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE COOKIES</purpose>
Beat to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> Gradually beat into this one cupful of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> then add one-fourth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s No. 1 Premium Chocolate,</ingredient> melted. Now add one well-beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> dissolved in two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Stir in about two cupfuls and a half of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Roll thin, and, cutting in round cakes, bake in a rather quick oven oven. The secret of making good cookies is the use of as little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will suffice.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE GINGERBREAD</purpose>
Mix in a large bowl one cupful of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>sour milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Dissolve one teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> in a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> add this and two tablespoonfuls of melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to the mixture. Now stir in two cupfuls of <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> and finally add two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> melted together. Pour the mixture into three well buttered deep tin plates, and bake in a moderately hot oven for about twenty minutes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">VANILLA ICING</purpose>
Break the <ingredient>white</ingredient> of one large <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into a bowl, and gradually beat into it one cupful of <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient> Beat for three minutes, add half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> and spread thinly on the cakes.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="14" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=16"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ICING</purpose>
Make a <ingredient>vanilla icing</ingredient>, and add one tablespoonful of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to it. Scrape fine one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a <implement>small iron</implement> or <implement>granite-ware saucepan,</implement> with two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy, then add another tablespoonful of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir the dissolved <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> into the <ingredient>vanilla icing</ingredient>.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PROFITEROLES</purpose>
Shave into a cup one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put the cup into a pan of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Make a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> the same as for &#233;clairs, save that instead of one tablespoonful of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> three must be used.</p>
<p>As soon as the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is cooked, beat in the <ingredient>melted chocolate.</ingredient> When cold, add the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and beat until light. Drop this batter on lightly buttered pans in round cakes, having about a dessertspoonful in each cake. Bake for about twenty minutes in a moderately hot oven. Serve either hot or cold, with <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> prepared the same as for Filling No. 1 for &#233;clairs. Heap the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> in the center of a flat dish, and arrange the profiteroles around it.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ICE-CREAM</purpose>
For about two quarts and a half of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> use a pint and a half of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a quart of thin <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two cupfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No.1 Chocolate,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and two heaping tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on to boil in a <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Put the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and one cupful of the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a bowl; add the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and beat the mixture until light. Stir this into the boiling <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and cook for twenty minutes, stirring often.</p>
<p>Scrape the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small saucepan. Add four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> (which should be taken from the second cupful) and two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy. Add this to the cooking mixture.</p>
<p>When the preparation has cooked for twenty minutes, take it from the fire and add the remainder of the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> which should be gradually beaten into the hot mixture. Set away to cool, and when cold, freeze.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAM PIES</purpose>
Beat to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and a cupful and a quarter of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient> Add two well-beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> half a cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and a cupful and a half of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with which has been mixed a teaspoonful and a half of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Bake this in four well-buttered, deep, tin plates for about fifteen minutes in a moderate oven.</p>
 
<pb n="15" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=17"/>
<p>Put half a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and on the fire. Beat together the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and a level tablespoonful of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir this mixture into the <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> beating well. Add one-sixth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and cook for fifteen minutes, stirring often. When cooked, flavor with half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient> Put two of the cakes on two large plates, spread the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> over them, and lay the other two cakes on top. Beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> of the two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a stiff froth, and then beat into them one cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Shave one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No.1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small pan with two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy. Now add three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir into the beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Spread on the pies and set away for a few hours.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE MOUSSE</purpose>
Put a three-quart mould in a wooden pail, first lining the bottom with <ingredient>fine ice</ingredient> and a thin layer of <ingredient>coarse salt.</ingredient> Pack the space between the mould and the pail solidly with <ingredient>fine ice</ingredient> and <ingredient>coarse salt,</ingredient> using two quarts of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>ice</ingredient> enough to fill the space. Whip one quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and drain it in a sieve. Whip again all the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> that drains through. Put in a small pan one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy. Add three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Sprinkle a cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> over the <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient> Pour the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in a thin stream into the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and stir gently until well mixed. Wipe out the chilled mould, and turn the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> into it. Cover, and then place a little ice lightly on top. Wet a piece of carpet in the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and cover the top of the pail. Set away for three or four hours; then take the mould from the ice, dip it in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> wipe, and then turn the mousse out on a flat dish.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CHARLOTTE</purpose>
Soak a quarter of a package of <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> in one-third of a cupful of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> for two hours. Whip one pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> to a froth, and put it in a bowl, which should be placed in a pan of <ingredient>ice-water.</ingredient> Put half an ounce of <ingredient>shaved chocolate</ingredient> in a small pan with two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir over the hot fire until smooth and glossy. Add to this a gill of <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> and the <ingredient>soaked gelatine,</ingredient> and stir until the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> is dissolved. Sprinkle a generous half cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> over the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Now add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> mixture, and stir gently until it begins to thicken. Line a quart charlotte-mould with lady fingers, and when the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is so thick that it will just pour, turn it gently into the
 
<pb n="16" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=18"/>
mould. Place the charlotte in a cold place for an hour or more, and, at serving time, turn out on a flat dish.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE BAVARIAN CREAM</purpose>
For one large mould of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> use half a package of <ingredient>gelatine,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two quarts of <ingredient>whipped cream,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and two and a half ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
<p>Soak the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> for two hours. Whip and drain the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> scrape the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on to boil. Put the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> in a small saucepan, and stir on a hot fire until smooth and glossy. Stir this into the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Now add the <ingredient>soaked gelatine</ingredient> and the remainder of the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Strain this mixture into a basin that will hold two quarts or more. Place the basin in a pan of <ingredient>ice-water,</ingredient> and stir until cold, when it will begin to thicken. Instantly begin to stir in the <ingredient>whipped cream,</ingredient> adding half the amount at first. When all the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> has been added, dip the mould in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and turn the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> into it. Place in the <implement>ice-chest</implement> for an hour or more.</p>
<p>At serving-time dip the mould in <ingredient>tepid water.</ingredient> See that the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> will come from the sides of the mould, and turn out on a flat dish. Serve with <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAM</purpose>
Soak a box of <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> in half a pint of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> for two hours. Put one quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and place on the fire. Shave two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small pan with four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy, and then stir into the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>yolks of five eggs</ingredient> with half a cupful of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add to the <ingredient>gelatine,</ingredient> and stir the mixture into the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Cook three minutes longer, stirring all the while. On taking from the fire, add two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and half a saltspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Strain, and pour into moulds that have been rinsed in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Set away to harden, and serve with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE BLANC-MANGE</purpose>
Put one quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and place on the fire. Sprinkle into it one level tablespoonful of <ingredient>sea-moss farina.</ingredient> Cover, and cook until the mixture looks <ingredient>white,</ingredient> stirring frequently. It will take about twenty minutes. While the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>farina</ingredient> are cooking, shave two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it into a small pan with four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy, then stir into the cooked mixture. Add a saltspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=19"/>
<illustration><caption>MARBLED FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 42.)</caption><description>Cubes of fudge in a decorative bowl.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>TURKISH PASTE WTH FRENCH FRUIT.<lb/>(See Page 40.)</caption><description>A plate of cubes of turkish paste.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE NOUGATINES.<lb/>(See Page 44.)</caption><description>A raised bowl filled with nougatines.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE DIPPED FRUIT FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 43.)</caption><description>A decorative bowl filled with fudge.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>STUFFED DATES CHOCOLATE DIPPED.<lb/>(See Page 39.)</caption><description>A plate of chocolate dipped.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=20"/>
<illustration><caption>WELLESLEY MARSHMALLOW FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 41.)</caption><description>Cubes fudge line parallelly on a decorative plate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE POP CORN BALLS.<lb/>(See Page 53.)</caption><description>A plate of pop corn balls.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>SURPRISE CHOCOLATE CREAMS.<lb/>(See Page 52.)</caption><description>A decorative plate filled with balls of chocolate creams.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE BUTTER CREAMS.<lb/>(See Page 51.)</caption><description>Pieces of chocolate butter creams serve in a decorative plate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>RIBBON CARAMELS.<lb/>(See Page 45.)</caption><description>A beautiful box filled with caramel cubes .</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="17" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=21"/>
a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Strain, and turn into a mould that has been rinsed in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Set the mould in a cold place, and do not disturb it until the blanc-mange is cold and firm. Serve with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAM RENVERSEE</purpose>
Use one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on the fire in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Shave the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small pan with three tablespoonfuls of the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy; then stir into the <ingredient>hot milk,</ingredient> and take the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> from the fire to cool.</p>
<p>Put three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into a charlotte-mould that will hold a little more than a quart, and place on the stove. When the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> melts and begins to smoke, move the mould round and round, to coat it with the <ingredient>burnt sugar,</ingredient> then place on the table. Beat together the remainder of the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>cold milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> to the mixture, and after straining into the charlotte-mould, place in a deep pan, with enough <ingredient>tepid water</ingredient> to come nearly to the top of the mould. Bake in a moderate oven until firm in the center. Test the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> by running a knife through the center. If firm and smooth, it is done. It will take forty or forty-five minutes to cook. When icy-cold, turn on a flat dish. Serve with <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> that has been flavored with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BAKED CHOCOLATE CUSTARD</purpose>
For five small custards use one pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> one-fourth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a piece of stick <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> about an inch long.</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> place on the fire and cook for ten minutes. Shave the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small pan with three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir this over a hot fire until smooth and glossy, and then stir it into the <ingredient>hot milk,</ingredient> after which take the liquid mixture from the fire and cool.</p>
<p>Beat together with a spoon the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and two tablespoonfuls of the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>cooled milk</ingredient> and strain. Pour the mixture into the cups, which place in a deep pan. Pour into the pan enough <ingredient>tepid water</ingredient> to come nearly to the top of the cups. Bake in a moderate oven until firm in the center. It will take about half an hour. Test by running a knife through the center. If the custard is milky, it is not done. Serve very cold.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=22"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE SOUFFL&#201;</purpose>
Half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one rounding tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and place on the fire. Beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>soft cream,</ingredient> and beat the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into it. Gradually pour the <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> on this, stirring all the time. Return to the fire and cook for six minutes. Put the <ingredient>shaved chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> in a small pan over a hot fire, and stir until smooth and glossy. Stir this into the mixture in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Take from the fire and add the <ingredient>yolks of the eggs,</ingredient> well beaten; then set away to cool. When cool add the <ingredient>whites of the eggs,</ingredient> beaten to a stiff froth. Pour the batter into a well-buttered earthen dish that will hold about a quart, and cook in a moderate oven for twenty-two minutes. Serve immediately with <ingredient>vanilla cream sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PUDDING</purpose>
Reserve one gill of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> from a quart, and put the remainder on the fire in a <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Mix three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> with the <ingredient>cold milk.</ingredient> Beat two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> with half a cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Add this to the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir into the <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> beating well for a minute. Shave fine two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it into a small pan with four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over a hot fire until smooth and glossy; then beat into the hot pudding. Cook the pudding in all ten minutes, counting from the time the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> are added. Serve cold with <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> This pudding can be poured while hot into little cups which have been rinsed in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> At serving time turn out on a flat dish, making a circle, and fill the center of the dish with <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> flavored with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>
<p><variation>The eggs may be omitted, in which case use one more tablespoonful of <ingredient>cornstarch.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE MERINGUE PUDDING.</purpose>
For a small pudding use one pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls and a half of <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> five tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> one-fourth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></p>
<p>Mix the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> with one gill of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Put the remainder of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> on to boil in the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Scrape the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> When the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> boils, add the <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and cook for ten minutes. Beat the <ingredient>yolks of the eggs</ingredient> with three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Pour the hot
 
<pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=23"/>
mixture on this, and beat well. Turn into a <implement>pudding-dish</implement> that will hold about a quart, and bake for twenty minutes in a moderate oven.</p>
<p>Beat the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> to a stiff, dry froth, and gradually beat in the remaining two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Spread this on the pudding, and return to the oven. Cook for fifteen minutes longer, but with the oven door open. Serve either cold or hot.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MILTON PUDDING</purpose>
Use one pint of <ingredient>stale bread</ingredient> broken in crumbs, one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> half a teaspoonful of ground <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate,</ingredient> grated. Put the <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in a bowl, and soak for two or three hours. Beat together the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Mash the <ingredient>soaked bread</ingredient> with a spoon, and add the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> mixture to the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Pour into a <implement>pudding-dish,</implement> and bake in a slow oven for about forty minutes. Serve with an <ingredient>egg sauce</ingredient> or a <ingredient>vanilla cream sauce.</ingredient></p>
<p>EGG SAUCE.--Beat the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> to a stiff, dry froth; and beat into this, a little at a time, one cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient> When smooth and light, add one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs.</ingredient> Beat the mixture a little longer; then stir in one cupful of <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> or three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Serve at once.</p>
<p>VANILLA CREAM SAUCE.--Beat to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and gradually beat into this two-thirds of a cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient> When this is light and creamy, add a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> then gradually beat in two cupfuls of <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient> Place the bowl in a pan of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir constantly for three minutes. Pour the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> into a warm bowl, and serve.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">SNOW PUDDING</purpose>
Put a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler</implement> and on the fire. Mix three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> with a gill of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and one-third of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Stir this into the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> when it boils. Beat the <ingredient>whites of four eggs</ingredient> to a stiff froth, and then gradually beat into them half a cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> and one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Add this to the cooking mixture, and beat vigorously for one minute. Rinse a mould in cold water, and pouring the pudding into it, set away to cool. At serving-time turn out on a flat dish, and serve with <ingredient>chocolate sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE SAUCE</purpose>
Put one pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and on the fire. Shave two ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker and Co.'s Chocolate,</ingredient> and put it in a small pan with four tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and 
 
<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=24"/>
two of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Stir over the fire until smooth and glossy, and add to the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Beat together for eight minutes the <ingredient>yolks of four eggs,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a saltspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and then add one gill of <ingredient>cold milk.</ingredient></p>
<p>Pour the <ingredient>boiling milk</ingredient> on this, stirring well. Return to the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and cook for five minutes, stirring all the time. Pour into a cold bowl and set the bowl in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Stir for a few minutes, and then occasionally until the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> is cold.</p>
<p>This <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> is nice for cold or hot cornstarch pudding, bread pudding, cold cabinet pudding, snow pudding, etc. It will also answer for a dessert. Fill <implement>custard glasses</implement> with it, and serve the same as soft custard; or have the glasses two-thirds full, and heap up with whipped cream.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CANDY</purpose>
One cupful of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> two cupfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one cupful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one-half pound of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> half the size of an <ingredient>egg.</ingredient> Boil the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> together, scrape the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> fine, and mix with just enough of the <ingredient>boiling milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to moisten; rub it perfectly smooth, then, with the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> stir into the boiling liquid; add the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and boil twenty minutes. Try as molasses candy, and if it hardens, pour into a buttered dish. Cut the same as nut candy.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CREAM CHOCOLATE CARAMELS</purpose>
Mix together in a <implement>granite-ware saucepan</implement> half a pint of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>thick cream,</ingredient> one generous tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and four ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate.</ingredient> Place on the fire and stir until the mixture boils. Cook until a few drops of it will harden if dropped into <ingredient>ice-water;</ingredient> then pour into well-buttered pans, having the mixture about three-fourths of an inch deep. When nearly cold, mark into squares. It will take almost an hour to boil this in a <implement>granite-ware pan,</implement> but not half so long if cooked in an iron frying-pan. Stir frequently while boiling. The caramels must be put in a very cold place to harden.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">SUGAR CHOCOLATE CARAMELS</purpose>
Mix two cupfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three-fourths of a cupful of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one generous tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and three ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate.</ingredient> Place on the fire and cook, stirring often, until a little of the mixture, when dropped in <ingredient>ice-water,</ingredient> will harden; then stir in one-fourth of a cupful of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and pour into a well-buttered pan, having the mixture about three-fourths of an inch deep. When nearly cold, mark it off in squares, and put in a cold place to harden. These caramels are sugary and brittle, and can be made in the hottest weather without trouble. If a deep <implement>granite-ware
 
<pb n="21" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=25"/>
saucepan</implement> be used for the boiling, it will take nearly an hour to cook the mixture; but if with an iron frying-pan, twenty or thirty minutes will suffice.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAMS, NO. 1</purpose>
Beat the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> to a stiff froth. Gradually beat into this two cupfuls of <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient> If the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> be large, it may take a little more <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Flavor with half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and work well. Now roll into little balls, and drop on a slightly buttered platter. Let the balls stand for an hour or more. Shave five ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate</ingredient> and put into a small bowl, which place on the fire in a saucepan containing <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> When the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is melted, take the saucepan to the table, and drop the creams into the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> one at a time, taking them out with a fork and dropping them gently on the buttered dish. It will take half an hour or more to harden the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAMS, NO. 2</purpose>
For these creams you should make a fondant in this way: put into a <implement>granite-ware saucepan</implement> one cupful of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient>--or a pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar.</ingredient> Stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is nearly melted, then place on the fire and heat slowly, but do not stir the mixture. Watch carefully and note when it begins to boil. When the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> has been boiling for ten minutes, take up a little of it and drop in ice-water. If it hardens enough to form a soft ball when rolled between the thumb and finger, it is cooked enough. Take the saucepan from the fire instantly, and set in a cool, dry place. When the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is so cool that the finger can be held in it comfortably, pour it into a bowl, and stir with a wooden spoon until it becomes thick and white. When it begins to look dry, and a little hard, take out the spoon, and work with the hand until the cream is soft and smooth. Flavor with a few drops of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and, after shaping, cover with <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> as directed in the preceding recipe.</p>
<p>Caution.--Do not stir the syrup while it is cooking, and be careful not to jar or shake the saucepan.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CONES</purpose>
Boil the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as directed for fondant in the recipe for <ingredient>Chocolate Creams, No. 2,</ingredient> but not quite so long--say about eleven minutes. The <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> when tested, should be too soft to ball. When cold, pour into a bowl, and beat until thick and creamy. If properly boiled, it will not become thick enough to work with the hands.</p>
<p>Have six ounces of <ingredient>Walter Baker &amp; Co.'s Premium No. 1 Chocolate</ingredient> melted in a bowl. Pour half of the <ingredient>creamed sugar</ingredient> into another bowl, and, after flavoring with a few drops of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> add to it about one-third of the <ingredient>dissolved chocolate.</ingredient>
 
<pb n="22" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=26"/>
Stir until thick and rather dry; then make into small cones, and drop on a slightly buttered platter. Put half of the remaining <ingredient>creamed sugar</ingredient> in a cup, and set in a saucepan containing <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Flavor with <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and stir over the fire until melted so much that it will pour from the spoon. Take the saucepan to the table and dip one-half the cones in, one at a time, just as the Chocolate Creams, No. 1,  were dipped in the <ingredient>melted chocolate.</ingredient> If liked, a second coating may be given the cones. Now put the remainder of the <ingredient>creamed sugar</ingredient> on to melt, and add two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> to it. Stir the remainder of the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> into this, and if too thick to dip the candy in, add <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> a few drops at a time, until the mixture is of the right consistency; then dip the rest of the cones in this.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">GENESEE BON-BONS</purpose>
Make the <ingredient>cream chocolate caramels</ingredient>, and get them quite firm by placing the pan on ice. Make the <ingredient>chocolate coating</ingredient> as directed for <ingredient>chocolate cones.</ingredient> Dip the <ingredient>caramels</ingredient> in this and put on a buttered dish.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE SYRUP</purpose>
Into a <implement>granite-ware saucepan</implement> put one ounce--three tablespoonfuls--of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Soluble Chocolate,</ingredient> and gradually pour on it half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stirring all the time. Place on the fire, and stir until all the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is dissolved. Now add one pint of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient> and stir until it begins to boil. Cook for three minutes longer, then strain and cool. When cool, add one tablespoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient> Bottle, and keep in a cold place.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">REFRESHING DRINKS FOR SUMMER</purpose>
Put into a <implement>tumbler</implement> about two tablespoonfuls of broken ice, two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>chocolate syrup,</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>whipped cream,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and half a gill of <ingredient>soda-water</ingredient> from a syphon bottle, or Apollinaris water. Stir well before drinking. A tablespoonful of <ingredient>vanilla ice-cream</ingredient> is a desirable addition. It is a delicious drink, even if the soda or Apollinaris water and ice-cream be omitted. A plainer drink is made by combining the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> a gill and a half of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>ice</ingredient>, shaking well.</p>
</recipe>
<section>
<hd rend="bold">A FEW SUGGESTIONS IN REGARD TO CHOCOLATE</hd>
<p>The best flavor to add to chocolate is vanilla; next to that, cinnamon. Beyond these two things one should use great caution, as it is very easy to spoil the fine natural flavor of the bean. Chocolate absorbs odors readily; therefore it should be kept in a pure, sweet atmosphere. As about eleven per cent. of the chocolate bean is starch, chocolate and cocoa are of a much finer flavor if boiled for a few minutes. Long boiling, however, ruins their flavor and texture.</p>
</section>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets" class2="generalfood">
 
<pb n="23" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=27"/>
<illustration><description>A decorative banner with the words "recipes" written on it. Two branches form a border around the banner and the rest of the chapter's title.</description></illustration>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">Recipes<lb/>Specially Prepared<lb/>by<lb/>Miss Elizabeth Kevill Burr</hd>
<p align="center">(All measurements should be level.)</p>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FORMULA FOR MAKING THREE GALLONS OF BREAKFAST COCOA</purpose>
<list><item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Cocoa.</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 gallons of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> hot,</item>
<item>1 1/2 gallons of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> hot.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>This should not be allowed to boil. Either make it in a large <implement>double-boiler,</implement> or a large saucepan or kettle over water. Mix the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> with enough <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to make a paste, and be sure it is free from lumps. Heat together the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and pour in the <ingredient>cocoa;</ingredient> then cook at least an hour, stirring occasionally.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CRACKED COCOA</purpose>
To one-third a cup of <ingredient>Baker's Cracked Cocoa</ingredient> (sometimes called "Cocoa Nibs") use three cups of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> cook slowly at least one hour--the longer the better. Then strain the liquid and add one cup (or more if desired) of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and serve very hot. Do not allow the mixture to boil after <ingredient>milk</ingredient> has been added.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">VANILLA CHOCOLATE WITH WHIPPED CREAM</purpose>
<list><item>One cake (1/2 a pound) of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Vanilla Sweet Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 cups of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 cups of hot <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>This must be made in a <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Put the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in upper part of the <implement>double-boiler.</implement> Stir and beat with a wooden spoon until the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is dissolved and smooth. Add the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and when thoroughly hot, strain, and serve with <ingredient>unsweetened whipped cream.</ingredient> More cooking will improve it.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CREAM PIE</purpose>
Line a <implement>pie plate</implement> with <ingredient>rich pie crust</ingredient>, putting on an extra edge of crust the same as for custard pie. Fill with the <ingredient>chocolate filling</ingredient> made after the following recipe. Bake in a hot oven until crust is done; remove, and when cool, cover with a <ingredient>meringue</ingredient> and brown very slowly in moderate oven.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="24" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=28"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE FILLING</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>yolks</ingredient>),</item>
<item>5 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> (level),</item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in upper part of the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and when hot and smooth, stir in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> which has been mixed with enough <ingredient>cold milk</ingredient> to be thin enough to pour into the <ingredient>hot milk.</ingredient> Cook, stirring constantly, until it thickens; then let it cook eight or ten minutes. Mix the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together and pour the hot mixture over them, stirring well; put back in <implement>double-boiler</implement> and cook, stirring constantly one minute. Remove, and when cool add one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MERINGUE</purpose>
<list><item>2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>whites</ingredient>),</item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Add <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and beat in a large shallow dish with fork or <implement>egg-whip</implement> until stiff and flaky and dish can be turned upside down. Beat in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> slowly, then the <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and beat until the dish can be turned upside down.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA STICKS</purpose>
<list><item>6 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> (scant),</item>
<item>1 <ingredient>egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> or pinch of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient></item>
<item>5 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/8 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/4 to 1 1/2 cups of sifted <ingredient>pastry flour.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cream the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> until soft; add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> gradually and beat well; add the beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> mix thoroughly. Sift <ingredient>cocoa,</ingredient> <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> and a pinch of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> with about one-half cup of the <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> stir this into the mixture first, then use the remainder of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and more if necessary, to make a firm dough that will not stick to the fingers. Set on the ice to harden. Sprinkle the board with <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and a very little <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Use small pieces of the dough at a time, toss it over the board to prevent sticking, roll out thin, cut in strips about one-half inch wide and three inches long. Place closely in pan and bake in moderately hot oven three or four minutes. Great care should be taken in the baking to prevent burning.</p>
<p>It is advisable to gather the scraps after each rolling, if soft, and set away to harden, for fear of getting in too much <ingredient>cocoa,</ingredient> thus making them bitter.</p>
<p>The colder and harder the dough is, the better it can be handled; therefore it can be made the day before using.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA FROSTING</purpose>
<list><item>4 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>About 1 3/4 cups of <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=29"/>
<illustration><caption>FIG AND NUT CHOCOLATES.<lb/>(See Page 48.)</caption><description>A decorative glass bowl filled with fig and nut chocolates.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE MARSHMALLOWS.<lb/>(See Page 48.)</caption><description>A plate of marshmallows lined in pyramid.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE PEPPERMINTS.<lb/>(See Page 47.)</caption><description>A decorative glass bowl of pepermints.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>PLAIN CHOCOLATE CARAMELS.<lb/>(See Page 45.)</caption><description>Caramels cubes arranged in pyramid form in a raised plate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE ALMOND BARS.<lb/>(See Page 49.)</caption><description>Almond bars arranged in a beautiful oval can.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=30"/>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE COCOANUT CAKES.<lb/>(See page 43.)</caption><description>A decorative plate filled with Cocoanut cakes .</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>VASSAR FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 41.)</caption><description>Fudge cubes in a decorative plate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE PEANUT CLUSTERS.<lb/>(See Page 39.)</caption><description>A decorative plate filled with peanuts.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE OYSTERETTES.<lb/>(See Page 40.)</caption><description>Oysterettes in a decorative platinum bowl .</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE COATED ALMONDS.<lb/>(See Page 39.)</caption><description>A plate of almonds.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="25" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=31"/>
<p>Put the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> in a small saucepan; add the <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and stir until perfectly smooth; then the <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and cook for one or two minutes, add <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and a speck of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then stir in enough <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to make it stiff enough to spread nicely. Beat until smooth and glossy and free from lumps.</p>
<p>If too thick, add a little <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> If not thick enough, add a little <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Never make a frosting so stiff that it will have to be made smooth with awet knife. It is better to let it run to the sides of the cake. For frosting sides of the cake, make a little stiffer.</p>
<p>This frosting never cracks as an egg frosting, but is hard enough to cut nicely.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA SAUCE</purpose>
<list><item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Melt the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the saucepan; mix the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> together and stir into the <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> add gradually the <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> stirring and beating each time; cook until it thickens. Just before serving, add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and a pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> if necessary.</p>
<p>Use more <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> if liked stronger. This sauce will be found excellent for cottage puddings, Dutch apple cakes, steamed apple puddings, etc.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>6 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 or 2 cups of <ingredient>sifted pastry flour.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cream the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> stir in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> gradually, add the <ingredient>unbeaten eggs,</ingredient> and beat all together until very creamy. Sift together one-half cup of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> the <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and <ingredient>baking powder;</ingredient> use this <ingredient>flour</ingredient> first, then alternate the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and remaining <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> using enough to make mixture stiff enough to drop from the spoon; add <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat until very smooth; then bake in loaf in moderately hot oven thirty-five or forty minutes.</p>
<p>Tests for baking cake. It is baked enough when:
<list><item>1. It shrinks from the pan.</item>
<item>2. Touching it on the top, springs back.</item>
<item>3. No singing sound.</item>
</list>
</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA MERINGUE PUDDING</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa</ingredient>,</item>
<item>2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>yolks</ingredient>),</item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in the upper part of the <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and heat. Mix <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> together and soften in a little cold
 
<pb n="26" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=32"/>
<ingredient>milk;</ingredient> mix until free from lumps. When the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is hot, add the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and cook, stirring often, eight or ten minutes. Beat <ingredient>yolks of eggs</ingredient> lightly; add <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and mix well. When mixture in <implement>double-boiler</implement> has cooked sufficiently, strain it over the mixture in the bowl. Put back in <implement>double-boiler</implement> and allow it to cook one or two minutes (stirring constantly), just enough to slightly thicken the <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Remove from the stove, and when cool add <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and put in the <implement>serving-dish.</implement> Cover with a <ingredient>meringue</ingredient>. Place dish on a board, put in the oven with the door open, and allow it to remain there for ten or fifteen minutes, and when the meringue will not stick to the fingers, close the door and let it brown slightly. This pudding can be eaten warm or cold, but is much better cold. This will serve four persons generously.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ALMONDS</purpose>
Blanch the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> by pouring <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> on them, and let them stand two or three minutes. Roast them in oven. Dip them in the following recipe for chocolate coating, and drop on <implement>paraffine paper.</implement>
<list><item>1/2 <ingredient>pound cake</ingredient> of <ingredient>Walter Baker's Vanilla Sweet Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in small saucepan over <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and when melted stir in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Mix well. If found to be too thick, add more <ingredient>water;</ingredient> if too thin, more <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">HOT CHOCOLATE SAUCE</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 square of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cook all together slowly until it is the consistency of <ingredient>maple syrup,</ingredient> or thicker if desired. Just before serving, add one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> This will keep indefinitely, and can be reheated.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA SPONGE CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>4 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of sifted <ingredient>pastry flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Separate <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> from <ingredient>whites of eggs;</ingredient> beat <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> in a small bowl with the <implement>Dover egg-beater</implement> until very thick; add <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and beat again until very thick. Sift <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> together and stir very lightly into the mixture; fold in the stiffly beaten <ingredient>whites of the eggs,</ingredient> and bake in a loaf in a moderate oven until done.</p>
<p>Do not butter the pan, but when cake is baked, invert the pan; and when cool, remove the cake.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE FROSTING</purpose>
<list><item>1 square of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>5 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>About three cups of sifted <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
 
<pb n="27" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=33"/>
<p>Melt <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in bowl over tea-kettle, add <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and when smooth add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and beat until very glossy. Make the frosting stiff enough to spread without using a wet knife. It will keep indefinitely.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CAKE, OR DEVIL'S FOOD</purpose>
<list><item>5 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/4 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate</ingredient> (melted),</item>
<item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 1/2 level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>bakng powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of sifted <ingredient>pastry flour.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p><ingredient>Cream</ingredient> the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> then the <ingredient>unbeaten eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and beat together until very smooth. Sift the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> with one-half a cup of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and use first; then alternate the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and the remaining <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and make the mixture stiff enough to drop from the spoon. Beat until very smooth and bake in loaf in moderate oven. For tests see Cocoa Cake recipe on page 25.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ICE-CREAM</purpose>
<list><item>1 quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 can of sweetened <ingredient>condensed milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>6 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in <implement>double-boiler,</implement> and when <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is hot and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> has melted, stir in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> previously mixed in a little <ingredient>cold milk.</ingredient> Cook ten minutes, then pour this over the <ingredient>condensed milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> mixed together; cook again for four minutes, stirring. Strain, and when cool add <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and freeze.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE WHIP</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>yolks</ingredient>),</item>
<item>6 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>5 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (<ingredient>whites</ingredient>).</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in <implement>double-boiler;</implement> mix <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> in a small quantity of <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> and stir into the <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> when the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> has been melted; stir until smooth, then cook twelve minutes. Mix together the <ingredient>yolks of the eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then pour the hot mixture over it; cook again one or two minutes, stirring. When very cold, just before serving, add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and fold in the stiffly beaten <ingredient>whites of the eggs.</ingredient> Pile lightly in a glass dish and serve with lady fingers. A meringue can be made of the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then folded in the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> mixture, but it does not stand as long.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=34"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA MARBLE CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>6 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Three level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> about one and three-quarter cups of <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> or <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make mixture stiff enough to drop from the spoon. Mix in the order given. Reserve one-third of this mixture and add to it four level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa</ingredient> and to the other one cup of <ingredient>shredded cocoanut.</ingredient> Bake thirty-five or forty minutes according to size and shape of pan.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">CHOCOLATE MARBLE CAKE</purpose>
This is the same as the <ingredient>Cocoa Marble Cake</ingredient>. Add to one-third of the mixture one and one-half squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate</ingredient> in place of the <ingredient>cocoa,</ingredient> and one cup of <ingredient>chopped walnuts</ingredient> to the other part in place of the <ingredient>shredded cocoanut.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE JELLY</purpose>
<list><item>1 pint of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient></item>
<item>2 pinches of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a package of <ingredient>gelatine,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in a saucepan. Cook, stirring until the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> melts, then let it boil for three or five minutes. Soften the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and pour the boiling mixture over it. Stir until dissolved, then add <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Pour into a mould and set aside to harden, serve with <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> or <ingredient>sweetened whipped cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COTTAGE PUDDING</purpose>
<list><item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Two level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> one and three-quarter cups of sifted <ingredient>flour</ingredient> or enough to make mixture stiff enough to drop from the spoon. Bake in buttered <implement>gem pans</implement> in moderately hot oven twenty-three or twenty-five minutes. If the cake springs back after pressing a finger on the top, it shows that it is baked enough. To make a cocoa cottage pudding add to the above rule six level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient> Serve with a <ingredient>vanilla sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">VANILLA SAUCE</purpose>
<list><item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
 
<pb n="29" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=35"/>
<p>Melt <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in saucepan, add <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and mix until smooth; add slowly the <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stirring and beating well. Add <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOANUT SOUFFL&#200;</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>softened in a little <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Yolks of 4 eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of shredded <ingredient>cocoanut,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Whites of 4 eggs.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Heat <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> add <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and cook ten minutes after it has thickened. Mix together, <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks of eggs.</ingredient> Pour hot mixture over, stirring well and set aside to cool. Add <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and <ingredient>cocoanut.</ingredient> Lastly fold in the stiffly beaten <ingredient>whites of the eggs.</ingredient> Bake in buttered pan, in moderate oven until firm. Serve hot with <ingredient>Chocolate Sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE SAUCE</purpose>
<list><item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 level tablespoonful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 square of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Melt <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in saucepan, add dry <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and mix until smooth, then add slowly the <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> beating well. Add the square of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and stir until melted. Add <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> just before serving.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA BISCUIT</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups or 1 pint of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 level teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or enough to make a firm but not a stiff dough.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Sift all the dry ingredients together, rub in the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with the tips of the fingers. Stir in the required amount of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Turn out on slightly floured board, roll or pat out the desired thickness, place close together in pan and bake in very hot oven ten or fifteen minutes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA FUDGE</purpose>
<list><item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>6 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>Pinch of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Mix all ingredients together but vanilla; cook, stirring constantly, until it begins to boil, then cook slowly, stirring occasionally, eight or ten minutes, or until it makes a firm ball when dropped in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> When cooked enough, add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat until it seems like very <ingredient>cold molasses</ingredient> in winter. Pour into a buttered pan; when firm, cut in squares. Great care must be taken not to beat too much, because it cannot be poured into the pan, and will not have a gloss on top.</p>
</recipe></chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets" class2="beverages">
 
<pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=36"/>
<hd rend="bold" size="larger" align="center">MISS M.E. ROBINSON'S RECIPES</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE</purpose>
<list><item>1 ounce or square of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/8 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Place the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in the <implement>agate chocolate-pot</implement> or saucepan, add the <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and boil three minutes, stirring once or twice, as the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is not grated. Add the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and allow it time to heat, being careful not to boil the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and keep it closely covered, as this prevents the scum from forming. When ready to serve turn in <implement>chocolate-pitcher</implement> and beat with <implement>Dover egg-beater</implement> until light and foamy.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA DOUGHNUTS</purpose>
One <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one-quarter teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> one-quarter teaspoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon extract (Burnett's)</ingredient>, two cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one-quarter cup of <ingredient>Baker's Breakfast Cocoa,</ingredient> two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Mix in the order given, sifting the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient> and <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> with the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Roll to one-third an inch in thickness, cut and fry.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA SPONGE CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 3/4 cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Beat <ingredient>yolks of eggs</ingredient> light, add <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> beat again thoroughly; then add the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with which the <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> have been sifted. Fold in the stiffly beaten <ingredient>whites of the eggs.</ingredient> Bake in a rather quick oven for twenty-five or thirty minutes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA MARBLE CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 <ingredient>egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>Baker's Cocoa.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cream the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and <ingredient>egg;</ingredient> beat thoroughly, then add <ingredient>flour</ingredient> (in which is mixed the <ingredient>baking powder</ingredient>) and <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> alternately, until all added. To one-third of the mixture add the <ingredient>cocoa,</ingredient> and drop the <ingredient>white</ingredient> and brown mixture in spoonfuls into small, deep pans, and bake about forty minutes in moderate oven.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=37"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA BUNS</purpose>
<list><item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 <ingredient>egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of scalded <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 compressed <ingredient>yeast cakes</ingredient> softened in</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>extract cinnamon,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>Baker's Breakfast Cocoa,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 1/2 to 4 cups of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Mix in order given, having dough as soft as can be handled, turn onto <implement>moulding board,</implement> roll into a square about an inch in thickness, sprinkle on one-half cup of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> fold the sides to meet the centre, then each end to centre, and fold again. Place in a bowl which is set in pan of warm water, let raise forty minutes. Shape, place in pan, let raise until doubled in size. Bake fifteen to twenty minutes. As you take from oven , brush the top with <ingredient>white of one egg</ingredient> beaten with one-half cup <ingredient>confectioners' sugar.</ingredient> Let stand five minutes. Then they are ready to serve.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. RORER'S CHOCOLATE CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>2 ounces of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 heaping teaspoonful of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 3/4 cups of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Dissolve the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in five tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> beat again, then the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> then the melted <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Give the whole a vigorous beating. Now beat the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> to a stiff froth, and stir them carefully into the mixture; add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Mix quickly and lightly, turn into well-greased cake pan and bake in a moderate oven forty-five minutes.--<attribution rend="italic">From Mrs. Rorer's Cook Book.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. LINCOLN'S CHOCOLATE CARAMELS</purpose>
One cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one-quarter of a pound of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> cut fine, half a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and one heaping tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Boil all together, stirring all the time. When it hardens in cold water, pour it into shallow pans, and as it cools cut in small squares.--<attribution rend="italic">From Mrs. Lincoln's Boston Cook Book.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MISS FARMER'S CHOCOLATE NOUGAT CAKE</purpose>
<list><item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 <ingredient>egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>bread flour,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> melted,</item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>almonds blanched and shredded.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Cream the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add gradually one and one-half cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>egg unbeaten</ingredient>; when well mixed, add two-thirds
 
<pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=38"/>
<ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> mixed and sifted with <ingredient>baking powder,</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> To melted <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> add one-third a cup of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> place on range, add gradually remaining <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and cook until smooth. Cool slightly and add to cake mixture. Bake fifteen to twenty minutes in round layer-cake pans. Put between layers and on top of cake <ingredient>White Mountain Cream</ingredient> sprinkled with <ingredient>almonds.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">From Boston Cooking School Cook book--Fannie Merritt Farmer.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. ARMSTRONG'S CHOCOLATE PUDDING</purpose>
Soften three cups of <ingredient>stale bread</ingredient> in an equal quantity of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Melt two squares of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate</ingredient> over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and mix with half a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> three beaten <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Mix this thoroughly with the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and place in well-buttered <implement>custard cups.</implement> Steam about half an hour (according to size) and serve in the cups or turned out on warm plate.-- <attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Helen Armstrong.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. ARMSTRONG'S CHOCOLATE CHARLOTTE</purpose>
Soak a quarter of a package of <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> in one-fourth of a cupful of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Whip one pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> to a froth and put it in a bowl, which should be placed in a pan of <ingredient>ice water.</ingredient> Put an ounce of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Chocolate</ingredient> in a small pan with two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir over the hot fire until smooth and glossy. Add to this a gill of <ingredient>hot milk</ingredient> and the <ingredient>soaked gelatine,</ingredient> and stir until the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> is dissolved. Sprinkle a generous half cupful of <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> over the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Now add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> mixture and stir gently until it begins to thicken. Line a quart charlotte mould with lady fingers, and when the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is so thick that it will just pour, turn it gently into the mould. Place the charlotte in a cold place for an hour or more, and at serving time turn out on a flat dish.--<attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Helen Armstrong.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE JELLY WITH CRYSTALLIZED GREEN GAGES</purpose>
Dissolve in a quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>grated chocolate;</ingredient> let come to a boil; simmer ten minutes; add a cup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a box of <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> (that has been softened in a cup of <ingredient>water</ingredient>) and strain through a <implement>jelly bag</implement> or two thicknesses of <implement>cheese-cloth.</implement> When almost cold, add a dessertspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and a tablespoonful of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Then <implement>whisk</implement> well; add half a pound of <ingredient>crystallized green gages</ingredient> cut into small pieces; pour into a pretty mould, and when cold serve with <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="advertisement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=39"/>
<section>
<hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO'S.<lb/>GERMAN<lb/>SWEET CHOCOLATE</hd>
<illustration><caption>FAC-SIMILE 1/4 LB. PACKAGE.</caption><description>A packaged chocolate bar with the brand name - GERMAN SWEET CHOCOLATE. Other information that are printed on top of the package are : Registered in U.S. Patent Office, DIRECTIONS--INTO ONE PINT OF BOILING MILK &#38; WATER (OF EACH ONE HALF) THROW TWO SQUARES OF CHOCOLATE SCRAPED FINE. THEN BOIL IT FIVE MINUTES LONGER OR MORE. STIRRING FREQUENTLY.--printed at the top of the border, SWEET CHOCOLATE--printed at both left and right borders, REGISTERED S. GERMAN, DORCHESTER, MASS--printed at the bottom of the border.</description></illustration>
</section>
 
<pb n="advertisement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=40"/>
<section> 
<hd rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">WALTER BAKER AND CO'S.<lb/>BREAKFAST<lb/>COCOA</hd>
<illustration><caption>FAC-SIMILE OF 1/2 LB. CAN.</caption><description>A can of coca with the illustration of a serving woman in 19th century dress carrying a tray with a flass and cup on it. Other information that are printed on the can are: Gold Medal, Paris, 1878, Gold Medal, Paris, 1900, BAKER'S BREAKFAST COCOA, N0 CHEMICALS, GUARANTEED UNDER THE FOOD AND DRUGS ACT, JUNE 30, 1906. SERIAL NO. 90.--printed at the left side of can; LA BELLE CHOCOLATI&#200;RE (cocoa's brand name), Walter Baker &#38; Co. Limited. Registered in U.S. Patent Office.--printed at the front of the can together with the woman illustration.</description></illustration>
</section>
 
<pb n="advertisement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=41"/>
<section>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO'S.<lb/>CARACAS SWEET CHOCOLATE</hd>
<illustration><caption>FAC-SIMILE 1/4 LB. PACKAGE</caption><description>A package of chocolate with an illustration of a female servant in Victorian dress, who is holding a tray with a cup and glass on it. Other information that are stated on the package are: BAKER'S CARACAS SWEET CHOCOLATE, REGISTERED IN U.S. PATENT OFFICE, MADE BY WALTER BAKER &#38; CO.LTD. DORCHESTER, MASS, VIENNA EXPOSITION 1873., A DELICIOUS CHOCOLATE, and EXCELLENT AS A CONFECTION.</description></illustration>
</section>
 
<pb n="advertisement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=42"/>
<section>
<hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO'S.<lb/>PREMIUM NO.1</hd>
<illustration><caption>FAC-SIMILE OF 1/2 LB. PACKAGE.</caption><description>A package of baker's chocolate with the word BAKER'S at left and right borders, HALF POUND NET WEIGHT, WALTER BAKER &#38; CO.LTD at the top border and HALF POUND NET WEIGHT DORCHESTER, MASS at the bottom border. Other information such as BAKER'S CHOCOLATE, NUTRITIVE, SALUTARY, AND DELICIOUS BEVERAGE, FOR MORE THAN A CENTURY!, and Made by Walter Baker &#38; Co., Limited. Dorchester, Mass are written at the middle of the package.</description></illustration>
</section>
 
<pb n="33" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=43"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. BEDFORD'S CHOCOLATE CRULLERS</purpose>
Cream two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and one-half of a cupful of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> gradually add the beaten <ingredient>yolks of three eggs</ingredient> and one and one-half cupfuls more of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one cupful of <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> grated and melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> one-third of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> dissolved in one-half of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> whipped to a stiff froth, and sufficient <ingredient>sifted flour</ingredient> to make a soft dough. Roll out, cut into oblongs; divide each into three strips, leaving the dough united at one end. Braid loosely, pinch the ends together and cook until golden-brown in <ingredient>smoking-hot fat.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Cornelia C. Bedford.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. BEDFORD'S HOT COCOA SAUCE FOR ICE-CREAM</purpose>
Boil together one and one-half cupfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and one cupful of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> for two minutes; add one tablespoonful of <ingredient>arrowroot</ingredient> dissolved in a little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> stir for a moment, then boil until clear. Add two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> which has been dissolved in a little <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and a tiny pinch of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and boil three minutes longer. Take from the fire and add one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Cornelia C. Bedford.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. BEDFORD'S CHOCOLATE MACAROONS</purpose>
Grate one-quarter of a pound of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and mix one-quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sifted powdered sugar</ingredient> and one-quarter of a pound of <ingredient>blanched and ground almonds.</ingredient> Add a pinch of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and mix to a <ingredient>soft paste</ingredient> with <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten until thick. Drop in half-teaspoonfuls on slightly buttered paper and bake in a moderate oven. Do not take from the paper until cold; then brush the under side with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and the paper can be readily stripped off.--<attribution rend="italic">Mrs. Cornelia C. Bedford.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. EWING'S CREAMY COCOA</purpose>
Stir together in a saucepan half a cup of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Breakfast Cocoa,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Add gradually one quart of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and let the mixture boil five minutes, stirring it constantly. Remove from the fire, add a quart of <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> and serve. If desired a spoonful of <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> may be put in each cup before filling with the <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient></p>
<p>The proportions given will make delicious, creamy cocoa, sufficient to serve twelve persons. The <ingredient>flour</ingredient> should be sifted before it is measured.--<attribution rend="italic">By Mrs. Emma P. Ewing, author of "The Art of Cookery."</attribution></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=44"/>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. EWING'S CREAMY CHOCOLATE</purpose>
Mix together half a cup of <ingredient>sifted flour,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> and half a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put into a saucepan half a cup of <ingredient>Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Premium No. 1 chocolate,</ingredient> finely shaved. Add one quart of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stir until dissolved, add the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and boil gently, stirring constantly, five minutes. Then stir in a quart of <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> and serve with or without <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">By Mrs. Emma P. Ewing, author of "The Art of Cookery."</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. HILL'S COCOA FRAPP&#201;</purpose>
Mix half a pound of <ingredient>cocoa</ingredient> and three cupfuls of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> cook with two cupfuls of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> until smooth; add to three quarts and a half of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> scalded with <ingredient>cinnamon bark;</ingredient> cook for ten minutes. Beat in the beaten <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> mixed with a cupful of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a pint of <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient> Cool, flavor with <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> and freeze. Serve in cups. Garnish with <ingredient>whipped cream.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Janet McKenzie Hill--Ladies' Home Journal.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. HILL'S CHOCOLATE PUFFS</purpose>
Stir a cupful of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a cupful of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and half a cupful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> boiling together; remove from fire, beat in an ounce of <ingredient>melted chocolate,</ingredient> and, one at a time, three large <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Shape with forcing bag and rose tube. Bake, cut off the tops and put into each cake a tablespoonful of <ingredient>strawberry preserves.</ingredient> Cover with <ingredient>whipped cream</ingredient> sweetend and flavored.--<attribution rend="italic">Janet McKenzie Hill--Ladies Home Journal.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MISS FARMER'S CHOCOLATE CREAM CANDY</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into <implement>granite saucepan;</implement> when melted add <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Heat to boiling point; then add <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and stir constantly until <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is melted. Boil thirteen minutes, remove from fire, add <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and beat until creamy and mixture begins to <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> slightly around edge of saucepan. Pour at once into a buttered pan, cool slightly and mark in squares. Omit vanilla, and add, while cooking, one-fourth of a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Boston Cooking School Cook Book--Fannie Merritt Farmer.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MRS. SALZBACHER'S CHOCOLATE HEARTS</purpose>
Melt, by standing over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> three ounces of <ingredient>unsweetened chocolate;</ingredient> add a pound of <ingredient>sifted powdered sugar</ingredient> and mix thoroughly; work to a <ingredient>stiff yet pliable paste</ingredient> with the <ingredient>unbeaten
 
<pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=45"/>
whites of three eggs</ingredient> (or less), adding <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> to flavor. If the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> seems too soft, add more <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Break off in small pieces and roll out about one-fourth of an inch thick, sprinkling the board and paste with <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> instead of flour. Cut with a tiny heart-shaped <implement>cake cutter</implement> (any other small <implement>cake cutter</implement> will do), and place on pans oiled just enough to prevent sticking. Bake in a very moderate oven. When done, they will feel firm to the touch, a solid crust having formed over the top. They should be very light, and will loosen easily from the pan after being allowed to stand a moment to cool. The success of these cakes depends upon the oven, which should not be as cool as for meringue, nor quite so hot as for sponge cake. If properly made, they are very excellent and but little labor. Use the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> for chocolate whips.-- <attribution rend="italic">From "Good Housekeeping."</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA CHARLOTTE<lb/>(Without Cream)</purpose>
<list><item>1 pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Whites of 2 eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cocoa.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Dissolve the <ingredient>cornstarch</ingredient> in a quarter of a cup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> add it to the pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> stir until it thickens, add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and the <ingredient>cocoa,</ingredient> which have been thoroughly mixed together. Remove from the fire, add the <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> and pour slowly over the stiffly <ingredient>beaten whites of eggs.</ingredient> Pour at once into a <implement>pudding mould,</implement> and put away in a cold place to harden. Serve with <ingredient>plain cream.</ingredient>--<attribution rend="italic">Mabel Richards Dulon.</attribution></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE FUDGE WITH FRUIT</purpose>
Two cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one-half cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one-half cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> one-half cup of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> mix all together and boil seven minutes; add one-half cup of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate</ingredient> and boil seven minutes longer. Then add two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>figs,</ingredient> two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>English walnuts</ingredient> and one teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE MACAROONS</purpose>
Stir to a <ingredient>paste whites of seven eggs,</ingredient> three-fourths a pound of <ingredient>sifted sugar,</ingredient> one-half a pound of <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> pounded very fine, and two ounces of grated <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate.</ingredient> Have ready <implement>wafer paper</implement> cut round, on which lay pieces of the mixture rolled to fit the wafer. Press one-half a <ingredient>blanched almond</ingredient> on each macaroon and bake in a moderate oven.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=46"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PETITS FOUR</purpose>
Bake a simple, <ingredient>light sponge cake</ingredient> in a shallow biscuit tin or <implement>dripping pan,</implement> and when cold turn out on the <implement>moulding board</implement> and cut into small dominoes or diamonds. They should be about an inch in depth. Split each one and spread <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> or <ingredient>frosting</ingredient> between the layers, then ice tops and sides with different <ingredient>tinted icings,</ingredient> pale green flavored with <ingredient>pistachio,</ingredient> pale pink with <ingredient>rose,</ingredient> yellow with <ingredient>orange,</ingredient> white with <ingredient>almond.</ingredient> Little domino cakes are also pretty. Ice the cakes on top and sides with <ingredient>white icing</ingredient>, then when hard put on a second layer of <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> using <emph rend="italic">Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s Unsweetened <ingredient>Chocolate</ingredient></emph> and made as for layer cake, dipping the brush in the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> to make the spots.</p>
<p>Candied violets, bits of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> cut in fancy shapes, <ingredient>candied cherries</ingredient> and <ingredient>angelica</ingredient> may all be utilized in making pretty designs in decoration.--<attribution rend="italic">American Housekeeper</attribution>.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">POTATO CAKE</purpose>
Two cups of <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>hot mashed potatoes,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>chopped walnuts,</ingredient> half a cup of <ingredient>sweet milk,</ingredient> two cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, five teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>melted chocolate,</ingredient> one tablespoonful each of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>baking powder.</ingredient> Bake in layers and use <ingredient>marshmallow filling.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">SPANISH CHOCOLATE CAKE</purpose>
One cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>sweet milk,</ingredient> three cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Put on the stove one cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one-half a cup of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient> grated; stir until dissolved; then stir into it one cup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolk of one egg</ingredient> stirred together; when cool flavor with <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> While this is cooling beat up the first part of the cake and add the <ingredient>chocolate custard</ingredient>. Bake in layers. Ice on top and between the layers.</p>
</recipe></chapter>
<chapter>
 
<pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=47"/>
<illustration><description>A decorative banner with the words "home made candies" written on it. Two branches with heart shape leaves, form a border around the banner and the rest of the chapter's title.</description></illustration>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">HOME MADE CANDIES<lb/>Recipes Specially Prepared<lb/>by<lb/>Mrs. Janet McKenzie Hill</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PEPPERMINTS, CHOCOLATE MINTS, Etc.<lb/>(Uncooked Fondant)</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>White of 1 egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Sifted confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>essence of peppermint</ingredient> or a few drops of <ingredient>oil of peppermint,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 or 2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Green color paste,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Pink color paste.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Beat the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> on a plate, add the <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and gradually work in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> enough to make a firm <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> Divide the <ingredient>sugar paste</ingredient> into three parts. To one part add the <ingredient>peppermint</ingredient> and a very little of the <ingredient>green color paste.</ingredient> Take the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> from the jar with a wooden tooth pick, add but a little. Work and knead the mixture until the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is evenly distributed throughout. Roll the candy into a sheet one-fourth an inch thick, then cut out into small rounds or other shape with any utensil that is convenient. Color the second part a very delicate pink, flavor with <ingredient>rose extract</ingredient> and cut out in the same manner as the first. To the last part add one or two squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and flavor with <ingredient>peppermint.</ingredient> Add also a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> as the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> will make the mixture thick and crumbly. Begin by adding a tablespoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then add more if necessary, knead and cut these as the others.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE CARAMEL WALNUTS<lb/>(Uncooked Fondant)</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>White of 1 egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>maple or caramel syrup,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Sifted confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 or more squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>English walnuts.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Beat the <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> slightly, add the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as needed, the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> also more <ingredient>water</ingredient> if necessary. Work with a silver plated knife and knead until thoroughly mixed, then break off small pieces of uniform size and roll them into balls, in the hollow of the hand, flatten the balls a little, set the half of an <ingredient>English walnut</ingredient> upon each, pressing the <ingredient>nut</ingredient> into the candy and thus flattening it still more. The <ingredient>caramel</ingredient> gives the chocolate a particularly nice flavor.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=48"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">HOW TO COAT CANDIES, &#38; C.,<lb/>WITH BAKER'S "DOT" CHOCOLATE</purpose>
Half a pound of <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> will coat quite a number of candy or other "centers," but as depth of chocolate and an even temperature during the whole time one is at work are essential, it is well, when convenient, to melt a larger quantity of <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> When cold, the <ingredient>unused chocolate</ingredient> may be cut from the dish and set aside for use at a future time. If the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> be at the proper temperature when the centers are dipped in it, it will give a rich, glossy coating free from spots, and the candies will not have a spreading base. After a few centers have been dipped set them in a cool place to harden. The necessary utensils are a <implement>wire fork</implement> and a very small <implement>double boiler.</implement> The inner dish of the <implement>boiler</implement> should be of such size that the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> will come nearly to the top of it. Break the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> in small pieces and surround with <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> stir occasionally while melting. When the <ingredient>melted chocolate</ingredient> has cooled to about 80&#176; F. it is ready to use. Drop whatever is to be coated into the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> with the fork push it below the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> lift out, draw across the edge of the dish and drop onto a piece of table <implement>oil cloth</implement> or onto waxed paper. Do not let a drop of water get into the chocolate.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE DIPPED PEPPERMINTS<lb/>(Uncooked Fondant)</purpose>
Prepare <ingredient>green, white, pink and chocolate colored mints</ingredient> by the first recipe. After they have dried off a little run a <implement>spatula</implement> under each and turn to dry the other side. Coat with <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">GINGER, CHERRY, APRICOT and NUT CHOCOLATES</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>White of 1 egg,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Sifted confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Almond or rose extract,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Preserved ginger,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Candied cherries,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Candied apricots,</ingredient></item>
<item>Halves of <ingredient>almond,</ingredient></item>
<item>Halves of <ingredient>pecan nuts,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Use the first four ingredients in making <ingredient>uncooked fondant</ingredient>. (<ingredient>Caramel syrup</ingredient> is a great addition to this fondant, especially if <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> are to be used. Use three tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> and one tablespoonful of <ingredient>water</ingredient> with one <ingredient>egg white</ingredient> instead of the two tablespoonfuls of water indicated in the recipe). Work the fondant for some time, then break off little bits and wrap around small pieces of the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> then roll in the hollow of the hand into balls or oblongs. For other candies, roll a piece of the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> into a ball, flatten it with the fingers and use to cover a whole <ingredient>pecan</ingredient> or <ingredient>English walnut meat.</ingredient> Set each shape on a plate as it is finished. They will harden very quickly. Dip these, one by one, in <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> and set on an <implement>oil cloth.</implement></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=49"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PEANUT CLUSTERS</purpose>
Shell a quart of <ingredient>freshly-roasted peanuts</ingredient> and remove the skins. Drop the <ingredient>peanuts,</ingredient> one by one, into the center of a dish of <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> made ready for use; lift out onto <implement>oil cloth</implement> with a dipping fork (a <implement>wire fork</implement> comes for the purpose, but a <implement>silver oyster fork</implement> answers nicely) to make groups of three <ingredient>nuts,</ingredient>--two below, side by side, and one above and between the others.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE COATED ALMONDS</purpose>
Select <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> that are plump at the ends. Use them without blanching. Brush, to remove dust. Melt <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> and when cooled properly drop the <ingredient>nuts,</ingredient> one at a time, into the center of it; push the <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> under with the fork, then drop onto waxed paper or <implement>oil cloth.</implement> In removing the fork make a design on the top of each nut. These are easily prepared and are particulary good.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN AND CHOCOLATE DIPPED PARISIAN SWEETS</purpose>
<list><item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>Sultana raisins,</ingredient></item>
<item>5 <ingredient>figs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>dates,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 ounces <ingredient>citron,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>nut meats,</ingredient> (<ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> <ingredient>filberts,</ingredient> <ingredient>pecans</ingredient> or <ingredient>walnuts,</ingredient> one variety or a mixture),</item>
<item>1 1/2 ounces of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Chocolate Fondant</ingredient> or <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Pour <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over the <ingredient>figs</ingredient> and <ingredient>dates,</ingredient> let boil up once; then drain as dry as possible; remove stones from the <ingredient>dates,</ingredient> the stem ends from the <ingredient>figs;</ingredient> chop the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> and <ingredient>nut meats</ingredient> (<ingredient>almonds</ingredient> should be blanched) in a <implement>food chopper;</implement> add the <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> and the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and work the whole to a smooth <ingredient>paste;</ingredient> add the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted, and work it evenly through the mass. Add more <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> if it is needed and roll the mixture into a sheet one-fourth an inch thick. Cut into strips an inch wide. Cut the strips into diamond-shaped pieces (or squares); roll these in <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> or dip them in <ingredient>chocolate fondant</ingredient> or in <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate,</ingredient> and sprinkle a little <ingredient>fine-chopped pistachio nut meats</ingredient> on the top of the dipped pieces. When rolling the mixture use <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> on board and rolling pin.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">STUFFED DATES, CHOCOLATE DIPPED</purpose>
Cut choice <ingredient>dates</ingredient> open on one side and remove the seeds. Fill the open space in the <ingredient>dates</ingredient> with a strip of <ingredient>preserved ginger</ingredient> or <ingredient>pineapple,</ingredient> <ingredient>chopped nuts</ingredient> or <ingredient>chopped nuts</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>white</ingredient> or <ingredient>chocolate fondant;</ingredient> press the <ingredient>dates</ingredient> into a compact form to keep in the filling, then dip them, one by one, in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="40" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=50"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE OYSERETTES,<lb/>PLAIN AND WITH CHOPPED FIGS</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>Oyster crackers,</ingredient> salted preferred, fine-chopped, <ingredient>roasted peanuts</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or 3 or 4 basket <ingredient>figs</ingredient> or a little <ingredient>French fruit</ingredient> cut in very small bits.</item>
<item>1/2 a pound or more of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Select <ingredient>fresh-baked crackers</ingredient> free from crumbs. Dip in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate,</ingredient> made ready as in previous recipes, and dispose on <implement>oil cloth</implement> or waxed paper. For a change add <ingredient>figs</ingredient> or other <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> cut very fine, or chopped <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> to the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> ready for dipping.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">TURKISH PASTE WITH FRENCH FRUIT, CHOCOLATE FLAVORED</purpose>
<list><item>3 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>granulated gelatine,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>ground cinnamon,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>French candied fruit,</ingredient> (<ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> <ingredient>angelica,</ingredient> <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> etc.), chopped fine.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Let the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> stand in the half cup of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> until it has taken up all of the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and the two-thirds a cup of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> over the fire until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is dissolved and the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is boiling, then add the <ingredient>gelatine</ingredient> and let cook twenty minutes; add the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and beat all together, then add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> let stand in a cool place for a time, then when it thickens a little turn into an <ingredient><emph rend="italic">un</emph>buttered bread</ingredient> pan and set aside until the next day. To unmold separate the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> from the pan--at the edge--with a sharp-pointed knife. Sift <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> over the top, then with the tips of the fingers gently pull the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> from the pan to a board dredged with <ingredient>confectioner's sugar;</ingredient> cut into strips, then into small squares. Roll each square in <ingredient>confectioner's sugar.</ingredient> In cutting keep <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> between the knife and the <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOICE CHOCOLATE PECAN PRALINES</purpose>
<list><item>3 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> cooked to caramel,</item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 cups of <ingredient>pecan nut meats.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream</ingredient> over the fire until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then let boil to the soft ball degree, or to 236&#176; F. Add the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted or shaved fine, and beat it in, then pour the mixture onto the cup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> cooked to caramel; let the mixture boil up once, then remove from the fire; add the <ingredient>nut meats</ingredient> and beat until the mass begins to thicken. When cold enough to hold its shape drop onto an <implement>oil cloth</implement> or marble, a teaspoonful in a place, and at once set a half <ingredient>nut meat</ingredient> on each. Two persons are needed to make these pralines,
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=51"/>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE PEANUT BRITTLE.<lb/>(See Page 52.)</caption><description>A plate of peanut brittle.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE MOLASSES KISSES.<lb/>(See Page 53.)</caption><description>A basketful of molasses kisses.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>ROSE AND PISTACHIO CHOCOLATE CREAMS.<lb/>(See Page 51.)</caption><description>A bowl filled with oval shaped chocolate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>DOUBLE FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 41.)</caption><description>A decorative plate filled with cubes fudge.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>COCOA FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 29.)</caption><description>Cubes fudge in a decorative bowl.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="list of illustrations" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=52"/>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE<lb/>DIPPED PEPPERMINTS.<lb/>(See Page 38.)</caption><description>A decorative bowl filled with chocolate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE<lb/>CARAMEL WALNUTS.<lb/>(See Page 37.)</caption><description>A plateful of caramel walnuts.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>MAPLE FONDANT ACORNS.<lb/>(See Page 48.)</caption><description>A beautiful raised plate filled with fondants acorns.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>GINGER, CHERRY, APRICOT<lb/>AND NUT CHOCOLATES.<lb/>(See Page 38.)</caption><description>A decorative bowl filled with chocolates.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE DIPPED<lb/>PARISIAN SWEETS.<lb/>(See Page 39.)</caption><description>Parisian sweets in a decorative oval bowl.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>ALMOND FONDANT BALLS.<lb/>(See Page 50.)</caption><description>A decorative glass bowlful of fondant balls.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=53"/>
lines one to drop the mixture, the other to decorate with the halves of the <ingredient>nuts.</ingredient> The mixture becomes smooth and firm almost instantly. <ingredient>Maple or brown sugar</ingredient> may be used in place of all or a part of the quantity of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> designated.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">VASSAR FUDGE</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>white granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cake of <ingredient>Baker's Premium No. 1 Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and when this becomes hot put in the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> broken up into fine pieces. Stir vigorously and constantly. Put in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> when it begins to boil. Stir until it creams when beaten on a saucer. Then remove and beat until quite cool and pour into buttered tins. When cold cut in diamond-shaped pieces.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">SMITH COLLEGE FUDGE</purpose>
Melt one-quarter cup of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Mix together in a separate dish one cup of <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> one-quarter cup of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and one-half cup of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Add this to the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and after it has been brought to a boil continue boiling for two and one-half minutes, stirring rapidly. Then add two squares of <ingredient>Baker's Premium No. 1 Chocolate,</ingredient> scraped fine. Boil this five minutes, stirring it first rapidly, and then more slowly towards the end. After it has been taken from the fire, add one and one-half teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Then stir constantly until the mass thickens. Pour into buttered pan and set in a cool place.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">WELLESLEY MARSHMALLOW FUDGE</purpose>
Heat two cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> and one cup of <ingredient>rich milk</ingredient> (<ingredient>cream</ingredient> is better). Add two squares of Baker's <ingredient>Chocolate,</ingredient> and boil until it hardens in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Just before it is done add a small piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> then begin to stir in <ingredient>marshmallows,</ingredient> crushing and beating them with a spoon. Continue to stir in <ingredient>marshmallows,</ingredient> after the fudge has been taken from the fire, until half a pound has been stirred into the fudge. Cool in sheets three-quarters of an inch thick, and cut in cubes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">DOUBLE FUDGE</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Boil seven minutes; then beat and spread in buttered tin to cool.</p>
 
<pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=54"/>
<p>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>walnut meats,</ingredient> chopped fine, </item>
<item><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> size of a walnut.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Boil ten minutes; then beat and pour on top of fudge already in pan. When cool, cut in squares.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MARBLED FUDGE.</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient> scraped fine or melted,</item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Stir the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream</ingredient> over a slack fire until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted; move the saucepan to a hotter part of the range and continue stirring until the mixture boils, then let boil, stirring every three or four minutes very gently, until the thermometer registers 236&#176; F., or, till a soft ball can be formed in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Remove from the fire and pour one-half of the mixture over the <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> Set both dishes on a <implement>cake rack,</implement> or on something that will allow the air to circulate below the dishes. When the mixture cools a litte, get some one to beat one dish of the fudge; add a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> to each dish, and beat until thick and slightly grainy, then put the mixture in a pan, lined with waxed paper, first a little of one and then of the other, to give a marbled effect. When nearly cold turn from the pan, peel off the <ingredient>paper</ingredient> and cut into cubes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FUDGE HEARTS OR ROUNDS</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>condensed milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Boil the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> to 236&#176; F., or to the "soft ball" degree; stir gently every few minutes; add the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and let boil up vigorously, then remove from the fire and add the <ingredient>chocolate;</ingredient> let stand undisturbed until cool, then add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat the candy until it thickens and begins to <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Pour into a pan lined with paper to stand until cooled somewhat; turn from the mold and with a <implement>French cutter</implement> or a sharp edged tube cut into symmetrical shapes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MARSHMALLOW FUDGE</purpose>
<list><item>1st BATCH</item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>Nearly half a pound of <ingredient>marshmallows</ingredient> split in halves.</item>
</list>
<list><item>2nd BATCH</item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> </item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
 
<pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=55"/>
<p>Start with the first batch and when this is nearly boiled enough, set the second batch to cook, preparing it in the same manner as the first. Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> over a rather slack fire, until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, when the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> boils wash down the sides of the pan as in making fondant, set in the thermometer and cook over a quick fire, without stirring, to the soft ball degree, 236&#176; F.; add the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted or shaved fine, and let boil up vigorously, then remove to a <implement>cake cooler</implement> (or two spoon handles to allow a circulation of air below the pan). In the meantime the second batch should be cooking and the <ingredient>marshmallows</ingredient> be gotten ready. When the first batch is about cold add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat the candy vigorously until it begins to thicken, then turn it into a pan lined with waxed paper. At once dispose the halves of <ingredient>marshmallows</ingredient> close together upon the top of the fudge. Soon the other dish of fudge will be ready; set it into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and when nearly cold, add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat as in the first batch, then pour it over the <ingredient>marshmallows.</ingredient> When the whole is about cold turn it onto a marble, or hard-wood board, pull off the <ingredient>paper</ingredient> and cut into cubes. If one is able to work very quickly, but one batch need be prepared, half of it being spread over the marshmallows.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE DIPPED FRUIT FUDGE</purpose>
<list><item>FRUIT FUDGE</item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>Maple Syrup,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>thick cream,</ingredient> or</item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and 1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> <ingredient>figs,</ingredient> and <ingredient>candied cherries</ingredient> and <ingredient>apricots,</ingredient> cut in small pieces.</item>
</list>
<list><item>CHOCOLATE FOR DIPPING</item>
<item>1/2 a cake or more of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Stir the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream</ingredient> until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, cover and let boil three or four minutes, then uncover and let boil stirring often but very gently until a soft ball may be formed in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> or, until the thermometer registers 236&#176; F. Set the saucepan on a <implement>cake cooler</implement> and when the mixture becomes cool, add the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> and beat until it becomes thick, then turn into pans lined with waxed paper. In about fifteen minutes cut into squares. Coat these with the <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center" >CHOCOLATE COCOANUT CAKES</purpose>
<list><item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup (scant measure) of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>One cup, less one tablespoonful, of <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>dessicated cocoanut,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Heat the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> to the boiling point, add the <ingredient>cocoanut</ingredient> and stir constantly while cooking to the soft ball degree, or, until a little of the candy dropped on a cold marble may be rolled into a ball. Drop, by small teaspoonfuls, onto 
 
<pb n="44" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=56"/>
a marble or waxed paper, to make small, thick, rather uneven rounds. When cold coat with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and cooled properly. These cakes are very easily coated.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BAKER'S CHOCOLATE "DIVINITY"</purpose>
<list><item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>maple syrup,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>The <ingredient>whites of 2 eggs,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>nut meats,</ingredient> chopped fine,</item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient> broken in pieces.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Let the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> stand on the back of the range, stirring occasionally, until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then cover and let boil five minutes. Remove the cover and let boil to soft crack, 287&#176; F., or, until when tested in <ingredient>water</ingredient> a ball that rattles in the cup will be formed. Add the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and beat over the fire, until the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is melted, then pour in a fine stream onto the <ingredient>whites of eggs,</ingredient> beaten dry, beating constantly meanwhile; add the <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> and pour into a pan lined with waxed paper. In about fifteen minutes lift the candy from the pan (by the ends of the paper left for the purpose) and cut it into small oblongs or squares. The candy must be stirred constantly during the last of the cooking. In cooking without a thermometer one is liable to remove the candy from the fire too soon--if this happens, return, <ingredient>egg whites</ingredient> and all, to the saucepan, set this into a dish of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> and stir constantly until the mixture thickens, then pour into the pan lined with paper. On no account let even a few drops of <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil into the candy.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE NOUGATINES</purpose>
<list><item>1 cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>honey</ingredient> (strained),</item>
<item>Piece of <ingredient>paraffine</ingredient> size of a pea,</item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>The <ingredient>whites of 2 eggs,</ingredient> beaten dry, </item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>almond</ingredient> or <ingredient>English walnut meats,</ingredient> chopped fine,</item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>About 1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient> <ingredient>honey,</ingredient> <ingredient>paraffine</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, stir occasionally and let boil to the hard ball degree, about 248&#176; F. Add the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> before beating them, and gradually pour on part of the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> beating constantly meanwhile with the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> beater; return the rest of the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> to the fire and let boil until it is brittle when tested in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> or to 290&#176; F. Then turn this gradually onto the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beating constantly meanwhile. Return the whole to the saucepan, set over the fire on an <implement>asbestos mat</implement> and beat constantly until it becomes crisp when tested in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Pour into a buttered pan a little larger than an ordinary bread pan and set aside to become cold. When cold cut into pieces about an inch and a quarter long and three-eighths of an inch wide and thick. Coat these with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=57"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PLAIN CHOCOLATE CARAMELS</purpose>
<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/8 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>whole milk,</ingredient> (not skimmed),</item>
<item>2 1/2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>cream of tartar</ingredient> and one cup of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over the fire, stir constantly, and when the mass has boiled a few moments, gradually stir in the rest of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Do not let the mixture stop boiling while the milk is being added. Stir every few moments and cook to 248&#176; F., or, until when tested in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> a hard ball may be formed; add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and beat them thoroughly through the candy, then turn it into two bread pans. When nearly cold cut into squares.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE NUT CARAMELS</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>2 cups of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 or 4 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>English walnut meats,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>, <emph rend="italic">one</emph> cup of the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> over the fire; stir and cook until the mixture boils vigorously, then gradually add the other cup of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Do not allow the mixture to stop boiling while the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is being added. Cook until the thermometer registers 250&#176;F., stirring gently--move the thermometer, to stir beneath it--every four or five minutes. Without a thermometer boil until--when tested by dropping a little in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient>--a hard ball may be formed in the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Remove from the fire, add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> and beat until the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is melted; beat in the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and turn into a biscuit pan, nicely oiled or buttered, to make a sheet three-fourths an inch thick. When nearly cold turn from the pan and cut into cubes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">RIBBON CARAMELS</purpose>
<list><item>CHOCOLATE LAYERS</item>
<item>1 1/4 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>) <emph rend="italic">scant</emph> measure,</item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1-16 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/4 cups of <ingredient>rich milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/4 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract.</ingredient></item>
</list>
<list><item>WHITE LAYER</item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 (scant) a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup, less one tablespoonful, of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>dessicated cocoanut.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>, <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>cream of tartar</ingredient> and the fourth a cup of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over the fire, stir until the mixture boils, then very gradually stir in the rest of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Let cook, stirring occasionally, to 248&#176; F., or until, when tested in <ingredient>water</ingredient> or on a cold marble, a pretty firm ball may be formed. Add the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> mix thoroughly and turn into two well-
 
<pb n="46" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=58"/>
buttered shallow pans. For the white layer, put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> over the fire, stir until boiling, then add the <ingredient>cocoanut</ingredient> and stir occasionally until a soft ball may be formed when a little of the mixture is dropped upon a cold marble. Put this mixture over the fire, to dissolve the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> but do not let it begin to boil until the chocolate layers are turned into the pans. When the white mixture is ready, turn enough of it onto one of the chocolate layers to make a layer about one-third an inch thick. Have the other chocolate layer cooled, by standing in <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> remove it from the pan and dispose above the cocoanut layer. Let stand until cold and firm, then cut in cubes; wrap each cube in waxed paper.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FONDANT</purpose>
<list><item>4 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> </item>
<item>or 3 drops of <ingredient>acetic acid.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> in a saucepan, set on the back part of the range, until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then draw the saucepan to a hotter part of the range, and stir until the boiling point is reached; add the <ingredient>cream of tartar</ingredient> or <ingredient>acid</ingredient> and, with the hand or a cloth wet repeatedly in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> wash down the sides of the saucepan, to remove any grains of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> that have been thrown there. Cover the saucepan and let boil rapidly three or four minutes. Remove the cover, set in the thermometer--if one is to be used--and let cook very rapidly to 240&#176; F., or the soft ball degree. Wet the hand in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and with it dampen a <implement>marble slab</implement> or a large platter, then without jarring the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> turn it onto the marble or platter. Do not scrape out the saucepan or allow the last of the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> to drip from it, as sugary portions will spoil the fondant by making it grainy. When the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is cold, with a metal scraper or a wooden <implement>spatula,</implement> turn the edges of the mass towards the center, and continue turning the edges in until the mass begins to thicken and grow white, then work it up into a ball, scraping all the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> from the marble onto the mass; knead slightly, then cover closely with a heavy piece of cotton cloth wrung out of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Let the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> stand for an hour or longer to ripen, then remove the damp cloth and cut the mass into pieces; press these closely into a <implement>kitchen bowl,</implement> cover with a cloth wrung out of <ingredient>water</ingredient> (this cloth must not touch the fondant) and then with heavy paper. The fondant may be used the next day, but is in better condition after several days, and may be kept almost indefinitely, if the cloth covering it be wrung out of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and replaced once in five or six days. Fondant may be used, <ingredient>white</ingredient> or delicately colored with <ingredient>vegetable
 
<pb n="47" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=59"/>
color-pastes</ingredient> or with <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> as frosting for small cakes, or &#233;clairs or for making candy "centers," to be coated with <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> or with some of the same fondant tinted and flavored appropriately.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">ALMOND CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item>CENTERS</item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>blanched almonds,</ingredient> chopped fine,</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Confectioner's sugar</ingredient> for kneading and shaping.</item>
</list>
<list><item>CHOCOLATE COATING</item>
<item>About 1 cup of <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>Few drops of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> as needed,</item>
<item>Halves of <ingredient>blanched almonds.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Mix the chopped <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> with the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> add <ingredient>confectioner's sugar,</ingredient> a little at a time, and knead the mass thoroughly, on a marble or large platter; shape into a long roll, then cut into small pieces of the same size. Shape these into balls a generous half inch in diameter and leave them about an hour to harden on the outside. Put the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> for the coating and the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> (shaved or broken in pieces) in a <implement>double boiler</implement> (with <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> in the lower receptacle); add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and beat until melted; take out the spoon and put in a dipping fork (a <implement>wire fork</implement> costing about ten cents) beat the <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient> to keep it from crusting and drop in a "center;" with the fork cover it with <ingredient>fondant:</ingredient> put the fork under it and lift it out, scrape the fork lightly on the edge of the dish, to remove superfluous candy, turn the fork over and drop the bon-bon onto waxed paper. Make a design with the fork in taking it from the candy. At once press half of a <ingredient>blanched almond</ingredient> on the top of the candy, or the design made with the fork will suffice. If at any time the coating be too thick, add a few drops of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> If any be left over, use it to coat whole <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> or <ingredient>cherries.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHERRY CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item>CENTERS</item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>candied cherries,</ingredient> chopped fine,</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>fondant.</ingredient></item>
</list>
<list><item>CHOCOLATE COATING</item>
<item>About one cup of <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>Bits of <ingredient>cherry.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Prepare the centers and coat in the same manner as the <ingredient>almond creams.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PEPPERMINTS</purpose>
Melt a little <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> and flavor it to taste with <ingredient>essence of peppermint;</ingredient> leave the mixture white or tint very delicately with <ingredient>green or pink color-paste.</ingredient> With a teaspoon drop the mixture onto waxed paper to make rounds of the same size--about one inch and a quarter in diameter--let these stand in a cool place about one hour. Put about a cup of <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> in a double
 
<pb n="48" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=60"/>
<implement>boiler,</implement> add two ounces of <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and a teaspoonful of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> then stir (over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient>) until the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> and <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> are melted and evenly mixed together; then drop the <ingredient>peppermints,</ingredient> one by one, into the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> mixture, and remove them with the fork to a piece of <implement>oil cloth;</implement> let stand until the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is set, when they are ready to use.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FIG-AND-NUT CHOCOLATES</purpose>
<list><item>5 <ingredient>figs,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 or 4 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>water</ingredient> or <ingredient>sherry wine,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>English walnut meats,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Powdered sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 or 4 ounces of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Remove the stem and hard place around the blossom end of the <ingredient>figs,</ingredient> and let steam, with the <ingredient>water</ingredient> or <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> in a <implement>double boiler</implement> until softened, then add the <ingredient>nuts</ingredient> and chop very fine. Add <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> as is needed to shape the mixture into balls. Melt the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> using enough to secure the shade of brown desired in the coating and add to the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> with the <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Coat the <ingredient>fig</ingredient>-and-<ingredient>nut balls</ingredient> and drop them with the fork onto a piece of <implement>oil cloth</implement> or waxed paper in the same manner as the cherry bon-bons. These may be dipped in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> instead of fondant.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE MARSHMALLOWS</purpose>
Cut the <ingredient>marshmallows</ingredient> in halves, and put them, one by one, cut side down, in <ingredient>chocolate fondant</ingredient> (as prepared for <ingredient>almond and cherry chocolate creams</ingredient>), melted over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and flavored to taste with <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> with the fork, that it may not crust over, lift out the marshmallow, turn it and, in removing the fork, leave its imprint in the <ingredient>chocolate;</ingredient> sprinkle at once with a little <ingredient>fine-chopped pistachio nut meat.</ingredient> To prepare the <ingredient>nuts,</ingredient> set them over the fire in <ingredient>tepid water</ingredient> to cover, heat to the boiling point, drain, cover with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then take them up, one by one, and with the thumb and finger push the meat from the skin.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MAPLE FONDANT ACORNS</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>maple syrup,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 3/4 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Confectioner's sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 or more squares of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>About 1/4 a cup of fine-chopped <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> browned in the oven.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Make fondant of the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> following the directions given for fondant made of <ingredient>granulated sugar</ingredient> (cream of tartar or other acid is not required in maple fondant). Work some of the fondant, adding <ingredient>confectioner's sugar</ingredient> as needed, into cone shapes; let these stand an hour or longer to harden upon the outside. Put a little of
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=61"/>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE PECAN PRALINES.<lb/>(See Page 40.)</caption><description>An oval dish filled with chocolate.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>PEPPERMINTS,<lb/>CHOCOLATE MINTS, ETC.<lb/>(See Page 37.)</caption><description>A waving glass bowl filled with chocolates and candies.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>WALNUT CREAM CHOCOLATES.<lb/>(See Page 50.)</caption><description>A glass bowl with shell print filled with chocolates.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>SMITH COLLEGE FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 41.)</caption><description>Cubes fudge arranged in pyramid form in a decorative rectangular dish.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>ALMOND FONDANT STICKS.<lb/>(See Page 49.)</caption><description>A decorative glass bowl filled with fondant sticks.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="list of illustrations" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=62"/>
<illustration><caption>BAKER'S CHOCOLATE "DIVINITY."<lb/>(See Page 44.)</caption><description>A flowered glass bowl filled with chocolate cubes.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>ALMOND AND CHERRY CHOCOLATE CREAMS.<lb/>(See Page 47.)</caption><description>A raised waving glass bowl filled with chocolates.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>FUDGE HEARTS OR ROUNDS.<lb/>(See Page 42.)</caption><description>Fudge hearts in a shell shaped glass bowl.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>CHOCOLATE NUT CARAMELS.<lb/>(See Page 45.)</caption><description>A decorative plate filled caramels.</description></illustration>
<illustration><caption>MARSHMALLOW FUDGE.<lb/>(See Page 42.)</caption><description>A rectangular dish filled with cubes fudge.</description></illustration>
 
<pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=63"/>
the fondant in a dish over <ingredient>hot water;</ingredient> add <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate</ingredient> and <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> as desired and beat till the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> is evenly mixed through the fondant, then dip the cones in the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and set them on a piece of <implement>oil cloth</implement> or waxed paper. When all are dipped, lift the first one dipped from the paper and dip the base again in the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> and then in the <ingredient>chopped-and-browned almonds.</ingredient> Continue until all have been dipped.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE ALMOND BARS</purpose>
<list><item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>3/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>(1/4 an ounce of <ingredient>paraffine</ingredient> at discretion),</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>blanched almonds,</ingredient> chopped fine,</item>
<item>1/3 the recipe for <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 or 4 ozs. of <ingredient>Baker's Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Melt the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and let boil to about 252&#176; F., or between a soft and a hard ball. Without the paraffine cook a little higher than with it. Add the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> mix thoroughly and turn onto a marble or platter over which <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> has been sifted. Turn out the candy in such a way that it will take a rectangular shape on the marble. When cool enough score it in strips about an inch and a quarter wide, and, as it grows cooler, lift the strips, one by one, to a board and cut them in pieces half or three-quarters of an inch wide. When cold, drop them, <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> side down, in <ingredient>chocolate fondant</ingredient> prepared for "dipping." With the fork push them below the <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient> lift out, drain as much as possible, and set onto <implement>oil cloth.</implement> These improve upon keeping.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">ALMOND FONDANT STICKS</purpose>
<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> A or <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a pound of <ingredient>almond paste,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire. Stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is dissolved. Wash down the sides of the kettle as in making fondant. Let boil to the soft ball degree or to 238&#176; F. Add the <ingredient>almond paste,</ingredient> cut into small, thin pieces, let boil up vigorously, then turn onto a damp marble. When nearly cold turn to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with a wooden <implement>spatula.</implement> It will take considerable time to turn this mixture to <ingredient>fondant.</ingredient> Cover and let stand half an hour. Add the <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and knead it in thoroughly. Add at the same time the <ingredient>vanilla.</ingredient> The <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> must be added warm. At once cut off a portion of the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> and knead it into a round ball; then roll it lightly under the fingers into a long strip the shape and size of a lead pencil; form
 
<pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=64"/>
as many of these strips as desired; cut the strips into two-inch lengths and let stand to become firm. Have ready the <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and in this coat the prepared sticks leaving the surface a little rough.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">ALMOND FONDANT BALLS</purpose>
Roll part of the <ingredient>almond fondant</ingredient> into small balls. Some of the <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> will be left after dipping the <ingredient>almond chocolate sticks.</ingredient> Remelt this over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and in it coat the balls lightly. As each ball is coated with the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> drop it onto a plate of <ingredient>chopped pistachio nut meats</ingredient> or of <ingredient>chopped cocoanut</ingredient> (fresh or dessicated). With a spoon sprinkle the chopped material over the balls.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">WALNUT CREAM-CHOCOLATES</purpose>
<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>granulated sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>condensed milk,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 or 4 tablespoonfuls of thick <ingredient>caramel syrup,</ingredient></item>
<item>A little <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>condensed milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire to boil, stir gently but often, and let cook to the soft ball stage, or to 238&#176; F. Pour on a damp marble and let stand undisturbed until cold; turn to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> then gather into a compact mass; cover with a bowl and let stand for thirty minutes; then knead the <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> put it into a <implement>double boiler;</implement> add the <ingredient>caramel syrup</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> stir constantly while the mixture becomes warm and thin; add a tablespoonful or two of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> if necessary, and drop the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> mixture into impressions made in <ingredient>cornstarch.</ingredient> Use two teaspoons to drop the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> When the candy is cold, pick it from the <ingredient>starch.</ingredient> With a small brush remove the <ingredient>starch</ingredient> that sticks to the candy shapes. Coat each piece with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient> As each piece is coated and dropped onto the <implement>oil cloth,</implement> set half an <ingredient>English walnut meat</ingredient> upon the top.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">TO MOLD CANDY IN STARCH IMPRESSIONS</purpose>
Many candies, especially such as are of some variety of fondant, are thin when warm and solidify on the outside when cold, so that they may be "dipped" or coated with <ingredient>chocolate.</ingredient> To shape candy of this sort, fill a low pan with <ingredient>cornstarch,</ingredient> making it smooth upon the top. Have ready molds made of plaster paris, glued to a thin strip of wood, press these into the <ingredient>cornstarch;</ingredient> lift from the <ingredient>starch</ingredient> and repeat the impressions as many times as the space allows. If molds are not available a thimble, round piece of wood, or the stopper of an oil or vinegar cruet will answer the purpose, though the impressions must be made one at a time.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=65"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE BUTTER CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> </item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>
<item>1/4 a cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 1/2ozs. of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> over the fire; stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then cook to the soft ball degree, or 236&#176; F.; pour on a damp marble and leave until cold; then pour on the <ingredient>Premium Chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and with a <implement>spatula</implement> turn to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> This process is longer than with the ordinary fondant. Cover the <ingredient>chocolate fondant</ingredient> with a bowl and let stand for thirty minutes; knead well and set over the fire in a <implement>double boiler;</implement> add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and stir until melted. The mixture is now ready to be dropped into small impressions in <ingredient>starch;</ingredient> when cold and brushed free of <ingredient>starch</ingredient> dip in <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient> When dropping the chocolate mixture into the <ingredient>starch</ingredient> it should be just soft enough to run level on the top. If too soft it will not hold its shape in coating.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">FONDANT FOR SOFT CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item>2 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>water.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire and stir until boiling, then wash down the sides of the saucepan, cover and finish cooking as in making ordinary fondant. Let cook to 238&#176; F. Turn the syrup onto a damp marble or platter and <emph rend="italic">before it becomes cold</emph> turn to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with a wooden <implement>spatula.</implement> When the fondant begins to stiffen, scrape at once into a bowl and cover with a damp cloth, but do not let the cloth touch the fondant. Use this fondant in the following recipes.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">ROSE CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>Fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Damask rose color-paste,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 to 1 whole teaspoonful of <ingredient>rose extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put a part or the whole of the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> into a <implement>double boiler</implement> over <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> With the point of a toothpick take up a little of the <ingredient>color-paste</ingredient> and add to the <ingredient>fondant;</ingredient> add the <ingredient>extract</ingredient> and stir until the mixture is hot, thin and evenly tinted. With two teaspoons drop the mixture into impressions made in <ingredient>starch;</ingredient> it should be hot and thin enough to run level on top. When the shapes are cold, remove from the <ingredient>starch,</ingredient> brush carefully and coat with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">PISTACHIO CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>Fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Green color-paste,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>almond extract,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Pistachio nuts</ingredient> in slices and halves,</item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
 
<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=66"/>
<p>Using <ingredient>green color-paste,</ingredient> <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and <ingredient>almond extract</ingredient> mold the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> in long shapes. Put a bit of <ingredient>nut</ingredient> in each impression, before filling it with <ingredient>fondant.</ingredient> When firm coat with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> and set half a <ingredient>pistachio nut</ingredient> on top.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">SURPRISE CHOCOLATE CREAMS</purpose>
<list><item><ingredient>Fondant,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Candied or Maraschino cherries,</ingredient></item>
<item>Flavoring of <ingredient>almond or vanilla,</ingredient></item>
<item><ingredient>Chopped peanuts,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Melt the <ingredient>fondant</ingredient> over <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and add the flavoring. Put a bit of <ingredient>cherry</ingredient> in the bottom of each <ingredient>starch impression,</ingredient> then turn in the melted <ingredient>fondant,</ingredient> to fill the impressions and have them level on the top. Let the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> broken in bits, be melted over <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> then add as many <ingredient>chopped peanuts</ingredient> as can be well stirred into it; let cool to about 80&#176; F. and in it drop the creams, one at a time; as coated dispose them on table <implement>oil cloth</implement> or waxed <ingredient>paper.</ingredient></p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE PEANUT BRITTLE</purpose>
<list><item>1 1/2 cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>2 level tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound of <ingredient><emph rend="italic">raw</emph> shelled peanuts,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 level teaspoonful of <ingredient>soda,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/2 a pound or more of <ingredient>Baker's "Dot" Chocolate.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> over the fire; stir till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is dissolved; wash down the sides of the saucepan with a cloth or the fingers dipped in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> cover and let boil three or four minutes, then uncover and let cook to 275&#176; F. (when a little is cooled and chewed it clings but does not stick to the teeth) add the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>peanuts</ingredient> and <emph rend="italic">stir constantly</emph> until the <ingredient>peanuts</ingredient> are nicely browned (or are of the color of well roasted peanuts). Dissolve the <ingredient>soda</ingredient> in the <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>vanilla</ingredient> and the <ingredient>soda</ingredient> and stir vigorously. When the candy is through foaming, turn it onto a warm and well-oiled marble or platter. As soon as it has cooled a little on the edges, take hold of it at the edge and pull out as thin as possible. Loosen it from the receptacle at the center by running a <implement>spatula</implement> under it, then turn the whole sheet upside down, and again pull as thin as possible. Break into small pieces and when cold coat with <ingredient>"Dot" Chocolate</ingredient> prepared as in previous recipes. Half of a <ingredient>roasted peanut</ingredient> may be set upon each piece as coated. Note that the <ingredient>peanuts</ingredient> used in the brittle are raw. The small <ingredient>Spanish peanuts</ingredient> are the best for this purpose. After the <ingredient>peanuts</ingredient> are shelled, cover them with <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> let boil up once, then skim out and push off the skin, when they are ready to use.</p>
</recipe>
 
<pb n="53" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=67"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE POP CORN BALLS</purpose>
<list><item>1 1/2 cup of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>,</item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>3 squares of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient></item>
<item>About 4 quarts of <ingredient>popped corn,</ingredient> well salted.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Set the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>glucose</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, stir until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is melted, then wash down the sides of the saucepan, cover and let boil three or four minutes, then remove the cover and let cook without stirring to the hard ball degree; add the <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and stir constantly until brittle in <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> remove from the fire and, as soon as the bubbling ceases, add the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>vanilla;</ingredient> stir, to mix the <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> evenly through the candy, then pour onto the <ingredient>popped corn,</ingredient> mixing the two together meanwhile. With buttered hands lightly roll the mixture into small balls. Press the mixture together only just enough to hold it in shape. Discard all the hard kernels in the <ingredient>corn.</ingredient> Have the <ingredient>corn</ingredient> warm and in a warm bowl.</p>
</recipe><recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CHOCOLATE MOLASSES KISSES</purpose>
<list><item>2 cups of <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> A <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/3 a cup of <ingredient>glucose</ingredient>, (<ingredient>pure corn syrup</ingredient>),</item>
<item>2/3 a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient></item>
<item>2 tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient></item>
<item>1/4 a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient></item>
<item>4 ounces of <ingredient>Baker's Premium Chocolate,</ingredient></item>
<item>1 tablespoonful of <ingredient>vanilla extract,</ingredient> or</item>
<item>1 teaspoonful of essence of <ingredient>pepper-mint.</ingredient></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Put all the ingredients, save the <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>chocolate</ingredient> and flavoring, over the fire; let boil rapidly to 260&#176; F., or until brittle when tested in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> During the last of the cooking the candy must be stirred constantly. Pour onto an oiled platter or marble; pour the <ingredient>chocolate,</ingredient> melted over <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> above the candy; as the candy cools on the edges, with a <implement>spatula</implement> or the fingers, turn the edges towards the center; continue this until the candy is cold enough to pull; pull over a hook until cold; add the flavoring, a little at a time, during the pulling, cut in short lengths and wrap in waxed paper.</p>
</recipe></chapter>
</body>
<back>
<div type="advertisement">
 
<pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=68"/>
<hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO., Ltd.<lb/>
ESTABLISHED 1780</hd>
<p>THIS House has grown to be the largest of its kind in the world and it has achieved that result by always maintaining the highest standard in the quality of its cocoa and chocolate preparations and selling them at the lowest price for which unadulterated articles of high grade can be put upon the market. Under cover of a similarity in name, trade-mark, label or wrapper, a number of unscrupulous concerns have, within recent years, made attampts to get possession of the great market won by this House, by trading on its good name--selling to unsuspecting consumers goods of distinctly inferior quality by representing them to be the products of the genuine "Baker's." The quantity of goods sold in this way is not so much of an injury to us as the discredit cast upon our manufacturers by leading some consumers to believe that these fraudulent articles are of our manufacture and that we have lowered the high standard maintained for so many years. It is difficult to bring the fraud home to all consumers, as those who are making use of it seek out-of-the-way places where deception will the more easily pass.</p>
<p>We have letters from housekeepers who have used the genuine Baker goods for years, expressing their indignation at the attempts of unscrupulous dealers to foist upon them inferior and adulterated articles by fraudulently representing them to be of our manufacture.</p>
<p>Statements in the press and in the reports of the Pure Food Commissioners show that there are on the market at this time many cocoas and chocolates which have been treated with
 
<pb n="55" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=69"/>
adulterants, more or less injurious to health, for the purpose of cheapening the cost and giving a fictitious appearance of richness and strength. The safest course for consumers, therefore, is to buy goods bearing the name and trade-mark of a well-known and reputable manufacturer, and to make sure by a careful examination that they are getting what they order.</p>
<p><emph rend="bold">Our Cocoa and Chocolate Preparations are ABSOLUTELY PURE--free from coloring matter, chemical solvents, or adulterants of any kind, and are therefore in full conformity to the requirements of all National and State Pure Food Laws.</emph></p>
<p>We have behind us one hundred and twenty-nine years of successful manufacture, and fifty-two highest awards from the great industrial exhibitions in Europe and America.</p>
<p>We ask the cooperation of all consumers who want to get what they order and what they pay for to help us--as much in their own interest as ours--in checking these frauds.</p>
<p align="right" rend="bold">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO., Ltd.</p>
<p align="center" rend="bold">Our registered guarantee under National<lb/>Pure Food Laws is Serial No. 90.</p>
</div>
<div type="advertisement">
 
<pb n="56" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=70"/>
<hd rend="bold" size="larger" align="center">WALTER BAKER &#38; CO.'S<lb/>
Cocoa and Chocolate Preparations</hd>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">BAKER'S BREAKFAST COCOA<lb/>
In 1-5 lb., 1-4 lb., 1-2 lb., 1 lb. and 5 lb. tins</hd>
<p>This admirable preparation is made from selected cocoa, from which the excess of oil has been removed. It is <emph rend="italic">absolutely pure,</emph> and it is <emph rend="italic">soluble.</emph> It has <emph rend="italic">more than three times the strength</emph> of cocoa mixed with starch, arrowroot or sugar, and is, therefore, far more economical. <emph rend="italic">costing less than one cent a cup.</emph> It is delicious, nourishing, strengthening, <emph rend="italic">easily digested</emph>, and admirably adapted for invalids as well as for persons in health.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">No alkalies or other chemicals or dyes are used in its preparation.</emph></p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-Mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">BAKER'S CHOCOLATE<lb/>
In 1-4 and 1-2 lb. cakes, 1 lb. packages, blue wrapper, yellow label</hd>
<p>It is the pure product of carefully selected cocoa beans, to which nothing has been added and from which nothing has been taken away. Unequalled for smoothness, delicacy and natural flavor. Celebrated for more than a century as a nutritious, delicious and flesh-forming beverage. The high reputation and constantly increasing sales of this article have led to imitations on a very extensive scale. To distinguish their product from these imitations Walter Baker &#38; Co., Ltd., have enclosed their cakes and pound packages in a new envelope or case of stiff paper, different from any other package. The color of the case is the same shade of deep blue heretofore used on the Baker packages, and no change has been made in the color (yellow) and design of the label. On the outside of the case, the name of the manufacturer is prominently printed in white letters. On the back of every package a colored lithograph of the trade-mark, "La Belle Chocolati&#200;re" sometimes called the Chocolate Girl, is printed. Vigorous proceedings will be taken against anyone imitating the package.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
 
<pb n="57" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=71"/>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BAKER'S VANILLA CHOCOLATE<lb/>In 1-2 lb. and 1-6 lb. cakes and 5c and 10c packages,</hd>
<p>is guaranteed to consist solely of choice cocoa and sugar, flavored with pure vanilla beans. Particular care is taken in its preparation, and a trial will convince one that it is really a delicious article for eating or drinking. It is the best sweet chocolate in the market. Used at receptions and evening parties in place of tea or coffee. The small cakes form the most convenient, palatable and healthful article of food that can be carried by bicyclists, tourists and students.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">CARACAS CHOCOLATE<lb/>In 1-8 and 1-4 lb. packages</hd>
<p>A delicious article. Good to eat and good to drink. It is one of the finest and most popular sweet chocolates on the market, and has a constantly increasing sale in all parts of the country. If you do not find it at your grocer's, we will send a quarter-pound cake by mail, prepaid, on receipt of 10 cents in stamps or money.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">CENTURY CHOCOLATE<lb/>
In 1-4 lb. packages</hd>
<p>A fine vanilla chocolate for eating or drinking. Put up in very artistic wrappers.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">AUTO-SWEET CHOCOLATE<lb/>In 1-6 lb. packages</hd>
<p>A fine eating chocolate, enclosed in an attractive wrapper with an embossed representation of an automobile in colors.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">GERMAN SWEET CHOCOLATE<lb/>
In 1-4 lb. and 1-8 lb. packages</hd>
is one of the most popular sweet chocolates sold anywhere. It is palatable, nutritious and healthful and is a great favorite with children.
 
<pb n="58" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=72"/>
<emph rend="italic">Beware of imitations. The genuine is stamped: "S. German, Dorchester, Mass."</emph>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark (La Belle Chocolati&#232;re) on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">DOT CHOCOLATE<lb/>In 1-2 lb. cakes; 12 lb. boxes</hd>
<p>A high grade chocolate specially prepared for home-made candies, and for sportsmen's use. If you do not find it at your grocer's write to us and we will put you in the way of getting it.</p>
<p>In "The Way of the Woods--A Manual for Sportsmen" Edward Breck, the author, says:</p>
<p>"Chocolate is now regarded as a very high-class food on account of its nutritive qualities. * * * * * A half cake will keep a man's strength up for a day without any other food. I never strike off from camp by myself without a piece of chocolate in my pocket. Do not, however, have anything to do with the mawkishly sweet chocolates of the candy shops or the imported milk chocolate, which are not suited for the purpose. We have something better here in America in Walter Baker &#38; Co.'s "Dot" brand, which is slightly sweetened."</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">CRACKED COCOA OR COCOA NIBS<lb/>
In 1-2 lb. and 1 lb. packages, and in 6 lb. and 10 lb. bags</hd>
<p>This is the freshly roasted bean cracked into small pieces. It contains no admixture, and presents the full flavor of the cocoa-bean in all its natural fragrance and purity. When properly prepared, it is one of the most economical drinks. Dr. Lankester says cocoa contains as much flesh-forming matter as beef.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">SOLUBLE COCOA</hd>
<p>This is a preparation for the special use of druggists and others in making hot or cold soda. It forms the basis for a delicious, refreshing, nourishing and strengthening drink.</p>
<p>It is perfectly soluble. It is absolutely pure. It is easily made. It possesses the full strength and natural flavor of the cocoa-bean. No chemicals are used in its preparation.</p>
<p rend="italic">The directions for making one gallon of syrup are as follows:</p>
<list><item>8 ounces of soluble cocoa,</item>
<item>8 1/2 pounds of white sugar,</item>
<item>2 1/2 quarts of water.</item>
</list>
 
<pb n="59" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=73"/>
<p>Thoroughly dissolve the cocoa in hot water, then add the sugar, and heat until the mixture boils. Strain while hot. After it has become cool, sugar may be added if desired.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">The Trade is supplied with 1, 4 or 10 lb. decorated canisters.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold">CHOCOLATE FOR CONFECTIONERS' USE</hd>
<p><emph rend="italic">Liquid Chocolates</emph>--plain, sweet, light, medium and dark.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Soluble Cocoa</emph>--for hot or cold soda.</p>
<p rend="italic">Absolutely Pure--free from coloring matter, chemical solvents, or adulterants of any kind, and therefore in full conformity to the requirements of all National and State Pure Food Laws.</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">VANILLA TABLETS</hd>
<p>These are small pieces of chocolate, made from the finest beans, and done up in fancy foil. The packages are tied with colored ribbons, and are very attractive in form and delicious in substance. They are much used for desserts and collations, and at picnics and entertainments for young people. They are strongly recommended by physicians as a healthy and nutritious confection for children.</p>
<p rend="bold">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">COCOA-BUTTER<lb/>
In 1-2 lb. and 1-5 lb. cakes, and in metal boxes for toilet uses</hd>
<p>One-half the weight of the cocoa-bean consists of a fat called "cocoa-butter," from its resemblance to ordinary butter. It is considered of great value as a nutritious, strengthening tonic, being preferred to cod-liver oil and other nauseous fats so often used in pulmonary complaints. As a soothing application to chapped hands and lips, and all irritated surfaces, cocoa-butter has no equal, making the skin remarkably soft and smooth. Many who have used it say they would not for any consideration be without it. It is almost a necessary article for every household.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">COCOA-SHELLS<lb/>
In 1 lb. and 1-2 lb. packages</hd>
<p>Cocoa-shells are the thin outer covering of the beans. They have a flavor similar to but milder than cocoa. Their very
 
<pb n="60" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=74"/>
low price places them within the reach of all; and as furnishing a pleasant and healthy drink, they are considered superior to tea and coffee.</p>
<p>Packed <emph rend="italic">only</emph> in 1 lb. and 1/2 lb. papers, with our label and name on them.</p>
<p rend="bold" align="center">Trade-mark on every package</p>
</subdiv>
<subdiv>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">CACAO DES AZT&#200;QUES<lb/>
In boxes, 6 lbs. each; 1-2 lb. bottles</hd>
<p>A compound formerly known as <emph rend="italic">Racabout des Arabes;</emph> a most nutritious preparation; indispensable as an article of diet for children, convalescents, ladies, and delicate or aged persons. It is composed of the best nutritive and restoring substances, suitable for the most delicate system. It is now a <emph rend="italic">favorite breakfast beverage for ladies and young persons,</emph> to whom it gives freshness and <emph rend="italic">embonpoint.</emph> It has solved the problem of medicine by imparting something which is easily digestable and at the same time <emph rend="italic">free from the exciting qualities</emph> of coffee and tea, thus making it especially desirable for nervous persons or those afflicted with weak stomachs.</p>
<p>It has a very agreeable flavor, is easily prepared, and has received the <emph rend="italic">commendation of eminent physicians</emph> as being the best article known for convalescents and all persons desiring a <emph rend="italic">light, digestable, nourshing and strengthening food.</emph></p>
<illustration><description>A Victorian woman sitting with her head resting on her left hand, her elbow is resting on a tea table. In her right hand is a teacup and on the table is a teapot.</description></illustration>
</subdiv>
</div>
<div type="index">
 
<pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=75"/>
<hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">INDEX TO RECIPES</hd>
<list>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MISS PARLOA'S:</hd>
<item>Plain Chocolate (for Drinking)................................. <ref target="choc010.jpg">8</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate, Vienna Style........................................ <ref target="choc010.jpg">8</ref></item>
<item>Breakfast Cocoa................................................ <ref target="choc011.jpg">9</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Layer Cake........................................... <ref target="choc011.jpg">9</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cake................................................. <ref target="choc012.jpg">10</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Marble Cake.......................................... <ref target="choc012.jpg">10</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Glac&#233; Cake.................................... <ref target="choc012.jpg">10</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Glac&#233;......................................... <ref target="choc013.jpg">11</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Biscuit.............................................. <ref target="choc013.jpg">11</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Wafers............................................... <ref target="choc013.jpg">11</ref></item>
<item>Cindrella Cakes................................................ <ref target="choc013.jpg">11</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate &#233;clairs....................................... <ref target="choc014.jpg">12</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cookies.............................................. <ref target="choc015.jpg">13</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Gingerbread.......................................... <ref target="choc015.jpg">13</ref></item>
<item>Vanilla Icing.................................................. <ref target="choc015.jpg">13</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Icing................................................ <ref target="choc016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Profiteroles......................................... <ref target="choc016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Ice-cream............................................ <ref target="choc016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cream Pies........................................... <ref target="choc016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Mousse............................................... <ref target="choc017.jpg">15</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Charlotte............................................ <ref target="choc017.jpg">15</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Bavarian Cream....................................... <ref target="choc018.jpg">16</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cream................................................ <ref target="choc018.jpg">16</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Blanc-mange.......................................... <ref target="choc018.jpg">16</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cream Renversee...................................... <ref target="choc021.jpg">17</ref></item>
<item>Baked Chocolate Custard........................................ <ref target="choc021.jpg">17</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Souffl&#233;....................................... <ref target="choc022.jpg">18</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Pudding.............................................. <ref target="choc022.jpg">18</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Meringue Pudding..................................... <ref target="choc022.jpg">18</ref></item>
<item>Milton Pudding................................................. <ref target="choc023.jpg">19</ref></item>
<item>Snow Pudding................................................... <ref target="choc023.jpg">19</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Sauce................................................ <ref target="choc023.jpg">19</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Candy................................................ <ref target="choc024.jpg">20</ref></item>
<item>Cream Chocolate Caramels....................................... <ref target="choc024.jpg">20</ref></item>
<item>Sugar &#160; " &#160; " &#160; ....................................... <ref target="choc024.jpg">20</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Creams, No.1......................................... <ref target="choc025.jpg">21</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; " &#160; No.2......................................... <ref target="choc025.jpg">21</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cones................................................ <ref target="choc025.jpg">21</ref></item>
<item>Genesee Bonbons................................................ <ref target="choc026.jpg">22</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate syrup................................................ <ref target="choc026.jpg">22</ref></item>
<item>Refreshing Drinks for Summer................................... <ref target="choc026.jpg">22</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MISS BURR'S:</hd>
<item>Cracked Cocoa.................................................. <ref target="choc027.jpg">23</ref></item>
<item>For Three Gallons Breakfast Cocoa.............................. <ref target="choc027.jpg">23</ref></item>
<item>Vanilla Chocolate with Whipped Cream...................... <ref target="choc027.jpg">23</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Cream Pie............................................ <ref target="choc027.jpg">23</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Filling.............................................. <ref target="choc028.jpg">24</ref></item>
<item>Meringue....................................................... <ref target="choc028.jpg">24</ref></item>
<item>Cocoa Sticks................................................... <ref target="choc028.jpg">24</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Frosting................................................. <ref target="choc028.jpg">24</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Sauce.................................................... <ref target="choc031.jpg">25</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cake..................................................... <ref target="choc031.jpg">25</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Meringue Pudding......................................... <ref target="choc031.jpg">25</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Almonds.............................................. <ref target="choc032.jpg">26</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Coatings............................................. <ref target="choc032.jpg">26</ref></item>
<item>Hot Chocolate Sauce............................................ <ref target="choc032.jpg">26</ref></item>
 
<pb n="62" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=76"/>
<item>Cocoa Sponge Cake.............................................. <ref target="choc032.jpg">26</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Frosting............................................. <ref target="choc032.jpg">26</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cake; or, Devil's Food............................... <ref target="choc033.jpg">27</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Ice-cream............................................ <ref target="choc033.jpg">27</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Whip................................................. <ref target="choc033.jpg">27</ref></item>
<item>Cocoa Marble Cake.............................................. <ref target="choc034.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Marble Cake.......................................... <ref target="choc034.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Jelly................................................ <ref target="choc034.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item>Cottage Pudding................................................ <ref target="choc034.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item>Vanilla Sauce.................................................. <ref target="choc034.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item>Cocoanut Souffl&#200;........................................ <ref target="choc035.jpg">29</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Sauce................................................ <ref target="choc035.jpg">29</ref></item>
<item>Cocoa Biscuit.................................................. <ref target="choc035.jpg">29</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Fudge.................................................... <ref target="choc035.jpg">29</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MISS ROBINSON'S:</hd>
<item>Plain Chocolate (1 quart)...................................... <ref target="choc036.jpg">30</ref></item>
<item>Cocoa Sponge Cake.............................................. <ref target="choc036.jpg">30</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Marble &#160; " &#160; .............................................. <ref target="choc036.jpg">30</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Doughnuts................................................ <ref target="choc036.jpg">30</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Buns..................................................... <ref target="choc037.jpg">31</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. RORER'S:</hd>
<item>Chocolate Cake................................................. <ref target="choc037.jpg">31</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. LINCOLN'S:</hd>
<item>Chocolate Caramels............................................. <ref target="choc037.jpg">31</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MISS FARMER'S:</hd>
<item>Chocolate Nougat Cake.......................................... <ref target="choc037.jpg">31</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Cream Candy.......................................... <ref target="choc044.jpg">34</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. ARMSTRONG'S:</hd>
<item>Chocolate Pudding.............................................. <ref target="choc038.jpg">32</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Charlotte............................................ <ref target="choc038.jpg">32</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Jelly with Crystallized Green Gages............. <ref target="choc038.jpg">32</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. BEDFORD'S:</hd>
<item>Chocolate Crullers............................................. <ref target="choc043.jpg">33</ref></item>
<item>Hot Cocoa Sauce for Ice-cream.................................. <ref target="choc043.jpg">33</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Macaroons............................................ <ref target="choc043.jpg">33</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. EWING'S:</hd>
<item>Creamy Cocoa................................................... <ref target="choc043.jpg">33</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Chocolate............................................... <ref target="choc044.jpg">34</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. HILL'S:</hd>
<item>Cocoa Frapp&#201;............................................ <ref target="choc044.jpg">34</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Puffs................................................ <ref target="choc044.jpg">34</ref></item>
 
<pb n="63" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=77"/>
<hd rend="bold" align="center">MRS. SALZBACHER'S</hd>
<item>Chocolate Hearts............................................... <ref target="choc044.jpg">34</ref></item>
<item>Cocoa Charlotte................................................ <ref target="choc045.jpg">35</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Fudge with Fruit..................................... <ref target="choc045.jpg">35</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Macaroons............................................ <ref target="choc045.jpg">35</ref></item>
<item>Petits Four.................................................... <ref target="choc046.jpg">36</ref></item>
<item>Potato Cake.................................................... <ref target="choc046.jpg">36</ref></item>
<item>Spanish Chocolate Cake......................................... <ref target="choc046.jpg">36</ref></item>
<hd rend="bold">MRS. HILL'S CANDY RECIPES:</hd>
<item>Peppermints, Chocolate Mints, etc.............................. <ref target="choc047.jpg">37</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Caramels Walnuts..................................... <ref target="choc047.jpg">37</ref></item>
<item>"Dot" Chocolate Coatings....................................... <ref target="choc048.jpg">38</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Dipped Peppermints................................... <ref target="choc048.jpg">38</ref></item>
<item>Ginger, Cherry, Apricot and Nut Chocolates................. <ref target="choc048.jpg">38</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Peanut Clusters...................................... <ref target="choc049.jpg">39</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Coated Almonds....................................... <ref target="choc049.jpg">39</ref></item>
<item> &#160; " &#160; Dipped Parisian Sweets............................... <ref target="choc049.jpg">39</ref></item>
<item>Stuffed Dates, Chocolate Dipped................................ <ref target="choc049.jpg">39</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Oysterettes.......................................... <ref target="choc050.jpg">40</ref></item>
<item>Turkish Paste with French Fruit................................ <ref target="choc050.jpg">40</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Pecan Pralines....................................... <ref target="choc050.jpg">40</ref></item>
<item>Vassar Fudge................................................... <ref target="choc053.jpg">41</ref></item>
<item>Smith College Fudge............................................ <ref target="choc053.jpg">41</ref></item>
<item>Wellesley Marshmallow Fudge.................................... <ref target="choc053.jpg">41</ref></item>
<item>Double Fudge................................................... <ref target="choc053.jpg">41</ref></item>
<item>Marbled Fudge.................................................. <ref target="choc054.jpg">42</ref></item>
<item>Fudge Hearts or Rounds......................................... <ref target="choc054.jpg">42</ref></item>
<item>Marshmallow Fudge.............................................. <ref target="choc054.jpg">42</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Dipped Fruit Fudge................................... <ref target="choc055.jpg">43</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Cocoanut Cakes....................................... <ref target="choc055.jpg">43</ref></item>
<item>Baker's Chocolate "Divinity"................................... <ref target="choc056.jpg">44</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Nougatines........................................... <ref target="choc056.jpg">44</ref></item>
<item>Plain Chocolate Caramels....................................... <ref target="choc057.jpg">45</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Nut Caramels......................................... <ref target="choc057.jpg">45</ref></item>
<item>Ribbon Caramels................................................ <ref target="choc057.jpg">45</ref></item>
<item>Fondant........................................................ <ref target="choc058.jpg">46</ref></item>
<item>Almond Chocolate Creams........................................ <ref target="choc059.jpg">47</ref></item>
<item>Cherry Chocolate Creams........................................ <ref target="choc059.jpg">47</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Peppermints.......................................... <ref target="choc059.jpg">47</ref></item>
<item>Fig and Nut Chocolates......................................... <ref target="choc060.jpg">48</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Marshmallows......................................... <ref target="choc060.jpg">48</ref></item>
<item>Maple Fondant Acorns........................................... <ref target="choc060.jpg">48</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Almond Bars.......................................... <ref target="choc063.jpg">49</ref></item>
<item>Almond Fondant Sticks.......................................... <ref target="choc063.jpg">49</ref></item>
<item>Almond Fondant Balls........................................... <ref target="choc064.jpg">50</ref></item>
<item>Walnut Cream Chocolates........................................ <ref target="choc064.jpg">50</ref></item>
<item>To Mold Candy for Dipping...................................... <ref target="choc064.jpg">50</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Butter Creams........................................ <ref target="choc065.jpg">51</ref></item>
<item>Fondant for Soft Chocolate Creams.............................. <ref target="choc065.jpg">51</ref></item>
<item>Rose Chocolate Creams.......................................... <ref target="choc065.jpg">51</ref></item>
<item>Pistachio Chocolate Creams..................................... <ref target="choc065.jpg">51</ref></item>
<item>Surprise Chocolate Creams...................................... <ref target="choc066.jpg">52</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Peanut Brittle....................................... <ref target="choc066.jpg">52</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Pop Corn Balls....................................... <ref target="choc067.jpg">53</ref></item>
<item>Chocolate Molasses Kisses...................................... <ref target="choc067.jpg">53</ref></item>
</list>
</div>
<div type="illustration">
 
<pb n="illustration" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=78"/>
<illustration><description>A dining room where a Victorian lady is serving a gentleman in the foreground, in the background a older couple are chatting in front of a fireplace.</description></illustration>
</div>
<div type="other">
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=79"/>
</div>
<div type="backcover">
 
<pb n="back cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=choc&#38;PageNum=80"/>
<illustration><description>A Victorian woman servant carrying a tray with a teacup and glass on it. The background has two medals on each side of the woman. Other printed information are as such: NO OTHER FOOD PRODUCT HAS A LIKE RECORD (printed above the victorian woman), WALTER BAKER &#38; CO. LTD ESTABLISHED 1780., and 52 HIGHEST AWARDS (printed below the victorian woman).</description></illustration>
</div>
</back>
</cookbook>
