<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<cookbook type="general" class1="generalfood" region="northeast" subregion="New England" bookID="1808engl">
<meta>

<dcTitle>The New-England Cookery, or the art of dressing all kinds of flesh, fish, and vegetables,...</dcTitle>

<dcCreator>Emerson, Lucy</dcCreator>

<dcSubject>Cookery, American -- New England Style.</dcSubject>

<dcDescription>Complete title: The New-England Cookery, or the art of dressing all kinds of flesh, fish, and vegetables, and the best modes of making pastes, puffs, pies, tarts, puddings, custards, and preserves, and all kinds of cakes, from the imperial plumb to plain cake.</dcDescription>

<dcPublisher>Montpelier: Josiah Parks</dcPublisher>

<dcContributor>Electronic edition created by Digital &amp; Multimedia Center, Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003.</dcContributor>

<dcContributor>Supplementary material by Jan Longone, Anne-Marie Rachman, Peter Berg, Yvonne Lockwood, and Val Berryman</dcContributor>

<dcDate>1808</dcDate>

<dcType>Text</dcType>

<dcFormat>xml-external-parsed-entity</dcFormat>

<dcFormat>gif</dcFormat>

<dcFormat>quicktime</dcFormat>

<dcIdentifier>http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/newenglandcookery/engl.xml</dcIdentifier>

<dcSource>OCLC 1084755</dcSource>

<dcLanguage>en</dcLanguage>

<dcRelation>Digitized as part of "Feeding America: The Historic American Cookbook Project." Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003. http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/</dcRelation>

<dcCoverage>United States, New England</dcCoverage>

<dcCoverage>Nineteenth century</dcCoverage>

<dcRights>The book digitized here was published in the United States before 1923 and is in the public domain according to U.S. copyright law. The digital version and supplementary materials are made available for all educational uses.</dcRights>
</meta>

<front>
<div type="frontcover">
<pb n="front cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=1"/>
</div>

<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=2"/>
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=3"/>
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=4"/>
</div>

<div type="titlepage">
<pb n="title page" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=5"/>

<doctitle align="center">THE<lb/><lb/>

<emph rend="bold" size="larger">NEW-ENGLAND COOKERY,</emph><lb/><lb/>

OR THE<lb/><lb/>

ART OF DRESSING<lb/><lb/>

ALL KINDS OF FLESH, FISH, AND VEGETABLES,<lb/><lb/>

AND THE<lb/><lb/>

BEST MODES OF MAKING<lb/><lb/>

PASTES, PUFFS, PIES, TARTS, PUDDINGS, CUSTARDS AND PRESERVES,<lb/><lb/>

AND ALL KINDS OF<lb/><lb/>

<emph rend="italic" size="larger">CAKES,</emph><lb/><lb/>

<emph rend="italic">From the Imperial PLUMB</emph><lb/>

TO PLAIN CAKE.</doctitle><lb/>

<emph rend="italic">Particularly adapted to this part of our Country.</emph><lb/><lb/>

<docauthor align="center">COMPILED BY LUCY EMERSON.</docauthor>

<docimprint align="center">Montpelier:<lb/>

PRINTED FOR JOSIAH PARKS.<lb/>

<emph rend="italic">Proprietor of the work.)</emph><lb/>

++++<lb/>

1808.</docimprint>
</div>

<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=6"/>
</div>

<div type="preface">
<pb n="preface" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=7"/>

<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">PREFACE.</hd>

<p>IT is with diffidence that I come before the public as an Authoress, even to this little work; I have no pretensions to the originality of the whole of the receipts herein contained, it is due to those LADIES who have gone before me.</p>

<p>THE improvement of the rising generation of <emph rend="italic">Females,</emph> in our Country, was the motive which prompted me to this undertaking.</p>

<p>IT is not so much for the <emph rend="italic">Lady</emph> of fashion, and fortune, as for those in the more humble walks of life, who by the loss of parents, or other unfortunate circumstances, are reduced to indigence. - The orphan, tho' left to the care of a virtuous guardian, will find it essentially necessary to have an opinion of her own.</p>

<p>BY having an opinion of her own, I would not be understood to mean an obstinate perseverance in trifles. It must ever remain a check upon the solitary orphan, that while those females who have parents, or brothers, or riches, to defend their indiscretions, that she must solely depend on <emph rend="italic">character.</emph> How important then, that every action,

<pb n="preface" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=8"/>

word, and thought, be regulated by the strictest purity, and every movement meet the approbation of the good and wise. If this treatise should tend in any way to guide the inexperienced Female in the Art of Cooking, and relieve them from that embarrassment, which they must otherwise experience it would be an ample compensation for this undertaking.</p>

<p>THE American Ladies are solicited to cast the veil of charity over those imperfections that may be found. Should any future edition appear, she hopes to render it more valuable. L.E.</p>

<emph rend="italic">MONTPELIER, 21st March, 1808.</emph>

</div>
</front>

<body>
<chapter class1="generalfood">
<pb n="NONE OF THE ABOVE" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=9"/>

<hd align="center" size="larger" placement="heading">DIRECTIONS for procuring the best FLESH, VEGETABLES, &amp;c.</hd>

<emph rend="italic" align="center">How to choose Flesh.</emph><lb/>

<p><ingredient>BEEF.</ingredient> The large stall fed <ingredient>ox beef</ingredient> is the best, it has a coarse open grain, and oily smoothness; dent it with your finger and it will immediately rise again; if old, it will be rough and spungy, and the dent remain.</p>

<p><ingredient>Cow Beef</ingredient> is less boned, and generally more tender and juicy than the ox, in America, which is used to labor.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Mutton,</ingredient></emph> grass-fed, is good two or three years old.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Lamb,</ingredient></emph> if under six months is rich, and no danger of imposition; it may be known by its size, in distinguishing either.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Veal,</ingredient></emph> is soon lost---great care therefore is necessary in purchasing. <ingredient>Veal</ingredient> bro't to market in panniers, or in carriages, is to be preferred to that bro't in bags, and flouncing on a sweaty horse.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Pork,</ingredient></emph> is known by its size, and whether properly fattened by its appearance.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">Fish, how to choose the best in market.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Salmon,</ingredient></emph> the noblest and richest <ingredient>fish</ingredient> taken in fresh water---the largest are the best. They are unlike almost every other <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> are ameliorated by being 3 or 4 days out of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> if kept from heat and the moon, which has much more injurious effect than the sun.</p>

<p>In all great fish-markets, great fish-mongers strictly examine the gills - if the bright redness is exchanged for a low brown, they are stale; but when live <ingredient>fish</ingredient> are brought flouncing into market,

<pb n="6" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=10"/>

you have only to select the kind most agreeable to your palate and the season.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Shad,</ingredient></emph> contrary to the generally received opinion are not so much richer flavored, as they are harder when first taken out of the water; opinions vary respecting them. I have tasted <ingredient>Shad</ingredient> thirty or forty miles from the place where caught, and really conceived that they had a richness of flavor, which did not appertain to those taken fresh and cooked immediately, and have proved both at the same table, and the truth may rest here, that a <ingredient>Shad</ingredient> 36 or 48 hours out of water, may not cook so hard and solid, and be esteemed so elegant, yet give a higher relished flavor to the taste.</p>

<p>Every species generally of <emph rend="italic">salt water Fish,</emph> are best fresh from the water, though the <emph rend="italic">Hannah Hill, <ingredient>Black Fish,</ingredient> <ingredient>Lobster,</ingredient> <ingredient>Oyster,</ingredient> <ingredient>Flounder,</ingredient> <ingredient>Bass,</ingredient> <ingredient>Cod,</ingredient> <ingredient>Haddock,</ingredient></emph> and <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Eel,</ingredient></emph> with many others, may be transported by land many miles, find a good market, and retain a good relish; but as generally, live ones are bought first, deceits are used to give them a freshness of appearance, such as pepperingthe gills, wetting the fins and tails, and even painting the gills, or wetting with animal blood. Experience and attention will dictate the choice of the best. Fresh gills, full bright eyes, moist fins and tails, denotes their being fresh caught; if they are soft, it is certain they are stale, but if deceits are used, your smell must approve or denounce them, and be your safest guide.</p>

<p>Of all fresh water fish, there are none that require, or so well afford haste in cookery, as the <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Salmon Trout,</ingredient></emph> they are best when caught under a fall or cateract - from what philosophical circumstance is yet unsettled, yet true it is, that at the foot of a fall the waters are much colder than at the head; <ingredient>Trout</ingredient> choose those waters; if taken

<pb n="7" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=11"/>

from them and hurried into dress, they are genuinely good; and take rank in point of superiority of flavor, of most other <ingredient>fish.</ingredient></p>
<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Perch</ingredient> and Roach,</emph> are noble pan <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> the deeper the water from whence taken, the finer are their flavors; if taken from shallow water, with muddy bottoms, they are impregnated therewith, and are unsavory.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Eels,</ingredient></emph> though taken from muddy bottoms, are best to jump in the pan.</p>

<p>Most white or soft <ingredient>fish</ingredient> are best bloated, which is done by salting, peppering and drying in the sun, and in a chimney; after 30 or 40 hours drying, are best broiled, and moistened with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> &amp;c.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">Poultry---how to choose.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Chickens,</ingredient></emph> of either kind are good, and the yellow leg'd the best, and their taste the sweetest.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Capons,</ingredient></emph> if young are good, are known by short spurs and smooth legs.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">A <ingredient>Goose,</ingredient></emph> if young, the bill will be yellow, and will have but few hairs, the bones will crack easily; but if old, the contrary, the bill will be red, and the pads still redder; the joints stiff and difficultly disjointed; if young, otherwise; choose one not very fleshy on the breast.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Ducks,</ingredient></emph> are similar to geese.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Wild Ducks,</ingredient></emph> have redder pads, and smaller than the tame ones, otherwise are like the goose or tame duck, or to be chosen by the same rules.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Wood Cocks,</emph> ought to be thick, fat and flesh firm, the nose dry, and throat clear.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Snipes,</emph> if young and fat, have full veins under the wing, and are small in the veins, otherwise like the Woodcock.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Partridges,</ingredient></emph> if young, will have black bills, yellowish legs; if old, the legs look bluish; if old or

<pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=12"/>

stale, it may be perceived by smelling at their mouths.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Pigeons,</ingredient></emph> young, have light red legs, and the flesh of a color, and prick easily - old have red legs, blackish in parts, more hairs, plumper and loose vents - so also of grey or green Plover, Black Birds, Thrash, <ingredient>Lark,</ingredient> and <ingredient>wild Fowl</ingredient> in general.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Hares,</ingredient></emph> are white flesh'd and flexible when new and fresh kill'd; if stale, their flesh will have a blackish hue, like old pigeons, if the cleft in her lip spread much, is wide and ragged, she is old; the contrary when young.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Leveret,</emph> is like the Hare in every respect, that some are obliged to search for the knob, or small bone on the fore leg or foot, to distinguish them.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Rabbits,</ingredient></emph> the wild are the best, either are good and tender; if old there will be much yellowish fat about the kidneys, the claws long, wool rough, and mixed with gray hairs; if young the reverse. As to their being fresh, judge by the scent, they soon perish, if trap'd or shot, and left in pelt or undressed; their taint is quicker than veal, and the most sickish in nature; and will not, like beef or veal be purged by fire.</p>

<p>The cultivation of <ingredient>Rabbits</ingredient> would be profitable in America, if the best methods were pursued - they are a very prolific and profitable animal - they are easily cultivated if properly attended, but not otherwise. - A <ingredient>Rabbit's</ingredient> borough, on which 8000 dollars may have been expended, might be very profitable; but on a smaller scale they would be well near market towns - easier bred, and more valuable.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Butter</ingredient></emph> -- Tight, waxy, yellow <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is better than white or crumbly, which soon becomes rancid frowy. Go into the centre of balls or rolls to prove and judge it; if in <implement>firkin,</implement> the middle is to be

<pb n="9" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=13"/>

preferred, as the sides are frequently distasted by the wood of the <implement>firkin</implement> - altho' <ingredient>oak</ingredient> are used for years. New pine tubs are ruinous to the <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> To have <ingredient>sweet butter</ingredient> in dog days, and thro' the vegetable seasons, send stone pots to honest, neat, and trusty dairy people, and procure it pack'd down in May, and let them be brought in, in the night, or cool rainy morning, covered with a clean cloth wet in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and partake of no heat from the horse, and set the pots in the coldest part of your cellar, or in the ice-house. Some say that May <ingredient>butter</ingredient> thus preserved, will go into the winter use, better than fall made <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Cheese</ingredient></emph> -- The red smooth moist coated, and tight pressed, square edged <ingredient>Cheese,</ingredient> are better than white coat, hard rinded, or bilged; the inside should be yellow and flavored to your taste. Old shelves which have only been wiped down for years are preferable to scoured and washed shelves. Deceits are used by <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-petreing the out side, or colouring with hemlock, cocumberries, or safron, infused into the <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> the taste of either supercedes every possible evasion.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Eggs</ingredient></emph> -- Clear, thin shell'd, longest oval and sharp ends are best; to ascertain whether new or stale - hold to the light, if the <ingredient>white</ingredient> is clear, the <ingredient>yolk</ingredient> regularly in the centre they are good - but if otherwise they are stale. The best possible method of ascertaining, is to put them into <ingredient>water,</ingredient> if they lie on their bilge, they are <emph rend="italic">good</emph> and <emph rend="italic">fresh</emph> - if they bob up on end they are stale, and if they rise they are addled, proved, and of no use.</p>

<hd>We proceed to ROOTS and VEGETABLES - <emph rend="italic">and the best cook cannot alter the first quality, they must be good, or the cook will be disappointed.</emph></hd>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Potatoes,</ingredient></emph> take rank for universal use, profit and

<pb n="10" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=14"/>

easy acquirement. The smooth skin, known by the name of Howe's <ingredient>Potatoe</ingredient>, is the most mealy and richest flavor'd; the yellow rusticoat next best; the red, and red rusticoat are tolerable; and the yellow Spanish have their value - those cultivated from imported <ingredient>seed</ingredient> on sandy or dry loomy lands, are best for table use; though the red or either will produce more in rich, loomy, highly manured garden grounds; new lands and a sandy soil, afford the richest flavor'd; and most mealy <ingredient>Potatoe</ingredient> much depends on the ground on which they grow - more on the species of <ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient> planted - and still more from foreign <ingredient>seeds</ingredient> - and each may be known by attention to connoisseurs; for a good <ingredient>Potatoe</ingredient> comes up in many branches of cookery, as herein after prescribed.---All <ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient> should be dug before the rainy seasons in the fall, well dryed in the sun, kept from frost and dampness during the winter, in the spring removed from the cellar to a dry loft, and spread thin, and frequently stirred and dried, or they will grow and be thereby injured for cookery.</p>

<p>A roast <ingredient>Potatoe</ingredient> is brought on with <ingredient>roast Beef,</ingredient> a Stake, a Chop, or Fricassee; good boiled with a boiled dish; make an excellent <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> for a <ingredient>turkey,</ingredient> <ingredient>water</ingredient> or <ingredient>wild fowl;</ingredient> make a good pie, and a good <ingredient>starch</ingredient> for many uses. All <ingredient>potatoes run out or depreciate in America; a fresh importation of the spanish might restore them to table use.</ingredient></p>

<p>It would swell this treatise too much to say every thing that is useful to prepare a good table, but I may be pardoned by observing, that the Irish have preserved a genuine mealy rich <ingredient>Potatoe</ingredient>, for a century, which takes rank of any known in any other kingdom; and I have heard that they

<pb n="11" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=15"/>

renew their <ingredient>seed</ingredient> by planting and cultivating the <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Seed</ingredient> Ball,</emph> which grows on the vine. The manner of their managing it to keep up the excellency of that root, would better suit a treatise on agriculture and gardening than this - and be inserted in a book which would be read by the farmer, instead of his amiable daughter. If no one treats on the subject, it may appear in the next edition.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Onions</ingredient></emph> - The Medeira white is best in market, esteemed softer flavored, and not so fiery, but the high red, round <ingredient>hard onions</ingredient> are the best; if you consult cheapness, the largest are best; if you consult taste and softness, the very smallest are the most delicate, and used at the first tables. <ingredient>Onions</ingredient> grow in the richest, highest cultivated ground, and better and better year after year, on the same ground.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Beets,</ingredient></emph> grow on any ground, but best on loom, or light gravel grounds; the <emph rend="italic">red</emph> is the richest and best approved; the <emph rend="italic">white</emph> has a sickish sweetness, which is disliked by many.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Parsnips,</ingredient></emph> are a valuable root, cultivated best in rich old grounds, and doubly deep plowed, <emph rend="italic">late sown,</emph> they grow thrifty, and are not so prongy; they may be kept any where and any how, so that they do not grow with heat, or are nipped with frost; if frosted let them thaw in earth; they are richer flavored when plowed out of the ground in April, having stood out during the winter, though they will not last long after and commonly more sticky and hard in the centre.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Carrots,</ingredient></emph> are managed as it respects plowing and rich ground, similarly to <ingredient>Parsnips.</ingredient> The yellow are better than the <ingredient>orange</ingredient> or red; middling siz'd, that is, a foot long and two inches thick at the top end, are better than overgrown ones; they are cultivated best with <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> sowed very thin, and

<pb n="12" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=16"/>

mixed with other <ingredient>seeds,</ingredient> while young, or six weeks after sown, especially if with <ingredient>onions</ingredient> on true <ingredient>onion</ingredient> ground. They are good with <ingredient>veal</ingredient> cookery, rich in soups, excellent with hash, in May and June.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Garlicks,</emph> Though used by the French, are better adapted to the uses of medicine than cookery.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Asparagus</ingredient></emph> - The mode of cultivation belongs to gardening; your business is only to cut and dress, the largest is best, the growth of a day sufficient, six inches long, and cut just above the ground; many cut below the surface, under an idea of getting tender shoots, and preserving the bed; but it enfeebles the root: dig round it and it will be wet with the <ingredient>juices</ingredient> - but if cut above ground, and just as the dew is going off, the sun will either reduce the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> or send it back to nourish the root - it is an excellent vegetable.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Parsley,</ingredient></emph> of the three kinds, the thickest and branchiest is the best, is sown among <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> or in a bed by itself, may be dried for winter use; tho' a method which I have experienced is much better - In September I dig my roots, procure an old thin stave dry <implement>cask,</implement> bore holes an inch diameter in every stave, 6 inches asunder round the <implement>cask</implement> and up to the top - take first a half bushel of rich garden mould and put into the <implement>cask,</implement> then run the roots through the staves, leaving the branches outside, <implement>press</implement> the earth tight about the root within, and thus continue on through the respective stories, till the <implement>cask</implement> is full; it being filled, run an iron bar through the centre of the dirt in the <implement>cask,</implement> and fill it with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it stand on the south and east side of a building till frosty nights, then remove it. (by slinging a roap round the <implement>cask</implement>) into the cellar; where, during the winter, I clip with my scissars the fresh <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> which

<pb n="13" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=17"/>

my neighbors or myself have occasion for; and in the spring transplant the roots in the bed in the garden, or in any unused corner - or let stand upon the wharf or the wash shed. It is an useful mode of cultivation, and a pleasurable tasted <ingredient>herb,</ingredient> and much used in garnishing viands.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Raddish, <ingredient>Salmon</ingredient></emph> colored is the best, <emph rend="italic">purple</emph> next best - <emph rend="italic">white</emph> - <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>turnip</ingredient></emph> - each are produced from southern <ingredient>seeds,</ingredient> annually. They grow thriftiest sown among <ingredient>onions.</ingredient> The <ingredient>turnip</ingredient> Raddish will last well through the winter.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Artichokes</ingredient></emph> - The Jerusalem is best, are cultivated like <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient>, (tho' their stocks grow 7 feet high) and may be preserved like the <ingredient>turnip</ingredient> raddish, or pickled - they like,</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Horse Raddish,</emph> once in the garden, can scarcely ever be totally eradicated; plowing or digging them up with that view, seems at times, rather to increase and spread them.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Cucumbers,</ingredient></emph> are of many kinds; the prickly is best for <ingredient>pickles,</ingredient> but generally bitter; the white is difficult to raise and tender; choose the bright green, smooth and proper sized.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Melons</ingredient></emph> - The <ingredient>Water Melon</ingredient> is cultivated on sandy soils only, above latitude 41 1-2, if a stratum of land be dug from a well, it will bring the first year good <ingredient>Water Melons;</ingredient> the red cored are highest flavored; a hard rine proves them ripe.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Muskmelons,</emph> are various, the rough skinned is best to eat; the short, round, fair skinned, is best for Mangoes.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Lettuce,</ingredient></emph> is of various kinds; the purple spotted leaf is generally the tenderest, and free from bitter - Your taste must guide your market.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Cabbage,</ingredient></emph> requires a page, they are so multifarious. Note, all cabbages have a higher relish that grow on <emph rend="italic">new unmanured grounds;</emph> if grown in an

<pb n="14" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=18"/>

old town and on old gardens, they have a rankness, which at times, may be perceived by a fresh air traveller. This observation has been experienced for years - that Cabbages require new ground, more than <ingredient>Turnips.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic">The Low Dutch,</emph> only will do in old gardens.</p>

<p>The <emph rend="italic">Early Yorkshire,</emph> must have rich soils, they will not answer for winter, they are easily cultivated, and frequently bro't to market in the fall, but will not last the winter.</p>

<p>The <emph rend="italic">Green Savoy,</emph> is fine and tender; and although they do not head like the Dutch or Yorkshire, yet the tenderness of the out leaves is a counterpoise, it will last through the winter, and are high flavored.</p>

<p>The <emph rend="italic">Yellow Savoy,</emph> takes next rank, but will not last so long; all Cabbages will mix, and participate of other species, like Indian Corn; they are culled, best in plants; and a true gardener will, in the plant describe those which will head, and which will not. This is new, but a fact.</p>

<p>The gradations in the Savoy <ingredient>Cabbage</ingredient> are discerned by the leaf; the richest and most scollup'd, and crinkled, and thickest Green Savoy, falls little short of a <emph rend="italic">Collisflower.</emph></p>

<p>The red and redest small tight heads, are best for <emph rend="italic">slaw,</emph> it will not boil well, comes out black or blue, and tinges other things with which it is boiled.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">BEANS.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic">The <ingredient>Clabboard Bean,</ingredient></emph> is easiest cultivated and collected, are good for <ingredient>string beans, will shell - must be poled.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic">The <ingredient>Windsor Bean,</ingredient></emph> is an earlier, good string, or <ingredient>shell Bean.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Crambury Bean,</ingredient></emph> is rich, but not universally approved equal to the other two.</p>
 
<pb n="15" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=19"/>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Frost Bean,</ingredient></emph> is good only to shell.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Six Weeks Bean,</ingredient></emph> is a yellowish <ingredient>Bean,</ingredient> and early brought forward, and tolerable.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Lazy Bean,</ingredient></emph> is tough, and needs no pole.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">English <ingredient>Bean</ingredient></emph> what <emph rend="italic">they</emph> denominate the <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Horse Bean,</ingredient></emph> is mealy when young, is profitable, easily cultivated, and may be raised on wornout grounds; I cannot but recommend the more extensive cultivation of them.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">The small <ingredient>White Bean,</ingredient></emph> is best for winter use, and excellent.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Calivanse,</emph> are run out, a yellow small bush, a black speck or eye, are tough and tasteless, and little worth in cookery, and scarcely bear exportation.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">Peas - Green Peas.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic">The Crown Imperial,</emph> takes rank in point of flavor, they blossom, purple and white on the top of the vines, will run from three to five feet high, should be set in light sandy soil only, or they run too much to vines.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">The <ingredient>Crown Pea,</ingredient></emph> is second in richness of flavor.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">The Rondekaval,</emph> is large and bitterish.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Early Carlton,</emph> is produced first in the season - good.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Marrow</ingredient> Fats,</emph> green, yellow, and is large, easily cultivated, not equal to others.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sugar Pea,</ingredient></emph> needs no bush, the pods are tender and good to eat, easily cultivated.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Spanish Manratto,</emph> is a rich <ingredient>Pea,</ingredient> requires a strong high bush.</p>

<p>All <ingredient>Peas</ingredient> should be picked <emph rend="italic">carefully</emph> from the vines as soon as dew is off, shelled and cleaned without <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and boiled immediately; they are thus the richest flavored.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">Herbs, useful in Cookery.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Thyme,</ingredient></emph> is good in soups and stuffings.</p>
 
<pb n="16" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=20"/>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sweet Marjoram,</ingredient></emph> is used in <ingredient>Turkeys.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Summer Savory,</ingredient></emph> ditto, and in <ingredient>Sausages</ingredient> and <ingredient>salted Beef,</ingredient> and <ingredient>legs of Pork.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sage,</ingredient></emph> is used in <ingredient>Cheese</ingredient> and <ingredient>Pork,</ingredient> but not generally approved.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Parsley,</ingredient></emph> good in <emph rend="italic">soups,</emph> and to <emph rend="italic">garnish <ingredient>roast Beef,</ingredient></emph> excellent with <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the spring.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Penny Royal,</emph> is a high aromatic, although a spontaneous <ingredient>herb</ingredient> in old ploughed fields, yet might be more generally cultivated in gardens, and used in cookery and medicine.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sweet Thyme,</ingredient></emph> is most useful and best approved in cookery.</p>

<hd align="center" rend="italic">FRUITS.</hd>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Pears,</ingredient></emph> There are many different kinds; but the large <ingredient>Bell Pear,</ingredient> sometimes called the <ingredient>Pound Pear,</ingredient> the yellowist is the best, and in the same town they differ essentially.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Hard Winter Pear,</ingredient></emph> are innumerable in their qualities, are good in sauces, and baked.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Harvest</emph> and <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Summer Pear</ingredient></emph> are a tolerable desert, are much improved in this country, as all other <ingredient>fruits</ingredient> are by grafting and inoculation.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Apples,</ingredient></emph> are still more various, yet rigidly retain their own species, and are highly useful in families, and ought to be more universally cultivated, excepting in the compactest cities. There is not a single family but might set a tree in some otherwise useless spot, which might serve the two fold use of shade and <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> on which 12 or 14 kinds of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> trees might easily be engrafted, and essentially <ingredient>preserve</ingredient> the orchard from the intrusion of boys, &amp;c. which is too common in America. If the boy who thus planted a tree, and guarded and protected it in a useless corner, and carefully engrafted different <ingredient>fruits,</ingredient> was to be indulged free access into orchards, whilst the neglectful boy

<pb n="17" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=21"/>

was prohibited - how many millions of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> trees would spring into growth - and what a saving to the union. The nett saving would in time extinguish the public debt, and enrich our cookery.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Currents,</emph> are easily grown from shoots trimmed off from old bunches, and set carelessly in the ground; they flourish in all soils, and make good <ingredient>jellies</ingredient> - their cultivation ought to be encouraged.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Black currents,</emph> may be cultivated - but until they can be dried, and until <ingredient>sugars</ingredient> are propagated, they are in a degree unprofitable.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Grapes,</ingredient></emph> are natural to the climate; grow spontaneously in every state in the union, and ten degrees north of the line of the union. The <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Madeira,</ingredient> Lisbon,</emph> and <emph rend="italic">Malaga</emph> <ingredient>Grapes,</ingredient> are cultivated in gardens in this country, and are a rich treat or desert. Trifling attention only is necessary for their ample growth.</p>

<p>Having pointed out the <emph rend="italic">best methods of judging of the qualities of Viands, Poultry, <ingredient>Fish,</ingredient> Vegetables, &amp;c.</emph> We now present the best approved methods of DRESSING and COOKING them; and to suit all tastes, present the following</p>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">RECEIPTS.</hd>

<emph rend="italic">To Roast Beef.</emph>
<p>THE general rules are, to have a brisk hot fire to hang down rather than to spit, to baste with <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and one quarter of an hour to every pound of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> though tender <ingredient>beef</ingredient> will require less, while old tough <ingredient>beef</ingredient> will require more roasting; pricking with a fork will determine you whether done or not; rare done is the healthiest and the taste of this age.</p>
 
<pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=22"/>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center">Roast Mutton.</purpose>

If a breast let it be cauled, if a leg, stuffed or not, let it be done more gently than beef, and done more; the chine, saddle or leg require more fire and longer time than the breast, &amp;c. Garnish with scraped horse redish, and serve with <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> <ingredient>collisflowers,</ingredient> <ingredient>water-cresses,</ingredient> or boiled <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>caper sauce,</ingredient> mashed <ingredient>turip,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lettuce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Roast Veal.</purpose>

As it is more tender than <ingredient>beef</ingredient> or <ingredient>mutton,</ingredient> and easily scorched, <ingredient>paper</ingredient> it, especially the fat parts, lay it some distance from the fire a while to heat gently, baste it well; a 15 pound piece requires one hour and a quarter roasting; garnish with <ingredient>green parsley</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Roast Lamb.</purpose>

Lay down to a clear good fire that will not want stirring or altering, baste with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> dust on <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> baste with the dripping, and before you take it up, add more <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and sprinkle on a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> shred fine; send to table with a nice sallad, <ingredient>green peas,</ingredient> fresh <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> or a colisflower, or <ingredient>asparagus.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To roast Mutton, Venison fashion.</purpose>

Take a hind quarter of fat <ingredient>mutton,</ingredient> and cut the legs like a haunch; lay it in a pan with the back side of it down; pour a bottle of <ingredient>red wine</ingredient> over it, and let it lie twenty four hours; then spit it, and baste it with the same liquor and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> all the time it is roasting, at a good quick fire and two hours and a half will do it. Have a little good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a boat, and current <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> in another.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To roast a Breast of Mutton with Forc'd-meat.</purpose>

A breast of <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> dressed thus is very good; the <ingredient>forc'd-meat</ingredient> must be put under the skin at the

<pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=23"/>

end, and then the skin pinned down with thorns; before you dredge it, wash it over with a bunch of feathers dipt in <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Garnish with <ingredient>lemon;</ingredient> and put good <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stuff a Turkey.</purpose>

Grate a <ingredient>wheat loaf</ingredient>, one quarter of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> finely chopped, two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> (if the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> be not sufficient,) fill the bird and sew it up.</p>

<p><variation>The same will answer for all <ingredient>Wild Fowl.</ingredient><lb/>
<emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Water Fowls</ingredient></emph> require <ingredient>onions.</ingredient><lb/>

The same ingredients stuff a <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>leg of Veal,</ingredient> fresh <ingredient>Pork,</ingredient></emph> or a <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>loin of veal,</ingredient></emph></variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">How to stuff and roast a Turkey, or Fowl.</purpose>

One pound soft <ingredient>wheat bread,</ingredient> 3 ounces <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> 3 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> a littlesweet <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and some add a gill of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> fill the bird therewith and sew it up, hang down to a steady solid fire, basting frequently with <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and roast until a steam emits from the breast, put one third of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>gravy;</ingredient> dust <ingredient>flour</ingredient> over the bird and baste with the <ingredient>gravy;</ingredient> serve up with boiled <ingredient>onions</ingredient> and <ingredient>cramberry sauce,</ingredient> <ingredient>mangoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>picles</ingredient> or <ingredient>cellery.</ingredient></p>

<p><variation>2. Others omit the <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and add <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> done with <ingredient>potatoes.</ingredient></variation></p>

<p><variation>3. Boil and mash 3 pints <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> wet them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> fill and roast as above.</variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stuff and roast a Goslin.</purpose>

Boil the inwards tender, chop them fine, put double quantity of grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> 4 ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> (and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> if you like) 2 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> moulded into the <ingredient>stuffing,</ingredient> parboil 4 <ingredient>onions</ingredient> and

<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=24"/>

chop them into the <ingredient>stuffing,</ingredient> add <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and roast the bird.</p>

<p>The above is a good <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> for every kind of <ingredient>Water Fowl</ingredient> which requires <ingredient>onion sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To smother a Fowl in Oysters.</purpose>
Fill the bird with dry <ingredient>Oysters,</ingredient> and sew it up and boil it in <ingredient>water</ingredient> just sufficient to cover the bird, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and season to your taste - when done tender, put into a deep dish and pour over it a pint of stewed <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> well buttered and peppered, garnish a <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> with sprigs of <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> or leaves of cellery: a <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> is best with a <ingredient>parsley sauce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stuff a leg of Veal,</purpose>

Take one pound of <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>pork</ingredient> (salted,) one pound grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> chop all very fine, with a handful of <ingredient>green parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> it, add 3 ounces <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and 3 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> (and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> if you like them,) cut the leg round like a ham and stab it full of holes, and fill in all the <ingredient>stuffing;</ingredient> then <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> the legand dust on some <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> if baked in an oven, put into a sauce pan with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> if potted, lay some scewers at the bottom of the pot, put in a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> and lay the leg on the scewers, with a gentle fire render it tender, (frequently adding <ingredient>water,</ingredient>) when done take out the leg, put <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the pot and brown the leg,the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in a seperate vessel must be thickened and buttered and a spoonful of <ingredient>ketchup</ingredient> added.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stuff a leg of Pork to bake or roast.</purpose>

Corn the leg 48 hours and stuff it with <ingredient>sausage meat</ingredient> and bake in an oven two hours and an half or roast.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To alamode a round of Beef.</purpose>

To a 14 or 16 pound round of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> put one

<pb n="21" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=25"/>

ounce <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> 48 hours after stuff it with the following: one and an half pound of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> two pound grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> chop all fine and rub in half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>thyme;</ingredient> lay it on scewers in a large pot, over three pints <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> (which it must occasionally be supplied with,) the steam of which in 4 or 5 hours will render the round tender if over a moderate fire; when tender, take away the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> and thicken with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and boil, brown the round with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> adding <ingredient>ketchup</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine</ingredient> to your taste.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To alamode a round.</purpose>

Take fat <ingredient>pork</ingredient> cut in slices or mince, season it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> and <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> make holes in the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> and stuff it the night before cooked; put some bones across the bottom of the pot to keep from burning, put in one quart clarret <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>water</ingredient> and one <ingredient>onion;</ingredient> lay the round on the bones, cover close and stop it round the top with dough; hang on in the morning and stew gently two hours; turn it, and stop tight and stew two hours more; when done tender, grate a <ingredient>crust of bread</ingredient> on the top and brown it before the fire; scum the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> and serve in a butter boat, serve it with the residue of the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the dish.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make the best Bacon.</purpose>

To each <ingredient>ham</ingredient> put one ounce <ingredient>saltpetre,</ingredient> one pint bay <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> shake together 6 or 8 weeks, or when a large quantity is together, bast them with the liquor every day; when taken out to dry, smoke three weeks with <ingredient>cobs</ingredient> or malt fumes. To every <ingredient>ham</ingredient> may be added a cheek if you stow away a barrel and not alter the composition, some

<pb n="22" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=26"/>

add a shoulder. For transportation or exportation, double the period of <alt synonym1="smoking">smoaking</alt>.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic"><emph rend="italic">To dress a Calves Head.</emph> Turtle fashion.</purpose>

The head and feet being well scalded and cleaned, open the head, taking the <ingredient>brains,</ingredient> wash, pick and cleanse, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> them and put bye in a cloth; boil the head, feet and hartslet one and a quarter, or one and an half hour, sever out the bones,cut the skin and <ingredient>meat</ingredient> in slices, strain the liquor on which boiled and put by; clean the pot very clean or it will burn too, make a layer of the slices, which dust with a composition mode of <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> one spoon, of <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> pulverized, two spoons (<ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> and <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> are most approved) a tea spoon of <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> then dust with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> then a layer of slices with slices of <ingredient>veal</ingredient> and <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> till completed, cover with the liquor, stew gently three quarters of an hour. To make the <ingredient>forced meat</ingredient> balls - take one and an half pound <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> one pound grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> 4 ounces raw <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> mince and season with above and work with 3 <ingredient>whites</ingredient> into balls, one or one and an half inch diameter, roll in flower, and fry in very hot <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till brown, then chop the <ingredient>brains</ingredient> fine and stir into the whole mess in the pot, put thereto, one third part of the fryed balls and a pint of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> or less, when all is heated through take off and serve in <implement>tureens,</implement> laying the residue of the balls and hard boiled and pealed <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> into a dish, garnish with slices of <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To roast a Pig.</purpose>

Spit your <ingredient>pig,</ingredient> and lay it down to a clear fire, kept good at both ends: put into the belly a few <ingredient>sage leaves,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a small <ingredient>crust of bread,</ingredient> and a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>: then sew up the

<pb n="23" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=27"/>

belly: <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it all over very well, and do so till the eyes begin to start. When you find the skin is tight and crisp, and the eyes are dropped, put two plates into the <implement>dripping pan,</implement> to save what <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> comes from it: put a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into a clean coarse cloth, and rub all over it till the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is quite taken off; then take it up into your dish, take the <ingredient>sage</ingredient> &amp;c. out of the belly and chop it small; cut off the head, open it and take out the <ingredient>brains,</ingredient> which chop, and put the <ingredient>sage</ingredient> and <ingredient>brains</ingredient> into half a pint of good <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> with a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> then cut your <ingredient>pig</ingredient> down the back, and lay it flat in the dish: Cut off the two ears, and lay one upon each shoulder; take off the under jaw, cut it in two, and lay one upon each side; put the <ingredient>head</ingredient> between the shoulders; pour the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> out of the plates into your <ingredient>sauce,</ingredient> and then into the dish; send it up to table garnished with <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and if you please, <ingredient>pap sauce</ingredient> in a bason.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame" class2="accompaniments"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF BOILING.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">General rules to be observed in Boiling.</purpose>

BE very careful that your pots and covers are well tinned, very clean, and free from sand. Mind that your pot really boils all the while; otherwise you will be disappointed in dressing any joint, though it has been a proper time over the fire. Fresh <ingredient>meat</ingredient> should be put in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, and <ingredient>salt meat</ingredient> whilst it is cold. Take care likewise to have sufficient room and <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the pot, and allow a quarter of an hour to every pound of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> let it weigh more or less.</p>
</recipe>

<pb n="24" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=28"/>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Beef or Mutton.</purpose>

When your <ingredient>meat</ingredient> is put in, and the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, take care to scum it very clean, otherwise the scum will boil down, stick to your <ingredient>meat;</ingredient> and make it look black. Send up your dish with <ingredient>turnips, greens,</ingredient> <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> or <ingredient>carrots.</ingredient> If it is a leg or <ingredient>loin of mutton,</ingredient> you may also put melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>capers</ingredient> in a boat.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a leg of Pork.</purpose>

A leg of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> must lie in <ingredient>salt</ingredient> six or seven days; after which put it into a pot to be boiled, without using any means to freshen it. It requires much <ingredient>water</ingredient> to swim in over the fire, and also to be fully boiled; so that care should be taken that the fire do not slacken while it is dressing. Serve it up with melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> buttered <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> or greens.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic">N.B.</emph> The other joints of the swine are most commonly roasted.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Pickled Pork.</purpose>

Wash the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> and scrape it clean. Put it in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is cold, and boil it till the rhind is tender. It is to be served up always with boiled greens, and is commonly a <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> of itself to roasted <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> or <ingredient>veal.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Veal.</purpose>

Let the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil, and have a good fire when you put in the <ingredient>meat;</ingredient> be sure to scum it very clean. A <ingredient>knuckle of veal</ingredient> will take more boiling in proportion to its weight, than any other joint, because the beauty is to have all the gristles soft and tender.</p>

<p><variation>You may either send up boiled <ingredient>veal</ingredient> with <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient>: or with <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> and greens.</variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Parsley Sauce.</purpose>

Tie <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> up in a bunch, and boil it till soft; shred it fine, and mix it with melted <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="25" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=29"/>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Calf's Head.</purpose>

The head must be picked very clean, and soaked in a large pan of <ingredient>water</ingredient> a considerable time before it is put into the pot. Tie the <ingredient>brains</ingredient> up in a cloth, and put them into the pot at the same time with the <ingredient>head;</ingredient> scum the pot well; then put in a piece of <ingredient>bacon,</ingredient> in proportion to the number of people to eat thereof. You will find it to be enough by the tenderness of the flesh about that part that joined to the neck. When enough, you may grill it before the fire, or serve with melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>bacon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>greens</ingredient>; and with the <ingredient>brains</ingredient> beat up with a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> in a separate plate, and the <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> slit and laid in the same plate, or serve the <ingredient>brains</ingredient> whole, and the <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> slit down the middle.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Lamb.</purpose>

A leg of <ingredient>Lamb</ingredient> of five pounds will not be boiled in less than an hour and a quarter; and if, as it ought to be, it is boiled in a good deal of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and your pot be kept clean scum'd, you may dish it up as white as a curd. Send it to table with <ingredient>stewed spinach;</ingredient> and melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a boat.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Neat's Tongue.</purpose>

A <ingredient>dried tongue</ingredient> should be soaked over night; when you dress it, put it into <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and let it have room; it will take at least four hours. A green <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> out of the pickle need not be soaked, but it will require nearly the same time. An hour before you dish it up, take it out and blanch it, then put it into the pot till you want it; this will make it eat the tenderer.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Ham.</purpose>

A <ingredient>ham</ingredient> requires a great deal of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> therefore put it into the copper cold, and let it only simmer

<pb n="26" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=30"/>

for two hours, and allow a full quarter of an hour to every pound of <ingredient>ham;</ingredient> by this means your <ingredient>ham</ingredient> will eat tender and well.</p>

<p>A dry <ingredient>ham</ingredient> should be soaked in <ingredient>water</ingredient> over night; a green one does not require soaking. Take care they are well cleaned before you dress them.</p>

<p>Before you send a <ingredient>ham</ingredient> to table take off the <ingredient>rind,</ingredient> and sprinkle it over with <ingredient>bread crumbs,</ingredient> and put it in an oven for a quarter of an hour: or you may crisp it with a hot <implement>salamander.</implement></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Haunch of Venison.</purpose>

<ingredient>Salt</ingredient> the haunch well, and let it lay a week; then boil it with a <ingredient>cauliflower,</ingredient> some <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> young <ingredient>cabbages</ingredient>, and <ingredient>beet-roots;</ingredient> lay your <ingredient>venison</ingredient> in the dish, dispose the garden things round it in separate plates, and send it to table.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Turkey, Fowl, Goose, Duck, &amp;c.</purpose>

<ingredient>Poultry</ingredient> are first boiled by themselves, and in a good deal of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> scum the pot clean, and you need not be afraid of their going to table of a bad colour. A large <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> with a forc'd meet in his craw will take two hours: one without an hour and a half; a <ingredient>hen turkey,</ingredient> three quarters of an hour; a large <ingredient>fowl,</ingredient> forty minutes; a small one, half an hour; a large <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> twenty minutes; a small one, a quarter of an hour. A full grown <ingredient>goose</ingredient> salted, an hour and a half; a large <ingredient>duck</ingredient> near an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="italic">Sauce for a boiled Turkey.</purpose>

Take a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> a blade of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and an <ingredient>anchovy</ingredient>: boil these together and strain them through a sieve, adding a little melted <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="italic">Sauce for a Fowl.</purpose>

<ingredient>Parceley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> or <ingredient>white oyster sauce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="27" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=31"/>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Cod.</purpose>
Gut and wash the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> very clean inside and out, and rub the back bone with a handful of <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> put it upon a <ingredient>fish</ingredient> plate, and boil it gently till it is enough; and remember always to boil the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> along with it. Garnish with scraped <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> small fried <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose rend="italic">Sauce.</purpose>

<ingredient>Oyster sauce,</ingredient> <ingredient>shrimp sauce,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lobster sauce</ingredient> with plain melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> in different boats, and <ingredient>mustard.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil a Cod's Head.</purpose>

After tying your cod's head round with pack-thread, to keep it from flying, put a <implement>fish-kettle</implement> on the fire, large enough to cover it with a little <ingredient>water;</ingredient> put in some <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> sliced; when your <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, lay your <ingredient>fish</ingredient> upon a <implement>drainer,</implement> and put it into the kettle; let it boil gently till it rises to the surface of the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> which it will do, if your kettle is large enough: then take it out, and set it to drain: slide it carefully off your <implement>drainer</implement> into your <implement>fish plate.</implement> Garnish with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> scraped.</p>

<p>Have <ingredient>oyster sauce</ingredient> in one bason, and <ingredient>shrimp sauce</ingredient> in another.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">For dressing dried Codfish.</purpose>

Put the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> first into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and wash it, then hang it over the fire and soak it six hours in scalding <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then shift it into clean <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and let it scald for one hour, it will be much better than to boil.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Salmon.</purpose>

Let it be well scraped and cleansed from scales and blood; after it has lain about an hour in <ingredient>salt and spring water,</ingredient> put it into a <implement>fish-kettle,</implement> with a proportionate quantity of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> and

<pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=32"/>

a bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs.</ingredient> Put it in while the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is luke warm, and boil it gently till enough, or about half an hour, if it be thick; or twenty minutes if it be a small piece. Pour off the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> dry it well, and dish it neatly upon a <implement>fish plate,</implement> in the centre, and garnish the dish with <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> scraped, (as done for roast beef,) or with fried <ingredient>smelts</ingredient> or <ingredient>gudgeons</ingredient>, and with slices of <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> round the rim.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">The <ingredient>sauce</ingredient></emph> to be melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> with and without <ingredient>anchovy;</ingredient> or <ingredient>shrimp</ingredient> or <ingredient>lobster sauce</ingredient> in different basons.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Mackerel.</purpose>

Having cleaned the <ingredient>mackerel</ingredient> well, and soaked them for some time in <ingredient>spring water,</ingredient> put them and the roes into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> with as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as will cover them, and a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Boil a small bunch of <ingredient>fennel</ingredient> along with them, and when you send them up, garnish with the roes, and the <ingredient>fennel</ingredient> shred fine.</p>

<p><emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Sauce.</ingredient></emph> --Grated <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a saucer; melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and <ingredient>green gooseberries</ingredient> boiled, in different basons; or, <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Garden Stuff: French Beans.</purpose>

Take your <ingredient>beans</ingredient> and string them, cut in two and then across, when you have done them all, sprinkle them over with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> stir them together, as soon as your <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils put them in and make them boil up quick, they will be soon done and they will look of a better green than when growing in the garden; if they are very young, only break off the ends, then break in two and dress them in the same manner.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil broad Beans.</purpose>

<ingredient>Beans</ingredient> require a great deal of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and it is not best to shell them till just before they are ready to

<pb n="29" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=33"/>

go into the pot, when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils put them in with some picked <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and some <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> make them boil up quick, when you see them begin to fall they are done enough, strain them off, garnish the dish with boiled <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and send plain <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a cup or boat.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil green Peas.</purpose>

When your <ingredient>peas</ingredient> are shelled and the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, which should not be much more than will cover them, put them in with a few leaves of <ingredient>mint,</ingredient> as soon as they boil put in a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as big as a walnut, and stir them about, when they are done enough, strain them off, and sprinkle in a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> shake them till the <ingredient>water</ingredient> drains off, send them hot to the table with melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a cup or boat.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Asparagus.</purpose>

First cut the white ends off about six inches from the head, and scrape them from the green part downward very clean, as you scrape them, throw them into a pan of clear <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and after a little soaking, tie them up in small even bundles, when your <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, put them in, and boil them quick; but by over boiling they will loose their <ingredient>heads</ingredient>: cut a <implement>slice</implement> of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> for a <ingredient>toast,</ingredient> and <ingredient>toast</ingredient> it brown on both sides; when your <ingredient>asparagus</ingredient> is done, take it up carefully; dip the <ingredient>toast</ingredient> in the <ingredient>asparagus</ingredient> water, and lay it in the bottom of your dish; then lay the heads of the <ingredient>asparagus</ingredient> on it, with the white ends outwards; pour a little melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> over the heads; cut an <ingredient>orange</ingredient> into small pieces, and stick them between for garnish.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To boil Cabbage.</purpose>

If your <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> is large, cut it into quarters; if small, cut it in halves; let your <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil, then put in a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and next your <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> with a little more <ingredient>salt</ingredient> upon it; make your <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil as

<pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=34"/>

soon as possible, and when the stalk is tender, take up your <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> into a <implement>cullender,</implement> or sieve, that the <ingredient>water</ingredient> may drain off, and send it to tables as hot as you can. Savoys are dressed in the same manner.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame">
<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF FRYING.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Beef Steaks.</purpose>

Cut the lean by itself, and beat it well with the back of a knife, fry the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> in just as much <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as will moisten the pan, pour out the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> as it runs out of the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> turn them often and do them over a gentle fire; then fry the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> by itself, and lay upon the lean: --<emph rend="italic">For <ingredient>sauce,</ingredient></emph> put to the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> a glass of <ingredient>red wine,</ingredient> half an <ingredient>anchovy,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a little beaten <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and a <ingredient>shallot</ingredient> cut small; give it two or three little boils, season it with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your palate, pour it over the <ingredient>steak,</ingredient> and send them to table.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Tripe.</purpose>

Cut your <ingredient>tripe</ingredient> into pieces about three inches long, dip them into the <ingredient>yolk</ingredient> of an egg, and a few crumbs of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> fry them of a fine brown, and then take them out of the pan, and lay them in a dish to drain. Have ready a warm dish to put them in, and send them to table, with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> in a cup.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Sausages with Apples.</purpose>

Take half a pound of <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> and six <ingredient>apples;</ingredient> <implement>slice</implement> four about as thick as a crown, cut the other two in quarters, fry them with the <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> of a fine light brown, and lay the <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> in the middle of the dish, and the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> round. Garnish with the quartered <ingredient>apples.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=35"/>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Beef Collops.</purpose>

Cut your <ingredient>beef</ingredient> in thin slices, about two inches long, lay them upon your <implement>dresser,</implement> and hack them with the back of a knife; grate a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over them, and dust on some <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> lay them into a <implement>stew-pan,</implement> and put in as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as you think sufficient for <ingredient>sauce;</ingredient> shred half an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> very fine, and a bundle of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient>: Roll a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and set them over a clear fire till they begin to simmer; shake them together often, but don't let them boil up; after they begin to simmer, ten minutes will do them; take out your <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and dish them up. Garnish the dish with <ingredient>pickles</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Scotch Collops.</purpose>

Dip the slices of <ingredient>lean veal</ingredient> in the <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> that have been beaten up with melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> some grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>lemon-peel.</ingredient> Fry them quick; shake them all the time, to keep the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> from oiling. Then put to them some <ingredient>beef gravy,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> or <ingredient>forced-meat</ingredient> balls. Garnish with <ingredient>sausages</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and slices of broiled or fried <ingredient>bacon.</ingredient></p>

<p><emph rend="italic">Observe,</emph> If you would have the collops white,do not dip them in eggs. And when fried tender but not brown, pour off the liquor quite clean; put in some <ingredient>cream</ingredient> to the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> and give it just a boil up.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Veal Cutlets.</purpose>

Cut a <ingredient>neck of veal</ingredient> into stakes, and fry them in <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> and having made a strong <ingredient>broth</ingredient> of the scrag end, boiled with two <ingredient>anchovies,</ingredient> some <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> some <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> shred very small, and browned with a little burnt <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> put the cutlets and a glass of <ingredient>white wine</ingredient> into this liquor.

<pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=36"/>

Tost them up together: thicken with a bit of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and dish all together; squeeze a <ingredient>Seville Orange</ingredient> over, and strew as much <ingredient>salt</ingredient> on as shall give a relish.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Mutton Cutlets.</purpose>

Take a handful of grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> shred very small, with some <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then take a <ingredient>loin of mutton,</ingredient> cut it into <ingredient>steaks,</ingredient> and let them be well beaten; then take the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs,</ingredient> and rub the <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> all over. Strew on the grated <ingredient>bread</ingredient> with these ingredients mixed together. For the <ingredient>sauce,</ingredient> take <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> with a spoonful or two of claret and a little <ingredient>anchovy.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Eggs as round as Balls.</purpose>
Having a deep frying-pan, and three pints of <ingredient>clarified butter,</ingredient> heat it as hot as for fritters, and stir it with a stick, till it runs round like a whirlpool; then break an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into the middle, and turn it round with your stick, till it be as <ingredient>hard</ingredient> as a poached <ingredient>egg;</ingredient> the whirling round of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> will make it as round as a ball; then take it up with a <implement>slice,</implement> and put it into a dish before the fire; they will keep hot half an hour, and yet be soft; so you may do as many as you please. You may poach them in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> in the same manner.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Trout.</purpose>

Dry them in a cloth, <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them, and fry them in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till they are of a fine brown; fry some <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> green and crisp, melt <ingredient>anchovy</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> with a spoonful of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient> Dish your <ingredient>fish</ingredient> and garnish with fried <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient> You may pour your <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> over the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> or send it in a boat which you please.</p>

<p><variation>In this manner you may fry <ingredient>perch,</ingredient> small pike,

<pb n="33" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=37"/>

jacks, roach, gudgeons, or a chine of fresh salmon.</variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Flat Fish.</purpose>

Dry the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> well in a cloth, rub them over in the <ingredient>yolk of an egg,</ingredient> and dust over some <ingredient>flour</ingredient>: let your <ingredient>oil,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>lard</ingredient> or dripping be ready to boil before you put in the <ingredient>fish;</ingredient> fry them off with a quick fire, and let them be of a fine brown. Before you dish them up, lay them upon a <implement>drainer</implement> before the fire sloping, for two or three minutes, which will prevent their eating greasy.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Oysters.</purpose>

You must make a batter of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> then take your <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and wash them; wipe them dry, and dip them in the batter, then roll them in some crumbs of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> beat fine, and fry them in very hot <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard.</ingredient></p>

<p>Or, beat four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put in a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, and a spoonful of grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> then make it as thick as batter for pancakes, with <ingredient>fine flour;</ingredient> drop the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> in, and fry them brown in clarified <ingredient>beef suet.</ingredient> They are to lie round any dish of fish. Ox-palates boiled tender, blanched, and cut in pieces, then fried in such batter is proper to garnish hashes or fricassees. </p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fry Chickens.</purpose>

Cut your <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> in pieces, half boil them with slices of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> in <ingredient>water</ingredient> sufficient to cover them, then take the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> from the pan and fry them in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till they are a light brown: then add the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> with a spoonful or two of <ingredient>sweet wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> thicken it with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Garnish with sippets within the dish.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame"> 
 
<pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=38"/>

<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF BROILING.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To broil Beef Steaks.</purpose>

LAY your <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> on a <implement>gridiron,</implement> over hot coals. Do not turn them till one side be done enough; and when the other side has been turned a little while, a fine <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> will lie on the top, which you should take care to preserve and lift it altogether with a pair of small tongs, or carefully with a knife and fork, into a hot dish, and put a little piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> under it, which will help to draw out the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></p>

<p>The general Sauce for <ingredient>steaks</ingredient> is, <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> for <ingredient>beef;</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> for <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> and <ingredient>gherkins</ingredient> pickled for <ingredient>mutton.</ingredient> But in the season, I would recommend a good sallad, or <ingredient>green cucumbers,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cellery</ingredient>, for <ingredient>beef</ingredient> and <ingredient>mutton;</ingredient> and <ingredient>green peas</ingredient> for <ingredient>lamb steaks.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To broil Chickens.</purpose>

Slit them down the back, and season them with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> lay them at a great distance, on a very clear fire. Let the inside lay downward, till they are above half done; then turn them, and take great care the fleshy side does not burn; throw over them some fine raspings of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and let them be of a fine brown but not burn. Let your sauce be good gravy with <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> and garnish with <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and the <ingredient>livers</ingredient> broiled, the <ingredient>gizzards</ingredient> cut, slashed, and broiled with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To broil Mackerel.</purpose>

Gutthem, wash them clean, pull out the <ingredient>roe</ingredient> at the neck end, boil it in a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then bruise it with a spoon; beat up the <ingredient>yolk of an egg,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> cut fine, shred <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> 
 
<pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=39"/>

some <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> boiled and chopped fine, a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a few <alt synonym1="crumbs">crums</alt> of <ingredient>bread;</ingredient> mix all well together, and fill the <ingredient>mackerel;</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them well and broil them nicely. Let your sauce be plain <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>catchup</ingredient> or <ingredient>walnut pickle.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To broil Cod's Sounds:</purpose>

You must first lay them in <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> a few minutes; take them out, and rub them well with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> to take off the skin and black dirt, and to make them look white; then put them in <ingredient>water</ingredient> and give them a boil. Take them out and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them well, <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> them, and broil them. When they are enough, lay them in the dish, and pour melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> into the dish. Broil them whole.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF STEWING.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stew Beef Steaks.</purpose>

Half broil the <ingredient>beef steaks,</ingredient> then put them into a <implement>stew pan,</implement> season them with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> according to your palate; just cover them with gravy. Also put in a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Let them stew gently for half an hour, then add the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs</ingredient> beat up, and stir all together for two or three minutes, and serve it up. Garnish with <ingredient>pickles</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> scraped.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stew Chickens.</purpose>

Cut two <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> into quarters, wash them and put them into a clean sauce-pan with a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>red wine,</ingredient> some <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> a bundle of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> and a piece of <ingredient>stale crust of bread.</ingredient> Cover them close, and stew

<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=40"/>

them half an hour. Then put in a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as big as an egg, rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and cover it again close for five or six minutes.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To Stew Pigeons.</purpose>

Stuff the birds with <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> made of <ingredient>ground pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient>: half roast them, then put them in a <implement>stewpan</implement> with a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> some <ingredient>pickled mushrooms</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon peel;</ingredient> when stewed enough, take out the birds, thicken the liquor with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolks of eggs.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To Stew Codfish.</purpose>

Cut your <ingredient>fish</ingredient> in pieces an inch thick, put them into your <implement>stew pan</implement> with <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a few sprigs of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it stew for a few minutes: then add <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> with their sauce strained, a <implement>slice</implement> of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a blade or two of <ingredient>mace</ingredient>: when it is done take the <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> and <ingredient>onion</ingredient> from the <ingredient>fish.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stew Pears.</purpose>

Pare six <ingredient>pears</ingredient> and either quarter them, or do them whole; (they make a pretty dish with one whole, and the rest cut in quarters, and the cores taken out.) Lay them in a deep earthern pot, with a few <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> a piece of <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> a gill of <ingredient>red wine,</ingredient> and a quarter of a pound of fine <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> If the <ingredient>pears</ingredient> are very large, they will take half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>red wine;</ingredient> cover them close with <ingredient>paper,</ingredient> and bake them till they are enough.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To stew Mushrooms.</purpose>

Take fresh <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> clean them well, let their skins be pulled off, and their gills scraped off, if they happen to be sound, or else do not

<pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=41"/>

use them; cut the <ingredient>mushrooms</ingredient> in large pieces, and put them all together in a sauce-pan, without any liquor; cover it close, and let them stew gently, with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> till they are tender, and covered with liquor; then take out your <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> and drain them, or else put some <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> to them, with some <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and when they have boiled up, pour off the sauce, and thicken it with a little <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> some will put in a <ingredient>shallot</ingredient> with the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> but that will spoil the flavor of the <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> which every body desires to <ingredient>preserve.</ingredient></p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="soups">
<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF SOUPS.</hd>

<recipe class1="soups">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Oyster Soup.</purpose>

Have ready a good <ingredient>fish stock,</ingredient> then take two quarts of <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> without the beards; bray the hard part in a morter, with the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of ten <ingredient>hard eggs.</ingredient> Set what quantity of <ingredient>fish stock</ingredient> you shall want over the fire with your <ingredient>oysters;</ingredient> season it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> When it boils, put in the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and let it boil till it is as thick as cream. Dish it up with <ingredient>bread</ingredient> cut in dice.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="soups">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Rice Soup.</purpose>

To two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> put three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> clean picked and washed, with a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> let it be covered very close, and simmer till your <ingredient>rice</ingredient> is tender; take out the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and grate half a <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> beat up the <ingredient>yolks of four eggs,</ingredient> and strain them to half a pint of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and as much pounded <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as will make it palatable, put this to your soup, and stir it very well together: set it over the fire, stiring it till it boils, and is of a good thickness; then send it to table.</p></recipe>

<pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=42"/>

<recipe class1="soups">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Turnip Soup.</purpose>

Pear a bunch of <ingredient>Turnips</ingredient> (save out three or four) put them into a gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with half an ounce of <ingredient>white pepper,</ingredient> an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> stuck with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> three blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> bruised, a good bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> and a large <ingredient>crust of bread.</ingredient> Boil them an hour and a half, then pass them thro' a sieve; clean a bunch of cellery, cut it small, and put it into your <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and liquor, with two of the <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> you saved, and two young <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> cut in dice; cover it close, and let it stew; then cut two <ingredient>turnips</ingredient> and <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> in dice, <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them, and fry them brown in <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> with two large <ingredient>onions</ingredient> cut thin, and fried likewise, put them all into your soup, with some <ingredient>vermacelli</ingredient>; let it boil softly, till your cellery is tender, and your soup is good. Season it with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your palate.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="soups">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Veal Broth.</purpose>

Take about four pounds of <ingredient>scrag of veal</ingredient> cut small, put it in three quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> when the scum rises skim it well, put in two <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> a <ingredient>turnip</ingredient> and three or four blades of <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> stew it gently for two hours, season it with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and strain it off; have ready four ounces of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>water</ingredient> till tender, strain it through a sieve, put it into the <ingredient>broth,</ingredient> and boil it ten minutes; put it in a <implement>tureen,</implement> with a handful of <alt synonym1="crisp">crispt</alt> <ingredient>bread</ingredient> in it.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="soups">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To ragoo a Breast of Veal, called alamode.</purpose>

Put a <ingredient>breast of veal,</ingredient> with an <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> a bundle of <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a blade or two of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and a very little <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> grated into a large <implement>stew-pan,</implement> and just cover it with <ingredient>water;</ingredient> when it grows tender take it up and bone it.</p>

<p>Put the bones into the liquor, and boil them till they make good <ingredient>gravy;</ingredient> then strain it off. Add

<pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=43"/>

to this liquor a quarter of a pint of rich <ingredient>beef gravy,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>truffles</ingredient> and <ingredient>morels</ingredient>, a spoonful of <ingredient>catchup,</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient> While those are boiling together <ingredient>flour</ingredient> the <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> and fry it in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till it comes to be of a fine brown. Then drain off the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and pour the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> to the <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> with a few <ingredient>mushrooms.</ingredient></p>

<p>Boil all together till the liquor becomes rich and thick, cut the <ingredient>sweetbread</ingredient> into four, and spread the pieces and <ingredient>forced-meat</ingredient> balls over the dish, having first laid the <ingredient>veal</ingredient> in the dish, and poured the <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> all over it. Garnish with sliced <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="breadsweets">
<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">TO MAKE PIES.</hd>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Veal Pie.</purpose>

Raise a high round pie, then cut a <ingredient>fillet of veal</ingredient> into three or four fillets, season it with <ingredient>savory seasoning,</ingredient> and a little minced <ingredient>sage</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs;</ingredient> lay it in the pie with slices of <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> at the bottom, and between each piece lay on <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and close the pie. When it is baked and half cold, fill it with <ingredient>clarified butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Venison Pastry.</purpose>

Raise a high round pie, shred a pound of <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> and put it into the bottom; cut your <ingredient>venison</ingredient> in pieces, and season it with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Lay it on the <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> lay on <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> close the pie, and bake it.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Stew Pie.</purpose>

Boil a <ingredient>shoulder of Veal,</ingredient> and cut up, <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> half pound, and slices of raw <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> make a layer of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> and a layer of <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> or <ingredient>biscuit</ingredient> dough into a pot, cover close and stew half an hour in three quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> only.</p></recipe>

<pb n="40" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=44"/>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Sea Pie.</purpose>
Four pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one and an half pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled into paste, wet with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> line the pot therewith, lay in split <ingredient>pigeons,</ingredient> <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> pies, <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> or birds, with slices of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and dust on <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> doing thus till the pot is full or your ingredients expended, add three pints <ingredient>water,</ingredient> cover tight with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and stew moderately two and an half hours.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Chicken Pie.</purpose>

Pick and clean six <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> (without scalding) take out their inwards and wash the birds while whole, then joint the birds, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> the pieces and inwards. Roll one inch thick <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 8, and cover a deep dish, and double at the rim or edge of the dish, put thereto a layer of <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> and a layer of thin slices of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> till the <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> and one and an half pound <ingredient>butter</ingredient> are expended, which cover with a thick <ingredient>paste;</ingredient> bake one and an half hour.</p>
<p><variation>Or if your oven be poor, parboil the <ingredient>chickens</ingredient> with half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and put the pieces with the remaining one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and half the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> into the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and while boiling, thicken the residue of the <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> and when the pie is drawn, open the crust, and add the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center"><emph rend="italic">Minced Pies.</emph> A Foot Pie.</purpose>

Scald neets <ingredient>feet,</ingredient> and clean well, (grass fed are best) put them into a large vessel of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> which change daily during a week, then boil the <ingredient>feet</ingredient> till tender, and take away the bones, when cold, chop fine, to every four pound minced <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> add one pound of <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> and four pound <ingredient>apple</ingredient> raw, and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> chop all together very fine, add one quart of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> two pound of stoned <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and

<pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=45"/>

sweeten to your taste; make use of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No.3--bake three quarters of an hour. </p>

<p>Weeks after, when you have occasion to use them, carefully raise the top crust, and with a round edg'd spoon, collect the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> into a bason, which warm with additional <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices</ingredient> to the taste of your circle, while the crust is also warm'd like a hoe cake, put carefully together and serve up, by this means you can have hot pies through the winter, and enrich'd singly to your taste.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Tongue Pie.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>neat's tongue,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> one third of a pound of <ingredient>Sugar,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> (or half of each) half ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient>--bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 1, in proportion to size.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Minced Pie of Beef.</purpose>

Four pound boiled <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> chopped fine, and salted; six pound of raw <ingredient>apple</ingredient> chopped also, one pound <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> or rich sweet cyder, one ounce <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> two pounds <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 3, three fourths of an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Observations.</purpose>

All <ingredient>meat</ingredient> pies require a hotter and brisker oven than <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> pies, in good cookeries, all <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> should be stoned. As people differ in their tastes, they may alter to their wishes. And as it is difficult to ascertain with precision the small articles of spicery; every one may relish as they like, and suit their taste.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">An egg Pie.</purpose>

Shred the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of twenty <ingredient>hard eggs</ingredient> with the same quantity of <ingredient>marrow</ingredient> and <ingredient>beef-suet;</ingredient> season

<pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=46"/>

it with <ingredient>sweet spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> <ingredient>orange,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon;</ingredient> fill and close the pie.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Apple Pie.</purpose>

Stew and strain the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> to every three pints, grate the peal of a fresh <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> add <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste -- and bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 3.</p>
<p><variation>Every species of <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> such as <ingredient>pears,</ingredient> <ingredient>plums,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberry,</ingredient> <ingredient>black berries</ingredient> may only be sweetened, without <ingredient>spices</ingredient> -- and bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 3.</variation></p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Currant Pies.</purpose>

Take green, full grown <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> add one third their quantity of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> proceeding as above.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A buttered apple Pie.</purpose>

Pare, quarter and core <ingredient>tart apples,</ingredient> lay in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 3 cover with the same; bake half an hour, when drawn, gently raise the top crust, add <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make an Apple or Pear Pie.</purpose>

Make a good <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> crust, lay some round the sides of the dish, pear and quarter your <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and take out the cores; lay a row of <ingredient>apples</ingredient> thick, throw in half the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> you intend for your pie; mince a <gap extent="one word"/> <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> fine, throw in a few <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> here and there one, then the rest of your <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and the rest of your <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> You must sweeten to your palate, and squeeze in a little <ingredient>lemon juice.</ingredient> Boil the peeling of the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> and the cores in <ingredient>fair water,</ingredient> with a blade of <ingredient>mace</ingredient> till it is very good; strain it, and boil the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> with the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> till it is rich; pour it into your pie, put on your upper crust, and bake it. You may put in a little <ingredient>quince</ingredient> or <ingredient>marmalade,</ingredient> if you please.</p>

<p>Thus make a <ingredient>pear</ingredient> pie, but don't put in any

<pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=47"/>

<ingredient>quince.</ingredient> You may <ingredient>butter</ingredient> them when they come out of the oven, or beat up the <ingredient>yolks of two eggs,</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> take off the lid, and pour in the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Cut the crust in little three cornered pieces, stick them about the pie, and send it to table.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make a Cherry, Plumb or Gooseberry Pie.</purpose>

Make a good crust, lay a little round the sides of your dish, throw <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> at the bottom, and lay in your <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> on the top. A few <ingredient>red currants</ingredient> will do well with them; put on your lid, and bake it in a slack oven.</p>

<p><variation>Make a plumb pie the same way, and also a <ingredient>gooseberry</ingredient> pie. If you would have it red, let it stand a good while in the oven after the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> is drown.</variation> A custard is very good with the <ingredient>gooseberry</ingredient> pie.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Apple Tart or Pear Tart.</purpose>

Pare them first, then cut them into quarters, and take the cores out; in the next place cut each quarter across again; throw them so prepared into a sauce-pan, with no more <ingredient>water</ingredient> in it than will just cover the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> let them simmer over a slow fire till they are perfectly tender. Before you set your <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> on the fire, take care to put a good large piece of <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> into the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Have the <implement>patty-pans</implement> in readiness, and strew fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> at the bottom; then lay in the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and cover them with as much of the same <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as you think convenient. Over each <ingredient>tart</ingredient> pour a teaspoonful of <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> and three spoonfuls of the liquor in which they are boiled. Then lay the lid over them, and put them into a slack oven.</p>

<p>If the tarts be made of <ingredient>apricots,</ingredient> &amp;c. you must neither pare them, nor cut them, nor stone them, 
 
<pb n="44" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=48"/>

nor use <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> which is the only material difference between these and other <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>

<p>Observe with respect to perserved tarts, only lay in the <ingredient>preserved fruit,</ingredient> and put a very thin crust over them, and bake them as short a time as possible.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Icing for Tarts.</purpose>

Beat and sift a quarter of a pound of fine <ingredient>loaf sugar.</ingredient> Put it into a morter with the <ingredient>white of one egg</ingredient> that has been well beat up. Add to those two spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and beat all together till it be so thick as just to run, observing to stir it all one way. It is laid on the <ingredient>tart</ingredient> with a brush or small bunch of feathers dipped in the icing. Set the tarts when so done, into a very gentle oven to harden. But take care not to let them stand too long for that will discolour them.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">An Almond Tart very good.</purpose>

To half a pound of <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> blanched, and very finely beat with <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> put a pint of thick <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two large <ingredient>Naples biscuits</ingredient> grated, and five <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> with near half a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> put all into a dish garnished with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and lay slips in diamonds cross the top; bake it in a cool oven; and when drawn out, stick slips of candid <ingredient>citron</ingredient> in each diamond.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Lemon Puffs.</purpose>

Take a pound and a quarter of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> beaten and sifted, and grate the <ingredient>rinds</ingredient> of two <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> and mix well with the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> of two new-laid <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very well, and mix them well with the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel;</ingredient> beat them together an hour and a quarter, then make them up in what form you please; be quick to set them in a moderate oven; do not take off the <ingredient>papers</ingredient> till cold.</p></recipe>

<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=49"/>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Rice Florendine.</purpose>

Soak half pint of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> and swell it in <ingredient>water</ingredient>: then boil it in three pints of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> put half pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in it while it is warm, one pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> fifteen <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and one gill of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to your taste; lay a thin <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> at the bottom of your dish and a thick one round the rim, put in the ingrediences, cut small pieces of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> and lay in chequers on the top, grate a little <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over it and bake it half an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Puff Pastes for Tarts.</purpose>

No. 1. Rub one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> whip 2 <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and add with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and one <ingredient>yolk;</ingredient> make into paste, roll in, in six or seven times one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> flowering it each roll. This is good for any small thing.</p>

<p>No. 2. Rub six pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into <alt synonym1="fourteen">founteen </alt>pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> make a stiff paste.</p>

<p>No. 3. To any quantity of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> rub in three fourths of its weight of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> (12 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a peck) rub in one third or half, and roll in the rest.</p>

<p>No. 4. Into two quarts of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> (salted) wet stiff with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> roll in, in nine or ten times, one and an half pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>

<p>No. 5. One pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three fourths of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> beat well.</p>

<p>No. 6. To one pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> rub in one fourth of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> wet with three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and rolled in a half pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Paste for Sweet Meats.</purpose>

No. 7. Rub one third of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and one pound of <ingredient>lard</ingredient> into two pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> wet with four <ingredient>whites</ingredient> well beaten; weater to make a paste, 
 
<pb n="46" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=50"/>

roll in the residue of <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> in ten or twelve rollings -- bake quick. </p>

<p>No. 8. Rub in one and an half pound of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> to six pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> wet with <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> roll in, in six or eight times, two and an half pounds of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> -- good for a <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> or <ingredient>meat</ingredient> pie.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Royal Paste.</purpose>

No. 9. Rub half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into 1 pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>whites</ingredient> beat to a foam, add two <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> two ounces of fine <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> roll often, rubbing one third, and rolling two thirds of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is best; excellent for tarts and <ingredient>apple</ingredient> cakes.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="breadsweets"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">PUDDINGS.</hd>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Rice Pudding.</purpose>

One quarter of a pound <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> (stired often to keep from burning) and boil quick, cool and add half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> 4 spoons <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> 8 <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> a dish and pour the above composition into it, and bake one and an half hour.</p>

<p>No. 2. Boil 6 ounces <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in a quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> on a slow fire 'till tender, stir in one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> interim <alt synonym1="beat">beet</alt> 14 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add to the pudding when cold with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices</ingredient> to your taste, adding <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or currents, baked as No. 1.</p>
<p>No. 3. Eight spoons <ingredient>rice</ingredient> boiled in two quarts <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> when cooled add 8 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 6 ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices,</ingredient> bake 2 hours.</p>

<p>No. 4. Boil in <ingredient>water</ingredient> half pound ground <ingredient>rice</ingredient> till soft, add 2 quarts <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and scald, cool and add 8 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 6 ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 1 pound <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and a small <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> bake 2 hours.</p>

<p>No. 5. <emph rend="italic">A cheap one,</emph> half pint <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> 2 quarts <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 
 
<pb n="47" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=51"/>

<ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> put cold into into a hot oven, bake two and an half hours.</p>

<p>No. 6. Put 6 ounces <ingredient>rice</ingredient> into <ingredient>water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it swell or soak tender, then boil gently, stiring in a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> when cool stir in a quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> 6 or 8 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, and add <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, bake.</p>

<p>N.B. The mode of introducing the ingredients, is a material point; in all cases where <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> are mentioned it is understood to be well beat; <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and the <ingredient>spices,</ingredient> fine and settled.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Nice Indian Pudding.</purpose>

No. 1. Three pints scalded <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 7 spoons <ingredient>fine Indian meal,</ingredient> stir well together while hot, let stand till cooled; add 7 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> 4 ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> bake one and an half hour.</p>

<p>No. 2. Three pints scalded <ingredient>milk</ingredient> to one pint meal salted; cool, add 2 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 4 ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> it will require two and an half hours baking.</p>

<p> No.3. <ingredient>Salt</ingredient> a pint meal, wet with one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweeten and put into a strong cloth, brass or <implement>bell metal vessel,</implement> stone or earthen pot, secure from wet and boil 12 hours.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Sunderlaud Pudding.</purpose>

Whip 6 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> take half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> one <alt synonym1="pint">point</alt> <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> 4 spoons <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>oil</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter</ingredient> pans, cups or bowls, bake in a quick oven one hour. Eat with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Whitpot.</purpose>

Cut half a loaf of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> in slices, pour three quarts <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 6 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <gap extent="one word"/> pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> put into a dish and cover with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> No.1, bake slow one hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Bread Pudding.</purpose>

One pound soft <ingredient>bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>biscuit</ingredient> soaked in one

<pb n="48" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=52"/>

quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> run thro' a sieve or <implement>cullender,</implement> add 7 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one gill <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> one pound stoned <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> half pint <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> bake three quarters of an hour, middling oven.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Flour Pudding.</purpose>
Seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a tea spoon of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> beat and put to one quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 5 spoons of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> to your taste, bake half an hour, and serve up with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A boiled Flour Pudding.</purpose>
One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 9 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 7 spoons <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put into a strong cloth and boiled three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Cream Almond Pudding.</purpose>
Boil gently a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> (grated) in a quart <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> when cool, beat 8 <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and 3 <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> strain and mix with one spoon <ingredient>flour</ingredient> one quarter of a pound <ingredient>almonds;</ingredient> settled, add one spoon <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and by degrees the cold <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and beat well together; wet a thick cloth and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it, and pour in the pudding, boil hard half an hour, take out, pour over it melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">An apple Pudding Dumplin.</purpose>

Put into <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> quartered <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> lie in a cloth and boil two hours, serve with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Pears, Plumbs, &amp;c.</purpose>

Are done the same way.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic"><emph rend="italic">Potatoe Pudding. </emph>Baked.</purpose>

No. 1. One pound boiled <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient>, one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 10 <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></p>

<p>No. 2. One pound boiled <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> marshed three quarters of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 3 gills <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or

<pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=53"/>

<ingredient>cream</ingredient>, the juice of one <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and the peal grated, half a pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> 7 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (taking out 5 <ingredient>whites,</ingredient>) 2 spoons <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Apple Pudding.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>apple</ingredient> sifted, one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> nine <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>sweet cream,</ingredient> one gill <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> a <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> a <ingredient>green lemon</ingredient> peel grated (if sweet <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of half a <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient>) put on to <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 7-- <ingredient>Currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> and <ingredient>citrons</ingredient> some add, but good without them.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Carrot Pudding.</purpose>

A coffee cup full of boiled and <ingredient>strained carrots,</ingredient> 5 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 2 ounces <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> each, <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> to your taste, baked in a deep dish without <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Crookneck or Winter Squash Pudding.</purpose>

Core, boil and skin a good <ingredient>squash,</ingredient> and bruize it well; take 6 large <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pared, cored, and stewed tender, mix together; add 6 or 7 spoonsful of dry <ingredient>bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> rendered fine as meal, half pint dry <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> 2 spoons of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> 2 do <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> 5 or 6 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten and strained, <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, one spoon <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat all smartly together, bake.</p>

<p><variation>The above is a good receipt for Pompkins, <ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient> or <ingredient>Yams</ingredient>, adding more moistening or <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and to the two laiter a few black or Lisbon <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or dry <ingredient>whortleberries</ingredient> scattered in, will make it better.</variation></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Pompkin.</purpose>

No. 1. One quart stewed and strained, 3 pints <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> 9 beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> laid into <ingredient>paste</ingredient> No. 7 or 8, and with a <implement>dough spur,</implement> cross and chequer it, and baked in dishes three quarters of an hour.</p>
 
<pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=54"/>

<p>No. 2. One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 1 pint pompkin, 4 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> in a crust, bake one hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Orange Pudding.</purpose>

Put sixteen <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> with half a pound <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted, grate in the <ingredient>rinds</ingredient> of two <ingredient>Seville oranges,</ingredient> beat in half pound of fine <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> add two spoons <ingredient>orange water,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> half pint <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two <ingredient>Naples biscuit</ingredient> or the crumbs of a fine loaf, or roll soaked in <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> mix all together, put it into rich <ingredient>puff-paste,</ingredient> which let be double round the edges of the dish; bake like a custard.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make a plain boiled Pudding.</purpose>

Take a pint of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> mix with it six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> will beaten, two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Put this mixture into a cloth or bag. Put it into <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and half an hour will boil it. Serve it up with melted <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Quaking Pudding.</purpose>

Take a <ingredient>penny white</ingredient> loaf grated, two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour of rice,</ingredient> and seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beaten up. Put them in a quart of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>new milk.</ingredient> Season them with <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, and <ingredient>white rose-water.</ingredient> Tie it up, boil it an hour, and then serve it up with melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A fine Biscuit Pudding.</purpose>

Grate three <ingredient>Naples biscuit,</ingredient> and pour a pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over them hot. Cover it close till cold, then add a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yolks of four eggs</ingredient> and two <ingredient>whites</ingredient> beat in a little <ingredient>orange flower</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and half a spoonful of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Mix these well, and boil them in a China bason, tied in a cloth, for an hour. Turn it out of the bason, and serve it up

<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=55"/>

in a dish with melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and some fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> sprinkled over it.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Boiled Plumb Pudding.</purpose>

Shred a pound of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> very fine, to which add three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned, a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a large spoonful of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> some <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten, three spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and five spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Mix them well, and boil them in a cloth three hours. Pour over this pudding melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> when dished.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A hunting Pudding.</purpose>

Mix a pound of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> shred fine with a pound of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> well cleaned, a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned and shred, five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little grated <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> two spoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Mix them well together. Tie it up in a cloth; and boil it full two hours. Serve it up with <ingredient>white wine</ingredient> and melted <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A plain baked Pudding.</purpose>

Boil a quart of <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> then stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> till thick; add half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 6 ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> but not all the <ingredient>whites.</ingredient> Mix them well, put it into a dish buttered, and it will be baked in three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Millet Pudding.</purpose>

Take half a pound of <ingredient>Millet,</ingredient> and boil it over night in two quarts of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> In the morning add six ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> six of melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> seven <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and sweeten to your taste. Add ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> with half the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> and bake it.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Poor Man's Pudding.</purpose>

Take some <ingredient>stale bread;</ingredient> pour over it some hot

<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=56"/>

<ingredient>water</ingredient> till it is well soaked; then <implement>press</implement> out the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and wash the <ingredient>bread;</ingredient> add some powdered <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, and a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> some <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> or sack, <ingredient>Lisbon sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>currants;</ingredient> mix them well together, and lay it in a pan well buttered on the sides; when it is well flatted with a spoon, lay some pieces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> on the top; bake it in a gentle oven, and serve it hot. You may turn it out of the pan when it is cold, and it will eat like a fine cheese-cake.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="eggscheesedairy"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">CUSTARDS.</hd>

<p>1. One pint <ingredient>cream</ingredient> sweetened to your taste, warmed hot; stir in <ingredient>sweet wine,</ingredient> till curdled, grate in <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>

<p>2. Sweeten a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> add <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and six <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> bake in <implement>tea cups</implement> or dishes or boil in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> taking care that it don't boil into the cups.</p>

<p>3. Put a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> to one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> boil well, add six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two spoons of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> -- bake. </p>

<p>4. <emph rend="italic"><ingredient>Boiled Custard</ingredient> -- </emph>One pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> two spoons of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>orange flower water,</ingredient> some <ingredient>mace;</ingredient> boil thick, then stir in sweetening, and lade off into china cups, and serve up.</p>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Rice Custard.</purpose>

Boil a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> a quartered <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> in a quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> add <ingredient>rice</ingredient> (well boiled) while boiling sweeten and flavor with <ingredient>orange</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> putting into cups or dishes, when cooled, set to serve up.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A Rich Custard.</purpose>

Four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beat and put to one quart <ingredient>cream</ingredient>,

<pb n="53" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=57"/>

sweetened to your taste, half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> -- baked.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A sick bed Custard.</purpose>

Scald a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweeten and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> a little, whip three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and stir in, bake on <ingredient>coals</ingredient> in a pewter vessel.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Currant Jelly.</purpose>

Having stripped the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> from the stalks, put them into a stone jar: stop it close; set it in a kettle of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> half way up the jar; let it boil half an hour; take it out, and strain the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> through a coarse <implement>hair sieve.</implement> To a pint of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> put a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> set it over a fine quick clear fire in a <implement>preserving-pan</implement> or <implement>bell mettle skillet.</implement> Keep stirring it all the time till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> be melted; then skim the scum off as fast as it rises.</p>

<p>When the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> is very clear and fine, pour it into earthen or china cups, or <implement>gallipots.</implement> When cold cut pieces of <ingredient>white paper</ingredient> just the bigness of the top of the pot, dip them in <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> lay them on the <ingredient>jelly;</ingredient> then cover the top close with <ingredient>white paper,</ingredient> and prick it full of holes. Set it in a dry place. You may put some in glasses for present use.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Raspberry Giam.</purpose>

Take a pint of <ingredient>currant jelly,</ingredient> and a quart of <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> bruise them well together, set them over a slow fire, keeping it stirring all the time till it boils. Let it boil five or six minutes, pour it into the <implement>gallipots,</implement> <ingredient>paper</ingredient> them as you do the currant jelly, and keep them for use. They will keep for two or three years, and have the full flavor of <ingredient>raspberries.</ingredient></p></recipe>
</chapter>
 
<pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=58"/>

<chapter class1="eggscheesedairy"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">SYLLABUBS.</hd>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make a fine Syllabub from the Cow.</purpose>

Sweeten a quart of <ingredient>cyder</ingredient> with <ingredient>double refined sugar,</ingredient> grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> into it, then <ingredient>milk</ingredient> <gap extent="one word"/> <ingredient>cow</ingredient> into your liquor, when you have thus added what quantity of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> you think proper, pour half a pint or more, in proportion to the quantity of <ingredient>syllabub</ingredient> you make, of the sweetest <ingredient>cream</ingredient> you can get all over it.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make a fine Cream.</purpose>

Take a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> sweeten it to your pallate, grate a little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> put in a spoonful of <ingredient>orange flower water</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> beat up four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and two <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> stir it all together one way over the fire till it is thick, have cups ready and pour it in.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Lemon Cream.</purpose>

Take the juice of four large <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> beaten fine, the <ingredient>whites of seven eggs</ingredient> and the <ingredient>yolk</ingredient> of one beaten very well; mix altogether, strain it, set it on a gentle fire, stiring it all the while and skim it clean, put into it the peel of one <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> when it is very hot, but not to boil; take out the <ingredient>lemon <alt synonym1="peel">peal</alt></ingredient> and pour it into china dishes. </p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="breadsweets"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">CAKES.</hd>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A rich Cake.</purpose>

Take six pounds of the best fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> work it to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with your hands; then throw in by degrees three pounds of <ingredient>double refined sugar,</ingredient> well <alt synonym1="beat">beet </alt> and sifted; mix them well together, then

<pb n="55" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=59"/>

work in three pounds of blanched <ingredient>almonds;</ingredient> and having beaten four pounds of <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and strained them through a sieve, put them in; beat them all together till they are thick and look white. Then add half a pint <ingredient>French brandy,</ingredient> half a pint of sack, a small quantity of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and about two ounces each, of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> with three large <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> all beaten in a morter as fine as possible. Then shake in gradually four pounds of well dried and sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> When the oven is well prepared and a <implement>tin hoop</implement> to bake it in, stir into this mixture (as you put it into the hoop) seven pounds of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> well washed and rubbed, and such a quantity of candid <ingredient>orange,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> in equal proportions as shall be thought convenient. The oven must be quick, and the cake will at least take four hours to bake it; <emph rend="italic">Or,</emph> you may make two or more cakes out of these ingredients. You must beat it with your hands, and the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> must be plumped by pouring upon them <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and drying them before the fire. Put them warm into the cake.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Portugal Cakes.</purpose>

Put a pound of fine <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> beaten, into a bread pan; beat it with your hands till it is very light, and looks curdling; then put thereto a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> very dry; beat them together, fill tin pans, and bake them in a slack oven: You may make <emph rend="italic">seed cakes</emph> the same way, only put in <ingredient>carraway-seeds</ingredient> instead of <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Dutch Cakes.</purpose>

Take five pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>carraway-seeds,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and something more than a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> put into it three quarters

<pb n="56" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=60"/>

of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> then make a hole in the middle of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and put in a full pint of good <ingredient>ale-yeast</ingredient>: pour in the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and make these into a <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> letting it stand a quarter of an hour before the fire to rise; then mould it, and roll it into cakes pretty thin; prick them all over pretty much, or they will blister, and bake them a quarter of an hour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Queen Cakes.</purpose>

Take a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> beat it fine, pour in <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites of 2 eggs,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> 6 spoonfuls of warm <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> and as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will make it up; stir them well together, and put them into your <implement>patty-pans,</implement> being well buttered; bake them in an oven almost as hot as for bread, for half an hour; then take them out and glaze them, and let them stand but a little after the glazing is on to rise.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Uxbridge Cakes.</purpose>

Take a pound of <ingredient>wheat flour,</ingredient> seven pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and four pounds of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> rub your <ingredient>butter</ingredient> cold very well among the meal. Dress the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> very well in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>seasoning,</ingredient> and knead it with so much good and new <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> as will make it into a pretty high <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> After it is kneaded well together, let it stand an hour to rise. You may put half a pound of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> in a cake.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Orange Cake.</purpose>

Take the <ingredient>peels of four oranges,</ingredient> being first pared, and the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> taken out; boil them tender, and beat them small in a marble morter; then take the <ingredient>pulp</ingredient> of them, and two more <ingredient>oranges,</ingredient> the <ingredient>seeds</ingredient> and skins being picked out, and mix them with the peelings that are beaten, set them on the

<pb n="57" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=61"/>

fire, with a spoonful or two of <ingredient>orange-flower water,</ingredient> keeping it stiring till that moister is pretty well dried up; then have ready to every pound of that <ingredient>pulp,</ingredient> four pounds and a quarter of <ingredient>double refined sugar,</ingredient> finely sifted. Make the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> very hot, dry it upon the fire, and then mix it and the <ingredient>pulp</ingredient> together; set it on the fire again, till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> be well melted, but take care it does not boil. You may put in a little peel, shred small or grated; and when it is cold, draw it up in double <ingredient>papers;</ingredient> dry them before the fire, and when you turn them, put two together, or you may keep them in deep glasses or pots, and dry them as you have occasion.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Common Biscuit.</purpose>

Beat up six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> with a spoonful of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and a spoonful of sack; then add a pound of fine <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> and a pound of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> mix these into the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> by degrees, with an ounce of <ingredient>coriander seeds;</ingredient> shape them on white thin <ingredient>paper</ingredient> or tin moulds, in any form you please. Beat the <ingredient>white of an egg,</ingredient> and with a feather rub it over, and dust fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over them. Set them in an oven moderately heated, till they rise and come to a good colour; and if you have no stove to dry them in, put them into the oven at night, and let them stand till morning.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Whigs.</purpose>

Take three pounds and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> rub it into the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> till none of it be seen; then take a pint or more of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> make it very warm, and with a half pint of <ingredient>ale-yeast,</ingredient> make it into a light <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> put in <ingredient>carraway-seeds,</ingredient> and what <ingredient>spice</ingredient> you please; then make it up, and lay it before the fire to rise; after this, work in three quarters of a pound of

<pb n="58" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=62"/>

<ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and then roll them pretty thin into what form you please; put them on tin plates and hold them before the fire to rise again, before you set them in; your oven must be pretty quick.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Buns.</purpose>

Take two pounds of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>ale yeast,</ingredient> with a little sack, and three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten; knead all these together with a little warm <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Lay it before the fire till it rise very light. Then knead into it a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a pound of <ingredient>round carraway comfits,</ingredient> and bake them in <alt synonym1="a">s</alt> quick oven, on floured <ingredient>papers,</ingredient> in what shape you please.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Good Fritters.</purpose>

Mix half a pint of good <ingredient>cream</ingredient> very thick with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> leaving out four <ingredient>whites;</ingredient> add six spoonfuls of sack, and strain them into the <ingredient>cream;</ingredient> put in a little grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> then put in another half pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and beat the batter near an hour; pare and <implement>slice</implement> your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> thin, dip every piece in the batter, and throw them into a pan with boiling <ingredient>lard.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Pan Cakes.</purpose>

Take a pint of thick <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> six spoonfuls of sack and half a pint of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> but only three <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> one grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a very little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> fry these thin in a dry pan.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Plumb Cake.</purpose>

Mix one pound <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> one drachm <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> each, a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> candid, and <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> bleached, 6 pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> (well dryed) beat 21 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and add with 1 quart new <ingredient>ale yeast,</ingredient> half pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> 3 half pints of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="59" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=63"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Plain Cake.</purpose>

Nine pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> 3 pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 3 pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 1 quart emptins, 1 quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 9 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 1 ounce of <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> 1 gill of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> 1 gill of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Another.</purpose>

Three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 1 pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and 6 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> worked into 1 pound of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A rich Cake.</purpose>

Rub 2 pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into 5 pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add 15 <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> (not much beaten) 1 pint of emptins, 1 pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> knead up stiff like <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> cover well and put by and let rise over night.</p>

<p>To 2 and an half pound <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> add 1 gill <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> to soak over night, or if new half an hour in the morning, add them with 1 gill <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and 2 and an half pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> work well and bake as loaf cake, No. 1.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Potatoe Cake.</purpose>

Boil <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient>, <alt synonym1="peel">peal</alt> and pound them, add <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> work with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> shape, as you please, bake and pour over them melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Johny Cake, or Hoe Cake.</purpose>

Scald 1 pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and put to 3 pints of <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> and half pint flower-- bake before the fire. Or scald with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> two thirds of the <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> or wet two thirds with <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> add <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> work up with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> pretty stiff, and bake as above.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Indian Slapjack.</purpose>

One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 1 pint of <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> 4 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 4 spoons of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> beat together, baked on gridles, or fry in a dry pan, or baked in a pan which has been rubed with <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> <ingredient>lard</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="60" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=64"/>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Loaf Cake.</purpose>

No. 1. Rub 6 pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 2 pound of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> 3 pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into 12 pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add 18 <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 1 quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 2 ounces of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> two small <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> a <implement>tea cup</implement> of <ingredient>coriander seed,</ingredient> each pounded fine and sifted, add 1 pint of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> 6 pound of stoned <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> 1 pint of <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, first having dried your flower in the oven, dry and roll the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> fine, rub your <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> half an hour, it will render the cake much whiter and lighter, heat the oven with dry wood, for one and an half hours, if large pans be used, it will then require 2 hours baking, and in proportion for smaller loaves. To frost it. Whip six <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> during the baking, add 3 pound of sifted <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> and put on thick, as it comes hot from the oven. Some return the frosted loaf into the oven, it injures and yellows it, if the frosting be put on immediately it does best without being returned into the oven.</p>

<p>No. 2. Rub 4 pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 3 and an half pound of <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> (half <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and half <ingredient>lard</ingredient>) into 9 pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> 1 dozen of <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> 2 ounces of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> 1 pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> 3 spoonfuls <ingredient>coriander seed,</ingredient> 3 gills of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> 1 gill of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> 3 gills of <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, 4 pounds of <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient></p>

<p>No. 3. Six pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two and an half pound of <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> (half <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half <ingredient>lard</ingredient>) six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and one ounce of <ingredient>coriander seed,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>emptins,</ingredient> two gills <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and three pounds of <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient></p>

<p>No. 4. Five pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> 2 and an half pounds of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> two and an half pounds of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> fifteen <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, one ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one gill <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> one gill of <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> -- baked like No. 1.</p></recipe>

<pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=65"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Another Plain Cake.</purpose>

No. 5. Two quarts <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three pound of shortning, warmed hot, add a quart of sweet cyder, this curdle, add eighteen <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> and <ingredient>orange</ingredient> to your taste, or <ingredient>fennel,</ingredient> carroway or <ingredient>coriander seeds;</ingredient> put to nine pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three pints <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, and bake well.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Cookies.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> boiled slowly in half pint watar, scum well and cool, add two tea spoons <ingredient>pearl ash</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> then two and half pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> rub in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and two large spoons of finely powdered <ingredient>coriander seed,</ingredient> wet with above; make rolls half an inch thick and cut to the shape you please; bake fifteen or twenty minutes in a slack oven--good three weeks.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Another Christmas Cookey.</purpose>

To three pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sprinkle a <implement>tea cup</implement> of fine powdered <ingredient>coriander seed,</ingredient> rub in one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and one and half pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> dissolve three tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>pearl ash</ingredient> in a <implement>tea cup</implement> of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> kneed all together well, roll three quarters of an inch think, and cut or stamp into shape and size you please, bake slowly fifteen or twenty minutes; though hard and dry at first, if put into an earthen pot, and dry cellar, or damp room, they will be finer, softer and better when six months old.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Molasses Gingerbread.</purpose>

One table spoon of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> some <ingredient>coriander</ingredient> or <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> put to four tea spoons <ingredient>pearl ash,</ingredient> dissolved in half pint <ingredient>water,</ingredient> four pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> (if in summer rub in the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> if in winter, warm the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and pour to the spiced <ingredient>flour,</ingredient>) knead well 'till stiff, the more the better, the lighter and whiter it will be; bake

<pb n="62" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=66"/>

brisk fifteen minutes; don't scorch; before it is put in, wash it with <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> beat together.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Gingerbread Cakes, or butter and sugar Gingerbread.</purpose>

Three pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> two ounces <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three small spoons <ingredient>pearl ash</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> knead it stiff, shape it to your fancy, bake fifteen minutes.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Soft Gingerbread to be baked in pans.</purpose>
Rub three pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> into four pounds <ingredient>flour</ingredient> add twenty <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> four <alt synonym1="spoons">spooos</alt> <ingredient>rosewater,</ingredient> bake as No. 1.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Butter drop do.</purpose>

Rub one quarter of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> sprinkle with <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> into one pound and a quarter <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one glass <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> bake as No. 1.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Gingerbread.</purpose>

Three pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> quarter pound <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one glass <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> rub into three pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> bake as No. 1.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A cheap seed Cake,</purpose>

Rub one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half an ounce <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> into four quarts <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> into which put one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> melted in one pint <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> nine <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one gill <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, (<ingredient>carraway seed</ingredient> and <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> if you please) make into two loaves, bake one and an half hour.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Queens Cake.</purpose>

Whip half pound <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> add one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <alt synonym1="glass">glaas</alt> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> half gill <ingredient>rosewater,</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices</ingredient> to your taste, all worked in

<pb n="63" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=67"/>

to one and a quarter pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> put into pans cover with <ingredient>paper,</ingredient> and bake in a quick well heat oven, twelve or sixteen minutes.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Pound Cake.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound or ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> one gill, <ingredient>spices</ingredient> to your taste; watch it well, it will bake in a slow oven in fifteen minutes.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Another (called) pound Cake.</purpose>

Work three quarters of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound of good <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 'till very white, whip ten <ingredient>whites</ingredient> to a foam, add the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and beat together, add one spoon <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and put the whole to one and a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> if yet too soft add <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and bake slowly.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Soft cakes in little pans.</purpose>

One and half pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> rubbed into two pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add one glass <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one do. <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> eighteen <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and a <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A light cake to bake in small cups.</purpose>

Half a pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> rubbed into two pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one glass <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one do. <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> two do. <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Shrewsbury Cake.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> mixed and beat with your hand, till very light, put the composition to one pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> roll it into small cakes--bake with a light oven.</p>

<p>N. B. In all cases where <ingredient>spices</ingredient> are named, it is supposed that they be pounded fine and sifted; <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> must be dried and rolled fine; <ingredient>flour</ingredient> dried in an oven; <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beat or whipped into a raging foam.</p></recipe>

<pb n="64" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=68"/>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Diet Bread.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> nine <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beat for an hour, add to fourteen ounces, <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one spoon <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> one do. <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> or <ingredient>coriander,</ingredient> bake quick.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Lemon Biscuit.</purpose>

Beat the <ingredient>yolks of ten eggs</ingredient> and the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> of five well together, with four spoonfuls of <ingredient>orange flower water,</ingredient> till they of a high froth, then put in in a pound of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> beat and sifted, beat it one way for three quarters of an hour; put in half a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and grate in the <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of two <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> and put in the <ingredient>pulp</ingredient> of a small one, beat them well; <ingredient>butter</ingredient> your tin moulds and put it in, sift a little fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over them and put them in a quick oven, but do not stop the mouth up at first for fear they should scroch.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Spunge Biscuit.</purpose>

Beat the <ingredient>yolks of twelve eggs</ingredient> for half an hour, then put in a pound and an half of fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> beat and sifted, <implement>whisk</implement> it well till you see it rise in bubbles, then beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> to a strong froth, and <implement>whisk</implement> them well with your <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks;</ingredient> beat in a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of two <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> grated, <ingredient>butter</ingredient> your tin moulds, put them in, and sift fine powder <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over them; put them in a hot oven, but do not stop the mout of it at first; they will take half an hour baking.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Biscuit.</purpose>

One pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> wet with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and break while the oven is heating, and in the same proportion.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Butter Biscuit.</purpose>

One pint of each <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and emptins, laid into <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in sponges; next morning add one pound <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted, not hot, and knead into as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will with another pint of warmed <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> be of a sufficient consistance to make it soft--some melt the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="65" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=69"/>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">RUSK. -- <emph rend="italic">To make.</emph></purpose>

No. 1 Rub in half pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> to four pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add one pint <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>; when risen well, bake in pans ten minutes, fast.</p>

<p>No. 2 One pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> rubbed into five pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>emptins</ingredient> and wet with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sufficient to bake as above.</p>

<p>No. 3 One pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> rubbed into six or eight pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, wet soft with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and bake.</p>

<p>No. 4. P.C. rusk. Put fifteen <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to four pounds <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and make into large <ingredient>biscuit;</ingredient> and bake double, or one top of another.</p>

<p>No. 5. One pint <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, to be laid over night in spunge, in morning, melt three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> in another pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> add luke warm, and beat till it rise well.</p>

<p>No. 6. Three quarters of a pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> put as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as they will wet, a <alt synonym1="spoon">fpoon</alt> of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one gill <ingredient>emptins</ingredient>, let it stand till very puffy or light; roll into small cakes and let it stand on oiled tins while the oven is heating, bake fifteen minute in a quick oven, then wash the top with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites</ingredient> while hot.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">A butter drop.</purpose>

Four <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> two <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound <alt synonym1="butter">bntter</alt>, one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two spoons <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> bake it in tin pans.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="accompaniments">

<pb n="66" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=70"/>

<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">PRESERVES</hd>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To keep Green Peas till Christmas.</purpose>

Take fine young <ingredient>peas,</ingredient> shell them, throw them into a <implement>cullender</implement> to drain, then lay a cloth four or five times double on a table, and spread them thereon; dry them very well, and have your bottles ready; fill them and cover them with <ingredient>mutton suet fat;</ingredient> when it is a little coll, fill the necks almost to the top, cork them and tie a bladder and a leather over them, and set them in a cool dry place.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Plumbs.</purpose>

Take plumbs before they have stones in them which you may know by putting a pin through; coddle them in many waters till they are as green as grass; peel them and coddle them again : you must take the weight of them in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and make a sirup put to your <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> then put them in, set them on the fire to boil slowly, till they be clear, skimming them often, and they will be verry green. Put them up in glasses, and keep them for use.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve currants.</purpose>

Take the weight of the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> add half a pint of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> let it melt; then put in your <ingredient>currants</ingredient> and let them do very leisurely; skim them, and take them up; let the sirup boil, then put them on again; and when they are clear, and the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> thick enough, take them off. When they are cold put them in glasses.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">For preserving Quinces.</purpose>

Thake a peck of <ingredient>Quinces,</ingredient> pare them take out the core with a sharp knife, if you wish to have them whole; boil parings and cores with two

<pb n="67" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=71"/>

pound frost <ingredient>grapes,</ingredient> in three quarts <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil the liquor an hour and an half, or till it is thick, strain it through a coarse <implement>hair sieve,</implement> add one and a quarter pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> to every pound of <ingredient>quince;</ingredient> put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into the sirup, scald and scim it till it is clear, put the <ingredient>quinces</ingredient> into the sirup, cut up two <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> and mix with the <ingredient>quince,</ingredient> hang them over a gentle fire for five hours, then put them in a stone pot for use, set them in a dry cool place.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">For preserving Quinces in Loaf Sugar.</purpose>

Take a peck of <ingredient>Quinces,</ingredient> put them into a kettle of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> hang them over the fire, boil them till they are soft, then take them out with a fork, when cold, pare them, quarter or halve them, if you like; take their weight <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> put into a <implement>bell metal kettle</implement> or sauce pan, with one quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> scald and <alt synonym1="skim">scim</alt> it till it is very clear, then put in your <ingredient>Quinces,</ingredient> let them boil in the sirup for half an hour, add <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> as before if you like, then put them in stone pots for use.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">For preserving <alt synonym1="strawberries">Strawburies</alt>.</purpose>

Take two quarts of Strawburies, squeeze them through a cloth, add half a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and two pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> put it into the sause pan, scald and skim it, take two pound of <ingredient>Strawberries</ingredient> with stems on, set your sauce pan on a <implement>chafing dish,</implement> put as many <ingredient>Strawberries</ingredient> into the dish as you can with the stems up without bruising them, let them boil for about ten minutes, then take them out gently with a fork and put them into a stone pot for use; when you have done the whole turn the sirup into the pot, wher hot; set them in a cool place for use.</p>

<p><ingredient>Currants</ingredient> and <ingredient>Cherries</ingredient> may be done in the same way, by adding a little more <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<pb n="68" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=72"/>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To keep White Bullace, Pears, Plumbs, or Damsons, &amp;c. for tarts or pies.</purpose>

Gather them when full grawn, and just as they begin to turn, pick all the largest out, save about two thirds of the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> to the other third put as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as you think will cover them, boil and skim them; when the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is boiled very soft, strain it through a coarse <implement>hair sieve;</implement> and to every quart of this liquor put a pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> boil it and skim it very will; then throw in your <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> just give them a scald; take them off the fire, and when cold, put them into bottles with wide mouths, pour your sirup over them, lay a piece of <ingredient>white paper</ingredient> over them, and cover them with <ingredient>oil.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Marmalade.</purpose>

To two pounds of <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> put three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a pint of <ingredient>spring water;</ingredient> then put them over the fire, and boil them till they are tender; then take them up and bruise them; then put them into the liquor, let it boil three quarters of an hour, and put them into your pots or saucers.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Mulberries whole.</purpose>

Set some <ingredient>Mulberries</ingredient> over the fire in a skillet or <implement>preserving pan;</implement> draw from them a pint of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> when it is strained; then take three pounds of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> beaten very fine, wet the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with the pint <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> boil <alt synonym1="up">np</alt> your <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and skim it, put in two pounds of ripe <ingredient>mulberries,</ingredient> and let them stand in the sirup till they are thoroughly warm, then set them on the fire, and let them boil very gently; do them but half enough, so put them by in the sirup till next day, then boil them gently again; when the sirup is pretty thick, and will stand in

<pb n="69" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=73"/>

round drops when it is cold, they are done enough, so put all into a <implement>gallipot</implement> for use.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Goosberries, Damsons, or plumbs.</purpose>

Gather them when dry, full grown, and not ripe; pick them one by one, put them into glass bottles that are very clean and dry, and cork them close with new corks; then put a kettle of <ingredient>water</ingredient> on the fire, and put in the bottles with care; wet not the corks, but let the <ingredient>water</ingredient> come up to the necks; make a gantle fire till they are a little codled and turn white; do not take them up till cold, then pitch the corks all over, or wax them close and thick; then set them in a cool dry cellar.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Peaches.</purpose>

Put your <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> just give them a scald, but don't let them boil, take them out, and put them in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then dry them in a sieve, and put them in long wide mouthed bottles: to half a dozen <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> take a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> clarity it, pour it over your <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> and fill the bottles with <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> stop them close and keep them in a close place.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Cherries.</purpose>

Take two pounds of <ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> one pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>fair water,</ingredient> melt some <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in it; when it is melted, put in your other <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and your <ingredient>cherries;</ingredient> then boil them softly, till all the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> be melted; then boil them fast, and skim them; take them off two or three times and shake them, and put them on again, and let them boil fast; and when they are of a good colour and the sirup will stand they are boiled enough.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To preserve Raspberries.</purpose>

Choose <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> that are not too ripe, and take

<pb n="70" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=74"/>

the weight of them in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> wet your <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and put in your <ingredient>berries,</ingredient> and let them boil softly; take heed of breaking them; when they are clear, take them up, and boil the sirup till it be thick enough, then put them in again; and when they are cold put them up in glasses.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To Keep Damsons.</purpose>

Take <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> when they are first ripe, pick them off carefully, wipe them clean, put them into <implement>snuff bottles,</implement> stop them up tight so that no air can get to them, nor <ingredient>water;</ingredient> put nothing into the bottles but plumbs, put the bottles into <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> hang them over the fire, let them heat slowly, let the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boil slowly for half an hour, when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is cold take out the bottles, set the bottles into a cold place, they will keep twelve months if the bottles are stopped tight, so as no air nor <ingredient>water</ingredient> can get to them. They will not keep long after the bottles are opened; the plumbs must be hard.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">American Citron.</purpose>

Take the <ingredient>rinds</ingredient> of large <ingredient>watermelons</ingredient> not too ripe, pare off the outside <ingredient>rind,</ingredient> cut them in thin pieces soak them in weak <ingredient>brine</ingredient> four days, the fourth day scald the <ingredient>brine</ingredient> and pour it hot to the mellons, then soak the mellons four or five days in clear <ingredient>water,</ingredient> change the <ingredient>water</ingredient> each day and pour it hot to the <ingredient>melons,</ingredient> to four pounds of <ingredient>melons</ingredient> take five pounds of clear <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> dissolve the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil it up, rise the scum with an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> beaten up and put into it or <ingredient>lime water;</ingredient> then put your <ingredient>melons</ingredient> in and boil them half an hour, boil <ingredient>lemon peel</ingredient> and <ingredient>grape juice</ingredient> with your <ingredient>melons</ingredient>: to preserve them you will repeat scalding them once in a few weeks.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="accompaniments">

<pb n="71" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=75"/>

<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">OF PICKLING.</hd>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Asparagus.</purpose>

Gather your <ingredient>asparagus,</ingredient> and lay them in an earthen pot; make a <ingredient>brine of water</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> strong enough to bear an egg, pour it hot on them and keep it close covered. When you use them, lay them in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> two hours, then boil and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> them for table. If you use them as a <ingredient>pickle,</ingredient> boil them as they come out of the <ingredient>brine,</ingredient> and lay them in <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Mushrooms.</purpose>

Cut the stems of small buttons at the bottom; wash them in two or three waters with a piece of <implement>flannel.</implement> Have in readiness a <implement>stewpan</implement> on the fire, with some <ingredient>spring water</ingredient> that has had a handful of <ingredient>common salt</ingredient> thrown into it; and as soon as it boils, put in your buttons. When they have boiled about three or four minutes, take them off the fire, and throw them into a <implement>cullender;</implement> from thence spread them as quick as you can upon a linnen cloth, and cover them with another. Have ready several wide mouthed bottles; and as you put in the <ingredient>mushrooms,</ingredient> now and then mix a blade of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> sliced amongst them; then fill your bottles with distilled <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> If you pour over them some melted <ingredient>mutton fat,</ingredient> that has been well strained, it will keep them better than <ingredient>oil</ingredient> itself would.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Walnuts.</purpose>

Put them into strong <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> for nine days, and stir them twice a day, observing to change the <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> every three days. Then let them stand in a <implement>hair sieve</implement> till they turn black. 
 
<pb n="72" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=76"/>

Put them into strong stone jars, and pour boiling <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> over them. Cover them up, and let them stand till they be cold. Then give the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> three more boilings, pour it each time on the <ingredient>walnuts,</ingredient> and let it stand till it be cold between every boiling. Then tie them down with <ingredient>paper</ingredient> and a bladder over them, and let them stand two or three months. Then make the following <ingredient>pickle.</ingredient>-- To every two quarts of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> put half an ounce of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and the same of <ingredient>olives</ingredient>; of black pepper,<ingredient>Jamaica pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and <ingredient>long pepper,</ingredient> an ounce each, and two ounces of <ingredient>common salt.</ingredient> Boil it ten minutes, pour it hot on your <ingredient>walnuts,</ingredient> and tie them down covered with <ingredient>paper</ingredient> and a bladder.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle or make Mangoes of Melons.</purpose>

Take <ingredient>green melons,</ingredient> as many as you please, and make a <ingredient>brine</ingredient> strong enough to bear an egg; then pour it boiling hot on the <ingredient>melons,</ingredient> keeping them down under the <ingredient>brine;</ingredient> let them stand five or six days; then take them out, slit them down on one side, take out all the <ingredient>seeds,</ingredient> scrape them well in the inside, and wash them clean in <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> then take a <ingredient>clove</ingredient> of a <ingredient><alt synonym1="garlic">garlick</alt></ingredient>, a little <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> sliced, and a little whole <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> put all these proportionably into the <ingredient>melons,</ingredient> filling them up with <ingredient>mustard seeds;</ingredient> then lay them in an earthen pot with the slit upwards, and take one part of <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> and two parts of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> enough to cover them, pouring it upon them scalding hot and keep them close stopped.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Barberries.</purpose>

Take of <ingredient>white wine vinegar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> of each an equal quantity; to every quart of this liquor, put in half a pound of cheap <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then pick the worst of your barberries and put into this liquor

<pb n="73" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=77"/>

and the best into glasses; then boil your <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> with the worst of your barberries, and skim it very clean, boil it till it looks of a fine color, then let it stand to be cold, before you strain it; then strain it through a cloth, wringing it to get all the color you can from the barberries; let it stand to cool and settle, then pour it clear into the glasses; in a little of the <ingredient>pickle,</ingredient> boil a little <ingredient>fennel;</ingredient> when cold, put a little bit at the top of the pot or glass, and cover it close with a bladder or leather. To every half pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> put a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>white salt.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Cucumbers.</purpose>

Let your <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> be small, fresh gathered and free from spots; then make <ingredient>pickle of salt and water,</ingredient> strong enough to bear an egg; boil the <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> and skim it well, and then pour it upon your <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> and stive them down for twenty four hours; then strain them out into a <implement>cullender,</implement> and dry them well with a cloth, and take best <ingredient>white wine vinegar,</ingredient> with <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> sliced <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>white pepper corns</ingredient>, log <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and races of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> (as much as you please) boil them up together, and then clap the <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> in, with a few <ingredient>vine leaves,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and as soon as they begin to turn their color, put them into jars, stive them down close, and when cold, tie on a bladder and leather.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Artichoke Bottoms.</purpose>

Boil <ingredient>Artichokes</ingredient> till you can pull the leaves off; then take off the chokes, and cut them from the stalk; (take great care you do not let the knife touch the top) throw them into <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> for an hour them take them out, and lay them into a cloth to drain; then put them into large wide mouthed glasses, put a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient>

<pb n="74" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=78"/>

between then; fill them either with distilled <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sugar vinegar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spring water,</ingredient> cover them with <ingredient>mutton fat</ingredient> fried, and tie them down with a bladder and leather.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Salmon.</purpose>

Take your <ingredient>salmon,</ingredient> seale and gut it, and wash it very clean; have a kettle of <ingredient>spring water</ingredient> boiling, with a handful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>all-spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> put in the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> and boil it three quarters of an hour, if small; if large one hour; then take the <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> out, and let it stand till it is cold; strain the liquor through a sieve; when it is cold, put your <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> very close in a tub or pan, and pour the liquor over it; when you want to use it, put it into a dish, with a little of the <ingredient>pickle,</ingredient> and garnish it with <ingredient>green fennel.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Peppers.</purpose>

Take your <ingredient>peppers</ingredient> and cut a slit in the side of them, put them in <ingredient>cold salt</ingredient> and water for twelve hours, then take them out and put them in fresh <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and hang them over the fire in a brass kettle, letting the <ingredient>water</ingredient> be as hot as you can bear your hand in, let them remain over the fire till they turn yellow, when they turn yellow, shift the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and put them in more <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> of the same warmth; then cover them with <ingredient>cabbage leaves</ingredient> till they turn green, when they are done, drain the <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> off, then boil your <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and pour it over them; they will be fit for use in three days.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To pickle Beets.</purpose>

Put into a gallon of <ingredient>cold vinegar</ingredient> as many <ingredient>beets</ingredient> as the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> will hold, and put thereto half an ounce of whole <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> if you like it, and one <ingredient>head of garlic.</ingredient></p>
 
<pb n="75" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=79"/>

<p><emph rend="italic">Note.</emph> Boil the <ingredient>beets</ingredient> in clear <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with their dirt on as they are taken ot of the earth, then take them out and peel them, and when the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> is cold put them in, and in two days they will be fit for use. The <ingredient>spice</ingredient> must be boiled in <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">OF SOUSING.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To souse Pigs feet and ears.</purpose>

After you have cleaned your <ingredient>pigs feet</ingredient> and <ingredient>ears,</ingredient> boil them till they are tender; then boil as much <ingredient>spring water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> in it, as will cover them; when both are cold, put the <ingredient>feet</ingredient> and <ingredient>ears</ingredient> into a pan, and pour the <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> over them; and when you use them, take them out, split them in two, and lay them in a dish; chop some <ingredient>green parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient><alt synonym1="shallot">shalott</alt></ingredient> fine, mix it with <ingredient>oil</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> and pour over them; or put them into a batter and fry them, serve with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>mustard</ingredient> in a boat.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To souse Mackerel.</purpose>

Put some <ingredient>spring water</ingredient> into a <implement>fish-kettle</implement> with a handful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>bay leaves,</ingredient> and make it boil; then put in your <ingredient>mackerel,</ingredient> (observe they are covered with the liquor) and boil them twenty minutes very gently; then take them out, put them in a long pan, and pour the liquor over them; and when they are cold, put them in a dish with some of the liquor, and garnish with <ingredient>green fennel.</ingredient></p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="meatfishgame"><hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">OF SAUSAGES.</hd>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Fine Sausages.</purpose>

You must take six pounds of good <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> free from <ingredient>skin,</ingredient> gristles, and <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> cut it small, and beat it in a morter till it is very fine; then shred six

<pb n="76" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=80"/>

pounds of <ingredient>beef-suet</ingredient> very fine and free from <ingredient>skin,</ingredient> shred it as fine as possible; take a good deal of <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> wash it very clean, pick off the leaves, and shred it very fine; spread your <ingredient>meat</ingredient> on a clean <implement>dresser</implement> or table, then shake the <ingredient>sage</ingredient> all over, about three large spoonfuls, shred the thin <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of a middling <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> very fine and throw over, with as many <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> when shred fine, as will fill a large spoon; grate two <ingredient>nutmegs</ingredient> over, throw over two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> a large spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then throw over the <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> and mix it all well together; put it down close in a pot; when you use them, roll them up with as much <ingredient>egg</ingredient> as will make them roll smooth; make them the size of a <ingredient>sausage,</ingredient> and fry them in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or good dripping; be sure it be hot before you put them in, and keep rolling them about when they are thorough hot, and of a fine light brown, they are enough. You may chop this <ingredient>meat</ingredient> very fine if you do not like it beat. <ingredient>Veal</ingredient> eats well done thus, or <ingredient>veal</ingredient> and <ingredient>pork</ingredient> together. You may clean some <ingredient>guts</ingredient> and fill them.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">Oxford Sausages.</purpose>

Take a pound of <ingredient>lean veal,</ingredient> a pound of young <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> <ingredient>fat</ingredient> and lean, free from <ingredient>skin</ingredient> and gristle, a pound of <ingredient>beef-suet,</ingredient> chopped all fine together; put in half a pound of grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> half the <ingredient>peel of a lemon</ingredient> shred fine, a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, six <ingredient>sage leaves</ingredient> washed and chopped very fine, a tea spoonful of <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> some <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> <ingredient>savory,</ingredient> and <ingredient>marjoram</ingredient> shred fine; mix it all well together and put it close down in a pan; when you use it, roll it out the size of a common <ingredient>sausage,</ingredient> and fry them in fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> of a fine brown, or broil them over a clear fire, and send them to table as hot as possible.</p></recipe>

</chapter>
 
<pb n="77" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=81"/>

<chapter class1="accompaniments">

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="bold" size="larger" placement="heading">TO BOTTLE GREEN CURRANTS.</purpose>

Gather your <ingredient>currants</ingredient> while they are green and almost full grown when the sun is hot upon them, pick them from the stalks, and put them into narrow mouthed bottles; cork them close, and set them in dry sand, and they will keep all the winter.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To bottle Cramberries.</purpose>

Gather your cramberries on a fine dry dry, and put them into dry bottles; cork them tight, and put them upright in a cool dry place, aud they will keep for two years.</p>
</recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="beverages"><hd align="center" size="larger" placement="heading">OF WINES.</hd>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Currant Wine.</purpose>

Gather your <ingredient>currants</ingredient> when the weather is dry, and are full ripe: strip them carefully from the stalk, put them into a pan, and bruise them with a <implement>wooden pestle;</implement> let it stand about twenty hours, after which strain it through a sieve. Add three pounds fine <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> to every four quarts of the liquor; and then shaking or stiring it well, fill your vessel, and put about a quart of <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> to every seven gallons; as soon as it fine, bottle it off.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Currant Wine another way.</purpose>

Gather your <ingredient>currants</ingredient> when full ripe, which will commonly be about the middle of July; break them well in a tub or vat, (some have a <implement>mill</implement> constructed for the purpose, consisting of a <implement>hopper,</implement> fixed upon two lignum vitae rollers) <implement>press</implement> and measure your <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> add two thirds, <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and to each gallon of that mixture (i.e. <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient>) put three pounds of muscovado <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> (the cleaner and dryer the better; very coarse <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> clarified,

<pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=82"/>

will do equally as well) stir it well, till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is quite dissolved, and then turn it up. If you can possibly prevent it, let not your <ingredient>juice</ingredient> stand over night, as it should not ferment before mixture.</p>

<p>Observe that your <implement>casks</implement> be sweet and clean, and such as never have had either <ingredient>beer</ingredient> or <ingredient>cyder</ingredient> in them, and, if new, let them be first well seasoned.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Damson wine.</purpose>

Gather your <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> dry, weigh them and bruise them with your hand; put them into an earthern <implement>stein</implement> that has a faucet, and a wreath of straw before the faucet; add to every eight pounds of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> a gallon of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> boil the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> skim it, and put it to your <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> scalding hot; let it stand two whole days; then draw it off, and put it into a vessel fit for it; and to every gallon of liquor put two pounds and an half of fine <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> let the vessel be full and stop it close; the longer it stands the better; it will keep a year in the vessel; bottle it out. The small <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> is the best. You may put a very small lump of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient> in every bottle.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make English Champaign, or the fine Currant Wine.</purpose>

Take to three gallons of <ingredient>water</ingredient> nine pounds of <ingredient>Lisbon sugar;</ingredient> boil the <ingredient>water</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> half an hour, skim it clean, then have one gallon of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> picked, but not bruised; pour the liquor boiling hot over them; and when cold work it with half a pint of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> two days, pour it through a <implement>flannel</implement> or sieve; then put it into a barrel fit for it, with half an ounce of <ingredient>isinglass</ingredient> well bruised; when it has done working, stop it close for a month; then bottle it, and in every bottle put a 
 
<pb n="79" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=83"/>

small lump of <ingredient>double refined sugar</ingredient>: This is excellent <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and has a beautiful colour.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Sarogosa Wine, or English Sack.</purpose>

To every quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> put a sprig of <ingredient>rue,</ingredient> and to every gallon a handful of <ingredient>fennel roots;</ingredient> boil these half an hour, and strain it off, and to every gallon of this liquor put three pounds of <ingredient>honey;</ingredient> boil it two hours and skim it well; when it is cold pour it off, and turn it into the vessel, or such <implement>casks</implement> as are fit for it; keep it a year in the vessel, and then bottle it. It is a very good sack.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Shrub.</purpose>

Take two quarts of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and put it in a large bottle, adding to it the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of five <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> the peels of two and half a <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> stop it up, let it stand three days, and add to it three pints of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and a pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> mix it, strain it twice through a <implement>flannel,</implement> and bottle it up. It is a pretty <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and a <ingredient>cordial.</ingredient></p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To recover Wine that has turued sharp.</purpose>

Rack off your <ingredient>wine</ingredient> into another vessel, and to ten gallons put the following powder--Take <ingredient>oyster-shells,</ingredient> scrape and wash off the brown, dirty outside of the shell, and dry them in an oven till they will powder; put a pound of this powder to every nine or ten gallons of your <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> stir it well together, and stop it up, then let it stand to settle two or three days or till it is fine. As soon as it is fine, bottle it off and cork it well.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To fine wine the Lisbon way.</purpose>

To every twenty gallons of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> take the <ingredient>white of ten eggs,</ingredient> and a small handful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> beat them together to a froth, and mix them well with a quart more of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> then pour the <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and the

<pb n="80" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=84"/>

<ingredient>whites</ingredient> into the vessel and in a few days it will be fine.</p>
</recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To clear Wine, Cyder, &amp;c.</purpose>

Take half a pound of <ingredient>hartshorn,</ingredient> and dissolve it in cyder, if it be for cyder, or <ingredient>Rhenish wine</ingredient> for any other liquor. This is quite sufficient for a <implement>hogshead.</implement></p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="beverages">
<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">OF BEER.</hd>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Spruce beer out of the Essence.</purpose>

For a <implement>cask</implement> of eighteen gallons take seven ounces of the <ingredient>essence of spruce,</ingredient> and fourteen pounds of <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> mix them with a few gallons of <ingredient>hot water;</ingredient> put it into the <implement>cask;</implement> then fill the <implement>cask</implement> with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> stir it well, make it about luke warm; then add about two thirds of a pint of good <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> or the <ingredient>grounds of porter;</ingredient> let it stand four or five days to work then bung it up tight, and let it stand two or three days, and it will be fit for immediate use after it has been bottled.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Spruce beer out of Shed Spruce.</purpose>
To one quart of <ingredient>Shed Spruce,</ingredient> two gallons of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and so in proportion to the quantity you wish to make, then add one pint of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to every two gallons, let it boil four or five hours and stand till it is luke warm, then put one pint of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> to ten gallons, let it work, then put into your <implement>cask</implement> and bung it up tight, and in two days it will be fit for use.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Spruice beer another way.</purpose>

Take four ounces of <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> let them boil half an hour in one gallon of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> strain the <ingredient>hop water</ingredient> then add sixteen gallons of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> two gallons of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>essence of spruce,</ingredient> dissolved in one quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> put it in a clean

<pb n="81" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=85"/>

<implement>cask,</implement> then shake it well together, and add half a pint of emptins, then let it stand and work one week, if very warm weather less time will do, when it is drawn off to bottle, add one spoonful of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to every bottle.</p></recipe>

<recipe class1="beverages">
<p><purpose align="center" rend="italic">To make Hop Beer.</purpose>

To make a barrel of <ingredient>beer,</ingredient> take five ounces of good <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> add two or three pails of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> simmer six hours, strain this into your barrel when hot, add one gallon of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> stir this well together, and then fill your barrel with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> stir the whole together. It will be fit for use in about forty eight hours.</p>

<p>A less quantity may be made by the same rule, but always observe to have the vessel full, so that the <ingredient>beer</ingredient> when it works may discharge the filth that rises on the surface.</p></recipe>

</chapter>

<chapter class1="eggscheesedairy">
<hd align="center" rend="bold" size="larger">OF CURING BUTTER.</hd>

<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>Take two parts of the best <ingredient>common salt,</ingredient> one part of <ingredient>refined sugar,</ingredient> and one part of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> petre; beat them up together, and blend the whole completely.</p>

<p>Take one ounce of this composition for every fifteen ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> work it well into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and put it down for use.</p>

<p>It must be noted, that <ingredient>butter</ingredient> thus cured requires to stand three weeks before used. -- If sooner opened the salts are not sufficiently blended with it, and sometimes the coolness of the nitre will then be preceived, which totally disappears afterwards.</p></recipe>

</chapter>
</body>

<back> 
<div type="index">

<pb n="index" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=86"/>

<list><item rend="italic">Pg.</item>

<item>How to choose all kinds of articles for cooking 5</item>

<hd align="center">ROASTING.</hd>

<item>Beef 												<ref target="engl021.gif">17</ref></item>
<item>Mutton 											<ref target="engl022.gif">18</ref></item>
<item>Veal 												<ref target="engl022.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Lamb 												<ref target="engl022.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mutton, Venison fashion 					<ref target="engl022.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Do. with forc'd meet 						<ref target="engl022.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Turkey or Fowl 								<ref target="engl023.gif">19</ref></item>
<item>To stuff do. 									<ref target="engl023.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To stuff a Goslin 							<ref target="engl023.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To smother a Fowl in Oysters 				<ref target="engl024.gif">20</ref></item>
<item>To stuff a leg of Veal 						<ref target="engl024.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Do. Pork 										<ref target="engl024.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To alamode a round of Beef 				<ref target="engl025.gif">21</ref></item>
<item>To roast a Pig 								<ref target="engl026.gif">22</ref></item>
<item>To dress a Calves Head Turtle fashion	<ref target="engl026.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">BOILING.</hd>

<item>General rules 									<ref target="engl027.gif">23</ref></item>
<item>Beef or Mutton 								<ref target="engl028.gif">24</ref></item>
<item>A leg of Pork 									<ref target="engl028.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pickled Do. 									<ref target="engl028.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Veal 												<ref target="engl028.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Parsley sauce									<ref target="engl028.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Calve's Head 									<ref target="engl029.gif">25</ref></item>
<item>Lamb												<ref target="engl029.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Neat's Tongue 									<ref target="engl029.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Ham 												<ref target="engl029.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Haunch of Venison 							<ref target="engl030.gif">26</ref></item>
<item>Turkey, Goose, &amp;c.						<ref target="engl030.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Sauce for Turkey 								<ref target="engl030.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Do. for Fowl 									<ref target="engl030.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Fresh Cod 										<ref target="engl031.gif">27</ref></item>
<item>Cod's Head 										<ref target="engl031.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Dried Codfish 									<ref target="engl031.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Salmon 											<ref target="engl031.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mackerel 										<ref target="engl032.gif">28</ref></item>
<item>French Beans 									<ref target="engl032.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Broad Do. 										<ref target="engl032.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Green Peas 										<ref target="engl033.gif">29</ref></item>
<item>Asparagus 										<ref target="engl033.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Cabbage 											<ref target="engl033.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">FRYING.</hd>

<item>Beef Steaks 									<ref target="engl034.gif">30</ref></item>
<item>Tripe 											<ref target="engl034.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Sausages 										<ref target="engl034.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Beef Collops 									<ref target="engl035.gif">31</ref></item>
<item>Scotch Do. 										<ref target="engl035.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Veal Cutlets 									<ref target="engl035.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mutton Do. 										<ref target="engl035.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Eggs 												<ref target="engl036.gif">32</ref></item>
<item>Trout 											<ref target="engl036.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Flat Fish 										<ref target="engl037.gif">33</ref></item>
<item>Oysters 											<ref target="engl037.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Chickens 										<ref target="engl037.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">BROILING.</hd>

<item>Beef Steaks 									<ref target="engl038.gif">34</ref></item>
<item>Chickens 										<ref target="engl038.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mackerel 										<ref target="engl038.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Cod's Sounds 									<ref target="engl039.gif">35</ref></item>

<hd align="center">STEWING.</hd>

<item>Beef Steaks 									<ref target="engl039.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Chickens 										<ref target="engl039.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pigeons 											<ref target="engl040.gif">36</ref></item>
<item>Codfish 											<ref target="engl040.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pears 											<ref target="engl040.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mushrooms 										<ref target="engl040.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">SOUPS.</hd>

<item>Oyster <ref target="engl041.gif">37</ref></item>
 
<pb n="index" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=87"/>

<item>Rice Do. 										<ref target="engl041.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Turnip Do. 										<ref target="engl042.gif">38</ref></item>
<item>Veal Broth 										<ref target="engl042.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">PIES.</hd>

<item>Veal Pie 										<ref target="engl042.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Venison Pastry 								<ref target="engl043.gif">39</ref></item>
<item>Stew Pie 										<ref target="engl043.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Sea Do. 											<ref target="engl044.gif">40</ref></item>
<item>Chicken Do. 									<ref target="engl044.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Minc'd Do. 										<ref target="engl044.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Foot Do. 										<ref target="engl044.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Tongue Do. 										<ref target="engl045.gif">41</ref></item>
<item>Minc'd Pie of beef 							<ref target="engl045.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Egg Do. 											<ref target="engl045.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Apple Do. 										<ref target="engl046.gif">42</ref></item>
<item>Currant Do. 									<ref target="engl046.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Buttered Apple Do. 							<ref target="engl046.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Apple or Pear Do. 							<ref target="engl046.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Cherry, or Plumb Do. 						<ref target="engl047.gif">43</ref></item>
<item>Apple or Pear tart 							<ref target="engl047.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Icing for Tarts 								<ref target="engl048.gif">44</ref></item>
<item>Almond Do. 										<ref target="engl048.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Lemon Puffs 									<ref target="engl048.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Rice Florendine 								<ref target="engl049.gif">45</ref></item>
<item>Puff pastes for Tarts 						<ref target="engl049.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pastes for sweet Meats 						<ref target="engl049.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">PUDDINGS.</hd>

<item>Rice Do. 										<ref target="engl050.gif">46</ref></item>
<item>Indian Do. 										<ref target="engl051.gif">47</ref></item>
<item>Sunderland Do. 								<ref target="engl051.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Whitpot Do. 									<ref target="engl051.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Bread Do. 										<ref target="engl051.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Flour Do. 										<ref target="engl052.gif">48</ref></item>
<item>Cream Almond Do. 								<ref target="engl052.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Apple Dumplin Do. 							<ref target="engl052.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Potatoe Do. 									<ref target="engl052.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Apple Do. 										<ref target="engl053.gif">49</ref></item>
<item>Carrot Do. 										<ref target="engl053.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Squash Do.										<ref target="engl053.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pumpkin Do. 									<ref target="engl053.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Orange Do.										<ref target="engl054.gif">50</ref></item>
<item>Plain Bread Do. 								<ref target="engl054.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Quaking Do. 									<ref target="engl054.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Biscuit Do. 									<ref target="engl054.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Boiled Plumb Do. 								<ref target="engl055.gif">51</ref></item>
<item>Hunting Do. 									<ref target="engl055.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Plain baked Do. 								<ref target="engl055.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Millet Do. 										<ref target="engl055.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Poor Man's Do. 								<ref target="engl055.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">CUSTARDS.</hd>

<item>Various kinds 									<ref target="engl056.gif">52</ref></item>
<item>Rich Do. 										<ref target="engl056.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Rice Do. 										<ref target="engl056.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Sick bed Do. 									<ref target="engl057.gif">53</ref></item>
<item>Currant Jelly 									<ref target="engl057.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Rasberry Giam 									<ref target="engl057.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">SYLLABUBS.</hd>

<item>Syllabubs 										<ref target="engl058.gif">54</ref></item>
<item>Creams 											<ref target="engl058.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">CAKES.</hd>

<item>A rich Cake 									<ref target="engl058.gif">54</ref></item>
<item>Portugal Do. 									<ref target="engl059.gif">55</ref></item>
<item>Dutch Do. 										<ref target="engl059.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Queen Do. 										<ref target="engl060.gif">56</ref></item>
<item>Uxbridge Do. 									<ref target="engl060.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Orange Do. 										<ref target="engl060.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Common Biscuit 								<ref target="engl061.gif">57</ref></item>
<item>Whigs 											<ref target="engl061.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Buns 												<ref target="engl062.gif">58</ref></item>
<item>Fritters 										<ref target="engl062.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Pan Cakes 										<ref target="engl062.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Plain Do. 										<ref target="engl062.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Rich Do. 										<ref target="engl063.gif">59</ref></item>
<item>Potatoe Do. 									<ref target="engl063.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Johny Do. 										<ref target="engl063.gif">do</ref></item>
 
<pb n="index" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=88"/>

<item>Indian Slapjack 								<ref target="engl063.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Loaf Cake 										<ref target="engl063.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Gingerbread 									<ref target="engl064.gif">60</ref></item>
<item>Molasses Do. 									<ref target="engl065.gif">61</ref></item>
<item>Various kinds Do. 							<ref target="engl066.gif">62</ref></item>
<item>Pound Cake 										<ref target="engl066.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>A variety Do. 									<ref target="engl067.gif">63</ref></item>
<item>Diet Bread 										<ref target="engl068.gif">64</ref></item>
<item>Lemon Biscuit									<ref target="engl068.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Spounge Do. 									<ref target="engl068.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Butter Do. 										<ref target="engl068.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">RUSKS</hd>

<item>Of various kinds 								<ref target="engl069.gif">65</ref></item>
<item>Butter Drop 									<ref target="engl069.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">PRESERVES></hd>

<item>Plumbs 											<ref target="engl070.gif">66</ref></item>
<item>Currants 										<ref target="engl070.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Quinces 											<ref target="engl071.gif">67</ref></item>
<item>Strawberries 									<ref target="engl071.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Mulberries 										<ref target="engl072.gif">68</ref></item>
<item>Pears, Plumbs, or Damsons for tarts 	<ref target="engl072.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Peaches 											<ref target="engl073.gif">69</ref></item>
<item>Cherries 										<ref target="engl073.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Rasberries 										<ref target="engl073.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Gooseberries 									<ref target="engl073.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Damsons 											<ref target="engl073.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Plumbs 											<ref target="engl073.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To keep Damsons 								<ref target="engl074.gif">70</ref></item>
<item>American Citron 								<ref target="engl074.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">PICKLING.</hd>

<item>Asparagus 										<ref target="engl075.gif">71</ref></item>
<item>Mushrooms 										<ref target="engl075.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Walnuts 											<ref target="engl075.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Make Mangoes 									<ref target="engl076.gif">72</ref></item>
<item>Barberries 										<ref target="engl076.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Cucumbers 										<ref target="engl077.gif">73</ref></item>
<item>Artichoke 										<ref target="engl077.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Salmon 											<ref target="engl078.gif">74</ref></item>
<item>Peppers 											<ref target="engl078.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Beets 											<ref target="engl078.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">SOUSING.</hd>

<item>Pigs feet and ears 							<ref target="engl079.gif">75</ref></item>
<item>Mackerel 										<ref target="engl079.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">SAUSAGES.</hd>

<item>Fine 												<ref target="engl079.gif">75</ref></item>
<item>Oxford 											<ref target="engl080.gif">76</ref></item>

<hd align="center">TO BOTTLE.</hd>

<item>Green Currants 								<ref target="engl081.gif">77</ref></item>
<item>Cramberries 									<ref target="engl081.gif">do</ref></item>

<hd align="center">WINES.</hd>

<item>Currant Do. 									<ref target="engl081.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Fine Do. 										<ref target="engl082.gif">78</ref></item>
<item>Damson Do. 										<ref target="engl082.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>English Sack 									<ref target="engl083.gif">79</ref></item>
<item>Shrub 											<ref target="engl083.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To restore Wine 								<ref target="engl083.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>To Clarify Do. 								<ref target="engl084.gif">80</ref></item>

<hd align="center">OF BEER.</hd>

<item>Spruce 											<ref target="engl084.gif">do</ref></item>
<item>Hop Do. 											<ref target="engl085.gif">81</ref></item>
<item>CURING BTTER 									<ref target="engl085.gif">do</ref></item>

</list></div>

<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=89"/>
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=90"/>
 
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=91"/>
</div>

<div type="backcover">

<pb n="back cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=engl&#38;PageNum=92"/>
</div>
</back>
</cookbook>
