<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<cookbook type="frugal" class1="foodandnonfood" region="general" bookID="1830frch">
<meta><dcTitle>The Frugal Housewife.</dcTitle><dcCreator>Child, Lydia Maria Francis</dcCreator><dcSubject>Home economics. Cookery, American.</dcSubject><dcDescription>Complete title: The Frugal Housewife. Dedicated to Those Who Are Not Ashamed of Economy.</dcDescription><dcPublisher>Boston: Carter and Hendee.</dcPublisher><dcContributor>Electronic edition created by Digital &amp; Multimedia Center, Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003.</dcContributor><dcContributor>Supplementary material by Jan Longone, Anne-Marie Rachman, Peter Berg, Yvonne Lockwood, and Val Berryman</dcContributor><dcDate>1830.</dcDate><dcType>Text</dcType><dcFormat>xml-external-parsed-entity</dcFormat><dcFormat>jpeg</dcFormat><dcFormat>quicktime</dcFormat><dcIdentifier>http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/frugalhousewifechild/frch.xml</dcIdentifier><dcSource>OCLC 6054157</dcSource><dcLanguage>en</dcLanguage><dcRelation>Digitized as part of "Feeding America: The Historic American Cookbook Project." Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003. http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/</dcRelation><dcCoverage>United States</dcCoverage><dcCoverage>Nineteenth century</dcCoverage><dcRights>The book digitized here was published in the United States before 1923 and is in the public domain according to U.S. copyright law. The digital version and supplementary materials are made available for all educational uses.</dcRights></meta>
<front>
<div type="frontcover"><pb n="front cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=1"/></div>
<div type="other"><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=2"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=3"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=4"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=5"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=6"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=7"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=8"/></div>
<div type="titlepage"><pb n="title page" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=9"/><doctitle align="center">THE<lb/>FRUGAL HOUSEWIFE<lb/>DEDICATED TO THOSE<lb/>WHO ARE NOT ASHAMED OF ECONOMY.</doctitle><docauthor align="center">BY<lb/>THE AUTHOR OF HOBOMOK.</docauthor><p>A fat kitchen maketh a lean will.--FRANKLIN.</p><p>'Economy is a poor man's revenue; extravagance a rich man's ruin.'</p><doctitle align="center">SECOND EDITION.<lb/>CORRECTED AND ARRANGED BY THE AUTHOR.<lb/>TO WHICH IS ADDED<lb/>HINTS TO PERSONS OF MODERATE FORTUNE.</doctitle><docimprint align="center">BOSTON.<lb/>PUBLISHED BY CARTER AND HENDEE.<lb/>M DCCC XXX.</docimprint></div>
<div type="copyrightstmt"><pb n="copyright statement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=10"/><p>THE Author having received a great many letters requesting the publication of 'HINTS TO PEOPLE OF MODERATE FORTUNE,' has deemed it proper to annex them to this little work; as both were written from the same motive, viz: an honest and independent wish to be USEFUL.</p><p align="center">DISTRICT OF MASSACHUSETTS, TO WIT:</p><p align="right" rend="italic">District Clerk's Office.</p><p>BE IT REMEMBERED, that on the thirtieth day of January, A. D. 1830, and in the fiftyfourth year of the Independence of the United States of America, Carter and Hendee, of the said district, have deposited in this office the title of a book, the right whereof they claim as proprietors, in the words following, to wit:</p><p>'The Frugal Housewife. Dedicated to those who are not ashamed of Economy. By the author of Hobomok.</p><p align="indent1">A fat kitchen maketh a lean will.--FRANKLIN.</p><p align="indent1">"Economy is a poor man's revenue; extravagance a rich man's ruin."</p><p>Second edition. Corrected and arranged by the Author. To which is added Hints to Persons of Moderate Fortune.'</p><p>In conformity to the act of the Congress of the United States, entitled 'An act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of maps, charts, and books, to the authors and proprietors of such copies, during the times therein mentioned;' and also to an act, entitled 'An net suplementary to an act, entitled, "An act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of maps, charts, and books, to the authors and proprietors of such copies, during the times therein mentioned;" and extending the benefits thereof to the arts of designing, engraving, and etching historical and other prints.'</p><p align="right">JNO. W. DAVIS,</p><p align="right" rend="italic">Clerk of the District of Massachusetts.</p><p align="center">PRINTED BY I. R. BUTTS.....BOSTON.</p></div>
<div type="introduction"><pb n="3" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=11"/><hd align="center">INTRODUCTORY CHAPTER.</hd><p>THE true economy of housekeeping is simply the art of gathering up all the fragments, so that nothing be lost. I mean fragments, of <emph rend="italic">time,</emph> as well as <emph rend="italic">materials.</emph> Nothing should be thrown away so long as it is possible to make any use of it, however trifling that use may be; and whatever be the size of a family, every member should be employed either in earning, or saving money.</p><p>'Time is money.' For this reason, cheap as stockings are, it is good economy to knit them. Cotton and woollen yarn are both cheap; hose that are knit wear twice as long as woven ones; and they can be done at odd minutes of time, which would not be otherwise employed! Where there are children, or aged people, it is sufficient to recommend knitting that it is an <emph rend="italic">employment.</emph></p><p>In this point of view, patchwork is good economy. It is indeed a foolish waste of time to tear cloth into bits for the sake of arranging it anew in fantastic figures; but a large family may be kept out of idleness, and a few shillings saved by thus using scraps of gowns, curtains, &amp;c.</p><p>In the country, where grain is raised, it is a good plan to teach children to prepare and braid straw for their own bonnets, and their brothers' hats.</p><p>Where turkeys and geese are kept, handsome feather fans may as well be made by the younger<pb n="4" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=12"/> members of a family, as to be bought. The earlier children are taught to turn their faculties to some account, the better for them and for their parents.</p><p>In this country, we are apt to let children romp away their existence, till they get to be thirteen, or fourteen. This is not well.--It is not well for the purses and patience of parents; and it has a still worse effect on the morals and habits of the children. <emph rend="italic">Begin early</emph> is the great maxim for everything in education. A child of six years old can be made useful; and should be taught to consider every day lost in which some little thing has not been done to assist others.</p><p>Children can very early be taught to take all the care of their own clothes.</p><p>They can knit garters, suspenders, and stockings; they can make patchwork and braid straw; they can make mats for the table, and mats for the floor; they can weed the garden, and pick cranberries from the meadow, to be carried to market.</p><p>Provided brothers and sisters go together, and are not allowed to go with bad children, it is a great deal better for the boys and girls on a farm to be picking blackberries at six cents a quart, than to be wearing out their clothes in useless play. They enjoy themselves just as well; and they are earning something to buy clothes, at the same time they are tearing them.</p><p>It is wise to keep an exact account of all you expend--even of a paper of pins. This answers two purposes; it makes you more careful in spending money; and it enables your husband to judge precisely whether his family live within his income. No false pride, or foolish ambition to appear as well as others, should ever induce a person to live one cent beyond the income of which he is certain. If you have two dollars a day, let nothing but sickness induce you to spend more than nine shillings; if you<pb n="5" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=13"/> have one dollar a day, do not spend but seventyfive cents; if you have half a dollar a day, be satisfied to spend forty cents.</p><p>To associate with influential and genteel people with an appearance of equality, unquestionably has its advantages; particularly where there is a family of sons and daughters just coming upon the theatre of life; but like all other external advantages, these have their proper price, and may be bought too dearly. They who never reserve a cent of their income, with which to meet any unforeseen calamity, 'pay too dear for their whistle,' whatever temporary benefits they may derive from society. Self-denial, in proportion to the narrowness of your income, will eventually be the happiest and most respectable course for you and yours. If you are prosperous, perseverance and industry will not fail to place you in such a situation as your ambition covets; and if you are not prosperous, it will be well for your children that they have not been educated to higher hopes than they will ever realize.</p><p>If you are about to furnish a house, do not spend all your money, be it much, or little. Do not let the beauty of this thing, and the cheapness of that, tempt you to buy unnecessary articles. Doctor Franklin's maxim was a wise one, 'nothing is cheap that we do not want.' Buy merely enough to get along with, at first. It is only by experience that you can tell what will be the wants of your family. If you spend all your money, you will find you have purchased many things you do not want, and have no means left to get many things, which you do want. If you have enough, and more than enough, to get everything suitable to your situation, do not think you must spend it all, merely because you happen to have it. Begin humbly. As riches increase, it is easy and pleasant to increase in hospitality and splendour; but it is always painful and inconvenient to decrease.<pb n="6" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=14"/> After all, these things are viewed in their proper light by the truly judicious and respectable. Neatness, tastefulness, and good sense, may be shown in the management of a small household, and the arrangement of a little furniture, as well as upon a larger scale; and these qualities are always praised, and always treated with respect and attention. The consideration which many purchase by living beyond their income, and of course living upon others, is not worth the trouble it costs. The glare there is about this false and wicked parade is deceptive; it does not in fact procure a man valuable friends, or extensive influence. More than that, it is wrong--morally wrong, so far as the individual is concerned; and injurious beyond calculation to the interests of our country. To what are the increasing beggary, and discouraged exertions of the present period owing? A multitude of causes have no doubt tended to increase the evil; but the root of the whole matter is the extravagance of all classes of people! We never shall be prosperous, till we make pride and vanity yield to the dictates of honesty and prudence! We never shall be free from embarrassment, until we cease to be ashamed of industry and economy! Let women do their share towards reformation--Let their fathers and husbands see them happy without finery; and if their husbands and fathers have (as is often the case) a foolish pride in seeing them decorated, let them gently and gradually check this feeling, by showing that they have better and surer means of commanding respect--Let them prove by the exertion of ingenuity and economy, that neatness, good taste, and gentility, are attainable without great expense.</p><p>The writer has no apology to offer for this cheap little book, of economical hints, except her deep conviction that such a book is needed. In this case, renown is out of the question; and ridicule is a matter of indifference.</p><pb n="7" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=15"/><p>The information conveyed is of a common kind; but it is such as the majority of young housekeepers do not possess, and such as they cannot obtain from cookery books. Books of this kind have usually been written for the wealthy: I have written for the poor! I have said nothing about <emph rend="italic">rich</emph> cooking; those who can afford to be epicures will find the best of information in the 'Seventyfive Receipts.' I have attempted to teach how money can be <emph rend="italic">saved,</emph> not how it can be <emph rend="italic">enjoyed.</emph> If any persons think some of the maxims too rigidly economical,--let them inquire how the largest fortunes among us have been made. They will find thousands and millions have been accumulated, by a scrupulous attention to sums 'infinitely more minute than sixty cents.'</p><p>In early childhood, you lay the foundation of poverty or riches, in the habits you give your children.--Teach them to save everything,--not for their <emph rend="italic">own</emph> use, for that would make them selfish--but for <emph rend="italic">some</emph> use. Teach them to <emph rend="italic">share</emph> everything with their playmates; but never allow them to <emph rend="italic">destroy</emph> anything.</p><p>I once visited a family where the most exact economy was observed; yet nothing was mean, or uncomfortable. It is the character of true economy to be as comfortable and genteel with a little, as others can be with much. In this family, when the father brought home a package, the older children would, of their own accord, put away the paper and twine neatly, instead of throwing them in the fire, or tearing them to pieces. If the little ones wanted a piece of twine to play <alt synonym1="cat's cradle">scratch-cradle,</alt> or spin a top, there it was, in readiness; and when they threw it upon the floor, the older children had no need to be told to put it again in its place.</p><p>The other day, I heard a mechanic say, 'I have a wife and two little children; we live in a very small house; but, to save my life, I cannot spend less than twelve hundred a year.' Another replied, 'You<pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=16"/> are not economical; I spend but eight hundred.' I thought to myself,--'Neither of you pick up your twine and paper.' A third one, who was present, was silent; but after they were gone, he said, 'I keep house, and comfortably too, with a wife and children, for six hundred a year; but I suppose they would have thought me mean, if I had told them so.' I did not think him mean; it merely occurred to me that his wife and children were in the habit of picking up paper and twine.</p><p>Economy is generally despised as a low virtue, tending to make people ungenerous and selfish. This is true of avarice; but it is not so of economy. The man who is economical, is laying up for himself the permanent power of being useful and generous.--He who 
thoughtlessly gives away ten dollars, when he owes a hundred more than he can pay, deserves no praise,--he obeys a sudden impulse, more like instinct than reason: it would be real charity to check this feeling; because the good he does may be doubtful, while the injury he does his family and creditors is certain. True economy is a careful treasurer in the service of benevolence; and where they are united, respectability, prosperity, and peace will follow.</p></div>
</front>
<body>
<chapter class1="household"><pb n="9" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=17"/><hd align="center">ODD SCRAPS FOR THE ECONOMICAL.</hd><p>IF you would avoid waste in your family, attend to the following rules, and do not despise them because they appear so unimportant: 'many a little makes a mickle.'</p><p>Look frequently to the pails, to see that nothing is thrown to the pigs, which should have been in the grease-pot.</p><p>Look to the grease-pot, and see that nothing is there which might have served to nourish your own family, or a poorer one.</p><p>See that the beef and pork are always <emph rend="italic">under</emph> brine; and that the brine is sweet and clean.</p><p>Count towels, sheets, spoons, &amp;c., occasionally; that those who use them may not become careless.</p><p>See that the vegetables are neither sprouting, nor decaying; if they are so, remove them to a drier place and spread them.</p><p>Examine preserves, to see that they are not contracting mould; and your pickles, to see that they are not growing soft and tasteless.</p><p>As far as it is possible, have bits of bread eaten up before they become hard. Spread those that are not eaten, and let them dry to be pounded for puddings, or soaked for brewis. Brewis is made of crusts, and dry pieces of bread, soaked a good while in hot milk, mashed up, and salted and buttered like toast. Above all, do not let them accumulate in such quantities that they cannot be used. With proper care, there is no need of losing a particle of bread, even in the hottest weather.</p><p>Attend to all the mending in the house, once a<pb n="10" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=18"/> week, if possible. Never put out sewing. If it be impossible to do it in your own family, hire some one into the house, and work with them.</p><p>Make your own bread and cake. Some people think it is just as cheap to buy of the baker and confectioner; but it is not half as cheap. True, it is more convenient; and therefore the rich are justifiable in employing them; but those who are under the necessity of being economical, should make convenience a secondary object. In the first place, confectioners make their cake richer than people of moderate income can afford to make it; in the next place, your domestic, or yourself, may just as well employ your own time, as to pay them for theirs.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>When ivory-handled knives turn yellow,</purpose>
rub them with nice sand paper, or emery; it will take off the spots and restore their whiteness.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>When a carpet is faded,</purpose>
I have been told that it may be restored, in a great measure, (provided there be no grease in it) by being dipped into strong <ingredient>salt and water.</ingredient> I never tried this; but I know that <variation><purpose>silk pocket-handkerchiefs, and deep blue factory cotton, will not fade,</purpose>
if dipped in <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> while new.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>An <ingredient>ox's gall</ingredient> will 
 
<purpose>set any color,--silk, cotton, or woollen.</purpose>
I have seen the colors of calico, which faded at one washing, fixed by it. Where one lives near a slaughter-house, it is worth while to buy cheap fading goods and set them in this way. The <ingredient>gall</ingredient> can be bought for a few cents. Get out all the liquid and cork it up in a large <implement>phial.</implement> One large spoonful of this in a gallon of <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> is sufficient. <variation>This is likewise excellent for 
 
<purpose>taking out spots from bombazine, bombazet, &amp;c.</purpose>
After being washed in this, they look about as well as when new.</variation> It must be thoroughly stirred into the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and not put upon the cloth--It is used without soap. After being washed in this, cloth which you want to <emph rend="italic">clean</emph> should be washed in <ingredient>warm suds,</ingredient> without using soap.</p></formula>
<pb n="11" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=19"/>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="preserving tortoise shell and horn combs">Tortoise shell and horn combs</alt></purpose>
last much longer for having <ingredient>oil</ingredient> rubbed into them once in a while.</p></formula>
<p>Indian-meal and rye-meal are in danger of fermenting in summer; particularly Indian. They should be kept in a cool place, and stirred open to the air, once in a while. A large stone put in the middle of a barrel of meal is a good thing to keep it cool.</p>
<formula class="household"><p>The <ingredient>covering of oil-flasks</ingredient> sewed together with strong thread, and lined and bound neatly, makes useful 
 
<purpose>table-mats.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>A <implement>warming-pan</implement> full of <ingredient>coals,</ingredient> or a shovel of <ingredient>coals,</ingredient> held over 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="removing spots from furniture">varnished furniture, will take out white spots.</alt></purpose>
Care should be taken, not to hold the <ingredient>coals</ingredient> near enough to scorch; and the place should be rubbed with flannel while warm.</p><p><variation>Spots in furniture may usually be cleansed by rubbing them quick and hard, with a flannel wet with <ingredient>the same thing which took out the color;</ingredient> if <ingredient>rum,</ingredient> wet the cloth with <ingredient>rum,</ingredient> &amp;c.</variation> <variation>The very best restorative, for defaced varnished furniture, is <ingredient>rotten-stone</ingredient> pulverized, and rubbed on with <ingredient>linseed oil.</ingredient></variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Sal-volatile,</ingredient> or <ingredient>hartshorn,</ingredient> will 
 
<purpose>restore colors taken out by acid.</purpose>
It may be dropped upon any garment without doing harm.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Spirits of turpentine</ingredient> is good 
 
<purpose>to take grease spots out of woollen clothes; to take spots of paint, &amp;c., from mahogany furniture; and to cleanse white kid gloves.</purpose>
<variation><purpose>Cockroaches, and all vermin,</purpose>
have an aversion to <ingredient>spirits of turpentine.</ingredient></variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>An ounce of <ingredient>quicksilver,</ingredient> beat up with the <ingredient>white of two eggs,</ingredient> and put on with a feather, is the cleanest and surest 
 
<purpose>bed-bug poison.</purpose>
What is left should be thrown away: it is dangerous to have it about the house. <variation>If the vermin are in your walls, fill up the cracks with <ingredient>verdigris-green paint.</ingredient></variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>Lamps</purpose>
will have a less disagreeable smell, if you dip your wick-yarn in <ingredient>strong hot vinegar,</ingredient> and dry it.</p></formula>
<pb n="12" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=20"/>
<formula class="household"><p>Those who make 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="clean-burning candles">candles</alt></purpose>
will find it a great improvement to steep the wicks in <ingredient>lime-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> and dry them. The flame is clearer, and the tallow will not <emph rend="italic">'run.'</emph></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>Brittania ware</purpose>
should be first rubbed gently with a woollen cloth and <ingredient>sweet oil;</ingredient> then washed in <ingredient>warm suds,</ingredient> and rubbed with soft leather and <ingredient>whiting.</ingredient> Thus treated, it will retain its beauty to the last.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="to preserve eggs">Eggs will keep almost any length of time</alt></purpose>
in <purpose>lime-water</purpose>
properly prepared. One pint of <ingredient>coarse salt,</ingredient> and one pint of <ingredient>unslacked lime</ingredient> to a pailful of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> If there be too much <ingredient>lime</ingredient> it will eat the shells from the eggs; and if there be a single egg cracked, it will spoil the whole. They should be covered with <ingredient>lime water,</ingredient> and kept in a cold place. The yolk becomes slightly red; but I have seen eggs, thus kept, perfectly sweet and fresh at the end of three years. The cheapest time to lay down eggs, is early in spring and the middle and last of September. It is bad economy to buy eggs by the dozen, as you want them.</p></formula>
<p>New iron should be very gradually heated at first. After it has become inured to the heat it is not as likely to crack.</p><p>It is a good plan to put new earthen ware into cold water, and let it heat gradually, until it boils,--then cool again. Brown earthen ware in particular, may be toughened in this way. A handful of rye, or wheat brand, thrown in while it is boiling, will preserve the glazing, so that it will not be destroyed by acid or salt.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>Clean a brass kettle,</purpose>
before using it for cooking, with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Skim milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with a bit of <ingredient>glue</ingredient> in it, heated scalding hot, is excellent 
 
<purpose>to restore old, rusty, black Italian crape.</purpose>
If clapped and pulled dry, like nice muslin, it will look as well, or better, than when new.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>Wash-leather gloves</purpose>
should be washed in <ingredient>clean suds,</ingredient> scarcely warm.</p></formula>
<pb n="13" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=21"/><p>The oftener carpets are shaken, the longer they wear; the dirt that collects under them, grinds out the threads.</p><p>Do not have carpets swept any oftener than is absolutely necessary. After dinner, sweep the crumbs into a dusting pan with your hearth-brush; and if you have been sewing, pick up the shreds by hand. A carpet can be kept very neat in this way; and a broom wears it very much.</p>
<section class1="marketing"><p>Buy your woollen yarn in quantities from some one in the country, whom you can trust. The thread-stores make profits, upon it, of course.</p></section>
<formula class="household"><p>It is not well 
 
<purpose>to clean brass</purpose>
andirons, handles, &amp;c. with vinegar. It makes them very clean at first; but they soon spot and tarnish. <ingredient>Rotten-stone</ingredient> and <ingredient>oil</ingredient> are proper materials for cleaning brasses. If wiped every morning with flannel and <ingredient>N. England rum,</ingredient> they will not need to be cleaned half as often.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>If you happen to live in a house which has 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="to clean marble">marble fire-places,</alt></purpose>
never wash them with suds; this destroys the polish, in time. They should be dusted; the spots taken off with a nice oiled cloth, and then rubbed dry with a soft rag.</p></formula>
<p>Feathers should be very thoroughly dried before they are used. For this reason they should not be packed away in bags, when they are first plucked.--They should be laid lightly in a basket, or something of that kind, and stirred up often. The garret is the best place to dry them; because they will there be kept free from dirt and moisture; and will be in no danger of being blown away. It is well to put the parcels, which you may have from time to time, into the oven, after you have removed your bread, and let them stand a day.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>If feather-beds smell badly, or become heavy,</purpose>
from want of proper preservation of the feathers, or from old age, empty them and wash the feathers thoroughly<pb n="14" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=22"/> in a tub of <ingredient>suds;</ingredient> spread them in your garret to dry, and they will be as light and as good as new.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>New England rum</ingredient> constantly used 
 
<purpose>to wash the hair,</purpose>
keeps it very clean, and free from disease; and promotes its growth a great deal more than Macassar oil. <variation><ingredient>Brandy</ingredient> is very strengthening to the roots of the hair; but it has a hot, drying tendency, which N. E. rum has not.</variation></p></formula>
<p>If you wish to preserve fine teeth, always clean them thoroughly, after you have eaten your last meal at night.</p><p>Rags should never be thrown away because they are dirty. Mop-rags, lamp-rags, &amp;c. should be washed, dried, and put in the rag-bag. There is no need of expending soap upon them: boil them out in dirty suds, after you have done washing.</p><p>Linen rags should be carefully saved; for they are extremely useful in sickness. If they have become dirty and worn by cleaning silver, &amp;c. wash them and scape them into lint.</p><p>After old coats, pantaloons, &amp;c. have been cut up for boys, and are no longer capable of being converted into garments, cut them into strips, and employ the leisure moments of children, or domestics, in sewing and braiding them for door-mats.</p>
<formula class="household"><p>If you are troubled to get 
 
<purpose>soft water for washing,</purpose>
fill a tub or barrel, half full of <ingredient>ashes,</ingredient> and fill it up with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> so that you may have lye whenever you want it. A gallon of strong lye put into a great kettle of hard water will make it as soft as rain water. <variation>Some people use <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> or <ingredient>potash;</ingredient> but this costs something, and is very apt to injure the texture of the cloth.</variation></p></formula>
<section class1="farmgarden"><p>If you have a strip of land, do not throw away suds. Both ashes and suds are good manure for bushes and young plants.</p></section>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>When a white Navarino bonnet becomes soiled,</purpose>
rip it in pieces, and wash it with a sponge and <ingredient>soft<pb n="15" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=23"/> water.</ingredient> While it is yet damp, wash it two or three times with a clean sponge dipped into a strong <ingredient>saffron tea,</ingredient> nicely strained. Repeat this till the bonnet is as dark a straw color as you wish. Press it on the wrong side with a warm iron, and it will look like a new Leghorn.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>About the last of May, or the first of June, the little millers which lay moth-eggs begin to appear.--Therefore brush all your woollens, and pack them away in a dark place, covered with linen. <ingredient>Pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>red-cedar chips,</ingredient> <ingredient>tobacco,</ingredient>--indeed, almost any strong spicy smell is good 
 
<purpose>to keep moths out of your chests and drawers.</purpose>
But nothing is so good as <ingredient>camphor.</ingredient> Sprinkle your woollens with <ingredient>camphorated spirit,</ingredient> and scatter pieces of <ingredient>camphor-gum</ingredient> among them and you will never be troubled with moths. <variation>Some people buy camphor-wood for trunks, for this purpose; but they are very expensive, and the gum answers just as well.</variation></p></formula>
<recipe class1="beverages"><p>The <ingredient>first young leaves of the common currant-bush,</ingredient> gathered as soon as they put out, and dried on tin, can hardly be distinguished from 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="imitation green tea">green tea.</alt></purpose></p></recipe>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Cream of Tartar,</ingredient> rubbed upon soiled <ingredient>white</ingredient> 
 
<purpose>kid gloves,</purpose>
cleanses them very much.</p></formula>
<p>Bottles that have been used for rose-water, should be used for nothing else; if scalded ever so much, they will kill the spirit of what is put in them.</p><p>If you have a greater quantity of cheeses in the house than is likely to be soon used, cover them carefully with paper, fastened on with flour paste, so as to exclude the air. In this way they may be kept free from insects for years. They should be kept in a dry, cool place.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Pulverized alum</ingredient> possesses the property of <purpose>purifying water.</purpose> A large spoonful stirred into a <implement>hogshead</implement> of <ingredient>water</ingredient> will so purify it, that in a few hours the dirt will all sink to the bottom, and it will be as fresh and clear as spring water. Four gallons may be purified by a tea-spoonful.</p></formula>
<pb n="16" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=24"/><p>Save vials and bottles. Apothecaries and grocers will give something for them. If the bottles are of good thick glass, they will always be useful for bottling cider, or beer; but if they are thin French glass, like claret bottles, they will not answer.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="washing woollens">Woollens</alt></purpose>
should be washed in very <ingredient>hot suds,</ingredient> and not rinsed. Lukewarm water shrinks them.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>On the contrary, 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="washing silk">silk,</alt></purpose>
or anything that has silk in it, should be washed in <ingredient>water almost cold.</ingredient> Hot water turns it yellow. It may be washed in <ingredient>suds made of nice white soap;</ingredient> but no soap should be put upon it. <variation>Likewise avoid the use of hot irons in 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="ironing silk">smoothing silk.</alt></purpose>
Either rub the articles dry with a soft cloth, or put them between two towels, and press them with weights.</variation></p></formula>
<p>Do not let knives be dropped into hot dish-water. It is a good plan to have a large tin pot to wash them in, just high enough to wash the blades, <emph rend="italic">without wetting</emph> the handles. Keep your castors covered with <implement>blotting paper</implement> and green flannel. Keep your salt-spoons out of the salt, and clean them often.</p><p>Do not wrap knives and forks in woollens. Wrap them in good, strong paper. Steel is injured by lying in woollens.</p>
<section class1="marketing"><p>If it be practicable, get a friend in the country to procure you a quantity of lard, butter, and eggs, at the time they are cheapest, to be put down for winter use. You will be likely to get them cheaper and better than in the City market; but by all means put down your winter's stock. Lard requires no other care than to be kept in a dry, cool place. Butter is sweetest in September and June; because food is then plenty, and not rendered bitter by frost. Pack your butter in a clean, scalded <implement>firkin,</implement> cover it with strong brine, and spread a cloth all over the top, and it will keep good until the Jews get into Grand Isle. If you happen to have a bit of salt-petre dissolve it with the brine. Dairy-women say that butter<pb n="17" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=25"/> comes more easily, and has a peculiar hardness and sweetness, if the cream is scalded and strained before it is used. The cream should stand down cellar over night, after being scalded, that it may get perfectly cold.</p></section>
<p>Suet and lard keep better in tin than in earthen.</p>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="preserving suet">Suet</alt></purpose>
keeps good all the year round, if chopped and packed down in a stone-jar, covered with <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>Pick 
 
<purpose>suet</purpose>
free from veins and skin, melt it in <ingredient>water</ingredient> before a moderate fire, let it cool till it forms into a hard cake, then wipe it dry, and put it in clean paper in linen bags.</p></recipe>
<p>Preserve the backs of old letters to write upon. If you have children who are learning to write, buy coarse white paper by the quantity, and keep it locked up, ready to be made into writing books. It does not cost half as much as it does to buy them at the Stationer's.</p><p>Do not let coffee and tea stand in tin. Scald your wooden ware often; and keep your tin ware dry.</p>
<formula class="household"><p><purpose>When mattresses get hard and bunchy,</purpose>
rip them, take the hair out, pull it thoroughly by hand, let it lie a day or two, to air, wash the tick, lay it in as light and even as possible, and catch it down, as before. Thus prepared, they will be as good as new.</p></formula>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>It is poor economy to buy 
 
<purpose>vinegar,</purpose>
by the gallon. Buy a barrel, or half barrel of really strong <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> when you begin house-keeping. As you use it, fill the barrel with <ingredient>old cider,</ingredient> <ingredient>sour beer,</ingredient> or <ingredient>wine-settlings,</ingredient> &amp;c. left in pitchers, <implement>decanters,</implement> or <implement>tumblers,</implement> <ingredient>weak tea</ingredient> is likewise said to be good: nothing is hurtful, which has a tolerable portion of spirit, or acidity. Care must be taken not to add these things in too large quantities, or too often: if the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> once gets weak, it is difficult to restore it. If possible, it is well to keep such slops as I have mentioned in a different<pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=26"/> keg, and draw them off once in three or four weeks, in such a quantity as you think the vinegar will bear. If by any carelessness you do weaken it, a few <ingredient>white beans</ingredient> dropped in, or <ingredient>white paper dipped in molasses,</ingredient> is said to be useful. <variation>If <ingredient>beer</ingredient> grows sour it may be used to advantage for 
 
<purpose>pancakes and fritters.</purpose></variation> If very sour indeed, put a pint of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> to it, and two or three days after put a half pint of <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> and in ten days it will be first rate vinegar.</p></recipe>
<p>Barley-straw is the best for beds; dry corn husks slit into shreds are far better than straw.</p><p>Straw beds are much better for being boxed at the sides, in the same manner upholsterers prepare ticks for feathers.</p><p>Brass andirons should be cleaned, done up in papers, and put in a dry place, during the summer season.</p>
<section class1="marketing"><p>If you have a large family, it is well to keep white rags separate from colored ones, and cotton separate from woollen; they bring a higher price. Paper brings a cent a pound, and if you have plenty of room, it is well to save it. 'A penny saved is a penny got.'</p></section>
<p>Always have plenty of dish water, and have it hot. There is no need of asking the character of a domestic, if you have ever seen her wash dishes in a little greasy water.</p>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>When 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="to prepare molasses for cooking">molasses</alt></purpose>
is used in cooking, it is a prodigious improvement to boil and skim it, before you use it. It takes out the unpleasant raw taste, and makes it almost as good as sugar. Where <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> is used much for cooking, it is well to prepare one or two gallons in this way at a time.</p></recipe>
<p>In winter, always set the handle of your pump as high as possible, before you go to bed. Except in very rigid weather, this keeps the handle from freezing. When there is reason to apprehend extreme cold, do not forget to throw a rug, or horse-blanket over your pump; a frozen pump is a comfortless preparation for a winter's breakfast.</p><pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=27"/><p>Never allow ashes to be taken up in wood, or put into wood. Always have your tinderbox and lantern ready for use, in case of sudden alarm. Have important papers all together where you can lay your hand on them at once, in case of fire.</p><p>Keep an old blanket and sheet on purpose for ironing, and on no account suffer any other to be used. Have plenty of holders always made that your towels may not be burned out in such service.</p><p>Keep a coarse broom for the cellar stairs, wood-shed, yard, &amp;c. No good housekeeper allows her carpet broom to be used for such things.</p><p>There should always be a heavy stone on the top of your pork, to keep it down. This stone is an excellent place to keep a bit of fresh meat in the summer, when you are afraid of its spoiling.</p><p>Have all the good bits of vegetables and meat collected after dinner, and minced before they are set away; that they may be in readiness to make a little savoury mince meat for supper, or breakfast.</p><p>Vials, which have been used for medicine, should be put into cold ashes and water, boiled, and suffered to cool before they are rinsed.</p><p>If you live in the city, where it is always easy to procure provisions, be careful and not buy too much for your daily wants, while the weather is warm.</p><p>Never leave out your clothes-line over night; and see that your clothes-pins are all gathered into a basket.</p><p>Have plenty of crash towels in the kitchen; never let your white napkins be used there.</p><p>Soap your dirtiest clothes, and soak them in soft water over night.</p><p>Use hard soap to wash your clothes, and soft to wash your floors. Soft soap is so slippery, that it wastes a good deal in washing clothes.</p><p>Instead of covering up your glasses and pictures with muslin, cover the frames only with cheap, yellow<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=28"/> cambric, neatly put on, and as near the color of the gilt as you can procure it. This looks better; leaves the glasses open for use, and the pictures for ornament; and is an effectual barrier to dust as well as flies. It can easily be re-colored with saffron tea, when it is faded.</p>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>Have a bottle full of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> with as large a mouth as any bottle you have, into which cut your <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>orange peel,</ingredient> when they are fresh and sweet. This <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> gives a delicious 
 
<purpose>flavor to all sorts of pies, puddings, and cakes.</purpose>
<ingredient>Lemon</ingredient> is the pleasantest spice of the two; therefore they should be kept in separate bottles. <variation>It is a good plan to preserve <ingredient>rose leaves</ingredient> in <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> The flavor is pleasanter than rosewater; and there are few people who have the utensils for distilling.</variation> <variation><ingredient>Peach leaves</ingredient> steeped in <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> make excellent 
 
<purpose>spice for custards and puddings.</purpose></variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>It is easy to have a supply of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="preserving horseradish">horse-radish</alt></purpose>
all winter. Have a quantity grated, while the root is in perfection, put it in bottles, fill it with strong <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and keep it corked tight.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p>It is thought to be a 
 
<purpose>preventive to the unhealthy influence of cucumbers</purpose>
to cut the slices very thin, and drop each one into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> as you cut it. A few minutes in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> takes out a large portion of the slimy matter, so injurious to health. They should be eaten with high <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<section class1="marketing"><p>Where sweet oil is much used, it is more economical to buy it by the bottle than by the flask. A bottle holds more than twice as much as a flask, and it is never double the price.</p></section>
<formula class="household"><p>If you wish to have 
 
<purpose>free-stone hearths</purpose>
dark, wash them with <ingredient>soap,</ingredient> and wipe them with a wet cloth; some people rub in <ingredient>lamp-oil,</ingredient> once in a while, and wash the hearth faithfully afterwards. This does very well in a large, dirty family; for the hearth looks very clean, and is not liable to show grease spots. But if you wish to preserve the beauty of a free-stone<pb n="21" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=29"/> hearth, buy a quantity of <ingredient>free-stone powder</ingredient> of the stone cutter, and rub on a portion of it wet, after you have washed your hearth in hot <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When it is dry, brush it off, and it will look like new stone. <variation><purpose>Bricks</purpose>
can be kept clean with <ingredient>redding</ingredient> stirred up in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and put on with a brush. <ingredient>Pulverized clay</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>redding,</ingredient> makes a pretty rose color. Some think it is less likely to come off, if mixed with <ingredient>skim milk</ingredient> instead of water. But <ingredient>black lead</ingredient> is far handsomer than anything else for this purpose. It looks very well mixed with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> like redding; but it gives it a glossy appearance to boil the <ingredient>lead</ingredient> in <ingredient>soft soap,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> to keep it from burning. It should be put on with a brush, in the same manner as redding; it looks nice for a long time when done in this way.</variation></p></formula>
<p>Keep a bag for all odd pieces of tape and strings; they will come in use. Keep a bag or box, for old buttons, so that you may know where to go when you want one.</p><p>Run the heels of stockings faithfully; and mend thin places, as well as holes,; 'a stitch in time saves nine.'</p>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Poke-root</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>water</ingredient> and mixed with a good quantity of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> set about the kitchen, the pantry, &amp;c. in large deep plates, will 
 
<purpose>kill cockroaches</purpose>
in great numbers, and finally rid the house of them. <variation>The Indians say that <ingredient>Poke-root</ingredient> boiled into a soft poultice is the cure for the 
 
<purpose>bite of a snake.</purpose>
I have heard of a fine horse saved by it.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>A little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> sprinkled in 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="to prevent starch from sticking">starch</alt></purpose>
while it is boiling, tends to prevent it from sticking; it is likewise good to stir it with a clean <implement>spermaceti candle.</implement></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>A few <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> sliced and <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> poured over them makes an excellent 
 
<purpose>preparation for cleansing and stiffening old rusty black silk.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Green tea</ingredient> is excellent 
 
<purpose>to restore rusty silk.</purpose>
It should be boiled in iron, nearly a cup full to three<pb n="22" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=30"/> quarts. The silk should not be wrung, and should be ironed damp.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Lime</ingredient> pulverized sifted through coarse muslin, and stirred up tolerably thick in <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> makes a strong 
 
<purpose>cement for glass and china.</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Plaster of Paris</ingredient> is still better; particularly for mending broken images of the same material. It should be stirred up by the spoonful, as it is wanted.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>A bit of <ingredient>isinglass</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>gin,</ingredient> is said to make strong 
 
<purpose>cement for broken glass, china, and sea-shells.</purpose></p></formula>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>The 
 
<purpose>Lemon Syrup,</purpose>
usually sold at fifty cents a bottle, may be made much cheaper. Those who use a great quantity of it will find it worth their while to make it. Take about a pound of <ingredient>Havana sugar,</ingredient> boil it in <ingredient>water</ingredient> down to a quart; drop in the <ingredient>white of an egg</ingredient> to clarify it; strain it; add one quarter of an oz. of <ingredient>Tartaric acid,</ingredient> if you do not find it sour enough, after it has stood two or three days, and shaken freely, add more of the acid. A few drops of the <ingredient>Oil of Lemon</ingredient> improves it.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>If you wish 
 
<purpose>to clarify sugar and water you are about to boil,</purpose>
it is well to stir in the <ingredient>white of one egg,</ingredient> while cold; if put in after it boils, the egg is apt to get hardened before it can do any good.</p></recipe>
<p>Those who are fond of soda powders will do well to inquire at the apothecaries for the suitable acid and alkali, and buy them by the ounce, or the pound, according to the size of their families. Experience soon teaches the right proportions; and sweetened with a little sugar, or lemon syrup, it is quite as good as what one gives five times as much for, done up in papers. The case is the same with Rochelle powders.</p></chapter>
<chapter class1="generalnonfood"><pb n="23" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=31"/><hd align="center">SOAP.</hd>
<formula class="generalnonfood"><p>In the city I believe it is better to exchange ashes and grease for 
 
<purpose>soap;</purpose>
but in the country, I am certain it is good economy to make one's own soap. If you burn wood, you can make your own lye; but the ashes of coal is not worth much. Bore small holes in the bottom of a barrel, place four bricks around, and fill the barrel with <ingredient>ashes.</ingredient> Wet the <ingredient>ashes</ingredient> well, but not enough to drop; let it soak thus three or four days; then pour a gallon of <ingredient>water</ingredient> in every hour or two, for a day or more, and let it drop into a pail or tub beneath. Keep it dripping till the color of the lye shows the strength is exhausted. If your lye is not strong enough, you must fill your barrel with fresh <ingredient>ashes,</ingredient> and let the lye run through it. Some people take a barrel without any bottom, and lay sticks and straw across to prevent the ashes from falling through. Three pounds of <ingredient>grease</ingredient> should be put into a pail full of lye. The great difficulty in making soap <emph rend="italic">'come'</emph> originates in want of judgment about the strength of the lye. One rule may be safely trusted--If your lye will bear up an egg, or a potato, so that you can see a piece of the surface as big as ninepence, it is just strong enough. If it sink below the top of the lye, it is too weak, and will never make soap; if it is buoyed up half way, the lye is too strong; and that is just as bad. A bit of <ingredient>quick lime</ingredient> thrown in while the lye and <ingredient>grease</ingredient> are boiling together is of service. When the soap becomes thick and ropy carry it down cellar in pails and empty it into a barrel.</p></formula>
<formula class="generalnonfood"><p><purpose>Cold soap</purpose>
is less trouble, because it does not need to boil; the sun does the work of fire. The <ingredient>lye</ingredient> must be prepared and tried in the usual way. The <ingredient>grease</ingredient> must be tried out, and strained from the scraps. Two pounds of <ingredient>grease,</ingredient> (instead of three) must be used <pb n="24" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=32"/> to a pailful, unless the weather is very sultry, the <ingredient>lye</ingredient> should be hot when put to the <ingredient>grease.</ingredient> It should stand in the sun, and be stirred every day. If it does not begin to look like soap, in the course of five or six days, add a little <ingredient>hot lye</ingredient> to it; if this does not help it, try whether it be <ingredient>grease</ingredient> that it wants. Perhaps you will think cold soap wasteful because the <ingredient>grease</ingredient> must be strained; but if the scraps are boiled thoroughly in strong lye, the <ingredient>grease</ingredient> will all float upon the surface, and nothing be lost.</p></formula>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="medhealth"><hd align="center">SIMPLE REMEDIES.</hd>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Cotton wool</ingredient> wet with <ingredient>sweet oil</ingredient> and <ingredient>paregoric,</ingredient> relieves the 
 
<purpose>ear-ache</purpose>
very soon.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A good quantity of <ingredient>old cheese</ingredient> is the best thing to eat, when 
 
<purpose>distressed by eating too much fruit, or oppressed with any kind of food.</purpose>
Physicians have given it in cases of extreme danger.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Honey</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is very good for 
 
<purpose>worms;</purpose>
<variation>so is strong <ingredient>salt water;</ingredient></variation> <variation>likewise <ingredient>powdered sage</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> taken freely.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>For a sudden attack of 
 
<purpose>quincy, or croup,</purpose>
bathe the neck with <ingredient>bear's grease,</ingredient> and pour it down the throat. <variation>A linen rag soaked in <ingredient>sweet oil,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> and sprinkled with <ingredient>yellow Scotch snuff,</ingredient> is said to have performed wonderful cures in cases of croup: it should be placed where the distress is greatest.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Cotton wool</ingredient> and <ingredient>oil,</ingredient> are the best things for a 
 
<purpose>burn.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A poultice of <ingredient>wheat bran,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rye bran,</ingredient> and <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> very soon takes down the inflammation occasioned by a 
 
<purpose>sprain.</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Brown paper wet</ingredient> is healing to a 
 
<purpose>bruise.</purpose>
Dipped in <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> it is said to take down 
 
<purpose>inflammation.</purpose></variation></p></formula>
<pb n="25" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=33"/>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>In case of any 
 
<purpose>scratch, or wound, from which the lock-jaw is apprehended,</purpose>
bathe the injured part freely with <ingredient>lye,</ingredient> <variation>or <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> and <ingredient>water.</ingredient></variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A <ingredient>rind of pork</ingredient> bound upon a wound occasioned by a needle, pin, or nail, prevents the 
 
<purpose>lock-jaw.</purpose>
It should be always applied. <variation><ingredient>Spirits of turpentine</ingredient> is good to prevent the lock-jaw.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>If you happen to 
 
<purpose>cut yourself slightly while cooking,</purpose>
bind on some <ingredient>fine salt:</ingredient> <variation><ingredient>molasses</ingredient> is likewise good.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Black, or green tea</ingredient> steeped in <ingredient>boiling milk</ingredient> is excellent for the 
 
<purpose>dysentery.</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Cork burnt to charcoal,</ingredient> about as big as a hazle nut, macerated, and put in a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> is very efficacious in cases of 
 
<purpose>dysentery and cholera-morbus.</purpose></variation> <variation>If nutmeg be wanting, <ingredient>peppermint water</ingredient> may be used.</variation> <variation>Flannel wet with <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> powdered with <ingredient>Cayenne pepper,</ingredient> and laid upon the bowels, affords great relief in cases of extreme distress.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Dissolve as much <ingredient>table salt</ingredient> in <ingredient>keen vinegar,</ingredient> as will ferment and work clear. When the foam is discharged, cork it up in a bottle and put it away for use. A large spoonful of this in a gill of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> is very efficacious in cases of 
 
<purpose>dysentery and cholic.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Whortleberries, commonly called huckleberries, dried,</ingredient> are a useful medicine for children. Made into tea and sweetened with <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> they are very beneficial, 
 
<purpose>when the system is in a restricted state, and the digestive powers out of order.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Blackberries</ingredient> are extremely useful in cases of 
 
<purpose>dysentery.</purpose>
To eat the berries is very healthy; <variation><ingredient>tea made of the root and leaves</ingredient> is beneficial;</variation> and <variation>a <ingredient>syrup made of the berries</ingredient> is still better.</variation> <ingredient>Blackberries</ingredient> have sometimes effected a cure when physicians despaired.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Loaf sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> relieve a 
 
<purpose>sore throat;</purpose>
<variation>when very bad, it is good to inhale the <ingredient>steam of scalding hot vinegar</ingredient> through the tube of a <implement>tunnel.</implement> This should be tried carefully at first, lest the throat be scalded. For children, it should be allowed to cool a little.</variation></p></formula>
<pb n="26" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=34"/>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A stocking bound on warm from the foot, at night, is good for the 
 
<purpose>sore throat.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>An ointment made from the <ingredient>common ground-worms,</ingredient> which boys dig to bait fishes, rubbed on with the hand is said to be excellent, when the 
 
<purpose>sinews are drawn up</purpose>
by any disease, or accident.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A gentleman in Missouri advertises that he had an inveterate 
 
<purpose>cancer upon his nose</purpose>
cured by a strong <ingredient>potash made of the lye of the ashes of red oak bark,</ingredient> boiled down to the consistence of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient> The cancer was covered with this, and about an hour after covered with a <ingredient>plaster of tar.</ingredient> This must be removed in a few days, and if any protuberances remain in the wound, apply more <ingredient>potash</ingredient> to them, and the plaster again, until they entirely disappear: after which heal the wound with <ingredient>any common soothing salve.</ingredient> I never knew this to be tried.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>If a 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="bleeding">wound bleeds very fast,</alt></purpose>
and there is no physician at hand, cover it with the <ingredient>scrapings of sole-leather,</ingredient> scraped like coarse lint. This stops blood very soon. Always have <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>camphor,</ingredient> <ingredient>hartshorn,</ingredient> or something of that kind in readiness, as the sudden stoppage of blood almost always makes a person faint.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Balm-of-Gilead buds</ingredient> bottled up in <ingredient>N. E. rum,</ingredient> make the best cure in the world for fresh 
 
<purpose>cuts and wounds.</purpose>
Every family should have a bottle of it. The buds should be gathered in a peculiar state; just when they are well swelled, ready to burst into leaves, and well covered with gum. They last but two or three days in this state.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Plantain</ingredient> and <ingredient>house-leek,</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and strained before it is put away to cool, makes a very 
 
<purpose>cooling, soothing ointment.</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Plantain leaves</ingredient> laid upon a 
 
<purpose>wound</purpose>
are cooling and healing.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Half a spoonful of <ingredient rend="italic">citric acid,</ingredient> (which may always be bought of the apothecaries,) stirred in half a tumbler of <ingredient>water</ingredient> is excellent for the 
 
<purpose>head-ache.</purpose></p></formula>
<pb n="27" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=35"/>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Boiled potatoes</ingredient> are said to cleanse the hands as well as common soap; they prevent 
 
<purpose rend="italic">chops</purpose>
in the winter season, and keep the skin soft and healthy.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Water gruel,</ingredient> with three or four <ingredient>onions</ingredient> simmered in it, prepared with a lump of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> eaten just before one goes to bed, is said to be a cure for a hoarse 
 
<purpose>cold.</purpose>
<variation>A <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> made of <ingredient>horse-raddish root</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is excellent for a cold.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Very strong <ingredient>salt-and-water,</ingredient> when frequently applied has been known to cure 
 
<purpose>wens.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>The following poultice for the 
 
<purpose>throat distemper,</purpose>
has been much approved in England. The <ingredient>pulp of a roasted apple,</ingredient> mixed with an ounce of <ingredient>tobacco,</ingredient> the whole wet with <ingredient>spirits of wine, or any other high spirits;</ingredient> spread on a linen rag, and bound upon the throat at any period of the disorder.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Nothing is so good to take down 
 
<purpose>swellings,</purpose>
as a soft poultice of <ingredient>stewed white beans,</ingredient> put on in a thin muslin bag, and renewed every hour, or two.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>The <ingredient>thin white skin which comes from suet,</ingredient> is excellent to bind upon the feet for 
 
<purpose>chilblains.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Always apply <ingredient>laudanum</ingredient> to fresh 
 
<purpose>wounds.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A poultice of <ingredient>elder-blow tea</ingredient> and <ingredient>biscuit</ingredient> is good as a preventative to 
 
<purpose>mortification.</purpose>
The approach of mortification is generally shown by the formation of blisters filled with <emph rend="italic">blood;</emph> water blisters are not alarming.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Burnt alum</ingredient> held in the mouth is good for the 
 
<purpose>canker.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>The <ingredient>common dark blue violet</ingredient> makes a slimy tea, which is excellent for the 
 
<purpose>canker.</purpose>
<ingredient>Leaves</ingredient> and <ingredient>blossoms</ingredient> are both good. Those who have families should take some pains to dry these flowers.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>When people have a 
 
<purpose>sore mouth,</purpose>
from taking calomel, or any other cause, <ingredient>tea made of low-blackberry leaves</ingredient> is extremely beneficial.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Tea made of slippery elm</ingredient> is good for the 
 
<purpose>piles, and for humors in the blood.</purpose>
To be drank plentifully.<pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=36"/><variation><ingredient>Winter evergreen</ingredient> is considered good for 
 
<purpose>all humors, particularly scrofula.</purpose></variation> <variation>Some call it rheumatism-weed; because a <ingredient>tea</ingredient> made from it is supposed to check that 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="rheumatism">painful disorder.</alt></purpose></variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>An ointment of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> <ingredient>sulphur,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream-of-tartar,</ingredient> simmered together, is good for the 
 
<purpose>piles.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Elixir Proprietatis is a useful family medicine for all cases when the 
 
<purpose>digestive powers are out of order.</purpose>
One ounce of <ingredient>saffron,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>myrrh,</ingredient> and one ounce of <ingredient>aloes.</ingredient> Pulverize them; let the <ingredient>myrrh</ingredient> steep in half a pint of <ingredient>N. E. rum</ingredient> for four days; then add the <ingredient>saffron</ingredient> and <ingredient>aloes;</ingredient> let it stand in the sunshine, or in some warm place, for a fortnight; taking care to shake it well twice a day. At the end of the fortnight fill up the bottle, (a common sized one) with <ingredient>N. E. rum,</ingredient> and let it stand a month. It costs six times as much to buy it in small quantities, as it does to make it.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>The constant use of <ingredient>malt beer,</ingredient> or <ingredient>malt</ingredient> in any way, is said to be a preservative against 
 
<purpose>fevers.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Black cherry tree bark,</ingredient> <ingredient>barberry bark,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard-seed,</ingredient> <ingredient>petty-morrel root,</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> well steeped in <ingredient>cider</ingredient> is excellent for the 
 
<purpose>jaundice.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Cotton wool</ingredient> and <ingredient>oil,</ingredient> are the best things for a 
 
<purpose>burn.</purpose>
<variation><purpose>When children are burned</purpose>
it is difficult to make them endure the application of cotton wool. I have known the inflammation of a very bad burn extracted in one night, by the constant application of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mixed together. This feels cool and pleasant, and a few drops of <ingredient>paragoric</ingredient> will soon put the little sufferer to sleep. The bathing should be continued till the pain is gone.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A few drops of the <ingredient>oil of Cajput</ingredient> on <ingredient>cotton wool</ingredient> is said to be a great relief to the 
 
<purpose>tooth-ache.</purpose>
It occasions a smart pain for a few seconds, when laid upon the defective tooth. Any apothecary will furnish it ready dropped, on <ingredient>cotton wool,</ingredient> for a few cents.</p></formula>
<pb n="29" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=37"/>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A poultice made of <ingredient>common chickweed,</ingredient> that grows about one's door in the country, has given great relief to the 
 
<purpose>tooth-ache,</purpose>
when applied frequently to the cheek.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>A spoonful of <ingredient>ashes</ingredient> stirred in <ingredient>cider</ingredient> is good to prevent 
 
<purpose>sickness at the stomach.</purpose>
Physicians frequently order it in cases of <purpose>cholera-morbus.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><purpose>When a blister occasioned by a burn breaks,</purpose>
it is said to be a good plan to put <ingredient>wheat flower</ingredient> upon the naked flesh.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>The <ingredient>buds of the elder bush,</ingredient> gathered in early spring, and immersed with <ingredient>new butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>sweet lard,</ingredient> makes a very 
 
<purpose>healing and cooling ointment.</purpose></p></formula>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">GRUEL.</purpose>
Gruel is very easily made. Have a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> boiling in a skillet; stir up three or four large spoonfuls of nicely sifted <ingredient>oat-meal,</ingredient> <ingredient>rye,</ingredient> or <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> pour it into the skillet while the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils. Let it boil eight or ten minutes. Throw in a large handful of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> to boil, if the patient is well enough to bear them. When put in a bowl, add a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">ARROW-ROOT JELLY.</purpose>
Put rather more than a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, with some <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> grated <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and two spoonfuls of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Stir up a large spoonful of <ingredient>arrow-root powder</ingredient> in a cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> pour it in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, stir it well and let it boil three or four minutes. This is considered nice food in bowel complaints. <variation><ingredient>Milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> boiled, and a spoonful of <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> well mixed with a little <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> poured in while the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is boiling, is light food in cases of similar diseases.</variation></p></recipe>
<pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=38"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">TAPIOCA JELLY.</purpose>
Wash it two or three times; soak it five or six hours, simmer it in the same <ingredient>water</ingredient> with bits of fresh <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> until it becomes quite clear; then put in <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and <ingredient>loaf sugar.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SAGO JELLY.</purpose>
The <ingredient>sago</ingredient> should be soaked in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> an hour, and washed thoroughly; simmered with <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient> Add <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> when nearly done; and let it all boil together a few minutes.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BEEF-TEA.</purpose>
Beef-tea for the sick, is made by broiling a tender <ingredient>steak</ingredient> nicely, seasoning it with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> cutting it up, and pouring <ingredient>water</ingredient> over it, not quite boiling. Put in a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> at a time, and let it stand to soak the goodness out.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">WINE-WHEY.</purpose>
Wine-whey is a cooling and safe drink in fevers. Set half a pint of <ingredient>sweet milk</ingredient> at the fire, pour in one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and let it remain perfectly still, till it curdles; when the curds settle, strain it, and let it cool. It should not get more than blood-warm. A spoonful of <ingredient>rennet-water</ingredient> hastens the operation. Made palatable with <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> if the patient can bear it.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="fruitvegbeans"><pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=39"/><hd align="center">VEGETABLES.</hd><p>PARSNIPS should be kept down cellar covered up in sand, entirely excluded from the air. They are good only in the spring.</p><p>Cabbages put into a hole in the ground will keep well during the winter, and be hard, fresh, and sweet, in the spring. Many farmers keep potatoes in the same way.</p><p>Onions should be kept very dry; and never carried into the cellar except in severe weather, when there is danger of their freezing. By no means let them be in the cellar after March; they will sprout and spoil. Potatoes should likewise be carefully looked to in the spring, and the sprouts broken off. The cellar is the best place for them, because they are injured by wilting; but sprout them carefully, if you want to keep them. They never sprout but three times; therefore, after you have sprouted them three times, they will trouble you no more.</p><p>Squashes should never be kept down cellar when it is possible to prevent it. Dampness injures them. If intense cold makes it necessary to put them there, bring them up as soon as possible, and keep them in some dry, warm place.</p>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled cabbages">Cabbages</alt></purpose>
need to be boiled an hour; <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled beets">beets</alt></purpose>
an hour and a half.</variation> <variation>The lower part of a 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled squash">squash</alt></purpose>
should be boiled half an hour; the neck pieces fifteen or twenty minutes longer.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled parsnips">Parsnips</alt></purpose>
should boil an hour, or an hour and a quarter, according to size.</variation> <variation>New 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="bolied potatoes">potatoes</alt></purpose>
should boil fifteen or twenty minutes; three<pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=40"/> quarters of an hour, or an hour, is not too much for large, old <ingredient>potatoes;</ingredient> common sized ones half an hour. In the spring, it is a good plan to cut off a slice from the seed end of <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> before you cook them. The seed end is opposite to that which grew upon the vine; the place where the vine was broken off may be easily distinguished. By a provision of nature the seed end becomes watery in the spring; and unless cut off it is apt to injure the potato. If you wish to have <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> mealy, do not let them stop boiling for an instant; and when they are done turn the <ingredient>water</ingredient> off and let them steam for ten or twelve minutes over the fire. See they don't stay long enough to burn to the kettle.</variation> <variation>In Canada, they cut the skin all off and put them in pans, to be cooked over a stove, by steam. Those who have eaten them, say they are mealy, and white,--looking like large snow-balls, when brought upon the table.</variation></p></recipe>
<p>Potatoes boiled and mashed while hot, are good to use in making short cakes and puddings; they save flour, and less shortening is necessary.</p><p>It is said that a bit of unslacked lime, about as big as a robin's egg, thrown among old, watery potatoes, while they are boiling, will tend to make them mealy. I never saw the experiment tried.</p>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled asparagus">Asparagus</alt></purpose>
should be boiled fifteen or twenty minutes; half an hour if old.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled green peas">Green peas</alt></purpose>
should be boiled from twenty minutes to sixty, according to their age; <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled string beans">string beans</alt></purpose>
the same.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled corn">Corn</alt></purpose>
should be boiled from twenty minutes to forty, according to age.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled dandelions">Dandelions</alt></purpose>
half an hour, or three quarters according to age. <ingredient>Dandelions</ingredient> are very much improved by cultivation. If cut off, without injuring the root, they will spring up again, fresh and tender, till late in the season.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled beet-tops">Beet-tops</alt></purpose>
should be boiled twenty minutes;</variation> <variation>and 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled spinach">spinnage</alt></purpose>
three or four minutes.</variation> Put in no green vegetables till the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, if you would keep all their sweetness.</p></recipe>
<pb n="33" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=41"/><p>When green peas have become old and yellow, they may be made tender and green, by sprinkling in a pinch or two of pearlash, while they are boiling. Pearlash has the same effect upon all summer vegetables, rendered tough by being too old. If your well-water is very hard, it is always an advantage to use a little pearlash in cooking.</p>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="stewed tomatoes">Tomatoes</alt></purpose>
should be skinned by pouring <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over them. After they are skinned, they should be stewed half an hour, in tin, with a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a small bit of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> to keep them from burning. This is a delicious vegetable. It is easily cultivated, and yields a most abundant crop. <variation>Some people pluck them green, and pickle them.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>The best sort of 
 
<purpose>catsup</purpose>
is made from <ingredient>tomatoes.</ingredient> The vegetables should be squeezed up in the hand, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> put to them, and set by for twentyfour hours. After being passed through a sieve, <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>all-spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>garlic,</ingredient> and <ingredient>whole mustard-seed</ingredient> should be added. It should be boiled down one third, and bottled after it is cool. No liquid is necessary; as the <ingredient>tomatoes</ingredient> are very juicy. A good deal of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and spice is necessary to keep the catsup well. It is delicious with roast meat; and a cup full adds much to the richness of soup and chowder.</p></recipe>
<p>Celery should be kept in the cellar, the roots covered with tan, to keep them moist.</p><p>Green squashes that are turning yellow, and striped squashes, are more uniformly sweet and mealy than any other kind.</p><p>If the tops of lettuce be cut off when it is becoming too old for use, it will grow up again fresh and tender, and may thus be kept good through the summer.</p></chapter>
<chapter class1="medhealth" class2="accompaniments"><pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=42"/><hd align="center">HERBS.</hd><p>ALL herbs should be carefully kept from the air. Herb-tea, to do any good, should be made <emph rend="italic">very strong.</emph></p><p>Herbs should be gathered while in blossom. If left till they have gone to seed, the strength goes into the seed. Those who have a little patch of ground, will do well to raise the most important herbs; and those who have not, will do well to get them in quantities from some friend in the country; for apothecaries make very great profit upon them.</p>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Sage</ingredient> is very useful both as a medicine for the 
 
<purpose>head-ache,</purpose>--when made into tea--and for all kinds of stuffing, when dried and rubbed into powder. It should be kept tight from the air.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Summer-savoury</ingredient> is excellent to season soup, broth, and sausages. As a medicine, it relieves the 
 
<purpose>cholic;</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>penny-royal</ingredient> and <ingredient>tanzey</ingredient> are good for the same medicinal purpose.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Green wormwood bruised</ingredient> is excellent for a 
 
<purpose>fresh wound</purpose>
of any kind. In winter, when <ingredient>wormwood</ingredient> is dry, it is necessary to soften it in <ingredient>warm vinegar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>spirit,</ingredient> before it is bruised, and applied to the wound.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Hyssop tea</ingredient> is good for 
 
<purpose>sudden colds, and disorders on the lungs.</purpose>
It is necessary to be very careful about exposure after taking it; it is peculiarly opening to the pores.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Tea made of colt's-foot and flax-seed,</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>honey</ingredient> is a cure for 
 
<purpose>inveterate coughs. Consumptions</purpose>
<pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=43"/> have been prevented by it. It should be drank when going to bed; though it does good to drink it at any time. <variation><ingredient>Hoar-hound</ingredient> is useful in consumptive complaints.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Motherwort tea</ingredient> is very quieting to the 
 
<purpose>nerves. Students, and people troubled with wakefulness,</purpose>
find it useful.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Thoroughwort</ingredient> is excellent for 
 
<purpose>dyspepsy, and every disorder occasioned by indigestion.</purpose>
If the stomach be foul, it operates like a gentle emetic.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Sweet-balm tea</ingredient> is cooling 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="fever">when one is in a feverish state.</alt></purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Catnip, particularly the blossoms, made into tea,</ingredient> is good to prevent a threatened 
 
<purpose>fever.</purpose>
It produces a fine perspiration. It should be taken in bed, and the patient kept warm.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p>Housekeepers should always dry leaves of the <ingredient>burdock</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish.</ingredient> <ingredient>Burdocks</ingredient> warmed in <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> with the hard stalky parts cut out, is very 
 
<purpose>soothing, applied to the feet;</purpose>
they produce a sweet and gentle perspiration. <ingredient>Horse-radish</ingredient> is more powerful. It is excellent in cases of the 
 
<purpose>ague,</purpose>
placed on the part affected. Warmed in <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> and clapped.</p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Succory</ingredient> is a very valuable herb. The <ingredient>tea</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> is good for the 
 
<purpose>piles. It is a gentle and healthy physic,--a preventive of dyspepsy, humors, inflammation, and all the evils resulting from a restricted state of the system.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Elder-blow tea</ingredient> has a similar effect. It is 
 
<purpose>cool and soothing; and peculiarly efficacious either for babes, or grown people, when the digestive powers are out of order.</purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="medhealth"><p><ingredient>Lungwort,</ingredient> <ingredient>maiden-hair,</ingredient> <ingredient>hyssop,</ingredient> <ingredient>elecampane</ingredient> and <ingredient>hoar-hound</ingredient> steeped together is an almost certain cure for a 
 
<purpose>cough.</purpose>
A wine-glass full to be taken, when going to bed.</p></formula>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>Few people know how to keep the flavor of 
 
<purpose>sweet-majoram;</purpose>
the best of all herbs for broth, and<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=44"/> stuffing. It should be gathered in bud, or blossom, and dried in a <implement>tin-kitchen</implement> at a moderate distance from the fire; when dry it should be immediately rubbed, sifted, and corked up in a bottle carefully.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="household"><pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=45"/><hd align="center">CHEAP DYE STUFFS.</hd><p>A FEW general rules are necessary to be observed in coloring. The materials should be perfectly clean; soap should be rinsed out in soft water; the article should be entirely wetted, or it will spot; light colors should be steeped in brass, tin, or earthen; and if set at all, should be set with alum. Dark colors should be boiled in iron, and set with copperas. Too much copperas rots the thread.</p>
<formula class="household"><p>The appothecaries and hatters keep a compound of <ingredient>vitriol</ingredient> and <ingredient>indigo,</ingredient> commonly called <ingredient>'Blue Composition.'</ingredient> An ounce vial full may be bought for ninepence. It colors a fine 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="blue dye">blue.</alt></purpose>
It is an economical plan to use it for old silk linings, ribbons, &amp;c. The original color should be boiled out, and the material thoroughly rinsed in <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> so that no soap may remain in it; for soap ruins the dye. Twelve or sixteen drops of the <ingredient>Blue Composition</ingredient> poured into a quart bowl full of <ingredient>warm soft water,</ingredient> stirred, (and strained, if any settlings are perceptible) will color a great many articles. If you wish a deep blue, pour in more of the compound. Cotton must not be colored; the vitriol destroys it; if the material you wish to color has cotton threads in it, it will be ruined. After the things are thoroughly dried, they should be washed in <ingredient>cool suds,</ingredient> and dried again; this prevents any bad effects from the vitriol: if shut up from the air without being washed, there is danger of the texture being destroyed. <variation>If you wish to color 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="green dye">green,</alt></purpose>
have your cloth free as possible from the old color, clean, and rinsed, and, in the first place,<pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=46"/> color it a deep yellow.</variation> <variation><ingredient>Fustic</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>soft water</ingredient> makes the strongest and brightest 
 
<purpose>yellow dye;</purpose>
but <ingredient>saffron,</ingredient> <ingredient>barberry bush,</ingredient> <ingredient>peach leaves,</ingredient> or <ingredient>onion skins</ingredient> will answer pretty well.</variation> Next take a bowl full of strong <ingredient>yellow dye</ingredient> and pour in a great spoonful or more, of the <ingredient>Blue Composition.</ingredient> Stir it up well with a clean stick, and dip the article you have already colored yellow into it, and they will take a lively grass green. This is a good plan for old bombazet curtains, desert cloths, old flannel for covering a desk, &amp;c; it is likewise a handsome color for ribbons.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Balm blossoms,</ingredient> steeped in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> color a pretty 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="pink dye">rose-color.</alt></purpose>
This answers very well for the linings of children's bonnets, for ribbons, &amp;c. It fades in the course of one season; but it is very little trouble to recolor with it. It merely requires to be steeped and strained. Perhaps a small piece of <ingredient>alum</ingredient> might serve to set the color, in some degree. In earthen, or tin.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Saffron</ingredient> steeped in earthen and strained, colors a fine 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="yellow dye">straw color.</alt></purpose>
It makes a delicate or deep shade according to the strength of the tea. <variation>The dry, outside <ingredient>skins of onions</ingredient> steeped in scalding <ingredient>water</ingredient> and strained, color a 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="yellow dye">yellow very much like 'Bird of Paradise' color.</alt></purpose></variation> <variation>Peach leaves, or <ingredient>bark scraped from the barberry bush,</ingredient> colors a 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="yellow dye">common bright yellow.</alt></purpose></variation> In all these cases, a little piece of <ingredient>alum</ingredient> does no harm, and may help to fix the color. Ribbons, gauze handkerchiefs, &amp;c. are colored well in this way, especially if they be stiffened by a bit of <ingredient>Gum-Arabic,</ingredient> dropped in while the stuff is steeping.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>The <ingredient>purple paper, which comes on loaf sugar,</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> or <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> with a small bit of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> makes a fine 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="purple dye">purple-slate color.</alt></purpose>
Done in iron.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>White maple bark</ingredient> makes a good light 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="brown dye">brown-slate color.</alt></purpose>
This should be boiled in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> set with <ingredient>alum.</ingredient> The color is reckoned better when boiled in brass, instead of iron.</p></formula>
<pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=47"/><p>The purple slate, and the brown slate, are suitable colors for stockings; and it is an economical plan, after they have been mended and cut down, so that they will no longer look decent, to color old stockings, and make them up for children.</p>
<formula class="household"><p>A pailful of <ingredient>lye</ingredient> with a piece of <ingredient>copperas</ingredient> half as big as a hen's egg boiled in it, will color a fine 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="yellow dye">nankin color,</alt></purpose>
which will never wash out. This is very useful for the linings of bed-quilts, comforters, &amp;c. Old faded gowns colored in this way, may be made into good petticoats. Cheap cotton cloth may be colored to advantage for petticoats, and pelisses for little girls.</p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p>A very beautiful 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="yellow dye">nankin color</alt></purpose>
may likewise be obtained from <ingredient>birch-bark,</ingredient> set with <ingredient>alum.</ingredient> The bark should be covered with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and boiled thoroughly in brass, or tin. A bit of <ingredient>alum</ingredient> half as big as a hen's egg is sufficient. <variation>If <ingredient>copperas</ingredient> be used instead of alum, 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="gray dye">slate color</alt></purpose>
will be produced.</variation></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Tea-grounds</ingredient> boiled in iron, and set with <ingredient>copperas</ingredient> makes a very good 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="gray dye">slate color.</alt></purpose></p></formula>
<formula class="household"><p><ingredient>Log-wood</ingredient> and <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> in iron, set with <ingredient>copperas,</ingredient> makes a good 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="black dye">black.</alt></purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Rusty nails,</ingredient> or any <ingredient>rusty iron,</ingredient> boiled in <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> with a small bit of <ingredient>copperas,</ingredient> makes a good black,</variation>--<variation><ingredient>black ink-powder</ingredient> done in the same way answers the same purpose.</variation></p></formula>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="meatfishgame" class2="generalfood"><pb n="40" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=48"/><hd align="center">MEAT CORNED, OR SALTED, HAMS, &amp;C.</hd>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>WHEN you merely want 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="corned meat" synonym2="corned beef">to corn meat,</alt></purpose>
you have nothing to do but to rub in <ingredient>salt</ingredient> plentifully, and let it set in the cellar a day, or two. If you have provided more <ingredient>meat</ingredient> than you can use while it is good, it is well to corn it in season to save it. In summer it will not keep well more than a day and a half; if you are compelled to keep it longer, be sure and rub in more <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and keep it carefully covered from cellar-flies. In winter, there is no difficulty in keeping a piece of corned <ingredient>beef</ingredient> a fortnight or more. <variation>Some people corn meat by throwing it into their beef barrel for a few days; but this method does not make it so sweet.</variation> A little <ingredient>salt-petre</ingredient> rubbed in before you apply the <ingredient>common salt,</ingredient> makes the meat tender; but in summer it is not well to use it, because it prevents the other <ingredient>salt</ingredient> from impregnating; and the meat does not keep as well.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>If you wish to 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="salted pork">salt fat pork,</alt></purpose>
scald <ingredient>coarse salt</ingredient> in <ingredient>water</ingredient> and skim it, till the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> will no longer melt in the <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Pack your <ingredient>pork</ingredient> down in tight layers, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> every layer; when the brine is cool, cover the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> with it, and keep a heavy stone on the top to keep the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> under brine. Look to it once in a while, for the first few weeks, and if the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> has all melted, throw in more. This brine, scalded and skimmed every time it is used, will continue good twenty years. The rind of the pork should be packed towards the edge of the barrel.</p></recipe>
<pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=49"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>It is good economy to 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="salted beef">salt your own beef</alt></purpose>
as well as pork. Six pounds of <ingredient>coarse salt,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and eight ounces of <ingredient>salt-petre</ingredient> are enough to boil in four gallons of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Skim it clean while boiling. Put it to the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> cold; have enough to cover it, and be careful your <ingredient>beef</ingredient> never floats on the top. If it does not smell perfectly sweet, throw in more <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> if a scum rises upon it, scald and skim it again, and pour it on the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> when cold.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="cured leg of mutton">Legs of mutton</alt></purpose>
are very good, cured in the same way as ham. Six pounds of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> and five pints of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> will make pickle enough for one hundred weight. Small legs should be kept in pickle twelve or fifteen days; if large, four or five weeks are not too much. They should be hung up a day or two to dry, before they are smoked. Lay them in the oven, on crossed sticks, and make a fire at the entrance. <ingredient>Cobbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>walnut-bark,</ingredient> or <ingredient>walnut-chips,</ingredient> are the best to use for smoking, on account of the sweet taste they give the meat. The smallest pieces should be smoked forty-eight hours, and large legs four or five days. Some people prefer the <ingredient>mutton</ingredient> boiled as soon as it is taken from the pickle, before it is smoked; others hang it up till it gets dry thoroughly, and eat it in thin slices, like hung beef. When legs of meat are put in pickle, the thickest part of the leg should be placed uppermost,--that is, standing upright, the same as the creature stood when living. The same rule should be observed when they are hung up to dry; it is essential in order to keep in the juices of the meat. Meat should be turned over once or twice during the process of smoking.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>The old fashioned way for 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="cured ham">curing hams</alt></purpose>
is to rub them with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> very thoroughly, and let them lay twentyfour hours. To each <ingredient>ham</ingredient> allow two ounces of <ingredient>salt-petre;</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>common salt,</ingredient> and one<pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=50"/> quart of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient> First baste them with <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> next rub in the <ingredient>salt petre;</ingredient> and, last of all, the <ingredient>common salt.</ingredient> They must be carefully turned and rubbed every day for six weeks, then hang them in a chimney, or smoke-house, four weeks.</p><p>They should be well covered up in paper-bags, and put in a chest, or barrel, with layers of <ingredient>ashes,</ingredient> or <ingredient>charcoal,</ingredient> between. When you take out a <ingredient>ham</ingredient> to cut for use, be sure and put it away in a dark place, well covered up; especially in summer.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>Some very experienced epicures and cooks, think the old fashioned way of preparing 
 
<purpose>bacon</purpose>
is troublesome and useless. They say that <ingredient>legs of pork</ingredient> placed upright in pickle, for four or five weeks, are just as nice as those rubbed with so much care. The pickle for pork and hung-beef, should be stronger than for legs of mutton. Eight pounds of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> ten ounces of <ingredient>salt-petre,</ingredient> and five pints of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> is enough for one hundred weight of meat; <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover the meat well--probably, four or five gallons. Any one can prepare bacon, <variation>or 
 
<purpose>dried beef</purpose></variation> very easily, in a common oven, according to the above directions. <variation>The same pickle that answers for bacon is proper for 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="cow tongue">neat's tongues.</alt></purpose></variation> <variation><purpose>Pigs' tongues</purpose>
are very nice, prepared in the same way as neat's tongues; an abundance of them are sold for rein-deer's tongues, and, under that name, considered a wonderful luxury.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="cow tongue">Neat's tongue</alt></purpose>
should be boiled full three hours. If it has been in salt long, it is well to soak it over night in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Put it in to boil when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is cold. If you boil it in a small pot, it is well to change the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> when it has boiled an hour and a half; the fresh <ingredient>water</ingredient> should boil, before the half-cooked <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> is put in again. It is nicer for being kept in a cool place a day or two after being boiled. <variation>Nearly the same rules apply to 
 
<purpose>salt beef.</purpose>
<variation>A six pound piece of 
 
<purpose>corned beef</purpose>
should boil full three hours;</variation> and <ingredient>salt beef</ingredient> should be boiled four hours.<pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=51"/> The salter meat is the longer it should be boiled. If very salt it is well to put it in soak over night; change the <ingredient>water</ingredient> while cooking; and observe the same rules as in <ingredient>boiling tongue.</ingredient> If it is intended to be eaten when cold, it is a good plan to put it between clean boards, and press it down with heavy weights for a day or two.</variation> <variation>A small leg of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled bacon">bacon</alt></purpose>
should be boiled three hours; ten pounds four hours; twelve pounds five hours.</variation> All meat should boil moderately; furious boiling injures the flavor.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose>Buffalo's tongue</purpose>
should soak a day and a night, and boil as much as six hours.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="meatfishgame" class2="marketing"><pb n="44" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=52"/><hd align="center">CHOICE OF MEAT.</hd>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p>If people wish to be economical they should take some pains to ascertain what are the cheapest pieces of meat to buy; not merely those which are cheapest in price, but those which go farthest when cooked. 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="rack of lamb">That part of mutton called the rack,</alt></purpose>
which consists of the neck, and a few of the rib bones below, is cheap food. It is not more than four or five cents a pound; and four pounds will make a dinner for six people. <variation>The <ingredient>neck</ingredient> cut into pieces and boiled slowly an hour and a quarter, in little more than <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover it, makes very nice 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="mutton broth">broth.</alt></purpose>
A great spoonful of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> should be washed and thrown in with the meat. About twenty minutes before it is done, put in a little <ingredient>thickening,</ingredient> and season with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and sifted <ingredient>summer-savory,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sage.</ingredient></variation> <variation>The <ingredient>bones below the neck</ingredient> broiled make a good 
 
<purpose>mutton chop.</purpose></variation> If your family be small, a <ingredient>rack of mutton</ingredient> will make you two dinners,--broth once, and mutton chop with a few slices of <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> for another; if your family consist of six or seven, you can have two dishes for a dinner. <variation>If you boil the whole rack for broth, there will be some left for 
 
<purpose>mince meat.</purpose></variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose>Liver</purpose>
is usually much despised; but when well cooked, it is very palatable; and it is the cheapest of all animal food. <ingredient>Veal liver</ingredient> is by some considered the best. <ingredient>Veal liver</ingredient> is usually two cents a pound; <ingredient>beef liver</ingredient> is one cent. After you have fried a few slices of <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> put the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> in while the fat is very hot, and cook it through thoroughly. If you doubt whether it be done, cut into a slice and see whether<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=53"/> it has turned entirely brown, without any red stripe in the middle. Season it with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> if you live on a farm, and have <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in plenty. It should not be cooked on furiously hot coals, as it is very apt to scorch. Sprinkle in a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> stir it, and pour in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> to make gravy, just as you would for fried meat. <variation>Some think <ingredient>liver</ingredient> is better dipped in sifted <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> before it is fried.</variation> <variation>It is good broiled and buttered like a steak. It should be cut into slices about as thick as are cut for steaks.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p>The <ingredient>heart, liver, &amp;c, of a pig</ingredient> is good fried; so is that of a <ingredient>lamb.</ingredient> The latter is commonly called 
 
<purpose>lamb-fry;</purpose>
and a dinner may be bought for six or eight cents. Be sure and ask for the <ingredient>sweet bread;</ingredient> for butchers are extremely apt to reserve it for their own use; and therefore lamb-fry is almost always sold without it. Fry five or six slices of <ingredient>salt pork;</ingredient> after it is taken out, put in your lamb-fry while the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> is hot. Do it thoroughly; but be careful the fire is not too furious, as it is apt to scorch. Take a large handful of <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> see that it is washed clean, cut it up pretty fine; then pour a little <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> into the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> in which your dinner has been fried, and let the <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> cook in it a minute or two; then take it out in a spoon, and lay it over your slices of meat. Some people, who like thick <ingredient>gravies,</ingredient> shake in a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into the <implement>spider,</implement> before pouring in the <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<p>Bones from which roasting pieces have been cut, may be bought in the market for ten or twelve cents, from which a very rich soup may be made, besides skimming off fat for shortening. If the bones left from the rump be bought, they will be found full of marrow, and will give more than a pint of good shortening, without injuring the richness of the soup. The richest piece of beef for a soup is the leg and the shin of beef; the leg is on the hind quarter, and the shin is on the fore quarter. The leg rand, that<pb n="46" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=54"/> is the thick part of the leg above the bony parts, is very nice for mince pies. Some people have an objection to these parts of beef, thinking they must be stringy, but if boiled <emph rend="italic">very tender</emph> the sinews are not perceived, and add in fact to the richness of a soup.</p><p>The thick part of a thin flank is the most profitable part in the whole ox to buy. It is not so handsome in appearance as some other pieces, but it is thick meat, with very little bone, and is usually two cents less in the pound than more fashionable pieces. It is good for roasting and particularly for corning and salting. The navel end of the brisket is one of the best pieces for salting or corning, and is very good for roasting.</p><p>The rattle rand is the very best piece for corning or salting.</p><p>A bullock's heart is very profitable to use as a steak. Broiled just like beef. There are usually five pounds in a heart, and it can be bought for twenty-five cents. Some people stuff and roast it.</p><p>The chuck between the neck and the shoulder, is a very good piece for roasting,--for steaks, or for salting. Indeed it is good for almost anything; and it is cheap, being from four to five cents a pound.</p><p>The richest, tenderest, and most delicate piece of beef for roasting, or for steak is the rump and the last cut of the sirloin. It is peculiarly appropriate for an invalid, as it is lighter food than any other beef.</p><p>But if economy be consulted instead of luxury, the round will be bought in preference to the rump. It is heartier food, and of course less can be eaten; and it is cheaper in price.</p><p>The shoulder of veal is the most economical for roasting, or boiling. It is always cheap, let veal bear what price it may. Two dinners may be made from it; the shoulder roasted, and the knuck cut off to be boiled with a bit of pork and greens, or to be made into soup.</p><pb n="47" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=55"/><p>The breast of veal is a favorite piece, and is sold high.</p><p>The hind quarter of veal and the loin make two good roasting pieces. The leg is usually stuffed. The line has the kidney upon it; the fore quarter has the brisket on it. This is a sweet and delicate morsel; for this reason some people prefer the fore quarter to any other part.</p><p>Always buy a shoulder of pork for economy, for roasting, or corning to boil. Cut off the leg to be boiled. Many people buy the upper part of the spare-rib of pork, thinking it the most genteel; but the lower part of the spare-rib toward the neck is much more sweet and juicy; and there is more meat in proportion to the bone.</p><p>The breast, or shoulder, of mutton are both nice, either for roasting, boiling, or broth. The breast is richer than the shoulder. It is more economical to buy a fore-quarter of mutton than a hind-quarter; there is usually two cents difference per pound. The neck of fat mutton makes a good steak for broiling.</p><p>Lamb brings the same price, either fore-quarter, or hind-quarter; therefore it is more profitable to buy a hind-quarter than a fore-quarter; especially as its own fat will cook it, and there is no need of pork or butter in addition. Either part is good for roasting or boiling. The loin of lamb is suitable for roasting, and is the most profitable for a small family. The leg is more suitable for boiling than for anything else; the shoulder and breast are peculiarly suitable for broth.</p><p>The part that in lamb is called the loin in mutton is called the chop. Mutton chop is considered very good for broiling.</p>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose>Pig's head</purpose>
is a profitable thing to buy. It is despised, because it is cheap; but when well cooked it is delicious. <variation>Well cleaned, the tip of the 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="pig snout">snout</alt></purpose>
chopped<pb n="48" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=56"/> off, and put in <ingredient>brine</ingredient> a week, it is very good for boiling:</variation> the cheeks in particular, are very sweet; they are better than any other pieces of pork to bake with beans. The <ingredient>head</ingredient> is likewise very good baked about an hour and a half. It tastes like roast pork, and yields abundance of sweet fat, for shortening.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="generalfood"><pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=57"/><hd align="center">COMMON COOKING.</hd><p>IT is necessary to be very careful of fresh meat in the summer season. The moment it is brought into the house it should be carefully covered from the flies, and put in the coldest place in the cellar. If it consist of pieces, they should be spread out separate from each other, on a large dish, and covered. If you are not to cook it soon, it is well to sprinkle salt on it. The kidney, and fat, flabby parts should be raised up above the lean, by a skewer, or stick, and a little salt strewn in. If you have to keep it over night, it should be looked too the last thing when you go to bed; and if there is danger, it should be scalded.</p>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">VEAL.</purpose>
<variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled veal">Veal</alt></purpose>
should boil about an hour, if a neck-piece; if the meat comes from a thicker, more solid part, it should boil longer. No directions about these things will supply the place of judgment and experience. Both mutton and <ingredient>veal</ingredient> are better for being boiled with a small piece of <ingredient>salt-pork.</ingredient></variation> Veal broth is very good.</p><p><variation><purpose>Veal soup</purpose>
should be slowly stewed for two hours. Seasoned the same as above. Some people like a little sifted <ingredient>summer savory.</ingredient></variation></p><p><variation>Six or seven pounds of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted veal">veal</alt></purpose>
will roast in an hour and a half.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Fried veal</purpose>
is better for being dipped in <ingredient>white of egg,</ingredient> and rolled in nicely pounded <ingredient>crumbs of bread,</ingredient> before it is cooked. One egg is enough for a common dinner.</variation></p></recipe>
<pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=58"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CALF'S HEAD.</purpose>
<ingredient>Calf's head</ingredient> should be cleansed with very great care; particularly the lights. The head, the heart, and the lights should boil full two hours; the liver should be boiled only one hour. It is better to leave the wind-pipe on, for if it hangs out of the pot while the <ingredient>head</ingredient> is cooking, all the froth will escape through it. The brains, after being thoroughly washed, should be put in a little bag, with one <ingredient>pounded cracker,</ingredient> or as much <ingredient>crumbled bread,</ingredient>--seasoned with sifted <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> and tied up and boiled one hour. After the brains are boiled, they should be well broken up with a knife, and peppered, salted, and buttered. They should be put upon the table in a bowl by themselves. <ingredient>Boiling water,</ingredient> thickened with <ingredient>flour-and-water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted in it is the proper sauce; some people love <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> mixed with the <ingredient>melted butter;</ingredient> but all are not fond of it; and it is easy for each one to add it for themselves.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BEEF.</purpose>
<variation><purpose>Beef-soup</purpose>
should be stewed four hours over a slow fire. Just <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to keep the meat covered. If you have any <ingredient>bones</ingredient> left of roast meat, &amp;c, it is a good plan to boil them with the meat, and take them out half an hour before the soup is done. A pint of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> twelve or sixteen <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> should be put in twenty minutes before the soup is done. Be careful and not throw in <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> too plentifully; it is easy to add to it; and not easy to diminish. A <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> cut up and put in half an hour before it is done, adds to the flavor. If you have <ingredient>tomato catsup</ingredient> in the house, a cup full will make soup rich. Some people put in <ingredient>crackers;</ingredient> some thin slices of crust, made nearly as short as common<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=59"/> short-cake; and some stir up two or three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and drop it in with a spoon.</variation></p><p><variation>A quarter of an hour to each pound of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted beef">beef</alt></purpose>
is considered a good rule for roasting; but this is too much when the bone is large, and the meat thin. Six pounds of the <ingredient>rump</ingredient> should roast six quarters of an hour; but bony pieces less. It should be done before a quick fire.</variation></p><p><variation>The quicker 
 
<purpose>beef-steak</purpose>
can be broiled the better. Seasoned after it is taken from the <implement>gridiron.</implement></variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">ALAMODE BEEF.</purpose>
Tie up a <ingredient>round of beef</ingredient> so as to keep it in shape, make a stuffing of <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> a few <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> pounded, <ingredient>yolk of an egg.</ingredient> Cut holes in the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> and put in the stuffing, leaving about half the stuffing to be made into balls. Tie the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> up in a cloth, just cover it with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it boil an hour and a half; then turn it, and let it boil an hour and a half more. Then turn out the liquor, and put some skewers across the bottom of the pot, and lay the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> upon it, to brown; turn it that it may brown on both sides. Put a pint of <ingredient>claret,</ingredient> and some <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> and <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> into the liquor, and boil some balls, made of the stuffing in it.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">MUTTON AND LAMB.</purpose>
<variation>Six or seven pounds of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted mutton">mutton</alt></purpose>
will roast in an hour and a half.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="roasted lamb">Lamb</alt></purpose>
one hour.</variation> <ingredient>Mutton</ingredient> is apt to taste strong; this may be helped by soaking the meat in a little <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> for an hour before cooking. However, unless meat is very sweet, it is best to corn it, and boil it.</p><p>Fresh meat should never be put in to cook till the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils; and it should be boiled in as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible; otherwise the flavor is injured. 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled mutton">Mutton</alt></purpose>
enough for a family of five or six should boil an<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=60"/> hour and a half. <variation>A 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled leg of lamb">leg of lamb</alt></purpose>
should boil an hour, or little more than an hour, perhaps.</variation> Put a little <ingredient>thickening</ingredient> into <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> strain it nicely; and put <ingredient>sweet butter</ingredient> in it for sauce. <variation>If your family like 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="mutton broth" synonym2="lamb broth">broth,</alt></purpose>
throw in some clear <ingredient>rice</ingredient> when you put in the meat. The <ingredient>rice</ingredient> should be in proportion to the quantity of broth you mean to make. A large table spoonful is enough for three pints of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Seasoned with a very little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> <ingredient>Summer savory,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> rubbed through a sieve, thrown in.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PORK.</purpose>
Fresh <ingredient>pork</ingredient> should be cooked more than any other meat. <variation>A thick shoulder piece should be roasted full two hours and a half; and other pieces less in proportion. The slight sickness occasioned by eating 
 
<purpose>roasted pork</purpose>
may be prevented by soaking it in <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> the night before you cook it. If called to prepare it upon short notice, it will answer to baste it with <ingredient>weak brine</ingredient> while roasting,--and then turn the <ingredient>brine</ingredient> off, and throw it away.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">ROAST PIG.</purpose>
Strew <ingredient>fine salt</ingredient> over it an hour before it is put down. It should not be cut entirely open; fill it up plump with thick slices of <ingredient>buttered bread,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> and <ingredient>sage.</ingredient> Spit it with the head next the point of the spit; take off the joints of the leg and boil them with the liver, with a little whole <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> for <ingredient>gravy sauce.</ingredient> The upper part of the legs must be braced down with skewers. Shake on <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Put a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the <implement>dripping-pan,</implement> and stir it often. When the eyes drop out the <ingredient>pig</ingredient> is half done. When it is nearly done, baste it with <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Cut off the head, split it open between the eyes. Take out the brains and chop them fine<pb n="53" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=61"/> with the liver and some <ingredient>sweet-marjoram</ingredient> and <ingredient>sage;</ingredient> put this into <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and when it has boiled a few minutes, add it to the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> in the <implement>dripping pan.</implement> When your <ingredient>pig</ingredient> is cut open, lay it with the back to the edge of the dish; half a head to be placed at each end. A good sized <ingredient>pig</ingredient> needs to be roasted three hours.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SAUSAGES.</purpose>
Three tea-spoons of <ingredient>powdered sage,</ingredient> one and a half of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and one of <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> to a pound of meat, is good seasoning for sausages.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">MINCE MEAT.</purpose>
There is a great difference in preparing mince meat. Some make it a coarse, unsavory dish; and others make it nice and palatable. No economical housekeeper will despise it; for <ingredient>broken bits of meat and vegetables</ingredient> cannot so well be disposed of in any other way. If you wish to have it nice, mash your <ingredient>vegetables</ingredient> fine, and chop your meat very fine. Warm it with what remains of <ingredient>sweet gravy,</ingredient> or <ingredient>roast-meat drippings,</ingredient> you may happen to have. Two or three <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pared, cored, sliced, and fried, to mix with it is an improvement. Some like a little sifted <ingredient>sage</ingredient> sprinkled in.</p><p>It is generally considered nicer to chop your <ingredient>meat</ingredient> fine, warm it in <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> season it, and lay it upon a large slice of <ingredient>toasted bread</ingredient> to be brought upon the table without being mixed with potatoes; but if you have cold vegetables, use them.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BEANS AND PEAS.</purpose>
<variation><purpose>Baked beans</purpose>
are a very simple dish, yet few cook them well. They should be put in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and<pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=62"/> hung over the fire, the night before they are baked. In the morning they should be put in a <implement>cullender</implement> and rinsed two or three times. Then again placed in a kettle, with the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> you intend to bake, covered with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and kept scalding hot, an hour, or more. A pound of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> is quite enough for a quart of <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> and that is a large dinner for a common family. The <ingredient>rind of the pork</ingredient> should be slashed. Pieces of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> alternately fat and lean, are the most suitable; the <ingredient>cheeks</ingredient> are the best. A little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> sprinkled among the <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> when they are placed in the <implement>bean-pot,</implement> will render them less unhealthy. They should be just covered with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> when put into the oven; and the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> should be sunk a little below the surface of the <ingredient>beans.</ingredient> Bake three or four hours.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Stewed beans</purpose>
are prepared in the same way. The only difference is they are not taken out of the scalding <ingredient>water,</ingredient> but are allowed to stew in more <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with a piece of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> three hours or more.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Dried peas</purpose>
need not be soaked over night. They should be stewed slowly four or five hours in considerable <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with a piece of <ingredient>pork.</ingredient> The older beans and peas are, the longer they should cook. Indeed this is the case with all vegetables.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SOUSE.</purpose>
<ingredient>Pig's feet, ears, &amp;c.</ingredient> should be cleaned after being soaked in <ingredient>water</ingredient> not very hot; the hoofs will then come off easily with a sharp knife; the hard, rough places should be cut off; they should be thoroughly singed, and then boiled as much as four or five hours, until they are too tender to be taken out with a fork. When taken from the <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> it should be put into <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> After it is packed down tight, boil the jelly like liquor in which it was cooked with an equal quantity of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> as you think fit, and<pb n="55" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=63"/><ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> at the rate of a quarter of a pound to one hundred weight: to be poured on scalding hot.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">TRIPE.</purpose>
<ingredient>Tripe</ingredient> should be kept in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> or it will become too dry for cooking. The <ingredient>water</ingredient> in which it is kept should be changed more or less frequently, according to the warmth of the weather. Broiled like a steak, buttered, peppered, &amp;c. Some people like it prepared like souse.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">GRAVY.</purpose>
Most people put half a pint of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> into their <implement>tin-kitchen,</implement> when they set meat down to roast. This does very well; but gravy is better flavored and looks darker, to shake <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> upon the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> let it brown thoroughly, put <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> on again, and then baste the meat with about half a pint of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> (or more, according to the gravy you want.) When the meat is about done, pour these drippings into a skillet, and let it boil. If it is not thick enough shake in a little <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> but be sure to let it boil, and be well stirred, after the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is in. If you fear it will be too greasy, take off a cupful of the fat before you boil. <variation>The <ingredient>fat of beef, pork, turkeys and geese</ingredient> is as good for 
 
<purpose>shortening</purpose>
as lard.</variation> <ingredient>Salt</ingredient> gravy to your taste. If you are very particular about dark gravies, keep your <implement>drudging-box</implement> full of <ingredient>scorched flour</ingredient> for that purpose.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">POULTRY.</purpose>
There are various ways of deciding about the age of poultry.</p><p>If the bottom of the breast bone, which extends down between the legs, is soft, and gives easily, it is a sign of youth; if stiff, the poultry is old.</p><pb n="56" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=64"/><p>If young, the legs are lighter, and the feet do not look so hard, stiff, and worn.</p><p>There is more deception in geese than in any other kind of poultry. The above remarks are applied to them; but there are other signs more infallible. In a young goose the cavity under the wings is very tender; it is a bad sign if you cannot, with very little trouble push your finger directly into the flesh. There is another means by which you may decide whether a goose be tender, if it be frozen or not. Pass the head of a pin along the breast, or sides, and if the goose be young, the skin will rip, like fine paper under a knife.</p><p>Something may be judged concerning the age of a goose by the thickness of the web between the toes. When young, this is tender and transparent; it grows coarser and harder with time.</p><p><variation>In 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="broiled chicken">broiling chickens</alt></purpose>
it is difficult to do the inside of the thickest pieces without scorching the outside. It is a good plan to parboil them about ten minutes in a <implement>spider</implement> or skillet, covered close to keep the steam in; then put them upon the <implement>gridiron,</implement> broil and butter. It is a good plan to cover them with a plate, while on the <implement>gridiron.</implement> They may be basted with a very little of the <ingredient>water in which they were broiled;</ingredient> and if you have company who like <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> to pour upon the <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> the remainder of the liquor will be good use for that purpose.</variation></p><p><variation>An hour is enough for common sized 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted chicken">chickens</alt></purpose>
to roast. A smart fire is better than a slow one; but they must be tended closely. Slices of <ingredient>bread buttered, salted, and peppered,</ingredient> put into the stomach (not the crop) is excellent.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled chicken">Chickens</alt></purpose>
should boil about an hour. If old they should boil longer. In as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as will cook them.</variation> <variation><purpose>Chicken-broth</purpose>
made like mutton-broth.</variation></p><p><variation>A common sized 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted goose">goose</alt></purpose>
should roast full three quarters of an hour.</variation> <variation>The <ingredient>oil</ingredient> that drips from it should<pb n="57" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=65"/> be nearly all turned off: it makes the gravy too greasy; and it is nice for 
 
<purpose>shortening.</purpose>
It should first be turned into <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> when hardened, it should be taken off and scalded in a skillet. This process leaves it as sweet as lard.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="roasted duck">Ducks</alt></purpose>
do not need to be roasted more than fifteen or twenty minutes.</variation> <variation><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> melted in <ingredient>boiling flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> is proper 
 
<purpose>sauce for boiled lamb, mutton, veal, turkies, geese, chickens, and fish.</purpose>
Some people cut up <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> fine, and throw in. Some people like <ingredient>capers</ingredient> put in. Others heat <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> through on the <implement>gridiron,</implement> and take them out of the shells, and throw them into the <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></variation></p><p><variation>A good sized 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="roasted turkey">turkey</alt></purpose>
should be roasted two hours and a half, or three hours; very slowly at first.</variation> <variation>If you wish to make plain stuffing, pound a <ingredient>cracker,</ingredient> or crumble some <ingredient>bread</ingredient> very fine, chop some raw <ingredient>salt pork</ingredient> very fine, sift some <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> (and <ingredient>summer-savory,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sweet-marjorum</ingredient> if you have them in the house, and fancy them) and mould them all together seasoned with a little <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient> An <ingredient>egg</ingredient> worked in makes the stuffing cut better; but it is not worth while, when eggs are dear.</variation> <variation>About the same length of time is required for 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled turkey">boiling</alt></purpose>
and roasting.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="potted pigeon">Pigeons,</alt></purpose>
may be either roasted, potted, or stewed. Potting is the best, and the least trouble. After they are thoroughly picked and cleaned, put a small slice of <ingredient>salt pork</ingredient> and a little ball of <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> into the body of every <ingredient>pigeon.</ingredient> The stuffing should be made of one <ingredient>egg</ingredient> to one <ingredient>cracker,</ingredient> an equal quantity of <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> seasoned with <ingredient>sweet marjorum,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> if marjorum cannot be procured.</variation> <ingredient>Flour</ingredient> the <ingredient>pigeons</ingredient> well, lay them close together in the bottom of the pot, just cover them with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> throw in a bit of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and let them stew an hour and a quarter, if young; an hour and three quarters, if old. Some people turn off the liquor just before they are done, and brown the <ingredient>pigeons</ingredient> on the bottom of the pot; but<pb n="58" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=66"/> this is very troublesome, as they are apt to break to pieces.</p><p><variation><purpose>Stewed pigeons</purpose>
are cooked in nearly the same way, with the omission of the stuffing. Being dry meat they require a good deal of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="roasted pigeon">Pigeons</alt></purpose>
should be stuffed and roasted about fifteen minutes before a smart fire. Those who like birds just warmed through, would perhaps think less time necessary. It makes them nicer to <ingredient>butter</ingredient> them well just before you take them off the spit, and sprinkle them with nicely pounded <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cracker.</ingredient></variation> All poultry should be basted, and floured a few minutes before it is taken up.</p><p>The age of pigeons can be judged by the color of the legs. When young they are of a pale delicate brown; as they grow older the color is deeper and redder.</p><p><variation>A nice way of serving up <ingredient>cold chicken,</ingredient> or <ingredient>pieces of cold fresh meat,</ingredient> is to make them into a 
 
<purpose>meat pie.</purpose>
The <ingredient>gizzards, livers, and necks of poultry</ingredient> parboiled, are good for the same purpose. If you wish to bake your meat pie, line a deep earthen or tin pan with paste made of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lard;</ingredient> use but little <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> for the fat of the meat will shorten the crust. Lay in your bits of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> or <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> with two or three slices of <ingredient>salt pork;</ingredient> place a few thin slices of your paste here and there; drop in an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> if you have plenty. Fill the pan with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> seasoned with a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> If the meat be very lean, put in a piece of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or such <ingredient>sweet gravies</ingredient> as you may happen to have. Cover the top with crust, and put it in the oven, or <implement>bake-kettle,</implement> to cook twenty minutes or half an hour, or an hour, according to the size of the pie. Some people think this the nicest way of cooking whole <ingredient>chickens.</ingredient> When thus cooked they should be parboiled before they are put into the pan, and the <ingredient>water</ingredient> they are boiled in should be added. They need to be baked fifteen minutes longer than meat previously cooked.</variation></p><pb n="59" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=67"/><p><variation>If you wish to make a 
 
<purpose>pot pie</purpose>
instead of a baked pie you have only to line the bottom of a <implement>porridge pot</implement> with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> lay in your meat, season and moisten it in the same way, cover it with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and keep it slowly stewing about the same time that the other takes. In both cases it is well to lift the upper crust a little while before you take up the pie, and see whether the moisture has dried away; if so pour in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> well mixed.</variation></p><p>Potatoes should be boiled in a separate vessel.</p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to preserve poultry">If you have fear that poultry may become musty before you want to cook it,</alt></purpose>
skin an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> and put in it; a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> sprinkled in is good; it should be kept hung up, in a dry cool place.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>If poultry is injured, before you are aware of it,</purpose>
wash it very thoroughly in <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and sprinkle <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> inside when you cook it. Some people hang up poultry with a muslin bag of <ingredient>charcoal</ingredient> inside. It is a good plan to singe injured poultry over <ingredient>lighted charcoal,</ingredient> and to hold a piece of <ingredient>lighted charcoal</ingredient> inside, a few minutes.</variation></p><p><variation>Many people parboil the <ingredient>liver</ingredient> and <ingredient>gizzard,</ingredient> and cut it up very fine to be put into the 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="poultry gravy">gravy,</alt></purpose>
while the fowls are cooking; in this case, the <ingredient>water</ingredient> they are boiled in should be used to make the gravy.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">FISH.</purpose>
Cod has white stripes, and a haddock black stripes; they may be known apart by this. Haddock is the best for frying; and cod is the best for boiling, or for a chowder. A thin tail is a sign of a poor fish; always choose a thick fish.</p><p>When you are buying mackerel pinch the belly to ascertain whether it is good. If it gives under your finger, like a bladder half filled with wind, the fish is poor; if it feels hard like butter, the fish is good. It is cheaper to buy one large mackerel for ninepence, than two for four pence half-penny.</p><pb n="60" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=68"/><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="fried fish">Fish</alt></purpose>
should not be put in to fry until the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> is boiling hot; it is very necessary to observe this. It should be dipped in <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> before it is put in; and the skinny side uppermost, when first put in, to prevent its breaking. It relishes better to be fried after <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> than to be fried in <ingredient>lard</ingredient> alone.</variation> People are mistaken, who think fresh fish should be put into cold water, as soon as it is brought into the house; soaking it in water is injurious. If you want to keep it sweet, clean it, wash it, wipe it dry with a clean towel, sprinkle salt inside and out, put it in a covered dish, and keep it on the <emph rend="italic">cellar</emph> floor, until you want to cook it. If you live remote from the seaport, and cannot get fish while hard and fresh, wet it with an egg beaten, before you meal it, to prevent its breaking.</p><p><variation><purpose>Fish gravy</purpose>
is very much improved by taking out some of the <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> after the fish is fried, and putting in a little <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> The <ingredient>fat</ingredient> thus taken out will do to fry fish again; but it will not do for any kind of shortening. Shake in a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into the <ingredient>hot fat,</ingredient> and pour in a little <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> stir it up well as it boils a minute, or so. Some people put in <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> but this is easily added by those who like it.</variation></p><p><variation>A common sized 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled cod">cod fish</alt></purpose>
should be put in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is boiling hot, and boil about twenty minutes.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled haddock">Haddock</alt></purpose>
is not as good for boiling as cod; it takes about the same time to boil.</variation></p><p><variation>A piece of 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="boiled halibut">Halibot</alt></purpose>
which weighs four pounds is a large dinner for a family of six or seven. It should boil forty minutes. No <ingredient>fish</ingredient> put in till the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils. <ingredient>Melted butter</ingredient> for sauce.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="boiled clams">Clams</alt></purpose>
should boil about fifteen minutes in their own <ingredient>water;</ingredient> no other need be added, except a spoonful to keep the bottom shells from burning. It is easy to tell when they are done, by the shells starting wide open. After they are done they should be taken from the shells, washed thoroughly in their own<pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=69"/><ingredient>water,</ingredient> and put in a <implement>stewing pan.</implement> The <ingredient>water</ingredient> should then be strained through a cloth, so as to get out all the grit; the <ingredient>clams</ingredient> should be simmered in it ten or fifteen minutes; a little thickening of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> added; half a dozen slices of <ingredient>toasted bread,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cracker;</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to your taste. <ingredient>Salt</ingredient> is not needed.</variation></p><p><variation>Four pounds of <ingredient>fish</ingredient> are enough to make a 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="fish chowder">chowder,</alt></purpose>
for four or five people,--half dozen slices of <ingredient>salt pork</ingredient> in the bottom of the pot,--hang it high, so that the pork may not burn,--take it out when done very brown,--put in a layer of <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> cut in lengthwise slices,--then a layer formed of <ingredient>crackers,</ingredient> small or sliced <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> and <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> sliced as thin as a four-pence, mixed with pieces of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> you have fried; then a layer of <ingredient>fish</ingredient> again, and so on. Six <ingredient>crackers</ingredient> are enough. Strew a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> over each layer; over the whole pour a bowl full of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> enough to come up even with the surface of what you have in the pot. A sliced <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> adds to the flavor. A cup of <ingredient>Tomato catsup</ingredient> is very excellent. Some people put in a cup of <ingredient>beer.</ingredient> A few <ingredient>clams</ingredient> are a pleasant addition. It should be covered so as not to let a particle of steam escape, if possible. Do not open it, except when nearly done, to taste if it be well seasoned.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Salt fish</purpose>
should be put in a deep plate, with just <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover it, the night before you intend to cook it. It should not be boiled an instant; boiling renders it hard. It should lie in <ingredient>scalding hot water,</ingredient> two, or three hours. The less <ingredient>water</ingredient> is used, and the more <ingredient>fish</ingredient> is cooked at once, the better. <ingredient>Water</ingredient> thickened with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> while boiling, with <ingredient>sweet butter</ingredient> put in to melt, is the common sauce. It is more economical to cut <ingredient>salt pork</ingredient> into small bits, and try it till the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> is brown and crispy. It should not be done too fast, lest the sweetness be scorched out.</variation></p><pb n="62" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=70"/><p><variation><purpose>Salted shad and mackerel</purpose>
should be put into a deep plate and covered with <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> for about ten minutes after it is thoroughly broiled, before it is buttered. This makes it tender, takes off the coat of salt, and prevents the strong oily taste, so apt to be unpleasant in preserved fish.</variation> <variation>The same rule applies to smoked salmon.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Salt fish</purpose>
mashed with <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> with good <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>pork scraps,</ingredient> to moisten it is nicer the second day, than it was the first. The <ingredient>fish</ingredient> should be minced very fine, while it is warm. After it has got cold and dry it is difficult to do it nicely. <ingredient>Salt fish</ingredient> needs plenty of vegetables, such as <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>beets,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> &amp;c.</variation></p><p><variation>There is no way of preparing 
 
<purpose>salt fish for breakfast,</purpose>
so nice as to roll it up in little balls, after it is mixed with <ingredient>mashed potatoes,</ingredient> dip it into an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and fry it brown.</variation></p><p>A female lobster is not considered so good as a male. In the female, the sides of the head, or what look like cheeks, are much larger, and jut out more than those of the male. The mouth of a lobster is surrounded with what children call 'purses' edged with a little fringe. If you put your hand under these to raise it, and find it springs back hard and firm, it is a sign the lobster is fresh; if they move flabbily it is not a good omen.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="eggscheesedairy"><pb n="63" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=71"/><hd align="center">PUDDINGS.</hd>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BAKED INDIAN PUDDING.</purpose>
INDIAN pudding is good baked. Scald a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> (<ingredient>skimmed milk</ingredient> will do) and stir in seven heaped table spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a tea-cupful of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and a great spoonful of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> or sifted <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> Baked three or four hours. If you want whey, you must be sure and pour in a little <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> after it is all mixed.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BOILED INDIAN PUDDING.</purpose>
Indian pudding should be boiled four or five hours. Sifted <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> and <ingredient>warm milk</ingredient> should be stirred together pretty stiff. A little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and two or three great spoonfuls of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> added; a spoonful of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> if you like that spice. Boil it in a tight covered pan, or a very thick cloth; if the water gets in it will ruin it. Leave plenty of room; for Indian swells very much. The <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with which you mix it should be merely warm; if it be scalding, the pudding will break to pieces. Some people chop <ingredient>sweet suet</ingredient> fine, and warm in the <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> others warm thin slices of <ingredient>sweet apple</ingredient> to be stirred into the pudding. <variation><ingredient>Water</ingredient> will answer instead of milk.</variation></p></recipe>
<pb n="64" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=72"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">FLOUR, OR BATTER PUDDING.</purpose>
Common flour pudding, or batter pudding is easily made. Those who live in the country can beat up five or six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> with a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make it just thick enough to pour without difficulty. <variation>Those who live in the city, and are obliged to buy <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> can do with three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a quart, and more <ingredient>flour</ingredient> in proportion.</variation> Boil about three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BREAD PUDDING.</purpose>
A nice pudding may be made of <ingredient>bits of bread.</ingredient> They should be crumbled and soaked in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> over night. In the morning beat up three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> with it, add a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> tie it up in a bag, or in a pan that will exclude every drop of water, and boil it little more than an hour. No puddings should be put into the pot, till the water boils. <variation><ingredient>Bread</ingredient> prepared in the same way makes good 
 
<purpose>plum-puddings.</purpose>
<ingredient>Milk</ingredient> enough to make it quite soft; four <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> a little <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon-brandy,</ingredient> if you have it; a tea-cupful of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> to your taste, if you prefer it, a few dry, clean <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> sprinkled in, and stirred up thoroughly, is all that is necessary. It should bake about two hours.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">RENNET PUDDING.</purpose>
If your husband brings home company when you are unprepared, rennet pudding may be made at five minutes notice; provided you keep a piece of <ingredient>calf's rennet,</ingredient> ready prepared soaking in a bottle of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient> One glass of this <ingredient>wine</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> will make a sort of cold custard. Sweetened with <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> and spiced with <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> it is very good. It should be eaten immediately; in a few hours it begins to curdle.</p></recipe>
<pb n="65" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=73"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CUSTARD PUDDINGS.</purpose>
Custard puddings sufficiently good for common use can be made with five <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> and spiced with <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and very little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> It is well to boil your <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and set it away till it gets cold. <ingredient>Boiling milk</ingredient> enriches it so much that boiled skim-milk is about as good as new milk. A little <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach leaves,</ingredient> if you do not dislike the taste, boiled in the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and afterwards strained from it, give a pleasant flavor. Bake fifteen or twenty minutes.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">RICE PUDDINGS.</purpose>
If you wish a common rice pudding to retain its flavor, do not soak it, or put it in to boil when the water is cold. Wash it, tie it in a bag, leave plenty of room for it to swell, throw it in when the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boils, and let it boil about an hour and a half. The same sauce answers for all these kinds of puddings. If you have <ingredient>rice</ingredient> left cold, break it up in a little <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> pour <ingredient>custard</ingredient> over it and bake it as long as you should custard. It makes very good puddings and pies.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BIRD'S NEST PUDDING.</purpose>
If you wish to make what is called 'Bird's-nest puddings,' prepare your <ingredient>custard,</ingredient>--take eight or ten pleasant <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pare them and dig out the core, but leave them whole, set them in a <implement>pudding dish,</implement> pour your custard over them, and bake them about twenty or thirty minutes.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">APPLE PUDDING.</purpose>
A plain unexpensive apple pudding may be made by rolling out a bit of <ingredient>common pie-crust,</ingredient> and filling<pb n="66" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=74"/> it full of quartered <ingredient>apples;</ingredient> tied up in a bag and boiled an hour and a half; if the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> are sweet, it will take two hours; for acid things cook easily. <variation>Some people like little 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="apple dumplings">dumplings,</alt></purpose>
made by rolling up one <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> pared and cored, in a piece of <ingredient>crust,</ingredient> and tying them up in spots all over the bag. These do not need to be boiled more than an hour; three quarters is enough, if the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> are tender.</variation></p><p>Take a sweet, or pleasant-flavored <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> pare them, and bore out the core, without cutting the <ingredient>apple</ingredient> in two. Fill up the holes with washed <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> boil them in a bag, tied very tight, an hour and a half. Each <ingredient>apple</ingredient> should be tied up separately, in different corners of the <implement>pudding bag.</implement></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center"><alt synonym1="cherry dumplings">CHERRY PUDDING.</alt></purpose>
For cherry dumpling make a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> about as rich as you make short cake, roll it out, and put in a pint and a half, or a quart of <ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> according to the size of your family. Double the crust over the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> tie it up tight in a bag, and boil one hour and a half.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CRANBERRY PUDDING.</purpose>
A pint of <ingredient>cranberries</ingredient> stirred into a quart of <ingredient>batter,</ingredient> made like a batter pudding, but very little stiffer, is very nice, eaten with sweet sauce.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">WHORTLEBERRY PUDDING.</purpose>
<ingredient>Whortleberries</ingredient> are good both in flour and Indian puddings. A pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> stirred quite stiff with <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> and a quart of berries stirred in gradually with a spoon, makes a good-sized pudding. Leave room for it to swell; and let it boil three hours.</p><p>When you put them into <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> make your pudding<pb n="67" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=75"/> just like batter-puddings; but considerably thicker, or the berries will sink. Two hours is plenty long enough to boil. No pudding should be put in till the water boils. Leave room to swell.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PLUMB PUDDING.</purpose>
If you wish to make a really nice, soft custard-like plum-pudding, pound six <ingredient>crackers,</ingredient> or <ingredient>dried crusts of light bread,</ingredient> fine, and soak them over night in <ingredient>milk</ingredient> enough to cover them, put them in about three pints of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> beat up six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> put in a little <ingredient>lemon brandy,</ingredient> a whole <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and about three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> which have been rubbed in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Bake it two hours, or perhaps a little short of that. It is easy to judge from the appearance whether it is done.</p><p><variation>The surest way of making a light rich plumb pudding, is to spread slices of <ingredient>sweet, light bread</ingredient> plentifully with <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> on each side of the slices spread abundantly <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> nicely prepared; when they are all heaped up in a dish cover them with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> well beat up, and prepared just as you do for custards. Let it bake about an hour.</variation></p><p>One sauce answers for common use for all sorts of puddings. <ingredient>Flour-and-water</ingredient> stirred into <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> sweetened to your taste with either <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> or <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> according to your ideas of economy; a great spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> if you have it, <ingredient>butter</ingredient> half as big as a hen's egg. If you want to make it very nice put in a glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> on the top.</p><p><variation>When you wish better sauce than common, take a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and the same of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> mould them well together with your hand, add a little <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> if you choose. Make it into a lump, set it away to cool, and grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over it.</variation></p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="eggscheesedairy"><pb n="68" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=76"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CHEAP CUSTARDS.</purpose>
ONE quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> boiled; when boiling add three table spoonfuls of ground <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rice</ingredient> that is boiled, mixed smooth and fine in <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> and one <ingredient>egg</ingredient> beaten; give it one boil up, and sweeten to your taste. <ingredient>Peach leaves</ingredient> or any <ingredient>spice</ingredient> you please, boiled in the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets"><pb n="69" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=77"/><hd align="center">COMMON PIES.</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">MINCE PIES.</purpose>
BOIL a tender, nice piece of <ingredient>beef</ingredient>--any piece that is clear from sinews, and gristle; boil it till it is perfectly tender. When it is cold, chop it very fine, and be very careful to get out every particle of bone and gristle. The <ingredient>suet</ingredient> is sweeter and better to boil half an hour or more, in the liquor the beef has been boiled in; but few people do this. Pare, core, and chop the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> fine. If you use <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> stone them. If you use <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> wash and dry them at the fire. Two pounds of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> after it is chopped; three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>suet;</ingredient> one pound and a quarter of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> three pounds of <ingredient>apple;</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient> Put in a gill of <ingredient>brandy;</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon brandy</ingredient> is better, if you have any prepared. Make it quite moist with <ingredient>new cider.</ingredient> I should not think a quart would be too much; the more moist the better, if it does not spill out into the oven. A very little <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient> If you use <ingredient>corn meat,</ingredient> or <ingredient>tongue</ingredient> for pies, it should be well soaked, and boiled very tender. If you use <ingredient>fresh beef,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> is necessary in the seasoning. One ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient> Two <ingredient>nutmegs</ingredient> add to the pleasantness of the flavor; and a bit of <ingredient>sweet butter</ingredient> put upon the top of each pie, makes them rich; but these are not necessary. Baked three quarters of an hour. If your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> are rather sweet, grate in a whole <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<pb n="70" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=78"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PUMPKIN PIE.</purpose>
For common family pumpkin pies, three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> do very well to a quart of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Stew your <ingredient>pumpkin,</ingredient> and strain it through a sieve, or <implement>colander.</implement> Take out the seeds, and pare the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> or <ingredient>squash,</ingredient> before you stew it; but do not scrape the inside; the part nearest the seed is the sweetest part of the squash. Stir in the stewed <ingredient>pumpkin,</ingredient> till it is as thick as you can stir it round rapidly and easily. If you want to make your pie richer, make it thinner, and add another <ingredient>egg.</ingredient> One <ingredient>egg</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> makes very decent pies. Sweeten it to your taste, with <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> or <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> some <ingredient>pumpkins</ingredient> require more sweetening than others. Two tea-spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> two great spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>cinnamon;</ingredient> one great spoonful of <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient> <ingredient>Ginger</ingredient> will answer very well alone for <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> if you use enough of it. The outside of a <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> grated in is nice. The more <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> the better the pie; some put an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> to a gill of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CARROT PIE.</purpose>
Carrot pies are made like squash pies. The <ingredient>carrots</ingredient> should be boiled very tender, skinned and sifted. Both carrot pies and squash pies should be baked without an upper <ingredient>crust,</ingredient> in deep plates. To be baked an hour, in quite a warm oven.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CHERRY PIE.</purpose>
Cherry pies should be baked in a deep plate. Take the <ingredient>cherries</ingredient> from the stalks, lay them in a plate, and sprinkle a little <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> according to the sweetness of the <ingredient>cherries.</ingredient> Baked with a top and bottom <ingredient>crust,</ingredient> three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>
<pb n="71" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=79"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">WHORTLEBERRY PIE.</purpose>
<ingredient>Whortleberries</ingredient> make a very good common pie, where there is a large family of children. Sprinkle a little <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and sifted <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> into each pie. Baked in the same way, and as long as cherry pies.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">APPLE PIE.</purpose>
When you make apple pies, stew your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> very little indeed; just strike them through, to make them tender. Some people do not stew them at all; but cut them up in very thin slices, and lay them in the crust. Pies made in this way may retain more of the spirit of the <ingredient>apple;</ingredient> but I do not think the seasoning mixes in as well. Put in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste; it is impossible to make a precise rule; because <ingredient>apples</ingredient> vary so much in acidity. A very little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a small piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in each pie makes them richer. <ingredient>Cloves</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> are both suitable <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> <ingredient>Lemon-brandy</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> are both excellent. A wine glass full of each is sufficient for three or four pies. If your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> lack spirit, grate in a whole <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CUSTARD PIE.</purpose>
It is a general rule to put eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> to a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> in making custard pies; but six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> are a plenty for any common use. The <ingredient>milk</ingredient> should be boiled and cooled before it is used; and bits of <ingredient>stick-cinnamon</ingredient> and bits of <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> boiled in it. Sweeten it to your taste with clean <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> a very little sprinkling of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> makes them taste better. Grate in a <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Bake in a deep plate. About twenty minutes are usually enough. If you are doubtful, whether they are done, dip in the handle of a silver spoon, or the blade of a small knife, if it come out<pb n="72" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=80"/> clean, the pie is done. Do not pour them into your plates till the minute you put them into the oven; it makes the <ingredient>crust</ingredient> wet and heavy. To be baked with an under crust only. Some people bake the under crust a little before the custard is poured in; this is to keep it from being clammy.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CRANBERRY PIE.</purpose>
Cranberry pies need very little <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> A little <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> improves them. They need a great deal of sweetening. It is well to stew the sweetening with them; at least a part of it. It is easy to add if you find them too sour for your taste. <variation>When <ingredient>cranberries</ingredient> are strained, and added to about their own weight in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> they make very delicious 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="cranberry tarts">tarts.</alt></purpose></variation> No upper crust.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center"><alt synonym1="rhubarb pie">RHUBARB STALKS, OR PERSIAN APPLE.</alt></purpose>
<ingredient>Rhubarb stalks,</ingredient> or the <ingredient>Persian-apple,</ingredient> is the earliest ingredient for pies, which the spring offers. The skin should be carefully stripped, and the stalks cut into small bits, and stewed very tender. These are dear pies, for they take an enormous quantity of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Seasoned like apple pies. <ingredient>Gooseberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> &amp;c. are stewed, sweetened, and seasoned like apple-pies, in proportions suited to the sweetness of the fruit; there is no way to judge but by your own taste. Always remember it is more easy to add seasoning, than to diminish it.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PIE CRUST.</purpose>
To make pie crust for common use, a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is enough for half a pound of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Take out about a quarter part of the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> you intend to use, and lay it aside. Into the remainder of the<pb n="73" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=81"/><ingredient>flour,</ingredient> rub <ingredient>butter</ingredient> thoroughly with your hands, until it is so short that a handful of it clasped tight will remain in a ball, without any tendency to fall in pieces. Then wet it with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> roll it out on a board, rub over the surface with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> stick little lumps of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> all over it, sprinkle some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> over the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and roll the dough all up; <ingredient>flour</ingredient> the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> the rolling pin; roll it lightly and quickly; <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it again, stick in bits of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> do it up; flour the rolling pin, and roll quickly and lightly; and so on, till you have used up your <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Always roll from you. Pie crust should be made as cold as possible, and set in a cool place; but be careful it does not freeze. Do not use more flour than you can help in sprinkling and rolling. The paste should not be rolled out more than three times; if rolled too much, it will not be flaky.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets"><pb n="74" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=82"/><hd align="center">COMMON CAKES.</hd><p>IN all cakes where butter or eggs are used, the butter should be very faithfully rubbed into the flour, and the eggs beat to a foam, before the ingredients are mixed.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">GINGERBREAD.</purpose>
<variation>A very good way to make 
 
<purpose>molasses gingerbread</purpose>
is to rub four pounds and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> with half a pound of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> a gill of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> tea-cup of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>dissolved pearlash</ingredient> stirred together. All mixed, baked in shallow pans twenty or thirty minutes.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>Hard gingerbread</purpose>
is good to have in the family; it keeps so well. One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> rubbed into it; half a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> great spoonful of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> or more, according to the strength of the <ingredient>ginger;</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and a handful of <ingredient>caraway seed.</ingredient> Well beat up. Kneaded stiff enough to roll out and bake on flat pans. Bake twenty or thirty minutes.</variation></p><p><variation>A cake of 
 
<purpose>common gingerbread</purpose>
can be stirred up very quick in the following way. Rub in a bit of <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> as big as an egg into a pint of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> if you use <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> add a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> two or three great spoonfuls of <ingredient>ginger;</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> one cup and a half of <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> and a great spoonful of <ingredient>dissolved pearlash,</ingredient> put together and poured into the shortened <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> while it is foaming; to be put in the oven in a minute. It ought to be just thick enough to pour into the pans with difficulty; if these proportions<pb n="75" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=83"/> make it too thin, use less liquid the next time you try. Bake about twenty minutes.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose><alt synonym1="to restore short cake dough">If by carelessness you let a piece of short cake dough grow sour,</alt></purpose>
put it in a little <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> warm a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> according to the size of the dough, knead in a cup or two of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> (two cups, unless it is a very small bit,) two or three spoonfuls of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Knead it up thoroughly, roll it out on a flat pan and bake it twenty minutes. Everything mixed with <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> should be put in the oven immediately.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CUP CAKE.</purpose>
Cup cake is about as good as pound cake, and is cheaper. One cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> well beat together, and baked in pans or cups. Bake twenty minutes and no more.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">TEA CAKE.</purpose>
There is a kind of tea-cake still cheaper. Three cups of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>dissolved pearlash,</ingredient> and four cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> well beat up. If it is so stiff it will not stir easily, add a little more <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CIDER CAKE.</purpose>
Cider cake is very good, to be baked in small loaves. One pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> one tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash;</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste. Bake till it turns easily in the pans. I should think about half an hour.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="patriotic"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">ELECTION CAKE.</purpose>
Old fashion election cake is made of four pounds of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> four<pb n="76" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=84"/><ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> if you choose; half a pint of good <ingredient>yeast;</ingredient> wet it with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> as soft as it can be and be moulded on a board. Set to rise over night in winter; in warm weather three hours is usually enough for it to rise. A loaf, the size of common flour bread, should bake three quarters of an hour.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SPONGE CAKE.</purpose>
The nicest way to make sponge cake, or Diet-bread, is the weight of six eggs in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> the weight of four eggs in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>rose water.</ingredient> The <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> should be beaten thoroughly and separately. The <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> should be well beaten together; but after the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is sprinkled it should not be stirred a moment longer than is necessary to mix it well; it should be poured into the pan, and get into the oven with all possible expedition. Twenty minutes is about long enough to bake. Not to be put in till some other articles have taken off the first few minutes of furious heat.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="wedding"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">WEDDING CAKE.</purpose>
Good common wedding cake may be made thus: Four pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three pounds of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> four pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> twentyfour <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon brandy,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and three <ingredient>nutmegs.</ingredient> A little <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> makes it dark colored, which is desirable. Half a pound of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> improves it; but it is not necessary. To be baked two hours and a half or three hours. After the oven is cleared it is well to shut the door for eight or ten minutes, to let the violence of the heat subside, before cake or bread is put in.</p><p><variation>To make 
 
<purpose>icing</purpose>
for your wedding cake, beat the <ingredient>whites of eggs</ingredient> to an entire froth, and to each <ingredient>egg</ingredient> add<pb n="77" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=85"/> five tea-spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> gradually; beat it a great while. Put it on when your cake is hot, or cold, as is most convenient. It will dry in a warm room, a short distance from a gentle fire, or in a warm oven.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">LOAF CAKE.</purpose>
Very good loaf cake is made with two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a gill of <ingredient>sweet emptings,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> a large spoonful of <ingredient>lemon-brandy,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose-water;</ingredient> if it is not about as thin as good white bread dough, add a little <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> A common sized loaf is made by these proportions. Bake about three quarters of an hour.</p><p><variation>A handy way to make loaf cake is to take about as much of your <ingredient>white bread dough, or sponge,</ingredient> as you think your pan will hold, and put it into a pan in which you have already beat up three or four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> warmed, and half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> little sifted <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient> The materials should be well mixed and beat before the dough is put in; and then it should be all kneaded well together about as stiff as <ingredient>white bread.</ingredient> Put in half a pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> if you choose. It should stand in the pan two or three hours to rise; and be baked about three quarters of an hour, if the pan is a common sized bread-pan.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to restore loaf cake">If you have loaf cake slightly injured by time, or by being kept in the cellar,</alt></purpose>
cut off all appearance of mould from the outside, wipe it with a clean cloth, and wet it well with strong <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> sweetened with <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> then put it in your oven, and let the heat strike through it, for fifteen or twenty minutes. Unless very bad, this will restore the sweetness.</variation></p></recipe>
<pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=86"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">DOUGH NUTS.</purpose>
For dough-nuts take one pint of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as big as an egg, and a tea-spoonful of dissolved <ingredient>pearlash.</ingredient> When you have no <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a gill of <ingredient>lively emptings</ingredient> will do; but in that case they must be made over night. <ingredient>Cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon-brandy,</ingredient> if you have it. If you use part <ingredient>lard</ingredient> instead of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Not put in till the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> is very hot. The more <ingredient>fat</ingredient> they are fried in, the less they will soak <ingredient>fat.</ingredient></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PANCAKES.</purpose>
Pancakes should be made of half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three great spoonfuls of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two or three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful of dissolved <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> spiced with <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon-brandy,</ingredient> just as you happen to have it. <ingredient>Flour</ingredient> should be stirred in, till the spoon moves round with difficulty. If they are thin, they are apt to soak fat. Have the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> in your skillet boiling hot, and drop them in with a spoon. Let them cook till thoroughly brown. The <ingredient>fat</ingredient> which is left is good to shorten other cakes. The more <ingredient>fat</ingredient> they are cooked in, the less they soak.</p><p><variation>If you have no eggs, or wish to save them, use the above ingredients, and supply the place of eggs by two or three spoonfuls of <ingredient>lively emptings;</ingredient> but in this case they must be made five or six hours before they are cooked,--and in winter they should stand all night.</variation> A spoonful or more of <ingredient>N. E. rum</ingredient> makes pancakes light. <variation>Flip makes very nice pancakes. In this case, nothing is done but to sweeten your mug of <ingredient>beer</ingredient> with <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> put in one glass of <ingredient>N. E. rum;</ingredient> heat it till it foams, by putting in a hot poker; and stir it up with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as thick as other pancakes.</variation></p></recipe>
<pb n="79" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=87"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">FRITTERS.</purpose>
Flat-jack, or fritters, do not differ from pancakes, only in being mixed softer. The same ingredients are used in about the same quantities, only most people prefer to have no sweetening put in them, because they generally have <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> put on them, after they are done. Excepting for company, the <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> can be well dispensed with. They are not to be boiled in fat, like pancakes; the <implement>spider,</implement> or griddle, should be well greased, and the cakes poured on as large as you want them, when it is quite hot; when it gets brown on one side to be turned over upon the other. Fritters are better to be baked quite thin. Either <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>Indian,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rye,</ingredient> is good.</p><p><ingredient>Sour beer,</ingredient> with a spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> is good both for pancakes and fritters.</p><p><variation>If you have any cold <ingredient>rice</ingredient> left, it is nice to break it up fine in <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> put in a little <ingredient>salt;</ingredient> after you have put <ingredient>milk</ingredient> enough for the cakes you wish to make, (a half pint, or more,) stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> till it is thick enough to pour for fritters. It does very well without an <ingredient>egg;</ingredient> but better with one. To be fried like other flat-jacks. <ingredient>Sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> are to be put on when they are buttered, if you like.</variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">SHORT CAKE.</purpose>
If you have <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter-milk,</ingredient> it is well to make it into short cakes, for tea. Rub in a very small bit of <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> or three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> put in a tea-spoonful of strong <ingredient>dissolved pearlash,</ingredient> into your <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> and mix your cake pretty stiff, to bake in the <implement>spider,</implement> on a few embers.</p><p>When people have to buy butter and lard, short cakes are not economical food. A half pint of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> will make a cake large enough to cover a common plate. Rub in thoroughly a bit of <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> as big as a hen's egg, put in a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>dissolved<pb n="80" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=88"/> pearlash;</ingredient> wet it with <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> knead it stiff enough to roll well, to bake on a plate, or in a <implement>spider.</implement> It should bake as quick as it can, and not burn. The first side should stand longer to the fire than the last.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">INDIAN CAKES.</purpose>
Indian cake, or bannock, is sweet and cheap food. One quart of sifted <ingredient>meal,</ingredient> two great spoonfuls of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> two tea-spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a bit of <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> half as big as a hen's egg, stirred together; make it pretty moist with <ingredient>scalding water,</ingredient> put it into a well greased pan, smooth over the surface with a spoon, and bake it brown on both sides, before a quick fire. A little <ingredient>stewed pumpkin,</ingredient> scalded, with the <ingredient>meal,</ingredient> improves the cake. Bannock split and dipped in butter makes very nice toast.</p><p><variation>A richer Indian cake may be made by stirring one <ingredient>egg</ingredient> to a half pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweetened with two great spoonfuls of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> stirred in till it is just about thick enough to pour. <implement>Spider</implement> or <implement>bakekettle</implement> well greased; cake poured in, covered up, baked half an hour, or three quarters, according to the thickness of the cake. If you have <ingredient>sour milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>buttermilk,</ingredient> it is very nice for this kind of cake; the acidity corrected by a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>dissolved pearlash.</ingredient> It is a rule never to use pearlash for Indian, unless to correct the sourness of milk; it injures the flavor of the meal.</variation></p><p>Nice <ingredient>suet</ingredient> improves all kinds of Indian cakes very much.</p><p><variation>Two cups of <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> one table-spoonful <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> two cups <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a handful <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>saleratus,</ingredient> mixed up thin, and poured into a buttered <implement>bakekettle,</implement> hung over the fire uncovered, until you can bear your finger upon it, and then set down before the fire. Bake half an hour.</variation></p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets"><pb n="81" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=89"/><hd align="center">BREAD, YEAST, &amp;c.</hd><p>IT is more difficult to give rules for making bread than for anything else; it depends so much on judgment and experience. In summer, bread should be mixed with cold water; during a chilly, damp spell, the water should be slightly warm; in severe cold weather it should be mixed quite warm; and set in a warm place during the night. If your yeast is new and lively, a small quantity will make the bread rise; if it be old and heavy, it will take more. In these things I believe wisdom must be gained by a few mistakes.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>Six quarts of meal will make two good sized loaves of 
 
<purpose>brown bread.</purpose>
Some like to have it half <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> and half <ingredient>rye meal;</ingredient> others prefer it one third <ingredient>Indian,</ingredient> and two thirds <ingredient>rye.</ingredient> Many mix their <ingredient>brown bread</ingredient> over night; but there is no need of it; and it is more likely to sour, particularly in summer. If you do mix it the night before you bake it, you must not put in more than half the <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> I am about to mention, unless the weather is intensely cold. The meal should be sifted separately. Put the <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> in your bread pan, sprinkle a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> among it, and wet it thoroughly with <ingredient>scalding water.</ingredient> Stir it up while you are scalding it. Be sure and have <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> enough; for <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> absorbs a great deal of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When it is cool, pour in your <ingredient>rye;</ingredient> add two gills of <ingredient>lively yeast,</ingredient> and mix it with <ingredient>water</ingredient> as stiff as you can knead it. Let it stand an hour and a half, in a cool place in summer, on the hearth in winter. It should be put into a very hot oven and baked three<pb n="82" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=90"/> or four hours. It is all the better for remaining in the oven over night.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose>Flour bread</purpose>
should have a <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> set the night before. The <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> should be soft enough to pour; mixed with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> warm or cold, according to the temperature of the weather. One gill of <ingredient>lively yeast</ingredient> is enough to put into <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> for two loaves. I should judge about three pints of <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> would be right for two loaves. The warmth of the place in which the <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> is set, should be determined by the coldness of the weather. If your <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> looks frothy in the morning, it is a sign your bread will be good; if it does not rise, stir in a little more <ingredient>emptings;</ingredient> if it rises too much, taste of it, to see if it has any acid taste; if so, put in a tea spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> when you mould in your <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> be sure the <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> is well dissolved in <ingredient>water;</ingredient> if there are little lumps, your bread will be full of bitter spots. About an hour before your oven is ready, stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into your <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> till it is stiff enough to lay on a well floured board, or table. Knead it up pretty stiff and put it into well greased pans, and let it stand in a cool, or warm place, according to the weather. If the oven is ready, put them in fifteen or twenty minutes after the dough begins to rise up and crack; if the oven is not ready, move the pans to a cooler spot, to prevent the dough from becoming sour by too much rising. Common sized loaves will bake in three quarters of an hour. If they slip easily in the pans, it is a sign they are done. Some people do not set a soft sponge for flour bread; they knead it up all ready to put in the pans the night before, and leave it to rise. White bread and pies should not be set in the oven until the brown bread and beans have been in half an hour. If the oven be too hot, it will bind the crust so suddenly that the bread cannot rise; if it be too cold, the bread will fall. Flour bread should not be too stiff.</p><p><variation>Some people like one third of <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> in their flour.<pb n="83" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=91"/> Others like one third <ingredient>rye;</ingredient> and some think the nicest of all bread is one third <ingredient>Indian,</ingredient> one third <ingredient>rye,</ingredient> and one third <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> made according to the directions for flour bread. When <ingredient>Indian</ingredient> is used, it should be salted, and scalded, before the other meal is put in. A mixture of other grains is economical when flour is high.</variation></p></recipe>
<p>Heating ovens must be regulated by experience and observation. There is difference in wood in giving out heat; there is a great difference in the construction of ovens; and when an oven is extremely cold, either on account of the weather, or want of use, it must be heated more. Economical people heat ovens with pine wood, fagots, brush, and such light stuff. If you have none but hard wood, you must remember that it makes very hot coals, and therefore less of it will answer. A smart fire for an hour and a half is a general rule for common sized family ovens; provided brown bread and beans are to be baked. An hour is long enough to heat an oven for flour bread. Pies bear about as much heat as flour bread: pumpkin pies will bear more. If you are afraid your oven is too hot throw in a little flour, and shut it up for a minute. If it scorches black immediately, the heat is too furious; if it merely browns, it is right. Some people wet an old broom two or three times, and turn it round near the top of the oven, till it dries; this prevents pies and cake from scorching on the top. When you go into a new house, heat your oven two or three times, to get it seasoned, before you use it. After the wood is burned, rake the coals over the bottom of the oven and let them lie a few minutes.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p>Those who make their own bread should make 
 
<purpose>yeast</purpose>
too. When bread is nearly out always think whether yeast is in readiness; for it takes a day and night to prepare it. One handful of <ingredient>hops</ingredient> with two or three handsful of <ingredient>malt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>rye bran</ingredient> should be <pb n="84" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=92"/> boiled fifteen or twenty minutes, in two quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient>--then strained, hung on to boil again, and thickened with half a pint of <ingredient>rye</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> stirred up quite thick, and a little <ingredient>molasses;</ingredient> boil it a minute or two, and then take it off to cool. When just about luke-warm, put a cupful of good <ingredient>lively yeast;</ingredient> and set it in a cool place in summer, and a warm place in winter. If it is too warm when you put in the <ingredient>old yeast,</ingredient> all the spirit will be killed.</p><p>In summer yeast sours easily; therefore make but little at a time. Bottle it when it gets well a working; it keeps better when the air is corked out. If you find it acid, but still spirited, put a little <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> to it, as you use it; but by no means put it into your bread, unless it foams up, bright and lively as soon as the <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> mixes with it. Never keep yeast in tin; it destroys its life.</p><p><variation>There is another method of making yeast which is much easier, and I think quite as good. Stir <ingredient>rye</ingredient> and <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> till you make a stiff thickening. Then pour in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and stir it all the time, till you make it as thin as the yeast you buy; three or four table spoons heaping full are enough for a quart of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When it gets about cold, put in half a pint of <ingredient>lively yeast.</ingredient> When it works well, bottle it; but if very lively do not cork your bottle <emph rend="italic">very</emph> tight, for fear it will burst.</variation> Always think to make new yeast before the old is gone; so that you may have some to work with. Always wash and scald your bottle clean after it has contained sour yeast. Beware of freezing yeast.</p><p><variation><purpose>Milk yeast</purpose>
is made quicker than any other. A pint of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> with a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a large spoon of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> stirred in, set by the fire to keep luke-warm will make yeast fit for use in an hour. Twice the quantity of common yeast is necessary, and unless used soon is good for nothing. Bread made of this yeast dries sooner. It is convenient<pb n="85" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=93"/> in summer, when one wants to make biscuits suddenly.</variation></p><p><variation>A species of 
 
<purpose>leaven</purpose>
may be made that will keep any length of time. Three ounces of <ingredient>hops</ingredient> in a pail of <ingredient>water</ingredient> boiled down to a quart; strain it, and stir in a quart of <ingredient>rye meal</ingredient> while boiling hot. Cool it, and add half a pint of good <ingredient>yeast;</ingredient> after it has risen a few hours thicken it with <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> stiff enough to roll out upon a board; then put it in the sun and air a few days to dry. A piece of this cake, two inches square, dissolved in <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and thickened with a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> will make a large loaf of bread.</variation></p><p><variation><ingredient>Potatoes</ingredient> make very good 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="potato yeast">yeast.</alt></purpose>
Mash three large <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> fine; pour a pint of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over them; when almost cold stir in two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and a cup of good <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> This yeast should be used while new.</variation></p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="generalfood"><pb n="86" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=94"/><hd align="center">PRESERVES, &amp;c.</hd>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth"><p>ECONOMICAL people will seldom use preserves, except for sickness. They are unhealthy, expensive, and useless to those who are well. 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="barberry preserves">Barberries preserved in molasses</alt></purpose>
are very good for common use. Boil the <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> skim it, throw in the <ingredient>barberries,</ingredient> and simmer them till they are soft. If you wish to lay by a few for sickness, preserve them in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> by the same rule as other preserves. Melt the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> skim it, throw in the <ingredient>barberries;</ingredient> when done soft, take them out and throw in others.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p>A pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is the rule for all 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="fruit preserves">preserves.</alt></purpose>
The <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> should be melted over a fire moderate enough not to scorch it. When melted, it should be skimmed clean, and the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> dropped in to simmer till it is soft. Plumbs, and things of which the skin is liable to be broken, do better to be put in little jars, with their weight of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and the jars set in a kettle of boiling water, till the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is done. See the water is not so high as to boil into the jars.</p><p>When you put preserves in jars, lay a white paper thoroughly wet with brandy, flat upon the surface of the preserves; and cover them carefully from the air. If they begin to mould, scald them by setting them in the oven till boiling hot.</p></recipe>
<pb n="87" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=95"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CURRANT JELLY.</purpose>
Currant jelly is a useful thing for sickness. If it be necessary to wash your <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> be sure they are thoroughly drained, or your jelly will be thin. Break them up with a <implement>pestle,</implement> and squeeze them through a cloth. Put a pint of clean <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pint of a juice and boil it slowly, till it becomes ropy. Great care must be taken not to do it too fast; it is spoiled by being scorched. It should be frequently skimmed while simmering. If <ingredient>currants</ingredient> are put in a jar, and kept in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and cooked before they are strained, they are more likely to keep a long time without fermenting.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">CURRANT WINE.</purpose>
Those who have more <ingredient>currants</ingredient> than they have money, will do well to use no wine but of their own manufacture. Break and squeeze the <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> put three pounds and a half of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to two quarts of juice, and two quarts of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Put in a keg, or barrel. Do not close the bung tight, for three or four days, that the air may escape while it is fermenting. After it is done fermenting close it up tight. <variation>Where raspberries are plenty, it is a great improvement to use half <ingredient>raspberry juice,</ingredient> and half <ingredient>currant juice.</ingredient></variation> Brandy is unnecessary, when the above mentioned proportions are observed. It should not be used under a year or two. Age improves it.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">RASPBERRY SHRUB.</purpose>
Raspberry shrub mixed with water is a pure delicious drink for summer; and in a country where <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> are abundant, it is good economy to make<pb n="88" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=96"/> it answer instead of Port and Catalonia wine. Put <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> in a pan and scarcely cover them with strong <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> Add a pint of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pint of juice; (of this you can judge by first trying your pan to see how much it holds) scald it, skim it, and bottle it when cold.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">COFFEE.</purpose>
<variation>As 
 
<purpose>substitutes for coffee,</purpose>
some use <ingredient>dry brown-bread crusts,</ingredient> and roast them; others soak <ingredient>rye-grain</ingredient> in <ingredient>rum,</ingredient> and roast it; others roast <ingredient>peas</ingredient> in the same way as coffee. None of these are very good; and peas so used are considered unhealthy. Where there is a large family of apprentices and workmen, and coffee is very dear, it may be worth while to use the substitutes, or to mix them half and half with <ingredient>coffee;</ingredient> but, after all, the best economy is to go without.</variation></p><p>French coffee is so celebrated that it may be worth while to tell how it is made; though no prudent housekeeper will make it, unless she has boarders, who are willing to pay for expensive cooking.</p><p><variation>The 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="French coffee">coffee</alt></purpose>
should be roasted more than is common with us; it should not hang drying over the fire, but should be roasted quick; it should be ground soon after roasting, and used as soon as it is ground.--Those who pride themselves on first rate <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> burn it and grind it every morning. The powder should be placed in the <implement>coffee-pot</implement> in the proportions of an ounce to less than a pint of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> The <ingredient>water</ingredient> should be poured upon the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> boiling hot. The <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> should be kept at the boiling point; but should not boil. <ingredient>Coffee</ingredient> made in this way must be made in a <implement>biggin.</implement> It would not be clear in a common <implement>coffee-pot.</implement></variation></p><p>A bit of <ingredient>fish-skin</ingredient> as big as a ninepence, thrown into coffee while it is boiling, tends to make it clear. If<pb n="89" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=97"/> you use it just as it comes from the salt-fish it will be apt to give an unpleasant taste to the coffee: it should be washed clean as a bit of cloth, and hung up till perfectly dry. The <ingredient>white of eggs,</ingredient> and even <ingredient>egg shells</ingredient> are good to settle coffee. <ingredient>Rind of salt pork</ingredient> is excellent.</p><p>Some people think coffee is richer and clearer for having a bit of <ingredient>sweet butter,</ingredient> or a whole <ingredient>egg</ingredient> dropped in and stirred, just before it is done roasting, and ground up, shell and all, with the <ingredient>coffee.</ingredient> But these things are not economical, except on a farm, where butter and eggs are plenty. A half a gill of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> poured in after you take your <implement>coffee-pot</implement> off the fire, will <emph rend="italic">usually</emph> settle the coffee.</p><p>If you have not cream for <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> it is a very great improvement to boil your <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and use it while hot.</p></recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">PICKLES.</purpose>
<variation><ingredient>Musk-melons</ingredient> should be picked for 
 
<purpose>mangoes,</purpose>
when they are green and hard. They should be cut open after they have been in <ingredient>salt water</ingredient> ten days, the inside scraped out clean, and filled with <ingredient>mustard-seed,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> small <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> &amp;c. and sewed up again. Scalding <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> poured upon them.</variation></p><p><variation>When 
 
<purpose><alt synonym1="pickled walnuts">walnuts</alt></purpose>
are so ripe that a pin will go into them easily, they are ready for pickling. They should be soaked twelve days in very strong <ingredient>cold salt and water,</ingredient> which has been boiled and skimmed. A quantity of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> enough to cover them well, should be boiled with whole <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard-seed,</ingredient> small <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> or <ingredient>garlick,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish;</ingredient> this should not be poured upon them till it is cold. They should be pickled a few months, before they are eaten. To be kept close covered; for the air softens them. The liquor is an excellent catsup to be eaten on fish.</variation></p><pb n="90" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=98"/><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="pickled cucumbers">Cucumbers</alt></purpose>
should be in <ingredient>weak brine</ingredient> three or four days after they are picked; then they should be put in a tin or wooden pail of clean <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and kept slightly warm in the kitchen corner for two or three days. Then take as much <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> as you think your pickle jar will hold, scald it with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard-seed,</ingredient> <ingredient>flag-root,</ingredient> <ingredient>horse-radish,</ingredient> &amp;c. if you happen to have them; half of them will spice the pickles very well. Throw in a bit of <ingredient>alum</ingredient> as big as a walnut; this serves to make pickles hard. Skim the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> clean, and pour it scalding hot upon the <ingredient>cucumbers.</ingredient> Brass vessels are not healthy for preparing anything acid.</variation> <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="pickled red cabbages">Red cabbages</alt></purpose>
need no other pickling than <ingredient>scalding spiced vinegar</ingredient> poured upon them, and suffered to remain eight or ten days before you eat them. Some people think it improves them to keep them in <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> twentyfour hours before they are pickled.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose>If you find your pickles soft and insipid,</purpose>
it is owing to the weakness of the vinegar. Throw away the vinegar, (or keep it to clean your brass kettles,) then cover your pickles with <ingredient>strong scalding vinegar,</ingredient> into which a little <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> and <ingredient>alum</ingredient> have been thrown. By no means omit a pretty large bit of <ingredient>alum.</ingredient> Pickles attended to in this way, will keep for years, and be better and better every year.</variation></p><p><variation>Some people prefer 
 
<purpose>pickled nasturtion seed</purpose>
to capers. They should be kept several days after they are gathered, and then covered with <ingredient>boiling vinegar,</ingredient> and bottled when cold. They are not fit to eat for some months.</variation></p><p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="pickled martinoes">Martinoes</alt></purpose>
are prepared in nearly the same way as other pickles. The <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> in which they are put, two or three days previous to pickling, should be changed every day; because <ingredient>martinoes</ingredient> are very apt to become soft. No spice should be used but <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient> The <ingredient>martinoes</ingredient> and<pb n="91" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=99"/> the spice should be scalded <emph rend="italic">in</emph> the <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> instead of pouring the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> <emph rend="italic">over</emph> the <ingredient>martinoes.</ingredient></variation></p></recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes" class2="medhealth"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center">BEER.</purpose>
Beer is a good family drink. A handful of <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> to a pailful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and a half-pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> makes good hop beer. <ingredient>Spruce</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>hops</ingredient> is pleasanter than <ingredient>hops</ingredient> alone. <variation><ingredient>Boxberry,</ingredient> <ingredient>fever-bush,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet-fern,</ingredient> and <ingredient>horse-radish</ingredient> make a good and healthy 
 
<purpose>diet-drink.</purpose></variation> <variation>The <ingredient>winter evergreen,</ingredient> or <ingredient>rheumatism weed,</ingredient> thrown in, is very beneficial to 
 
<purpose>humors.</purpose></variation> Be careful and not mistake kill-lamb for <ingredient>winter-evergreen;</ingredient> they resemble each other. <ingredient>Malt</ingredient> mixed with a few <ingredient>hops</ingredient> makes a weak kind of beer; but it is cool and pleasant; it needs less <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> than <ingredient>hops</ingredient> alone. The rule is about the same for all beer. Boil the ingredients two or three hours, pour in a half-pint of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to a pailful, while the beer is scalding hot. Strain the beer, and when about lukewarm, put a pint of <ingredient>lively yeast</ingredient> to a barrel. Leave the bung loose till the beer is done working; you can ascertain this by observing when the froth subsides. If your family be large, and the beer will be drank rapidly, it may as well remain in the barrel; but if your family be small, fill what bottles you have with it; it keeps better bottled. A <ingredient>raw potato</ingredient> or two, cut up and thrown in, while the ingredients are boiling, is said to make beer spirited.</p><p><variation><purpose>Ginger beer</purpose>
is made in the following proportions. One cup of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> one pail and a half of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and a cup of <ingredient>lively yeast.</ingredient> Most people scald the <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> in half a pail of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and then fill it up with a pailful of cold; but in very hot weather some people stir it all up cold. <ingredient>Yeast</ingredient> must not be put in till it is cold, or nearly cold. If not to be drank within twentyfour hours, it must be bottled as soon as it works.</variation></p><pb n="92" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=100"/><p>Table beer should be drawn off into <emph rend="italic">stone</emph> jugs with a lump of <ingredient>white sugar</ingredient> in each, securely corked. It is brisk and pleasant, and continues good several months.</p></recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter><pb n="93" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=101"/><hd align="center">HINTS<lb/>TO<lb/>PERSONS OF MODERATE FORTUNE.<lb/>[FIRST PUBLISHED IN THE MASSACHUSETTS JOURNAL.]<lb/>When clouds are seen wise men put on their cloaks.--SHAKSPEARE.</hd>
<section class1="household"><hd align="center">FURNITURE.</hd><p>THE prevailing evil of the present day is extravagance. I know very well that the old are too prone to preach about modern degeneracy, whether they have cause or not; but laugh as we may at the sage advice of our fathers, it is too plain that our present expensive habits are productive of much domestic unhappiness, and injurious to public prosperity. Our wealthy people copy all the foolish and extravagant caprice of European fashion without considering that we have not their laws of inheritance among us,--and that our frequent changes of policy render property far more precarious here than in the old world. However, it is not to the rich I would speak. They have an undoubted right to spend their thousands as they please; and if they spend them ridiculously, it is consoling to reflect that they must, in some way or other, benefit the poorer classes. People of moderate fortunes have likewise an unquestioned right to<pb n="94" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=102"/> dispose of their hundreds as they please; but I would ask is it <emph rend="italic">wise</emph> to risk your happiness in a foolish attempt to keep up with the opulent? Of what <emph rend="italic">use</emph> is the effort which takes so much of your time, and <emph rend="italic">all</emph> of your income? Nay, if any unexpected change in affairs should deprive you of a few yearly hundreds, you will find your expenses have <emph rend="italic">exceeded</emph> your income; thus the foundation of an accumulating debt will be laid, and your family will have formed habits but poorly calculated to save you from the threatened ruin. Not one valuable friend will be gained by living beyond your means, and old age will be left to comparative, if not to utter poverty.</p><p>There is nothing in which the extravagance of the present day strikes me so forcibly as the manner in which our young people of moderate fortune furnish their houses.</p><p>A few weeks since, I called upon a farmer's daughter who had lately married a young physician of moderate talents, and destitute of fortune. Her father had given her at her marriage, all he ever expected to give her: viz. two thousand dollars. Yet the lower part of her house was furnished with as much splendor as we usually find among the wealthiest. The whole two thousand had been expended upon Brussels carpets, alabaster vases, mahogany chairs, and marble tables. I afterwards learned that the more useful household utensils had been forgotten; and that a few weeks after her wedding, she was actually obliged to apply to her husband for money to purchase baskets, iron spoons, clothes-lines, &amp;c; and her husband, made irritable by the want of money, pettishly demanded why she had bought so many things they did not want. Did the Doctor gain any patients, or she a single friend, by offering their visiters water in richly cut glass <implement>tumblers,</implement> or serving them with costly damask napkins, instead of plain soft<pb n="95" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=103"/> towels? No; their foolish vanity made them less happy, and no more respectable.</p><p>Had the young lady been content with Kidderminster carpets, and tasteful vases of her own making, she might have put <emph rend="italic">one</emph> thousand dollars at interest; and had she obtained six per cent, it would have clothed her as well as the wife of any man, who depends merely upon his own industry, ought to be clothed. This would have saved much domestic disquiet; for, after all, human nature is human nature; and a wife is never better beloved, because she teazes for money.</p></section>
<section class1="childrear"><hd align="center">EDUCATION OF DAUGHTERS.</hd><p>THERE is no subject so much connected with individual happiness and national prosperity, as the education of daughters. It is true, and therefore an old remark, that the situation and prospects of a country may be justly estimated by the character of its women; and we all know how hard it is to engraft upon a woman's character, habits, and principles, to which she was unaccustomed in her girlish days. It is always extremely difficult, and sometimes utterly impossible. Is the present education of young ladies likely to contribute to their own ultimate happiness, or to the welfare of the country? There are many honorable exceptions; but we do think the general tone of female education is bad. The greatest and most universal error is teaching girls to exaggerate the importance of getting married; and of course to place an undue importance upon the polite attentions of gentlemen. It was but a few days since, I heard a pretty and sensible girl say 'Did you ever see a man so ridiculously fond of his daughters as Mr.---?<pb n="96" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=104"/> He is all the time with them. The other night, at the party, I went and took Anna away by mere force; for I knew she must feel dreadfully to have her father waiting upon her all the time, while the other girls were talking with the beaux.' And another young friend of mine said, with an air most laughably serious, "I don't think Harriet and Julia enjoyed themselves at all last night. Don't you think, nobody but their <emph rend="italic">brother</emph> offered to hand them to the supper room?'</p><p>That a mother should wish to see her daughters happily married is natural and proper; that a young lady should be pleased with polite attentions is likewise natural and innocent; but this undue anxiety, this foolish excitement about showing off the attentions of somebody, no matter whom, is attended with consequences seriously injurious. It promotes envy and rivalship; it leads our young girls to spend their time between the public streets, the ball room, and the toilet; and worst of all, it leads them to contract engagements, without any knowledge of their own hearts, merely for the sake of being married as soon as their companions. When married, they find themselves ignorant of the important duties of domestic life; and its quiet pleasures soon grow tiresome to minds worn out by frivolous excitements. If they remain unmarried, their disappointment and discontent are of course in proportion to their exaggerated idea of the eclat attendant upon having a lover. The evil increases in a startling ratio; for these girls, so injudiciously educated, will, nine times out of ten, make injudicious mothers, aunts, and friends; thus follies will be accumulated unto the third and fourth generation. Young ladies should be taught that usefulness is happiness, and that all other things are but incidental. With regard to matrimonial speculations, they should be taught nothing! Leave the affections to nature and to truth; and all will end well. How many can I at this moment recollect, who have made<pb n="97" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=105"/> themselves unhappy by marrying for the sake of the <emph rend="italic">name</emph> of being married! How many do I know who have been instructed to such watchfulness in the game, that they have lost it by trumping their own tricks!</p><p>One great cause of the vanity, extravagance, and idleness that are so fast growing upon our young ladies, is the absence of <emph rend="italic">domestic education.</emph> By domestic education I do not mean the sending daughters into the kitchen some half dozen times, to weary the patience of the cook, and to boast of the next day in the parlor. I mean two or three years spent with a mother, assisting her in her duties, instructing brothers and sisters, and taking care of their own clothes. This is the way to make them happy as well as good wives; for being early accustomed to the duties of life, they will sit lightly as well as gracefully upon them.</p><p>But what time do modern girls have for the formation of quiet, domestic habits? Until sixteen they go to school; sometimes these years are judiciously spent, and sometimes they are half wasted; too often they are spent in acquiring the <emph rend="italic">elements</emph> of a thousand sciences, without being thoroughly acquainted with any; or in a variety of accomplishments of very doubtful value to people of moderate fortune; as soon as they leave school, (and sometimes before,) they begin a round of balls and parties, and staying with gay young friends. Dress and flattery take up all their thoughts. What time have they to learn to be useful? What time have they to cultivate the still and gentle affections, which must in every situation of life, have such an important effect on a woman's character and happiness?</p><p>As far as parents can judge what will be a daughter's station, education should be adapted to it; but it is well to remember that it is always easy to know<pb n="98" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=106"/> how to spend riches, and always safe to know how to bear poverty.</p><p>A superficial acquaintance with such accomplishments as music and drawing is useless and undesirable. They should not be attempted unless there is taste, talent, and time enough to attain excellence. I have frequently heard young women of moderate fortune say, 'I have not opened my piano these five years. I wish I had the money expended upon it. If I had employed as much time in learning useful things, I should have been better fitted for the cares of my family.'</p><p>By these remarks I do not mean to discourage an attention to the graces of life. Gentility and taste are always lovely in all situations. But good things, carried to excess, are often productive of bad consequences. When accomplishments and dress interfere with the duties and permanent happiness of life, they are unjustifiable, and displeasing; but where there is a solid foundation in mind and heart, all those elegancies are but becoming ornaments.</p><p>Some are likely to have more use for them than others; and they are justified in spending more time and money upon them. But no one should be taught to consider them valuable for mere parade and attraction. Making the education of girls such a series of 'Man-traps,' makes the whole system unhealthy by poisoning the motive.</p><p align="center">* * * * * * *</p><p>IN tracing evils of any kind, which exist in society, we must, after all, be brought up against the great cause of all mischief, <emph rend="italic">mismanagement in education;</emph> and this remark applies with peculiar force to the leading fault of the present day, viz. extravagance. It is useless to expend our ingenuity in purifying the stream unless the fountain be cleansed. If young men and young women are brought up to consider<pb n="99" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=107"/> frugality contemptible, and industry degrading, it is vain to expect they will at once become prudent and useful, when the cares of life press heavily upon them. Generally speaking, when misfortune comes upon those who have been accustomed to thoughtless expenditure, it sinks them to discouragement, or, what is worse, drives them to desperation. It is true there are exceptions. There are a few, an honorable few, who late in life, with Roman severity of resolution, learn the long neglected lesson of economy. But how small is the number, compared with the whole mass of the population! And with what bitter agony, with what biting humiliation is the hard lesson often learned! How easily might it have been engrafted on <emph rend="italic">early habits,</emph> and naturally and gracefully 'grown with their growth, and strengthened with their strength!'</p><p>Yet it was but lately that I visited a family, not of 'moderate fortune,' but of no fortune at all; one of those people who live 'nobody knows how;' and I found a young girl, about sixteen, practising on the piano, while an elderly lady beside her was darning her stockings. I was told (for the mother was proud of bringing up her child so genteelly) that the daughter had almost forgotten how to sew; and that a woman was hired into the house to do her mending. 'But why,' said I, 'have you suffered your daughter to be ignorant of so useful an employment? If she is poor, the knowledge will be necessary to her; if she is rich, it is the easiest thing in the world to lay it aside, if she chooses; she will merely be a better judge whether her work is well done by others.' 'That is true,' replied the mother; 'and I always meant she should learn; but she never has seemed to have any time. When she was eight years old, she could put a shirt together pretty well; but since that, her music, and her dancing, and her<pb n="100" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=108"/> school, have taken up her whole time. I did mean she should learn some domestic habits this winter; but she has so many visiters, and is obliged to go out so much, that I suppose I must give it up. I don't like to say too much about it; for, poor girl! she does so love company, and she does so hate anything like care and confinement! <emph rend="italic">Now</emph> is her time to enjoy herself, you know. Let her take all the comfort she can, while she is single!' 'But,' said I, 'you wish her to marry some time or other; and in all probability she will marry. When will she learn how to perform the duties, which are necessary and important to every mistress of a family?' 'Oh, she will learn them when she is obliged to,' answered the injudicious mother; 'at all events, I am determined she shall enjoy herself while she is young.'</p><p>And this is the way I have often heard mothers talk! Yet could parents foresee the almost inevitable consequences of such a system, I believe the weakest and vainest would abandon the false and dangerous theory. What a lesson is taught a girl in that sentence, <emph rend="italic">'Let her enjoy herself all she can, while she is single!'</emph> Instead of representing domestic life as the gathering place of the deepest and purest affections; as the sphere of woman's <emph rend="italic">enjoyments</emph> as well as of her <emph 
rend="italic">duties;</emph> as indeed the whole world to her; that one pernicious sentence teaches a girl to consider matrimony desirable because 'a good match' is a triumph of vanity, and it is deemed respectable to be 'well settled in the world;' but that it is a necessary sacrifice of her freedom and her gaiety. And then how many affectionate dispositions have been trained into heartlessness, by being taught that the indulgence of indolence and vanity were necessary to their happiness; and that to have this indulgence, they <emph rend="italic">must</emph> marry money! But who that marries for money, in this land of precarious fortunes, can tell<pb n="101" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=109"/> how soon they will loose the glittering temptation, to which they have been willing to sacrifice so much? And even if riches last as long as life, the evil is not remedied. Education has given a wrong end and aim to their whole existence; they have been taught to look for happiness where it never can be found, viz. in the absence of all occupation, or the unsatisfactory and ruinous excitement of fashionable competition.</p><p>The difficulty is, education does not usually point the female heart to its only true resting place. That dear English word <emph rend="italic">'home,'</emph> is not half so powerful a talisman as <emph rend="italic">'the world.'</emph> Instead of the salutary truth, that happiness is <emph rend="italic">in</emph> duty, they are taught to consider the two things totally distinct; and that whoever seeks one must sacrifice the other.</p><p>The fact is, our girls have no <emph rend="italic">home education.</emph> When quite young, they are sent to schools where no feminine employments, no domestic habits, can be learned; and there they continue till they 'come out' into the world. After this, few find any time to arrange, and make use of, the mass of elementary knowledge they have acquired; and fewer still have either leisure, or taste, for the inelegant every-day duties of life. Thus prepared, they enter upon matrimony. Those early habits, which would have made domestic care a light and easy task, have never been taught, for fear it would interrupt their happiness; and the result is, that when cares come, as come they must, they find them misery. I am convinced that indifference and dislike between husband and wife are more frequently occasioned by this great error in education, than by any other cause.</p><p>The bride is awakened from her delightful dream, in which carpets, vases, sofas, white gloves, and pearl ear-rings, are oddly jumbled up with her lover's looks and promises. Perhaps she would be surprised if she knew exactly how <emph rend="italic">much</emph> of the fascination of<pb n="102" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=110"/> being engaged was owing to the aforesaid inanimate concern. Be that as it will, she is awakened by the unpleasant conviction that cares devolve upon her. And what effect does this produce upon her character? Do the holy and tender influences of domestic love render self-denial and exertion a bliss? No! They would have done so, had she been <emph rend="italic">properly educated;</emph> but now she gives way to unavailing fretfulness and repining; and her husband is at first pained, and finally disgusted, by hearing 'I never knew what care was when I lived in my father's house.' 'If I were to live my life over again, I would remain single as long as I could, without the risk of being an old maid.' How injudicious, how short-sighted is the policy, which thus mars the whole happiness of life, in order to make a few brief years more gay and brilliant! I have known many instances of domestic ruin and discord produced by this mistaken indulgence of mothers. <emph rend="italic">I never knew but one, where the victim had moral courage enough to change all her early habits.</emph> She was a young, pretty, and very amiable girl; but brought up to be perfectly useless; a rag baby would, to all intents and purposes, have been as efficient a partner. She married a young lawyer, without property, but with good and increasing practice. She meant to be a good wife, but she did not know how. Her wastefulness involved him in debt. He did not reproach, though he tried to convince and instruct her. She loved him; and weeping replied, 'I try to do the best I can; but when I lived at home, mother always took care of everything.' Finally, poverty came upon him 'like an armed man;' and he went into a remote town in the Western States to teach a school. His wife folded her hands and cried; while he, weary and discouraged, actually came home from school to cook his own supper. At last, his patience, and her real<pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=111"/> love for him, impelled her to exertion. She promised to learn to be useful, if he would teach her. And she did learn! And the change in her habits gradually wrought such a change in her husband's fortune, that she might bring her daughters up in idleness, had not experience taught her that economy, like grammar, is a very hard and tiresome study, after we are twenty years old.</p><p>Perhaps some will think the evils of which I have been speaking are confined principally to the rich; but I am convinced they extend to all classes of people. All manual employment is considered degrading; and those who are compelled to do it, try to conceal it. A few years since, very respectable young men at our colleges cut their own wood, and blacked their own shoes. Now, how few, even of the sons of plain farmers and industrious mechanics, have moral courage enough to do without a servant; yet when they leave college, and come out into the battle of life, they <emph rend="italic">must</emph> do without servants; and in these times it will be fortunate if one half of them get what is called 'a decent living,' even by rigid economy and patient toil. Yet I would not that servile and laborious employment should be forced upon the young. I would merely have each one educated according to his probable situation in life; and be taught that whatever is his duty is honorable; and that no merely external circumstance can in reality injure true dignity of character. I would not cramp a boy's energies by compelling him always to cut wood, or draw water; but I would teach him not to be ashamed, should his companions happen to find him doing either one or the other. A few days since I asked a grocer's lad to bring home some articles I had just purchased at his master's. The bundle was large; he was visibly reluctant to take it; and wished very much that I should send for it. This, however, was impossible; and he subdued his pride; but<pb n="104" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=112"/> when I asked him to take back an empty bottle which belonged to the store, he, with a mortified look, begged me to do it up neatly in a paper, that it might look like a small package. Is this boy likely to be happier for cherishing a foolish pride, which will forever be jarring against his duties? Is he in reality, one whit more respectable, than the industrious lad who sweeps stores, or carries bottles, without troubling himself with the idea that all the world is observing his little unimportant self? For, in relation to the rest of the world, each individual is unimportant; and he alone is wise who forms his habits according to his own wants, his own prospects, and his own principles.</p></section>
<section class1="generalnonfood"><hd align="center">TRAVELLING AND PUBLIC AMUSEMENTS.</hd><p>THERE is one kind of extravagance rapidly increasing in this country, which in its effects on our purses and our <emph rend="italic">habits,</emph> is one of the worst kinds of extravagance; I mean the rage for travelling, and for public amusements. The good old home habits of our ancestors are breaking up--it will be well if our virtue and our freedom do not follow them! It is easy to laugh at such prognostics,--and we are well aware that the virtue we preach is considered almost obsolete,--but let any reflecting mind inquire how decay has begun in all republics, and then let them calmly ask themselves whether we are in no danger, in departing thus rapidly from the simplicity and industry of our forefathers.</p><p>Nations do not plunge <emph rend="italic">at once</emph> into ruin--governments do not change <emph rend="italic">suddenly</emph>--the causes which bring about the final blow, are scarcely perceptible in<pb n="105" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=113"/> the beginning; but they increase in numbers, and in power; they press harder and harder upon the energies and virtue of a people; and the last steps only are alarmingly hurried and irregular. A republic without industry, economy, and integrity, is Samson shorn of his locks. A luxurious and idle <emph rend="italic">republic!</emph> Look at the phrase!--The words were never made to be married together; everybody sees it would be death to one of them.</p><p>And are not <emph rend="italic">we</emph> becoming luxurious and idle? Look at our steamboats, and stages, and taverns! There you will find mechanics, who have left debts and employment to take care of themselves, while they go to take a peep at the great canal, or the opera-dancers. There you will find domestics all agog for their wages-worth of travelling; why should they look out for 'a rainy day?' There are hospitals enough to provide for them in sickness; and as for marrying, they have no idea of that, till they can find a man who will support them genteelly. There you will find mothers, who have left the children at home with Betsey, while they go to improve their minds at the Mountain House, or the Springs.</p><p>If only the rich did this, all would be well. They benefit others, and do not injure themselves. In any situation idleness is their curse, and uneasiness is the tax they must pay for affluence; but their restlessness is as great a benefit to the community as the motions of Prince Esterhazy, when at every step the pearls drop from his coat.</p><p>People of moderate fortune have just as good a right to travel as the wealthy; but is it not unwise? do they not injure themselves and their families? You say travelling is cheap? So is staying at home. Besides, do you count <emph rend="italic">all</emph> the costs?</p><p>The money you pay for stages and steamboats is the smallest of the items. There are clothes bought which would not otherwise be bought; those clothes<pb n="106" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=114"/> are worn out and defaced, twenty times as quick as they would have been at home; children are perhaps left with domestics, or strangers; their health and morals, to say the least, under very uncertain influence; your substance is wasted in your absence by those who have no self-interest to prompt them to carefulness; you form an acquaintance with a multitude of people, who will be sure to take your house in their way, when they travel next year; and finally, you become so accustomed to excitement, that home appears insipid, and it requires no small effort to return to the quiet routine of your duties. And what do you get in return for all this? Some pleasant scenes, which will soon seem to you like a dream; some pleasant faces, which you will never see again; and much of crowd, and toil, and dust, and bustle.</p><p>I once knew a family, which formed a striking illustration of my remarks. The man was a farmer, and his wife was an active, capable woman, with more of ambition than sound policy. Being in debt, they resolved to take fashionable boarders from Boston, during the summer season. These boarders, at the time of their arrival, were projecting a jaunt to the Springs; and they talked of Lake George <alt synonym1="crystals">chrystals,</alt> and Canadian music, and English officers, and 'dark blue Ontario,' with its beautiful little brood of<emph rend="italic">lakelets,</emph> as Wordsworth would call them; and how one lady was dressed superbly at Saratoga; and how another was scandalized for always happening to drop her fan in the vicinity of the wealthiest beaux. All this fired the quiet imagination of the good farmer's wife; and no sooner had the boarders departed to enjoy themselves in spite of heat, and dust, and fever-and-ague, than she stated her determination to follow them. 'Why have we not as good a right to travel, as they have?' said she; 'they have paid us money enough to go to Niagara with; and it really is a shame for people to live and die so ignorant of<pb n="107" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=115"/> their own country.' 'But then we want the money to pay for that stock, which turned out unlucky, you know.' 'Oh that can be done next summer; we can always get boarders enough, and those that will pay handsomely. Give the man a mortgage of the house, to keep him quiet till next summer.' 'But what will you do with the children?' 'Sally is a very smart girl; I am sure she will take as good care of them, as if I were at home.'</p><p>To make a long story short, the farmer and his wife concluded to go to Quebec, just to show they had a <emph rend="italic">right</emph> to put themselves to inconvenience, if they pleased. They went; spent all their money; had a watch stolen from them in the steamboat; were dreadfully sea-sick off Point Judith; came home tired, and dusty; found the babe sick, because Sally had stood at the door with it, one chilly, damp morning, while she was feeding the chickens; and the eldest girl screaming and screeching at the thoughts of going to bed, because Sally, in order to bring her under her authority, had told her a frightful 'raw-head-and-bloody-bones' story; the horse had broken into the garden, and made wretched work with the vegetables; and fifty pounds of butter had become fit for the grease-pot, because the hoops of the <implement>firkin</implement> had sprung, and Sally had so much to do, that she never thought of going to see whether the butter was covered with brine.</p>

<p>After six or eight weeks, the children were pretty well restored to orderly habits; and the wife, being really a notable and prudent woman, resolved to make up for her lost butter and vegetables, by doing without help through the winter. When summer came, they should have boarders, she said; and sure enough they had boarders in plenty; but not profitable ones. There were forty cousins, at whose houses they had stopped; and twenty people who had been very polite to them on the way; and it<pb n="108" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=116"/> being such a pleasant season, and <emph rend="italic">travelling so cheap,</emph> every one of these people felt they had a <emph rend="italic">right</emph> to take a journey; and they could not help passing a day or two with their friends at the farm. One after another came, till the farmer could bear it no longer. 'I tell you what, wife,' said he, 'I am going to jail as fast as a man can go. If there is no other way of putting a stop to this, I'll sell every bed in the house, except the one we sleep on.'</p><p>And sure enough, he actually did this; and when the fortyfirst cousin came down on a friendly visit, on account of what her other cousins had told her about the cheapness of travelling, she was told they should be very happy to sleep on the floor, for the sake of accommodating her, for a night or two; but the truth was they had but one bed in the house. This honest couple are now busy in paying off their debts, and laying by something for their old age. He facetiously tells how he went to New York to have his watch stolen, and his boots blacked like a looking glass; and she shows her Lake George diamond ring, and tells how the steamboat was crowded, and how afraid she was the <implement>boiler</implement> would burst, and always ends by saying, 'after all it was a toil of pleasure.'</p><p>However it is not our farmers, who are in the greatest danger of this species of extravagance; for we look to that class of people, as the strongest hold of republican simplicity, industry, and virtue. It is from adventurers, swindlers, broken down traders,--all that rapidly increasing class of idlers, too genteel to work, and too proud to beg, that we have most reason to dread examples of extravagance. A very respectable tavern-keeper, has lately been driven to establish a rule, that no customer shall be allowed to rise from the table till he pays for his meal. 'I know it is rude to give such orders to honest men,' said he, 'and three years ago I would as soon cut off my<pb n="109" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=117"/> hand as have done it; but now, travelling is so cheap, that all sorts of characters are on the move; and I find more than half of them will get away if they can, without paying a cent.'</p><p>With regard to public amusements, it is still worse. Rope-dancers, and opera-dancers, and all sorts of dancers, go through the country, making thousands as they go; while from high to low there is one universal, despairing groan of 'hard times,' 'dreadful gloomy times.'</p><p>These things ought not to be. People who have little to spend, should partake sparingly of useless amusements; those who are in debt should deny themselves entirely. Let me not be supposed to inculcate exclusive doctrines. I would have every species of enjoyment as open to the poor as to the rich; but I would have people consider well how they are likely to obtain the greatest portion of happiness, taking the whole of their lives into view; I would not have them sacrifice permanent respectability and comfort to present gentility and love of excitement; above all, I caution them to beware that this love of excitement does not grow into a habit, till the fireside becomes a dull place, and the gambling table, and the 
bar-room finish what the theatre 
began.</p><p>If men would have women economical, they must be so themselves! What motive is there for patient industry, and careful economy, when the savings of a month are spent at one trip to Nahant, and more than the value of a much desired, but rejected dress, is expended during the stay of a new set of comedians? We make a great deal of talk about being republicans; if we are so in reality, we shall stay at home, to mind our business, and educate our children, so long as one or the other need our attention, or can suffer by our neglect.</p></section>
<section class1="generalnonfood"><pb n="110" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=118"/><hd align="center">PHILOSOPHY AND CONSISTENCY.</hd><p>AMONG all the fine things Mrs Barbauld wrote, she never wrote anything better than her essay on the Inconsistency of Human Expectations. 'Everything,' says she, 'is marked at a settled price. Our time, our labor, our ingenuity, is so much ready money, which we are to lay out to the best advantage. Examine, compare, choose, reject; but stand to your own judgment; and do not, like children, when you have purchased one thing, repine that you do not possess another, which you would not purchase. Would you be rich? Do you think <emph rend="italic">that</emph> the single point worth sacrificing everything else to? You may then be rich. Thousands have become so from the lowest beginnings, by toil, and diligence, and attention to the minutest articles of expense and profit. But you must give up the pleasures of leisure, of an unembarrassed mind, and of a free, unsuspicious temper. You must learn to do hard, if not unjust things; and as for the embarrassment of a delicate and ingenuous spirit, it is necessary for you to get rid of it as fast as possible. You must not stop to enlarge your mind, polish your taste, or refine your sentiments; but must keep on in one beaten track, without turning aside to the right hand, or the left. "But," you say, "I cannot submit to drudgery like this; I feel a spirit above it." 'Tis well; be above it then; only do not repine because you are not rich. Is knowledge the pearl of price in your estimation? That, too, may be purchased by steady application, and long solitary hours of study and reflection. "But," says the man of letters, "what a hardship is it that many an illiterate fellow, who cannot construe the motto on his coach, shall raise a fortune, and make a figure, while I possess merely the common conveniences of life." Was it for fortune, then, that you<pb n="111" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=119"/> grew pale over the midnight lamp, and gave the sprightly years of youth to study and reflection? You have then mistaken your path, and ill employed your industry. "What reward have I then for all my labor?" What reward! A large, comprehensive soul, purged from vulgar fears and prejudices, able to interpret the works of man and God. A perpetual spring of fresh ideas, and the conscious dignity of superior intelligence. Good Heaven! what other reward can you ask! "But is it not a reproach upon the economy of Providence that such a one, who is a mean, dirty fellow, should have amassed wealth enough to buy half a nation?" Not in the least. He made himself a mean, dirty fellow, for that very end. He has paid his health, his conscience, and his liberty for it. Do you envy him his bargain? Will you hang your head in his presence, because he outshines you in equipage and show? Lift up your brow with a noble confidence, and say to yourself, "I have not these things, it is true; but it is because I have not desired, or sought them; it is because I possess something better. I have chosen my lot! I am content, and satisfied." The most characteristic mark of a great mind is to choose some one object, which it considers important, and pursue that object through life. If we expect the purchase we must pay the price.'</p><p>'There is a pretty passage in one of Lucian's dialogues, where Jupiter complains to Cupid, that though he has had so many intrigues, he was never sincerely beloved. "In order to be loved," says Cupid, "you must lay aside your &#230;gis and your thunder bolts, you must curl and perfume your hair, and place a garland on your head, and walk with a soft step, and assume a winning, obsequious deportment." "But," replied Jupiter, "I am not willing to resign so much of my dignity." "Then," returned Cupid, "leave off desiring to be loved."'</p><pb n="112" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=120"/><p>These remarks by Mrs. Barbauld are full of sound philosophy. Who has not observed in his circle of acquaintance, and in the recesses of his own heart, the same inconsistency of expectation, the same peevishness of discontent.</p><p>Says Germanicus, 'There is my dunce of a classmate has found his way into Congress, and is living amid the perpetual excitement of intellectual minds, while I am cooped up in an ignorant country parish, obliged to be at the beck and call of every old woman, who happens to feel uneasy in her mind.'</p><p>'Well, Germanicus, the road to political distinction was as open to you as to him; why did you not choose it?' 'Oh, I could not consent to be the tool of a party; to shake hands with the vicious, and flatter fools. It would gall me to the quick to hear my opponents accuse me of actions I never committed, and of motives, which worlds would not tempt me to indulge.' Since Germanicus is wise enough to know the whistle costs more than it is worth, is he not unreasonable to murmur because he has not bought it?</p><p>Matrona always wears a discontented look, when she hears the praises of Clio. 'I used to write her composition for her, when we were at school together,' says she; 'and now she is quite the idol of the literary world; while I am never heard of beyond my own family, unless some one happens to introduce me as the friend of Clio.' 'Why not write then; and see if the world will not learn to introduce Clio as the friend of Matrona?' 'I write! not for the world! I could not endure to pour my soul out to an undiscerning multitude; I could not see my cherished thoughts caricatured by some soulless reviewer; and my favorite fancies expounded by the matter-of-fact editor of some stupid paper.' Why does Matrona envy what she knows costs so much, and is of so little value?</p><pb n="113" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=121"/><p>Yet so it is, through all classes of society. All of us covet some neighbor's possession, and think our lot would have been happier, had it been different from what it is. Yet most of us could obtain worldly distinctions, if our habits and inclinations allowed us to pay the immense price at which they must be purchased. True wisdom lies in finding out all the advantages of a situation in which we <emph rend="italic">are</emph> placed, instead of imagining the enjoyments of one in which we are <emph rend="italic">not</emph> placed.</p><p>Such philosophy is rarely found. The most perfect sample I ever met, was an old woman, who was apparently the poorest and most forlorn of the human species--so true is the maxim which all profess to believe, and which none act upon invariably, viz. that happiness does not depend on outward circumstances. The wise woman, to whom I have alluded, <emph rend="italic">walks</emph> to Boston, from a distance of twentyfive or thirty miles, to sell a bag of brown thread and stockings; and then patiently foots it back again with her little gains. Her dress, though tidy, is a grotesque collection of 'shreds and patches,' coarse in the extreme. 'Why don't you come down in a wagon?' said I, when I observed that she was soon to become a mother, and was evidently wearied with her long journey. 'We han't got any horse,' replied she; 'the neighbors are very kind to me, but they can't spare ther'n; and it would cost as much to hire one, as all my thread will come to.' 'You have a husband--don't he do anything for you?' 'He is a good man; he does all he can; but he's a cripple and an invalid. He reels my yarn, and <emph rend="italic">specks</emph> the children's shoes. He's as kind a husband as a woman need to have.' 'But his being a cripple is a heavy misfortune to you,' said I. 'Why, ma'am, I don't look upon it in that light,' replied the thread-woman; 'I consider that I've great reason to be thankful he never took to any bad habits.' 'How<pb n="114" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=122"/> many children have you?' 'Six sons, and five <emph rend="italic">darters,</emph> ma'am.' 'Six sons and five daughters! What a family for a poor woman to support!' 'It's a family, surely, ma'am; but there an't one of 'em I'd be willing to lose. They are as good children as need to be-- all willing to work, and all clever to me. Even the littlest boy, when he gets a cent now and then for doing a <emph rend="italic">chore,</emph> will be sure and bring it to ma'am.' 'Do your daughters spin your thread?' 'No, ma'am; as soon as they are old enough, they go out to <emph rend="italic">sarvice.</emph> I don't want to keep them always delving for me; they are always willing to give me what they can; but it is right and fair they should do a little for themselves. I do all my spinning after the folks are abed.' 'Don't you think you should be better off, if you had no one but yourself to provide for?' 'Why, no ma'am, I don't. If I had'nt been married, I should always have had to work as hard as I could; and now I can't do more than that. My children are a great comfort to me; and I look forward to the time when they'll do as much for me, as I have done for them.'</p><p>Here was true philosophy! I learned a lesson from that poor woman, which I shall not soon forget. If I wanted true, hearty, well principled service, I would employ children brought up by such a mother.</p></section>
<section class1="generalnonfood"><hd align="center">REASONS FOR HARD TIMES.</hd><p>PERHAPS there never was a time when the depressing effects of stagnation in business were so universally felt, all the world over, as they are now.--The merchant sends out old dollars, and is lucky if he gets the same number of new ones in return; and <pb n="115" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=123"/> he who has a share in manufactures, has bought a 'Bottle Imp,' which he will do well to hawk about the street for the lowest possible coin. The effects of this depression must of course be felt by all grades of society. Yet who that passes through Cornhill at one o'clock, and sees the bright array of wives and daughters, as various in their decorations as the insects, the birds and the shells, would believe that the community was staggering under a weight which almost paralyzes its movements? 'Everything is so cheap,' say the ladies, 'that it is inexcusable not to dress well.' But do they reflect <emph rend="italic">why</emph> things are so cheap? Do they know how much wealth has been sacrificed, how many families ruined, to produce this boasted result? Do they not know enough of the machinery of society, to suppose that the stunning effects of crash after crash, may eventually be felt by those on whom they depend for support?</p><p>Luxuries are cheaper now, than necessaries were a few years since; yet it is a lamentable fact, that it costs more to live now, than it did formerly. When silk was nine shillings per yard, seven or eight yards sufficed for a dress; now it is four or five shillings, sixteen or twenty yards will hardly satisfy the mantua-maker.</p><p>If this extravagance were confined to the wealthiest classes, it would be productive of more good than evil. But if the rich have a new dress every fortnight, people of moderate fortune will have one every month. In this way finery becomes the standard of respectability; and a man's cloth is of more consequence than his character.</p><p>Men of fixed salaries spend every cent of their income, and then leave their children to depend on the precarious charity and reluctant friendship of a world they have wasted their substance to please. Men who rush into enterprise and speculation, keep up their credit by splendor; and should they sink, they and <pb n="116" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=124"/> their families carry with them extravagant habits to corrode their spirits with discontent, perchance to tempt them into crime. 'I know we are extravagant,' said one of my acquaintance, the other day; 'but how can I help it? My husband does not like to see his wife and daughters dress more meanly than those with whom they associate.' 'Then, my dear lady, your husband has not as much moral dignity and moral courage, as I thought he had. He should be content to see his wife and daughters respected for neatness, good taste, and attractive manners.' 'This all sounds very well in talk,' replied the lady; 'but say what you will about pleasing and intelligent girls, nobody will attend to them unless they dress in the fashion. If my daughters were to dress in the plain, neat style you recommend, they would see all their acquaintance asked to dance more frequently than themselves, and not a gentleman would join them in Cornhill.'</p><p>'I do not believe this in so extensive a sense as you do. Girls may appear genteelly without being extravagant; and though some fops may know the most approved color for a ribbon, or the newest arrangement for trimming, I believe gentlemen of real character merely notice whether a lady's dress is generally in good taste, or not. But granting your statement to be true, in its widest sense, of what consequence is it? How much will the whole happiness of your daughter's life be affected, by her dancing some fifty times less than her companions, or wasting some few hours less in the empty conversation of coxcombs? A man often admires a style of dress, which he would not venture to support in a wife. Extravagance has prevented many marriages, and rendered still more unhappy. And should your daughters fail in forming good connexions, what have you to leave them, save extravagant habits too deeply rooted to be eradicated. Think you those who now laugh at them for a <pb n="117" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=125"/> soiled glove, or an unfashionable ribbon, will assist their poverty, or cheer their neglected old age? No, they would find them as cold and selfish, as they are vain. A few thousands in the bank, are worth all the fashionable friends in christendom.'</p><p>Whether my friend was convinced or not I cannot say; but I saw her daughters in Cornhill the next week, with new French hats and blonde veils.</p><p>It is really melancholy to see how this fever of extravagance rages, and how it is sapping the strength of our happy country. It has no bounds; it pervades all ranks, and characterizes all ages.</p><p>I know the wife of a pavier who spends her three hundred a year in 'outward adorning,' and who will not condescend to speak to her husband, while engaged in his honest calling.</p><p>Mechanics, who should have too high a sense of their own respectability, to resort to such pitiful competition, will indulge their daughters in dressing like the wealthiest; and a domestic would certainly leave you, should you dare advise her to lay up one cent of her wages.</p><p>'These things ought not to be.' Every man and every woman should lay up some portion of their income, whether that income be large or small.</p></section>
<section class1="generalnonfood"><hd align="center">HOW TO ENDURE POVERTY.</hd><p>THAT a thorough, religious, <emph rend="italic">useful</emph> education is the best security against misfortune, disgrace and poverty, is universally believed and acknowledged; and to this we add the firm conviction, that when poverty comes, (as it sometimes will,) upon the prudent, the<pb n="118" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=126"/> industrious, and the well-informed, a judicious education is all powerful, in enabling them to <emph rend="italic">endure</emph> the evils it cannot always <emph rend="italic">prevent.</emph> A mind full of piety and knowledge is always rich; it is a bank that never fails; it yields a perpetual dividend of happiness.</p><p>In a late visit to the alms-house at ----, we saw a remarkable evidence of the truth of this doctrine. Mrs ---- was early left an orphan. She was educated by an uncle and aunt, both of whom had attained the middle age of life. Theirs was an industrious, well-ordered, and cheerful family. Her uncle was a man of sound judgment, liberal feelings, and great knowledge of human nature. This he showed by the education of the young people under his care. He allowed them to waste no time; every moment must be spent in learning something, or in doing something. He encouraged an entertaining, lively style of conversation, but discountenanced all remarks about persons, families, dress, and engagements; he used to say parents were not aware how such topics frittered away the minds of young people, and what inordinate importance they learned to attach to them, when they heard them constantly talked about.</p><p>In his family Sunday was a happy day; for it was made a day of religious instruction, without any unnatural constraint upon the gaiety of the young. The Bible was the text book; the places mentioned in it were traced on maps; the manners and customs of different nations were explained; curious phenomena in the natural history of those countries were read; in a word, everything was done to cherish a spirit of humble, yet earnest inquiry. In this excellent family Mrs ---- remained till her marriage. In the course of fifteen years, she lost her uncle, her aunt, and her husband. She was left destitute; but supported herself comfortably by her own exertions, and retained the respect and admiration of a large circle of friends. Thus she passed her life in cheerfulness<pb n="119" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=127"/> and honor during ten years; at the end of that time, her humble residence took fire, from an adjoining house in the night time, and she escaped by jumping from the chamber window. In consequence of the injury received by this fall, her right arm was amputated, and her right leg became entirely useless. Her friends were very kind and attentive; and for a short time she consented to live on their bounty; but aware that the claims on private charity are very numerous, she, with the genuine independence of a strong mind, resolved to avail herself of the public provision for the helpless poor. The name of going to the alms-house had nothing terrifying or disgraceful to <emph rend="italic">her;</emph> for she had been taught that <emph rend="italic">conduct</emph> is the real standard of respectability. She is there, with a heart full of thankfulness to the Giver of all things; she is patient, pious, and uniformly cheerful. She instructs the young, encourages the old, and makes herself delightful to all, by her various knowledge, and entertaining conversation. Her character reflects dignity on her situation; and those who visit the establishment, come away with sentiments of respect and admiration for this voluntary resident of the alms-house.</p><p align="center">* * * * * * *</p><p>What a contrast is afforded by the character of the woman, who occupies the room next hers. She is so indolent and filthy that she can with difficulty be made to attend to her own personal comfort; and even the most patient are worn out with her perpetual fretfulness. Her mind is continually infested with envy, hatred, and discontent. She thinks Providence has dealt hardly with her; that all the world are proud and ungrateful; and that every body despises her because she is in the alms-house. This pitiable state of mind is the natural result of her education.</p><p>Her father was a respectable mechanic, and might have been a wealthy one, had he not been fascinated<pb n="120" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=128"/> by the beauty of a thoughtless, idle, shewy girl, whom he made his wife. The usual consequences followed--he could not earn money so fast as she could spend it; the house became a scene of discord; the daughter dressed in the fashion, learned to play on the piano; was taught to think that being engaged in any useful employment was very ungenteel; and that to be <emph rend="italic">engaged to be married</emph> was the chief end and aim of woman; the father died a bankrupt; the weak and frivolous mother lingered along in beggary, for a while, and then died of vexation and shame.</p><p>The friends of the family were very kind to the daughter; but her extreme indolence, her vanity, pertness, and ingratitude, finally exhausted the kindness of the most generous and forbearing; and as nothing could induce her to personal exertion, she was at length obliged to take shelter in the alms-house. Here her misery is incurable. She has so long been accustomed to think dress and parade the necessary elements of happiness, that she despises all that is done for her comfort; her face has settled into an expression which looks like an embodied growl; every body is tired of listening to her complaints; and even the little children run away, when they see her coming.</p><p>May not those who have children to educate, learn a good lesson from these women? Those who have wealth, have recently had many and bitter lessons to prove how suddenly riches may take to themselves wings; and those who <emph rend="italic">certainly</emph> have but little to leave, should indeed beware how they bestow upon their children, the accursed inheritance of indolent and extravagant habits.</p></section>
</chapter>
</body>
<back>
<div type="index"><pb n="NONE OF THE ABOVE" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=129"/><hd align="center" rend="bold">INDEX.</hd><list><hd align="center">A.</hd><lb/><item>Advice, General, . . . . . . <ref target="frch011.jpg">3 to 10</ref></item><item>Alamode Beef, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch059.jpg">51</ref></item><item>Apple Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Apple Pie, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch079.jpg">71</ref></item><item>Arrow-root Jelly, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Ashes for Iand, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Ashes, care of, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Asparagus, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">B.</hd><lb/><item>Balm of Gilead, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Batter Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch072.jpg">64</ref></item><item>Beans and Peas cooked, . . . . . . <ref target="frch066.jpg">58</ref></item><item>Beef cooked, . . . . . . <ref target="frch058.jpg">50, 51</ref></item><item>Beef corned, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch048.jpg">40</ref></item><item>Beef salted, . . . . . . <ref target="frch049.jpg">41, 42</ref></item><item>Beef Tea, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch038.jpg">30</ref></item><item>Beer, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch099.jpg">91, 92</ref></item><item>Bed-bug Poison, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11</ref></item><item>Bird's nest Pudding, . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Bleeding Wounds, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Blisters of Burns broken, . . . . . <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Bottles of Rose-water, . . . . . . <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Bottles, Vials, &amp;c, . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16</ref></item><item>Brass Kettles, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Brass Andirons, &amp;c, . . . . . . <ref target="frch021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Brasses in Summer, . . . . . . <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Bread, Yeast, &amp;c, . . . . . <ref target="frch089.jpg">81 to 85</ref></item><item>Bread Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch072.jpg">64</ref></item><item>Brine, . . . . . . <ref target="frch048.jpg">40, 41, 42</ref></item><item>Brittania Ware, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><pb n="122" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=130"/><item>Brooms, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Broth, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch060.jpg">52</ref></item><item>Bruises, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch042.jpg">34</ref></item><item>Butter, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16</ref></item><item>Burns, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28</ref></item><item>Burdock Leaves, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>Buffalo's Tongue, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch051.jpg">43</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">C.</hd><lb/><item>Canker, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Cabbages, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch039.jpg">31</ref></item><item>Catsup, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Carpets, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Cancers, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Calf's Head, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch058.jpg">50</ref></item><item>Carrot Pie, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch078.jpg">70</ref></item><item>Cakes, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch082.jpg">74 to 80</ref></item><item>Cement, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch030.jpg">22</ref></item><item>Celery, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Chopped Hands, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Chilblains, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Cholera Morbus, . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">25,</ref> <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Chickens, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch064.jpg">56</ref></item><item>Chicken Pie, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch062.jpg">58</ref></item><item>Chowder, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch069.jpg">61</ref></item><item>Cherry Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Cherry Pie, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch078.jpg">70</ref></item><item>Cheeses, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Cheapest pieces of Meat, . . . . <ref target="frch052.jpg">44 to 48</ref></item><item>Cider Cake, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch083.jpg">75</ref></item><item>Clothes Line, &amp;c, . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Clothes washed, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Clams, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch068.jpg">60</ref></item><item>Combs, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11</ref></item><item>Cockroaches, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch029.jpg">21</ref></item><item>Colds, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27,</ref> <ref target="frch042.jpg">34</ref></item><item>Corn, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32</ref></item><item>Coughs, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch042.jpg">34, 35</ref></item><item>Coloring, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch045.jpg">37 to 39</ref></item><pb n="123" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=131"/><item>Cod, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch067.jpg">59</ref></item><item>Coffee, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch096.jpg">88</ref></item><item>Croup, or Quincy, (Goose-grease, or any kind of oily grease, is nearly as good as Bear's-grease for this disorder.) . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24</ref></item><item>Cranberry Pudding, . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Cranberry Pie, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch080.jpg">72</ref></item><item>Currant-loaf Tea, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Cucumbers, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch028.jpg">20</ref></item><item>Cucumbers, pickled, . . . . . . <ref target="frch098.jpg">90</ref></item><item>Custards, cheap, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch076.jpg">68</ref></item><item>Custard Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Custard Pie, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch079.jpg">71</ref></item><item>Cup Cake, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch083.jpg">75</ref></item><item>Cut wounds, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch033.jpg">25</ref></item><item>Currant Jelly, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch095.jpg">87</ref></item><item>Currant Wine, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch095.jpg">87</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">D.</hd><lb/><item>Dandelions, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32</ref></item><item>Diet Bread, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch084.jpg">76</ref></item><item>Dish-water, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Dough Nuts, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch086.jpg">78</ref></item><item>Ducks, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch065.jpg">57</ref></item><item>Dyspepsy, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24,</ref> <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>Dysentery, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch033.jpg">25,</ref> <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Dye Stuffs, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch045.jpg">37 to 39</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">E.</hd><lb/><item>Ear-ache, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24</ref></item><item>Earthen Ware, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Eggs, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Election Cake, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch083.jpg">75</ref></item><item>Elixir Proprietatis, . . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28</ref></item><item>Education of Daughters, . . . . . . <ref target="frch103.jpg">95</ref></item><pb n="124" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=132"/><hd align="center">F.</hd><lb/><item>Faded Carpets, Cloth, &amp;c, . . . . . <ref target="frch018.jpg">10</ref></item><item>Feathers, and Feather Beds, . . . . . <ref target="frch021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Fevers, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28,</ref> <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>Fish, fried, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch068.jpg">60</ref></item><item>Fish, salt, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch069.jpg">61, 62</ref></item><item>Flour Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch072.jpg">64</ref></item><item>Fresh Wounds, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Fresh Meat in Summer, . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19,</ref> <ref target="frch057.jpg">49</ref></item><item>Fritters, or Flatjacks, . . . . . . <ref target="frch087.jpg">79</ref></item><item>Furniture, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch101.jpg">93</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">G.</hd><lb/><item>Geese, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch064.jpg">56</ref></item><item>Gingerbread, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch082.jpg">74</ref></item><item>Ginger Beer, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch099.jpg">91</ref></item><item>Gloves, white, . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11,</ref> <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Gravy for Meat, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch063.jpg">55</ref></item><item>Gravy for Poultry, . . . . . . <ref target="frch067.jpg">59</ref></item><item>Gravy for Fish, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch068.jpg">60</ref></item><item>Green Peas, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32,</ref> <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Gruel, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">H.</hd><lb/><item>Haddock, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch067.jpg">59</ref></item><item>Hams cured, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch049.jpg">41, 42</ref></item><item>Hair, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Head-ache, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26,</ref> <ref target="frch042.jpg">34</ref></item><item>Herbs, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch042.jpg">34,</ref> <ref target="frch044.jpg">36</ref></item><item>Hearths, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch028.jpg">20</ref></item><item>Horse Radish, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch028.jpg">20</ref></item><item>Horse Radish Leaves, . . . . . . <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>How to endure Poverty, . . . . . <ref target="frch122.jpg">114</ref></item><lb/><hd 
align="center">I.</hd><lb/><item>Icing for Cake, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch084.jpg">76</ref></item><item>Indian Puddings,. . . . . . . . <ref target="frch071.jpg">63</ref></item><item>Indian Cake, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch088.jpg">80</ref></item><item>Inflammation, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24</ref></item><pb n="125" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=133"/><item>Iron, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Ironing, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">J.</hd><lb/><item>Jaundice, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">K.</hd><lb/><item>Knife Handles, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch018.jpg">10</ref></item><item>Knives, washed, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">L.</hd><lb/><item>Lamb, cooked, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch059.jpg">51</ref></item><item>Lard, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16, 17</ref></item><item>Leaven, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch093.jpg">85</ref></item><item>Lemon Brandy, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch028.jpg">20</ref></item><item>Lemon Syrup, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch030.jpg">22</ref></item><item>Lettuce, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Loaf Cake, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch085.jpg">77</ref></item><item>Lobster, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch070.jpg">62</ref></item><item>Lockjaw, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch033.jpg">25</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">M.</hd><lb/><item>Mackerel, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch067.jpg">59,</ref> <ref target="frch070.jpg">62</ref></item><item>Mangoes, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch097.jpg">89</ref></item><item>Martinoes, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch099.jpg">90</ref></item><item>Marble Fireplaces, . . . . . . <ref target="frch021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Mats for the Table, . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11</ref></item><item>Mattrasses, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch025.jpg">17</ref></item><item>Meal, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11</ref></item><item>Meat, corned and salted, . . . . <ref target="frch048.jpg">40 to 43</ref></item><item>Meat Pie, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch066.jpg">58</ref></item><item>Meat, choice of, . . . . . . <ref target="frch052.jpg">44 to 48</ref></item><item>Meat in Summer, . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19,</ref> <ref target="frch057.jpg">49</ref></item><item>Mince Meat, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch061.jpg">53</ref></item><item>Mince Pies, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch077.jpg">69</ref></item><item>Moths, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Molasses, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Mortification, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Mutton and Lamb, cooked, . . . . . <ref target="frch059.jpg">51</ref></item><item>Mutton, corned and dried, . . . . . <ref target="frch049.jpg">41</ref></item><pb n="126" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=134"/><hd align="center">N.</hd><lb/><item>Navarino Bonnets, . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14, 15</ref></item><item>Nasturtion-seed, pickled, . . . . . <ref target="frch098.jpg">90</ref></item><item>Nerves, excited, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">O.</hd><lb/><item>Ointment of Ground Worms, . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Ointment of Lard and Sulphur, . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28</ref></item><item>Ointment of Elder Buds, (Page 29, for <emph rend="italic">immersed</emph>, read <emph rend="italic">simmered</emph>) . . . . . <ref target="frch037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Ointment of House Leek, . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Oil, sweet, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch028.jpg">20</ref></item><item>Old Clothes, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Onions, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch039.jpg">31</ref></item><item>Ovens heated, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch041.jpg">83</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">P.</hd><lb/><item>Pancakes, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch086.jpg">78</ref></item><item>Pastry, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch080.jpg">72</ref></item><item>Paper, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch025.jpg">17</ref></item><item>Parsnips, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch039.jpg">31</ref></item><item>Peas, green, . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32, 33</ref></item><item>Peas, dry, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch062.jpg">54</ref></item><item>Pigeons, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch065.jpg">57</ref></item><item>Pie Crust, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch080.jpg">72</ref></item><item>Pictures covered, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Piles, . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27, 28,</ref> <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>Pickles, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch088.jpg">80,</ref> <ref target="frch098.jpg">90</ref></item><item>Pig, roasted, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch060.jpg">52</ref></item><item>Plum Puddings, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch075.jpg">67</ref></item><item>Poultry, young or old, . . . . . . <ref target="frch063.jpg">55</ref></item><item>Potatoes, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch040.jpg">32</ref></item><item>Pork, salted, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch048.jpg">40</ref></item><item>Pork, cooked, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch060.jpg">52</ref></item><item>Provisions, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Preserves, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch094.jpg">86</ref></item><item>Pumpkin Pie, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch078.jpg">70</ref></item><pb n="127" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=135"/><item>Puddings, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch071.jpg">63 to 67</ref></item><item>Pump Handle, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Philosophy and Consistency, . . . . <ref target="frch118.jpg">110</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">R.</hd><lb/><item>Rags, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14,</ref> <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Raspberry Shrub, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch095.jpg">87</ref></item><item>Rennet Pudding, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch072.jpg">64</ref></item><item>Rhubarb or Persian Apple Pie, . . . . . <ref target="frch080.jpg">72</ref></item><item>Rice Puddings, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Rusty Crape, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Rusty Silk, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch029.jpg">21</ref></item><item>Reasons for Hard Times, . . . . . <ref target="frch122.jpg">114</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">S.</hd><lb/><item>Sauces for Pudding, . . . . . . <ref target="frch075.jpg">67</ref></item><item>Salt Fish, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch069.jpg">61</ref></item><item>Salt Fish, warmed, . . . . . . <ref target="frch070.jpg">62</ref></item><item>Sago Jelly, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch038.jpg">30</ref></item><item>Sausages, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch060.jpg">52</ref></item><item>Short Cake, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch087.jpg">79</ref></item><item>Silk washed, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16</ref></item><item>Sinews, contracted, . . . . . . <ref target="frch034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Soap, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch031.jpg">23</ref></item><item>Sore Throat, . . . . . . <ref target="frch033.jpg">25, 26</ref></item><item>Sore Mouth, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Soda Powders, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch030.jpg">22</ref></item><item>Souse, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch062.jpg">54</ref></item><item>Sprain, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24</ref></item><item>Spots on Furniture, Cloth, &amp;c, . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11</ref></item><item>Sponge Cake, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch084.jpg">76</ref></item><item>Squash Pie, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch078.jpg">70</ref></item><item>Squashes, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch039.jpg">31,</ref> <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Straw Beds, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Stockings, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch029.jpg">21</ref></item><item>Suet, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch025.jpg">17</ref></item><item>Swellings, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Sweet Marjoram, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch043.jpg">35</ref></item><pb n="128" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=136"/><hd align="center">T.</hd><lb/><item>Tapioca Jelly, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch038.jpg">30</ref></item><item>Tea Cake, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch083.jpg">75</ref></item><item>Teeth, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Throat Distemper, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Tooth ache, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch036.jpg">28, 29</ref></item><item>Towels, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Tomatoes, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Tongue, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch050.jpg">42, 43</ref></item><item>Tripe, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch063.jpg">55</ref></item><item>Turkeys, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch065.jpg">57</ref></item><item>Travelling and Public Amusements, . . . <ref target="frch112.jpg">104</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">V.</hd><lb/><item>Veal, cooked, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch057.jpg">49</ref></item><item>Vials, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Vinegar, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch025.jpg">17</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">W.</hd><lb/><item>Walnuts, pickled, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch097.jpg">89</ref></item><item>Water, soft, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Water, purified, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Wash-Leather Gloves, . . . . . . <ref target="frch020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Wens, . . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Wedding Cake, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch084.jpg">76</ref></item><item>White Kid Gloves, . . . . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11,</ref> <ref target="frch023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Whortleberry Pudding, . . . . . . <ref target="frch074.jpg">66</ref></item><item>Whortleberry Pie, . . . . . . 
. <ref target="frch079.jpg">71</ref></item><item>Wicks of Lamps, Candles, &amp;c, . . . <ref target="frch019.jpg">11, 12</ref></item><item>Wine Whey, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch038.jpg">30</ref></item><item>Woollen Yarn, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Woollens washed, . . . . . . . <ref target="frch024.jpg">16</ref></item><item>Worms, . . . . . . . . <ref target="frch032.jpg">24</ref></item><lb/><hd align="center">Y.</hd><lb/><item>Yeast, . . . . . . <ref target="frch091.jpg">83, 84, 85</ref></item></list></div>
<div type="other"><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=137"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=138"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=139"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=140"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=141"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=142"/></div>
<div type="backcover"><pb n="back cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=frch&#38;PageNum=143"/></div>
</back>
</cookbook>
