<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<cookbook type="general" class1="generalnonfood" region="general" bookID="1831notm">
<meta>
<dcTitle>The Cook Not Mad, or Rational Cookery...together with sundry Miscellaneous kinds of information, of importance to housekeepers in general, nearly all tested by experience.</dcTitle>
<dcCreator>Author unknown</dcCreator>
<dcSubject>Cookery, American.</dcSubject>
<dcDescription>Complete title: The Cook Not Mad, or Rational Cookery; Being a Collection of Original and Selected Receipts, Embracing not only the art of curing various kinds of meats and vegetables for future use, but of Cooking in its general acceptation, to the taste, habits, and degrees of luxury, prevalent with the American Publick, in Town and Country. To which are added, Directions for preparing comforts for the SICK ROOM together with sundry Miscellaneous kinds of information, of importance to housekeepers in general, nearly all tested by experience. [Motto, Gen. Chap. 27, V. 1, 2, 3, 4.]</dcDescription>
<dcPublisher>Watertown: Knowlton &#38; Rice</dcPublisher>
<dcContributor>Electronic edition created by Digital &#38; Multimedia Center, Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003.</dcContributor>
<dcContributor>Supplementary material by Jan Longone, Anne-Marie Rachman, Peter Berg, Yvonne Lockwood, and Val Berryman</dcContributor>
<dcDate>1831</dcDate>
<dcType>Text</dcType>
<dcFormat>xml-external-parsed-entity</dcFormat>
<dcFormat>jpeg</dcFormat>
<dcFormat>quicktime</dcFormat>
<dcIdentifier>http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/cooknotmad/notm.xml</dcIdentifier>
<dcSource>OCLC 7192000</dcSource>
<dcLanguage>en</dcLanguage>
<dcRelation>Digitized as part of "Feeding America: The Historic American Cookbook Project." Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003. http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/</dcRelation>
<dcCoverage>United States</dcCoverage>
<dcCoverage>Nineteenth century</dcCoverage>
<dcRights>The book digitized here was published in the United States before 1923 and is in the public domain according to U.S. copyright law. The digital version and supplementary materials are made available for all educational uses.</dcRights></meta>
<front>
<div type="frontcover">
<pb n="front cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=1"/>
</div>
<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=2"/>
<p><gap extent="one word"/> Eldred</p>
<ednote>Handwritten inscription.</ednote>
</div>
<div type="titlepage">
<pb n="title page" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=3"/>
<p>Mary McKelvey</p>
<ednote>Handwritten inscription.</ednote>
<doctitle align="center"><emph rend="bold">THE<lb/><lb/>COOK NOT MAD,<lb/><lb/>OR<lb/><lb/>RATIONAL COOKERY;</emph><lb/><lb/>BEING<lb/><lb/>A COLLECTION OF ORIGINAL AND SELECTED<lb/><lb/>RECEIPTS,<lb/><lb/>Embracing not only the art of curing various kinds of<lb/>meats and vegetables for future use, but of Cooking<lb/>in its general acception, to the taste, habits, and<lb/>degrees of luxury, prevalent with the <lb/><lb/>AMERICAN PUBLICK,<lb/><lb/>IN<lb/><lb/>TOWN AND COUNTRY.<lb/><lb/>TO WHICH ARE ADDED,<lb/><lb/>Directions for preparing comforts for the SICK ROOM<lb/>together with sundry Miscellaneous kinds of infor-<lb/>mation, of importance to housekeepers in general,<lb/>nearly all tested by experience.<lb/><lb/>[Motto, Gen. Chap. 27, V. 1, 2, 3, 4.]</doctitle>
<docimprint align="center"><emph rend="italic">WATERTOWN:</emph><lb/>PUBLISHED BY KNOWLTON &#38; RICE.<lb/>1831.</docimprint>
</div>
<div type="copyrightstmt">
<pb n="copyright statement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=4"/>
<hd align="center">NORTHERN DISTRICT OF NEW-YORK, TO WIT:</hd>
<p><emph rend="bold" size="larger">L. S.</emph> BE IT REMEMBERED, That on the eleventh day of October, in the fifty-fifth year of the Independence of the United States of America, A.D. 1830, Knowlton &#38; Rice, Booksellers of the said District, have deposited in this Office the title of a book the right whereof they ciaim as proprietors in the words following, to wit: "The Cook not mad, or Rational Cookery; being a collection of original and selected receipts, embracing not only the art of curing various kinds of meats and vegetables for future use, but of cooking, in its general acceptation, to the taste, habits, and degrees of luxury, prevalent with the American Publick, in town and country; to which are added, directions for preparing comforts for the Sick Room; together with sundry Miscellaneous kinds of information, of importance to housekeepers in general, nearly all tested by experience. [Motto, Gen. Chap. 27, V. 1,2,3,4.]" In conformity to the act of the Congress of the United States, entitled "An act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of Maps, Charts, and Books, to the authors and proprietors of such copies, during the times therein mentioned;" and also to the act entitled "An act supplementary to an act entitled 'An act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of Maps, Charts, and Books, to the authors and proprietors of such copies during the times therein mentioned,' and extending the benefits thereof to the arts of Designing, Engraving and Etching historical and other prints."</p>
<p align="center">RUTGER B. MILLER,<lb/><emph rend="italic">Clerk of the Northern District of New-York.</emph></p>
</div>
<div type="preface">
<pb n="preface" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=5"/>
<hd align="center" rend="bold">PREFACE.</hd>
<p>THE science of domestick economy, especially that division which treats of culinary or kitchen duties, has ever occupied the attention of those who have 'lived by eating,' from the days of hungry Esau, to the present moment. Every nation has its <emph rend="italic">peculiar dishes,</emph> and so also has every family its own <emph rend="italic">mode of cooking</emph> them. The <emph rend="italic">former</emph> is attributable to location--hot and cold latitudes yielding their own vegetables, and being the resort of those animals only whose constitutions are in unison with the climate. The <emph rend="italic">latter</emph> is owing to the degree of skill possessed by those who prepare the bounties of Providence for the palate.</p>
<p>A Work on Cookery should be adapted to the meridian in which it is intended to circulate. It is needless to burden a country Cookery Book with receipts for dishes depending entirely upon seaboard markets or which are suitable only to prepare food for the tables of city people, whose habits and customs differ so materially from those living in the country. Still further would the impropriety be carried were we to introduce into a work intended for the <emph rend="italic">American Publick</emph> such <emph rend="italic">English,</emph> <emph rend="italic">French</emph> and <emph rend="italic">Italian</emph> methods of rendering things indigestible, which are of themselves innocent, or of distorting and disguising the most loathsome objects to render them sufferable to already vitiated tastes.</p>
<p>These evils are attepted to be avoided. Good <emph rend="italic">republican dishes</emph> and garnishing, proper to fill an every day bill of fare, from the condition of the poorest to the richest individual, have been principally aimed at.</p>
<p>Pastry has had more than usual attention, lest, as is common in books of this kind, the good housewife be
<pb n="IV" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=6"/>
left without a sufficient guide, not only to keep up her store of the better things for her own family circle, but to be prepared for accidental or invited company.</p>
<p>To meet the objections that may be raised against this little production on the ground of its containing many directions for getting up our most common repasts, let it be remembered that not a few young women enter upon the duties of the wedded life without having been scarcely initiated into the mysteries of the eating department, and therefore to them the most trivial matters on this head become of importance.--The health of a family, in fact, greatly depends upon its cookery. The most wholesome viands may be converted into corroding poisons. Underdone or overdone food in many instances produces acute or morbid affections of the stomach and bowels, which lead to sickness and perhaps death.</p>
<p>The curing and preservation of meats, &#38;c. claim no small share of notice, for without proper instructions a well meaning wife, will, to use a homely adage, "throw more out at the window than the husband can bring in at the door." 
<illustration><description>A small illustration of a hand pointing to the right.</description></illustration>
Some over-genteel folks may smile at the supposed interest the wife, or female head of a family must take in all these concerns; but, suffer the remark, where this is not the state of things, a ruinous waste is the consequence.</p>
<p>It has not been thought irrelevant to remember the wants of the sick room, so far as to aid the prescriptions of the physician, or indeed to render a call upon him many a time unnecessary. Abstinence from our common fare, and partaking of innocent broths, <unclear>gruels,</unclear> &#38;c. often restores a disordered state of the stomach or checks inflammation as effectually as the doctor's potions. It is said that <emph rend="italic">total abstinence</emph> from food was the most usual remedy with Napoleon Buonaparte, for any indisposition of body; and few men enjoyed better health, or endured more fatigue of body and mind than did this great man throughout an eventful life of nearly fifty years. His last complaint was even said to be hereditary in the family.</p>
<p>This small digression will be overlooked in the preface to a system of Cookery which has for its main object the health of its friends. Temperance in the
<pb n="V" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=7"/>
quality and quantity of our diet contributes more to our health and comfort than we are aware of. It was the remark of an eminent physician upon the inquiries of a patient, "that it was of less importance <emph rend="italic">what kind</emph> of food we ate, than the <emph rend="italic">quantity</emph> and the <emph rend="italic">mode of its preparation,</emph> for the stomach."</p>
<p>It is not required that every particular be attended to in a receipt for cooking. Directions are given according to the taste of writers, or their knowledge of what is approved by others. Both these criteria may be used with freedom when brought into practice, for "of all sorts is the world made up." Let every one, therefore, consider the best prescription in Cookery, as nothing more than a basis to be followed to the letter, or deviated from, according to taste and circumstances.</p>
</div>
<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=8"/>
</div>
</front>
<body>
<chapter>
<pb n="7" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=9"/>
<hd align="center">RATIONAL COOKERY.</hd>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" id="no1">
<p>No 1. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A good pickle for Hams.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One ounce of <ingredient>salt petre,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> half pint of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to each <ingredient>ham;</ingredient> put your <ingredient>salt petre</ingredient> into the <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and rub your <ingredient>hams</ingredient> in it, then put your <ingredient>hams</ingredient> into a <implement>sweet cask,</implement> put your <ingredient>salt</ingredient> into <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover your <ingredient>hams,</ingredient> turn it on to them and turn them often for six weeks. If the <ingredient>hams</ingredient> are large, add more <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then smoke them ten days. <variation><purpose>Beef for drying,</purpose>

done in the same way,</variation> <variation>also <purpose><alt synonym1="pickled beef tongue">Beef tongues.</alt></purpose>

</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" id="no2">
<p>No 2. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To corn Beef.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To one hundred pounds of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> three ounces <ingredient>salt petre,</ingredient> five pints of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> a small quantity of <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> will improve it, but good without.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" id="no3">
<p>No 3. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To pickle one hundred pounds of Beef to keep a year.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put together three quarts <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> six ounces <ingredient>salt petre,</ingredient> one and a half pints of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> sufficient to cover your meat after laid into the barrel. Sprinkle the bottom of the barrel with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and also slightly sprinkle between the layers of meat as you pack, when done, pour in your <ingredient>pickle</ingredient> and lay on a stone or board to keep the whole down. <ingredient>Beef</ingredient> salted after
<pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=10"/>
this method during the fall or winter may be kept nice and tender through the summer by taking it up about the first of May, scald and skim the brine, add three quarts of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> when cold pour back upon the <ingredient>beef.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" id="no4">
<p>No 4. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To salt Pork.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Sprinkle <ingredient>salt</ingredient> in the bottom of the barrel, and take care to sprinkle the same plentifully between each layer afterwards. Let the layers be packed very snug by having the <ingredient>pork</ingredient> cut as large as can be handled conveniently, and laid in rind downwards, and the interstices snugly filled up with smaller pieces. <ingredient>Pork</ingredient> will only take a proper quantity of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> be there ever so much in the barrel. The surplus answers for another time.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Caution.</emph>--Although the same brine will answer for pickling beef, as that for hams, and pork generally, yet the two kinds of meat should never be in the brine at the same time. A small piece of beef placed in a barrel where there is pork, would spoil the latter quickly. A beef barrel, likewise, should never be used for pork, no matter how thoroughly scalded or cleansed.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 5. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To roast Beef.</purpose>

</p>
<p>The general rules are, to have a brisk hot fire, to be placed on a spit, to baste with <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and one quarter of an hour to every pound of <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> though tender <ingredient>beef</ingredient> will require more roasting; pricking with a fork will determine whether done or not: rare done is the healthiest, and the taste of this age.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 6. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Roast Mutton.</purpose>

</p>
<p>If a <ingredient>breast,</ingredient> let it be <process>cauled,</process> if a <ingredient>leg,</ingredient> stuffed or not, let it be done more gently than beef, and
<pb n="9" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=11"/>
done more; the <ingredient>chine,</ingredient> <ingredient>saddle</ingredient> or <ingredient>leg</ingredient> requires more fire and longer time than the breast, &#38;c. Serve with <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> or boiled <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>caper sauce,</ingredient> mashed <ingredient>turnip,</ingredient> or <ingredient>lettuce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 7. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Roast Veal.</purpose>

</p>
<p>As it is more tender than beef or mutton, and easily scorched, paper it, especially the fat parts, let there be a brisk fire, baste it well: a <ingredient>loin</ingredient> weighing fifteen pounds requires two hours and a half roasting; garnish with <ingredient>green parsley</ingredient> and sliced <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 8. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Roast Lamb.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Lay down to a clear good fire that will not want too much stirring or altering, baste with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> dust on <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and before you take it up add more <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> sprinkle on a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> shred fine; send to table with an elegant sallad, green peas, fresh beans or asparagus.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 9. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Alamode Beef.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a <ingredient>round of beef,</ingredient> and stuff it with half pound <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> the soft of half a loaf of <ingredient>wheat bread,</ingredient> boil four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very hard, chop them up; add <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> and one ounce <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> pounded, chop them all together with two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very fine, and add a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> season very high with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> cut holes in your <ingredient>beef</ingredient> to put your stuffing in, then stick whole <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> into the <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> then put it into a <implement>two pail pot,</implement> with sticks at the bottom; if you wish to have the <ingredient>beef</ingredient> round when done, put it into a cloth and bind it tight by winding several times with twine; put it into your pot with two or three quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and one <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> if
<pb n="10" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=12"/>
the round be large, it will take three or four hours to bake it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 10. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff a leg of Veal.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take one pound of <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> half pound of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> salted, one pound grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> chop all very fine, with a handful of <ingredient>green parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> it, add three ounces <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> if you like them, cut the <ingredient>leg</ingredient> round like a ham, and stab it full of holes, and fill in all the stuffing; then <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> the leg and dust on some <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> if baked in an oven, put it into a sauce pan with a little <ingredient>water;</ingredient> if potted, lay some skewers at the bottom of the pot, put in a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> and lay the <ingredient>leg</ingredient> on the skewers, with a gentle fire render it tender, frequently adding <ingredient>water,</ingredient> when done, take out the <ingredient>leg,</ingredient> put <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the pot and brown the <ingredient>leg,</ingredient> the gravy in a separate vessel must be thickened and buttered, and a spoonful of <ingredient>ketchup</ingredient> added, and <ingredient>wine</ingredient> if agreeable.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 11. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff a Pig, to roast or bake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil the inwards tender, mince fine, add half loaf <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>sage,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> mix the whole well together; stuff and sew up; if the <ingredient>pig</ingredient> be large let it be doing two and a half hours; baste with <ingredient>salt and water.</ingredient></p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Gravy for the same.</emph>--Half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> work in two spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one <measurement>gill</measurement> <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one <measurement>gill</measurement> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> if agreeable.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 12. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff a leg of Pork, to bake or roast.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Corn the <ingredient>leg</ingredient> forty-eight hours and stuff with <ingredient>sausage meat</ingredient> and bake it in an oven two hours and a half, or roast it.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="11" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=13"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 13. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff a Turkey.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Grate a <ingredient>wheat loaf,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> finely chopped, two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> if the pork be not sufficient, fill the bird and sew up. <variation>The same will answer for all <purpose><alt synonym1="to stuff wild fowl">wild fowls.</alt></purpose>

</variation></p>
<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to stuff waterfowl">Waterfowls</alt></purpose>

require <ingredient>onions.</ingredient></variation> <variation>The same ingredients stuff a <purpose><alt synonym1="to stuff a leg of veal, to stuff pork, to stuff a loin of veal">leg of veal, fresh pork, or a loin of veal.</alt></purpose>

</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 14. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff and roast a Turkey or Fowl.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound <ingredient>soft wheat bread,</ingredient> three ounces <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>sweet thyme,</ingredient> <ingredient>marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and some add a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> fill the bird therewith, and sew up; hang down to a steady solid fire, basting frequently with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and roast until a steam emits from the breast; put one third of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the gravy, dust <ingredient>flour</ingredient> over the bird, and baste with the gravy; served up with boiled onions and cranberry sauce, mangoes, pickles or celery.</p>
<p><variation>2. Others omit the sweet herbs, and add <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> done with <ingredient>potatoes.</ingredient></variation></p>
<p><variation>3. Boil and <alt synonym1="mash">marsh</alt> three pints <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> moisten them with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> add <ingredient>sweet herbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> fill and roast as above.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 15. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff and roast a Gosling.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil the <ingredient>inwards</ingredient> tender, chop them fine, put double quantity of <ingredient>grated bread,</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> if you like, and two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> into the stuffing, add <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and roast the bird.</p>
<p><variation>The above is a good <purpose>stuffing for every kind of waterfowl,</purpose>

which requires onion sauce.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<pb n="12" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=14"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 16. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stuff and roast four Chickens.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Six ounces <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> half loaf <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> six ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a handful of <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> shreded fine, <ingredient>summer savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> mix the whole well together, fill and sew up; roast one hour, baste with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and dust on <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Gravy for the same.</emph>--Half pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three spoonfuls <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine</ingredient> if you like.</p>
<p><variation>The same composition will answer for six <purpose><alt synonym1="stuffed and roasted pigeon">pigeons,</alt></purpose>

roasted in a pot. The <ingredient>pigeons</ingredient> must be kept from burning by laying skewers on the bottom of the pot, adding three pints <ingredient>water;</ingredient> cover close, let them do one hour and a quarter; when done pour on a quart of <ingredient>stewed oysters,</ingredient> well seasoned with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient><alt synonym1="pepper.">pepper</alt></ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 17. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To broil Chickens.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take those that are young and tender, break the breast bone, season high with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> broil half an hour on hot coals. Six ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three spoonfuls <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> will make a gravy.</p>
<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="broiled pigeon">Pigeons</alt></purpose>

may be broiled in the same way in twenty minutes.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 18. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To smother a fowl in Oysters.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Fill the bird with <ingredient>dry oysters</ingredient> and sew up and boil in <ingredient>water</ingredient> just sufficient to cover the bird, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and season to your taste; when done tender, put it into a deep dish and pour over it a pint of <ingredient>stewed oysters,</ingredient> well buttered and peppered, if a turkey, garnish with sprigs of <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> or <ingredient>leaves of celery;</ingredient> a <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> is best with a parsley sauce.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="13" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=15"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" id="no19">
<p>No 19. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To dress a Calf's Head-Turtle fashion.</purpose>

</p>
<p>The <ingredient>head</ingredient> and <ingredient>feet</ingredient> being well scalded and cleaned, open the <ingredient>head,</ingredient> take out the brains, wash, pick and cleanse, add <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> and put them in a cloth, boil the <ingredient>head,</ingredient> <ingredient>feet</ingredient> and <ingredient>heartslet</ingredient> about one and a half hour, sever out the bones, cut the skin and meat in slices, strain the liquor in which boiled and put by; make the pot very clean or it will burn on, make a layer of the slices, which dust with a composition made of <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> and one spoonful of <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> pulverised, (two spoonfuls <ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> and <ingredient>thyme</ingredient> are most approved,) a tea spoonful of <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> then dust with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> then a layer of slices, with slices of <ingredient>veal</ingredient> and seasoning till completed, cover with the liquor, stew gently three quarters of an hour. To make forcemeat balls--take one pound and a half of <ingredient>veal,</ingredient> one pound grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> four ounces raw <ingredient>salt pork;</ingredient> mince and season with above, and work with three <ingredient>whites of eggs</ingredient> into balls, one or one and a half inches diameter, roll in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and fry in very <ingredient>hot butter</ingredient> till brown; then chop the brains fine and stir into the whole mess in the pot, put thereto one third part of the fried balls and a pint of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> or less; when all is heated through, take off and serve in <implement>tureens,</implement> laying the residue of the balls and hard peeled <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> into a dish; garnish with slices of <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> put in <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> to your taste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 20. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Calf's head turtle fashion--another way.</purpose>

</p>
<p><ingredient>Head</ingredient> and <ingredient>entrails</ingredient> boiled the day before, the 
<pb n="14" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=16"/>
liquor of which is to be preserved; then slice the <ingredient>head,</ingredient> <ingredient>feet,</ingredient> &#38;c. in the bottom of the pot, and season with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>spices,</ingredient> pounded fine, and mixed together, then another layer of the meat,--then put in as much of the liquor they were boiled in as will cover the whole; let it be done over a small fire--the dish is to be garnished with forcemeat balls made of veal. See <ref target="no19">No 19.</ref></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 21. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To clarify Drippings.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put your <ingredient>drippings</ingredient> into a clean sauce-pan over a stove or slow fire; when it is just going to boil, skim it well, let it boil, and then let it stand till it is a little cooled; then pour it through a sieve into a pan.</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Obs.</emph>--Well-cleansed drippings, and the fat skimmings of the broth-pot, when fresh and sweet, will baste every thing as well as butter, except game and poultry, and should supply the place of butter for common fries, &#38;c.; for which they are equal to lard, especially if you repeat the clarifying twice over.</p>
<p>N. B. If you keep it in a cool place, you may preserve it a fortnight in summer, and longer in winter. When you have done frying, let the drippings stand a few minutes to settle, and then pour it through a sieve into a clean basin or stone pan, and it will do a second and third time as well as it did the first; only the fat you have fried fish in must not be used for any other purpose.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 22. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To clarify Suet to fry with.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Cut <ingredient>beef or mutton suet</ingredient> into thin slices, pick out all the veins and skins, &#38;c. put it into a thick and well tinned sauce pan, and set it
<pb n="15" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=17"/>
over a very slow stove, or in an oven, till it be melted; you must not hurry it; if not done very slowly it will acquire a burnt taste, which you cannot get rid of; then strain it through a <implement>hair sieve</implement> into a clean pan: when quite cold, tie a paper over it, and keep it for use. <variation><purpose><alt synonym1="to clarify hog's lard">Hog's lard</alt></purpose>

is prepared in the same way.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 23. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Veal Cutlets.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Let your <ingredient>cutlets</ingredient> be about half an inch thick; trim and flatten them with a knife or <implement>cleaver;</implement> you may fry them in fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or good <ingredient>drippings;</ingredient> when brown on one side, turn them and do the other; if the fire is very fierce, they must change sides oftener.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 24. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To broil Beef Steak.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Have your <ingredient>steak</ingredient> about an inch thick, if tender it is spoiled by being pounded, but if tough pound it well, lay it on your <implement>gridiron,</implement> broil it quick, have plenty of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in your dish, <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and serve it immediately whilst hot.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 25. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To broil shad.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take fresh <ingredient>shad,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> it well, broil half an hour; make a smoke with small chips while broiling, when done add <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine</ingredient> if agreeable.--<variation><purpose><alt synonym1="broiled salmon">SALMON</alt></purpose>

or any kind of fresh fish may be prepared in the same manner.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 26. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To stew Oysters.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To a quart of <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> put two ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> if too salt, add some <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> to your taste; stew them from fifteen to twenty minutes, by keeping them at a good scalding heat, without boiling; toast a slice of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> or use <ingredient>crackers,</ingredient> and lay them in a dish, turn
<pb n="16" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=18"/>
your <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> on, and they are ready to serve.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 27. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Oysters fried.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Simmer them in their own <ingredient>liquor</ingredient> for a couple of minutes, take them out and lay them on a cloth to drain, and then <ingredient>flour</ingredient> them, <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread crumb</ingredient> them, put them into <ingredient>boiling fat,</ingredient> and fry them a delicate brown.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 28. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Clarified Butter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a nice, clean stew pan, over a very clear, slow fire; watch it, and when it is melted, carefully skim off the buttermilk, &#38;c. which will swim on the top; let it stand a minute or two for the impurities to sink to the bottom; then pour the clear <ingredient>butter</ingredient> thro' a sieve into a clean basin, leaving the sediment at the bottom of the stew pan.</p>
<p>N. B. Butter thus purified will be as sweet as marrow, a very useful covering for potted meats &#38;c. and for frying fish.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 29. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Burnt Butter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put two ounces of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into a frying pan; when it becomes a dark brown colour, add to it a table spoonful and a half of good <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>
<p>N. B. This is used as sauce for boiled fish, or poached eggs.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 30. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Parsley and Butter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Wash some <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> very clean, and pick it carefully leaf by leaf; put a teaspoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> into half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water:</ingredient> boil the <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> about ten minutes; drain it on a sieve; mince it quite fine, and then bruise it to a pulp. Put it into a <implement>sauceboat,</implement> and mix with it, by degrees, about half a pint of good melted <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> do not put much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to it.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="17" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=19"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 31. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Egg Sauce.</purpose>

</p>
<p>This agreeable accompaniment to roasted poultry, or salted fish, is made by putting three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> into <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and boiling them for about twelve minutes, when they will be hard; put them into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> till you want them. This will make the yelks firmer, and prevent their surface turning black, and you can cut them much neater: use only two of the whites; cut the whites into small dice, the yelks into bits about a quarter of an inch square; put them into a sauce boat; pour to them half a pint of <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and stir them together.</p>
<p>The <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> for egg sauce need not be made very thick. <variation>If you are for superlative egg sauce, pound the <ingredient>yelks of a couple of eggs,</ingredient> and rub them with the <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> to thicken it.</variation></p>
<p>N. B. Some cooks garnish salt fish with <ingredient>hard boiled eggs</ingredient> cut in half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 32. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Lemon Sauce.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Pare a <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and cut it into slices twice as thick as a half dollar; divide these into dice, and put them into a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>melted butter.</ingredient></p>
<p>Some cooks mince a bit of the <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> (parted very thin,) very fine, and add it to the above.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 33. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Sage and Onion, or Goose stuffing Sauce.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Chop very fine an ounce of <ingredient>onion</ingredient> and half an ounce of <ingredient>green sage leaves;</ingredient> put them into a stewpan with four spoonfuls of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> simmer gently for ten minutes; then put in a tea spoonful of <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and one ounce of fine <ingredient>bread crumbs;</ingredient> mix well together; then
<pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=20"/>
pour to it a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> (or <ingredient>broth,</ingredient> or <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient>) stir well together, and simmer it a few minutes longer.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="soups">
<p>No 34. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Soup made of a Beef's Hock.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Let the <ingredient>bones</ingredient> be well broken, boil five hours in eight quarts <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one <measurement>gill</measurement> <ingredient>rice</ingredient> to be added, <ingredient>salt</ingredient> sufficiently; after three hours boiling, add twelve <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> pared, some small <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> and two <ingredient>onions;</ingredient> a little <ingredient>summer savory</ingredient> will make it grateful.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="soups">
<p>No 35. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Veal Soup.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a <ingredient>shoulder of veal,</ingredient> boil in five quarts <ingredient>water</ingredient> three hours, with two spoons <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> four <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> six <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> and <ingredient>summer-savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> sufficiently; half a pound <ingredient>butter</ingredient> worked into four spoons <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to be stirred in while hot.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="soups">
<p>No 36. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Soup of Lamb's head and pluck.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>head,</ingredient> <ingredient>heart</ingredient> and <ingredient>lights,</ingredient> with one pound <ingredient>pork</ingredient> into five quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> after boiling one hour, add the <ingredient>liver,</ingredient> continue boiling half an hour more, which will be sufficient; <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer-savory</ingredient> and <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> may be added in the midst of the boiling; take half pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> work it into one pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> also a small quantity <ingredient>summer-savory,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> work the whole well together--drop this in small balls into the soup while hot, it is then fit for the table.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 37. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">General rules to be observed in boiling.</purpose></p>
<p>The first necessary caution is that your pots and covers are always kept clean--be careful that your pot is constantly boiling, by this
<pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=21"/>
means you may determine with precision the time necessary to accomplish any dish you may wish to prepare in this way--put fresh meat into boiling water, and salt into cold--never crowd your pot with meat, but leave sufficient room for a plenty of water--allow a quarter of an hour to every pound of meat.</p>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 38. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To boil Ham.</purpose>

</p>
<p>This is an important article, and requires particular attention, in order to render it elegant and grateful. It should be boiled in a large quantity of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and that for a long time, one quarter of an hour for each pound; the rind to be taken off when warm. It is most palatable when cold, and should be sent to the table with eggs, horse radish or mustard. This affords a sweet repast at any time of day.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 39. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To boil a Turkey, fowl or Goose.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Poultry boiled by themselves are generally esteemed best, and require a large quantity of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> scum often and they will be of a good colour. A large <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> with forced meat in his craw will require two hours; one without, an hour and a half; <variation>a large <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> one hour and a quarter;</variation> <variation>a full grown <ingredient>goose</ingredient> two hours, if young, one hour and a half</variation>--and other <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> in proportion; serve up with <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>beets,</ingredient> <alt synonym1="mashed">marshed</alt> <ingredient>turnips,</ingredient> <ingredient>stewed oysters</ingredient> with <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
</section>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 40. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To dress Bass, and many other kinds of fish.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Season high with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> one slice <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> one <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> <ingredient>summer-savory</ingredient> and <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> minced fine and well mixed, one <measurement>gill</measurement> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> stuff the <ingredient>fish</ingredient>--bake in the oven one
<pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=22"/>
hour; thin slices of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> laid on the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> as it goes into the oven; when done pour over <ingredient>dissolved butter;</ingredient> serve up with <ingredient>stewed oysters,</ingredient> <ingredient>cranberries,</ingredient> boiled <ingredient>onions</ingredient> or <ingredient>potatoes.</ingredient> The same method may be observed with fresh <ingredient>Shad,</ingredient> <ingredient>Codfish,</ingredient> <ingredient>Blackfish</ingredient> and <ingredient>Salmon.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 41. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To dress a Sturgeon.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Clean your <ingredient>sturgeon</ingredient> well, parboil it in a large quantity of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till it is quite tender, then change the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and boil it till sufficiently done, then hash it as you would beef, adding the usual articles for seasoning. <variation>Some prefer it done in the form of veal cutlet, which is by taking slices of <ingredient>sturgeon,</ingredient> dipping them in the <ingredient>yelks of eggs</ingredient> well beat, then rolled in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and fried in <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 42. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For dressing Codfish.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put the <ingredient>fish</ingredient> first into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and wash it, then hang it over the fire and soak it six hours in <ingredient>scalding water,</ingredient> then shift it into clean <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> and let it scald for one hour, it will be much better than to boil.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="soups">
<p>No 43. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Chowder.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a <ingredient>bass</ingredient> weighing four pounds, boil half an hour; take six slices raw <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> fry them till the lard is nearly extracted, one doz. <ingredient>crackers</ingredient> soaked in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> five minutes; put the <ingredient>bass</ingredient> into the <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> also the pieces of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> and and <ingredient>crackers,</ingredient> add two <ingredient>onions</ingredient> chopped fine, cover close and fry for twenty minutes; serve with <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> <ingredient>pickles,</ingredient> <ingredient>apple sauce</ingredient> or <ingredient>mangoes;</ingredient> garnish with <ingredient>green parsley.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 44. <hd rend="italic" align="center">How to keep green peas till winter.</hd></p>
<p>Take young peas, shell and put them in a <implement>cullender</implement> to drain, then lay a cloth four or five
<pb n="21" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=23"/>
times double on a table, and spread them on, dry them very well, and have your bottles ready, fill them, cover over with mutton suet fat when it is a little soft; fill the necks almost to the top, cork up, tie a bladder and leather over them and set away in a dry cool place.</p>
</section>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 45. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Beef steak Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take slices of <ingredient>beef steak</ingredient> half an inch thick, lay them three deep in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno8">No. 8,</ref> adding <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and slices raw <ingredient>onion</ingredient> between each layer, dusting on <ingredient>flour</ingredient> at the same time, together with a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--add half pint <ingredient>water;</ingredient> bake one and a half hour.--This must be put in an earthen vessel and covered with a crust, as for a chicken pie.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 46. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A lamb Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a <ingredient>shoulder</ingredient> and cut it into small pieces, parboil it till tender, then place it in <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno8">No. 8,</ref> in a deep dish; add <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to each layer of <ingredient>lamb,</ingredient> till your dish be full; fill with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and cover over with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> put in a hot oven, bake one hour and a half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 47. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A stew Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a <ingredient>shoulder of veal,</ingredient> cut it up, and boil an hour, then add <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> a sufficient quantity, <ingredient>butter</ingredient> half a pound, add slices raw <ingredient>salt pork,</ingredient> cover the meat with <ingredient>biscuit dough;</ingredient> cover close and stew half an hour in three quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> only.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 48. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A sea Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound and a half <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> wet with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> line the pot therewith, lay in one dozen split <ingredient>pigeons,</ingredient> with slices of <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and 
<pb n="22" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=24"/>
dust on <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> doing thus till the pot is full, or your ingredients expended, add three pints <ingredient>water,</ingredient> cover tight with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and stew moderately two hours and a half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 49. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Chicken Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take two <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> joint and put them in a pot with four ounces of <ingredient>pork</ingredient> cut in slices, add <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> boil until tender, turn them out and set away to cool; make a rich <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> with which line the dish half an inch thick, then a layer of <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> with pieces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and sprinkle on <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> put on your gravy from the <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> and continue to do so until filled up; roll out a thick crust, bake an hour in a hot oven; serve it up with <ingredient>melted butter</ingredient> and any <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> you like.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 50. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Save-all Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In every family there are pieces of fresh <ingredient>meat</ingredient> left of roasted meats: these take from the bones, boil and season, put in <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> make a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> and place in a deep dish, put your meat in, cover it and bake one hour. All meats can be used in this way and with good <ingredient>paste</ingredient> and <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> make a clever dinner.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="breadsweets">
<p>No 51. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Mince Meat</purpose>

</p>
<p>Never hash your meat, it is a poor way of cooking, and is hard of digestion--but take the <ingredient>corned beef</ingredient> that you wish to make use of in this way, put it into a bowl, chop FINE with a <implement>chopping knife,</implement> then add your <ingredient>potatoe</ingredient> and chop fine with it. Add <ingredient>turnip,</ingredient> <ingredient>beet,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cabbage</ingredient> if you like, and put all into a <implement>spider</implement> with the addition of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>drippings;</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> warm moderately.</p>
<pb n="23" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=25"/>
<p><variation><emph rend="italic">Another way.</emph>--Cold fresh <ingredient>meat</ingredient> boiled or roasted, chop it fine, make a batter with a couple of <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> season your meat, do it up in balls, dip them in your batter, make ready hot <ingredient>drippings,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> fry them a fine brown.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 52. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A good way to cook Codfish.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Soak your <ingredient>codfish</ingredient> an hour and a half and let it get scalding hot, but not to boil, it will harden the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> boil your <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> and make a gravy of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> serve it up immediately.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 53. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Another way to cook Codfish</purpose>

</p>
<p>After soaked as above directed, and cold, chop your <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> to which add three times the quantity of <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> chopped fine with the <ingredient>fish,</ingredient> put in <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to season it, do it up in balls, roll them in dry <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> make ready <ingredient>hot lard</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in a fryingpan, and fry them until a nice brown, turn them that they be brown on every side.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 54. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A Tongue Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound <ingredient>neat's tongue,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> or half of each, half ounce <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient>--bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno1">No. 1,</ref> in proportion to size.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame">
<p>No 55. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Minced pie of Beef.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four pounds boiled <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> chopped fine, salted; six pounds of raw <ingredient>apples</ingredient> chopped, also, one pound <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> one quart <ingredient>wine</ingredient> or rich sweet <ingredient>cider,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> of each one ounce, two pounds <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> two pounds <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3,</ref> three fourths of an hour.</p>
</recipe>
<p>All meat pies require a hotter and brisker oven than fruit pies; in good cookeries all raisins
<pb n="24" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=26"/>
should be stoned. As people differ in their tastes, they may alter to their wishes.--And as it is difficult to ascertain with precision the small articles of spicery, every one may relish as they like and suit their taste.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 56.<purpose rend="italic" align="center"> <ingredient>Apple</ingredient> Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Stew and strain the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> to every three pints grate the <ingredient>peel of a fresh lemon,</ingredient> add <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, and bake in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3.</ref></p>
<p><variation>Every species of <purpose><alt synonym1="fruit pie">fruit,</alt></purpose>

such as <ingredient>pears,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>blackberries,</ingredient> &#38;c. may be only sweetened, without spice, and bake in <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3.</ref></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 57. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Dried Apple Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take two quarts <ingredient>dried apples,</ingredient> put them into an earthern pot that contains one gallon, fill it with <ingredient>water</ingredient> and set it in a hot oven, adding one handful of <ingredient>cranberries;</ingredient> after baking one hour fill up the pot again with <ingredient>water;</ingredient> when done and the <ingredient>apple</ingredient> cold, strain it and add thereto the <ingredient>juice of three or four limes,</ingredient> <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> to your tase, lay in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3.</ref></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 58. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A buttered Apple Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Pare, quarter and core <ingredient>tart apples,</ingredient> lay in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3,</ref> cover with the same; bake half an hour; when drawn, gently raise the top crust, add <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> and a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>rose water.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 59. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Currant Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take green, full grown <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> and one third their quantity of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> to every quart of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> add half pint <ingredient>water,</ingredient> pro-<gap extent="one word"/> as above.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="25" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=27"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 60. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Potatoe Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Scald one quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> grate in four large <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> while the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is hot, when cold add four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, four ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and sweeten to your taste, lay in <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno7">No. 7</ref> bake half an hour.</p>
</recipe>
<p>N. B. A bowl containing two quarts, filled with water, and set into the oven prevents any article from being scorched, such as cakes, pies and the like.</p>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 61. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Custards.</purpose>

</p>
<p>1. One quart <ingredient>milk</ingredient> scalded, six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> six ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two spoonfuls <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient>--bake.</p>
<p><variation>2. Sweeten a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> add <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> and six <ingredient>eggs;</ingredient> bake in <implement>tea cups</implement> or dishes, or boil in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> taking care that it don't boil into the cups.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 62. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Boiled Custards.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> two spoons <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>orange flower water,</ingredient> some <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> boil, then stir in <ingredient>sweetening,</ingredient> when cold add four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and lade off into china cups, bake, and serve up.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 63. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Rice Custard.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil two spoonfuls of <ingredient>ground rice,</ingredient> with a quarter of a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated in one quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> when cold add five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and four ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> flavour with <ingredient>orange or rose water.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 64. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Common baked Custard.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beat and put to one quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> sweetened to your taste, half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient>--bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 65. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A sick bed Custard.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Scald a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweeten and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> a 
<pb n="26" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=28"/>
little, whip three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and stir in, bake on coals in a pewter vessel.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 66. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Tarts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Stew and strain the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> add <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, lay in <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno3">No. 3,</ref> squeeze thereon <ingredient>orange juice</ingredient>--bake gently.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 67. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Tarts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Pare thin two <ingredient>oranges,</ingredient> boil the peel tender, and shred it fine, pare and core twenty <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> put them in a stewpan with as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible; when half done add half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> the <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> and <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> boil till pretty thick; when cold put in a shallow dish, or pans lined with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> turn out, to be eaten cold.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 68. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Raspberry Tarts with Cream.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Roll out some thin <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient> and lay it in a pan of what size you choose; put in <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> strew over them fine <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> cover with a thin lid, then bake, cut it open and have ready the following mixture: warm half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> the <ingredient>yelks of two or three eggs</ingredient> well beaten, and a little <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and when this is added to the tarts return the whole to the oven for five or six minutes.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 69. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Currant and Raspberry Tarts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>For a tart, line the dish, put in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> lay bars across and bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 70. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="cranberry tarts">Cranberries.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Stewed, strained and sweetened, put into <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno9">No. 9,</ref> add <ingredient>spices</ingredient> till grateful, and baked gently.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 71. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Gooseberry Tarts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Lay clean <ingredient>berries</ingredient> and sift over them <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient>
<pb n="27" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=29"/>
then berries, and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> till a deep dish be filled, intermingling a handful of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> and one <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> cover with <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno9">No. 9,</ref> and bake somewhat more than other tarts.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 72. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="grape tarts">Grapes,</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Must be cut in two and stoned and done like a gooseberry.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 73. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Rice Pudding with Fruit.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Swell the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> over the fire, mix <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> of any kind, <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> <ingredient>black currants,</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> boil it well; serve it with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 74. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Baked Rice Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Swell the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> as above, add more <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> bake in a deep dish.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 75. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A cheap Rice Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Half a pint of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> six ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two quarts <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> put cold into a hot oven, bake two hours and a half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 76. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A tasty Indian Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pints scalded <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> seven spoonfuls <ingredient>fine indian meal,</ingredient> stir well together while hot, let it stand till cooled: and four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> bake four hours.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 77. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="indian pudding">Another.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pints scalded <ingredient>milk</ingredient> to one pint <ingredient>meal salted;</ingredient> cool, add two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> four ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> or <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice</ingredient> sufficient; it will <alt synonym1="require">requir</alt> two hours and a half baking.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 78. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="indian pudding">Another.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p><ingredient>Salt</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>meal,</ingredient> wet with one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> sweeten and put them into a strong cloth, brass or <implement>bell metal vessel,</implement> stone or earthen pot, secure from wet and boil twelve hours.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=30"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 79. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A Sunderland Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Whip six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half the <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> take half a <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> four spoonfuls <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>oil</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter</ingredient> the pans, cups or bowls; bake in a quick oven one hour.--Eat with sweet sauce.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 80. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A Whitpot Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Cut half a loaf of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> in slices, pour thereon two quarts of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> put into a dish, cover with <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno1">No 1,</ref> bake slow one hour.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 81. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Bread Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> scald <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and turn on when cut in pieces, four ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> the same of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> bake without paste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 82. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A Flour Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> scalded, add five spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> while hot: when cool add seven <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten, six ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> to your taste, bake one hour, serve up with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 83. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A boiled flour Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> four to six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> nine spoonfuls of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put into a strong cloth and boiled one hour and a half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 84. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="apple pudding dumpling">An apple pudding Dumplin.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Put into <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> quartered <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> lay in a cloth boil one hour, serve with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 85. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="pear dumpling" synonym2="plum dumpling">Pears, plums, &#38;c.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Are done in the same way.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 86.<purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cottage potatoe Pudding or Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil and pare and mash two pounds of <ingredient>potatoes,</ingredient> beat them fine with a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> bake three quarters
<pb n="29" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=31"/>
of an hour. <variation>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants</ingredient> may be added, or leave out the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and add a quarter of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> it will make a good cake.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 87. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A pint of stewed sifted <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> mix the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> and <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> before the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is put in; add <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, bake it in a <ingredient>rich crust.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 88. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Carrot Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A coffee cup full of boiled and strained <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> of each two ounces, <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> to your taste, bake in a deep dish without paste, one hour.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 89. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A crookneck or winter squash Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Core, boil and skin a good <ingredient>squash,</ingredient> and bruise it well; take six large <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> pared, cored and stewed tender, mix together; add six or seven spoonfuls of <ingredient>dry bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>biscuit,</ingredient> rendered fine as meal, one pint <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> two spoons <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> five or six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten and strained, <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to your taste, one spoonful <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat all smartly together, bake one hour.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 90. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="pumpkin pudding">Pumpion Pudding.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>No 1. One quart stewed and strained, three pints <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> six beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> laid into <ingredient>paste</ingredient> <ref target="pasteno7">No 7,</ref> or <ref target="pasteno3">3,</ref> cross and checker it, and bake in dishes three quarters of an hour.</p>
<p><variation>No 2. One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>pumpion,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> in a crust, bake one hour.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=32"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 91. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Orange Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Grate the <ingredient>rind of an orange,</ingredient> put to it six ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> scrape raw <ingredient>apple</ingredient> and mix with it; put a <ingredient>paste</ingredient> into the dish and bars of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> over the mixture.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 92. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Lemon Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> grated with the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> mix with four ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one cup of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> baked in a <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 93. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Marlborough Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take twelve spoons of <ingredient>stewed apples,</ingredient> twelve of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> twelve of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> twelve of <ingredient>melted butter,</ingredient> and twelve of beaten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste; lay in <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> No. 3, in a deep dish; bake one hour and a quarter.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 94. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A plum Pudding boiled.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pints <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>plums,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> mix the whole together; put it into a strong cloth floured, boil three hours, serve with <ingredient>sweet sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 95. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Sago Pudding, for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil a pint and a half of <ingredient>new milk</ingredient> with four spoonfuls of <ingredient>sago</ingredient> washed and picked, <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> mix four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> put <ingredient>paste</ingredient> around the dish, and bake slowly.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 96. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Bread and butter Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Slice <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and spread with <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> lay in a dish a layer of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> with <ingredient>currants</ingredient> between each layer, <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> pour on an <ingredient>unboiled custard.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 97. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Arrow root Pudding, for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three table spoonfuls of <ingredient>arrow root</ingredient> mixed with a little <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> then stir it into a quart
<pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=33"/>
of <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> stir it until cold, add four <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> beaten, <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> bake half an hour.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 98. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Quince Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil four <ingredient>quinces</ingredient> soft and sift them, add half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> any kind which you like, bake it in <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 99. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Eve's Pudding</purpose>

</p>
<p>Grate twelve ounces of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> mix with it the same quantity of <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> the same of <ingredient>apples</ingredient> made fine, the same of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> mix with these four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> boil three hours; serve with <ingredient>pudding sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 100. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Batter Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Six ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beat up well with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> thick as cream either to boil or bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 101. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Nottingham Pudding.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Pare six good <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> take out the cores with the point of a small knife, leave your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> otherwise whole, fill up where you take out the core with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> place them in a dish and pour over them <ingredient>batter</ingredient> prepared as batter pudding, bake one hour.</p>
</recipe>
<p><emph rend="italic">General Rule.</emph>--Observe, always to rub your butter and sugar into every thing that is made hard, and mix it quickly, for if slowly done the cake is apt to be heavy.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 102. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Good Rye and Indian, or Wheat and Indian Bread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>From two thirds to three fourths <ingredient>Indian,</ingredient> ground rather coarse, (do <emph rend="italic">not</emph> scald your <ingredient>Indian,</ingredient>) one fourth to one third <ingredient>rye</ingredient> or <ingredient>wheat,</ingredient> if <ingredient>rye,</ingredient> do not have it bolted, but merely ground to be sifted; good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> made rather soft, more like batter than dough, put it into pans
<pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=34"/>
to rise; <emph rend="italic">baked one and a half hours in a hot oven.</emph></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" id="no103">
<p>No 103. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make common Wheat Bread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To eight quarts of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> put a pint of <ingredient>distiller's yeast,</ingredient> wet up the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> with <ingredient>warmed milk</ingredient> and set it by to rise or ferment.</p>
<p><variation>If you use <ingredient>brewer's yeast,</ingredient> put half a teacupful into a pint of <ingredient>warmed milk,</ingredient> thicken it up a litle with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and let it ferment ten or twelve hours, when it is ready to go into your bread; wet up the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as before directed with <ingredient>warmed milk</ingredient> and set the dough by to rise or ferment.</variation> Bake one and a quarter hours; all over that time does injury.</p>
<p>N. B. Should dough intended for bread ferment so much as to become sour, put two teaspoonfuls of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> into a tea cup of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and work it thoroughly in, just before going into the oven.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 104. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Nice Cookies that will keep good three months.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Nine cups <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three and a half of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> five of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> large coffee cup of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with a heaping teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> dissolved in it; rub your <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> great spoonful of <ingredient>caraway.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<hd align="center">SIX RECEIPTS FOR MAKING</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 105. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Puff paste for Tarts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In the following a whole or part of the eggs may be dispensed with.</p>
<p id="pasteno1">No 1. Rub one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> whip two <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and add with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> make into paste, roll in six or seven times one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> flouring it each roll. This is good for any small thing.</p>
<pb n="33" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=35"/>
<p id="pasteno2"><variation>No 2. Rub six pounds of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into fourteen pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>whites of eggs,</ingredient> add <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> make a stiff paste.</variation></p>
<p id="pasteno3"><variation>No 3. To any quantity of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> rub in three fourths of its weight of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>whites of eggs;</ingredient> if a large quantity of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> rub in one third or half of the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and roll in the rest.</variation></p>
<p id="pasteno4"><variation>No 4. Into two quarts <ingredient>flour, salted,</ingredient> and wet stiff with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> roll in, in nine or ten times, one and a half pounds <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></variation></p>
<p id="pasteno5"><variation>No 5. One pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three fourths of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> beat well.</variation></p>
<p id="pasteno6"><variation>No 6. To one pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> rub in one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> wet with three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and rolled in half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center">A paste for Sweet Meats.</purpose>

</p>
<p id="pasteno7">No 7. Rub one third of one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and one pound of <ingredient>lard</ingredient> into two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> wet with four <ingredient>whites,</ingredient> well beaten; <ingredient>water</ingredient> as much as necessary; to make a paste, roll in the residue of <ingredient>shortening</ingredient> in ten or twelve rollings--bake quick.</p>
<p id="pasteno8"><variation>No 8. Rub in one and a half pounds of <ingredient>suet</ingredient> to six pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a spoonful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> wet with <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> roll in, in six or eight times, two and a half pounds of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--good for a chicken or meat pie.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="accompaniments">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center">Royal Paste.</purpose>

</p>
<p id="pasteno9">No 9. Rub half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>whites</ingredient> beat to a foam, two ounces fine <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> roll often, rubbing one third, and rolling two thirds of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is best; excellent for tarts.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 106. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Johnny cake, or hoe cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Scald one pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and put three pints of <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> and a half a pint of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> bake before the fire. <variation>Or scald with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> two thirds
<pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=36"/>
of the <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> or wet two thirds with <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> add <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> and <ingredient>shortening,</ingredient> work up with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> pretty stiff, and bake as above.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 107. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Indian Slapjack.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pint <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> four spoons of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> little <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> beat together, baked on griddles, or fry in a dry pan or baked in a pan which has been rubbed with <ingredient>suet,</ingredient> <ingredient>lard</ingredient> or <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 108. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Loaf Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> more <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> put in than for bread, and made rather soft with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> let it stand over night, when risen beat twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add two pounds and a quarter of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> one of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and beat it all together; let it rise a second time, bake about an hour and a quarter.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 109. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make puff paste rich.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Half a pound of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> rubbed into a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> wet with as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible, and done quick, add half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the course of rolling out four diferent times, sprinkling <ingredient>flour</ingredient> between each time; roll it up and lay by to make up. Three quarters of a pound, half each of <ingredient>lard</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> for more common paste and for meat pies, and half a pound in all for invalids and those that wish to be very economical.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 110. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make fruit Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To one pound and four ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> put one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=37"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 111. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Soft Wafers.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One tea cup of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one half to remain until risen.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 112. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Hard Wafers.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 113. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cup Cake</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> small tea spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> spoonful of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 114. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Washington Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> one <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> tea cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 115. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Jumbles.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two cups of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will make it thin, and any good <ingredient>spice</ingredient> you like.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="wedding">
<p>No 116. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Wedding Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Eighteen pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> twelve of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> twelve of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> six of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> six of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> three of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> twelve dozen <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> half pound of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and as much other <ingredient>spice</ingredient> as you like.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 117. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Rusk.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One tea cup of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> seven pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 118. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Crullers, sometimes called Miracles or Wonders.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Six ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> twelve ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound twelve ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> fry in <ingredient>hot lard.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=38"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 119. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Fruit Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> one tea cup of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 120. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Doughnuts.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound and a quarter of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three quarters of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one tea cup of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> let it rise, then fry in <ingredient>hot lard.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 121. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Dough Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two pounds <ingredient>light dough,</ingredient> one pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one tea spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 122. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Good common Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two cups of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> as you like.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 123. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Biscuit.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> made sufficiently hard to rise with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 124. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> five <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 125. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Muffins.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> small cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> some <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> to be made stiffer than pound cake, bake it on a griddle in drops.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 126. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Soft Gingerbread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> three teacups of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> one
<pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=39"/>
teacup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one large spoonful of <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 127. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Sugar Gingerbread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one tea cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two tea spoons of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> one <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 128. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Sugar Gingerbread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> made hard and rolled out.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 129.<purpose rend="italic" align="center">Hard Gingerbread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> one tea cup of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> three teaspoons of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make a stiff dough, <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to your taste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 130. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Orange Gingerbread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two pounds and a quarter <ingredient>fine flour,</ingredient> a pound and 3 quarters <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> 12 ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> 3 ounces undried <ingredient>orange peel</ingredient> chopped fine, 1 ounce each of <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> melt twelve ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> mix the whole together, lay it by for twelve hours, roll it out with as little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as possible, cut it in pieces three inches wide, mark them in the form of checkers with the back of a knife, rub them over with the <ingredient>yelk of an egg,</ingredient> beat with a tea cup of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> when done wash them again with the egg.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 131.<purpose rend="italic" align="center">Sponge Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> the weight of them in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> the whites of five in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> beat the yelk and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together, the whites of the other five <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> separately,
<pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=40"/>
do not add the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> untill ready to bake, add <ingredient>essence of lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 132. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Composition Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound and twelve ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound and twelve ounces of <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> put into a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one tea spoon of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> two <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 133. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Whigs, or Wigs.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> tea cup of <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 134. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Queen's Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three fourths of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> whites beaten separately and put in just as the cake goes into the oven; butter little tins, fill half full, sift on <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 135. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Another Queen's Cake</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> beat separately whites and yelks, <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<p>N. B. Let it be observed and understood that all cake is better to beat yelks and whites of eggs separately, and adding the whites just before going into the oven; the butter and sugar to be worked together to a cream, before any addition is made to them.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 136. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Shrewsbury Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> three fourths of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 137. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Federal Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pounds and a quarter of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one
<pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=41"/>
pound and three quarters of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> quarter of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two cups of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 138. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Jumbles.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>caraway seed,</ingredient> roll them in <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 139. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Pound Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> ten ounces of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 140. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Minute Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Five tea cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> tea spoon of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" occasion="Thanksgiving">
<p>No 141. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Thanksgiving Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Six pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pint of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> made over night with <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> that it may rise by morning, add three pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two and a half pounds of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> three pounds of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> two of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> bake one hour and a half.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 142. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Pearlash Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound and a quarter of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> ten ounces <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> six ounces <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one teaspoonful of <ingredient>pearlash.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 143. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cream Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 144. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Mineral Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half cup of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a little
<pb n="40" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=42"/>
<ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 145. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="pumpkin pie">Pumpion Pie</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>One quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> one pint of <ingredient>strained pumpion,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> add <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and sweeten to your taste. <variation>N. B. We have seen excellent pumpion pie made by nicely paring the pumpion before stewing, and straining it through a <implement>colender</implement> in lieu of a sieve.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 146. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">An Excellent Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one tea cup of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> with <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> set it to rise, then add two pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one quarter of a pound of <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>stoned raisins</ingredient> chopped fine, one <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> and a <ingredient>peel of lemon</ingredient> chopped fine, a glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> yelks and whites beaten separately and thoroughly, <ingredient>orange</ingredient> and <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> a quick bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 147. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Tunbridge Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Rub six ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> then mix six ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> beat two <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and make with the above into a paste, roll it very thin, and cut with the top of a <implement>tumbler,</implement> prick them and cover with <ingredient>caraway,</ingredient> and sift on <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 148. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Route drop Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Mix two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> then wet into a stiff paste with two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> drop them on tins floured; a short time bakes them.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 149. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Clove Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Three pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of
<pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=43"/>
<ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> two spoonfuls <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> mixed with <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 150. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Common pancakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Make a light batter of <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk;</ingredient> fry in a small pan in <ingredient>hot dripping</ingredient> or <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> may be added; <variation>or when eggs are scarce make the batter with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>pearlash.</ingredient></variation></p>
<p>These are most frequently eaten without any trimmings; but sugar grated on, or sweet, or lemon and sugar sauce may be served with them.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 151. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Rice Pancakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil half a pound of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> to a jelly in a small quantity of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> when cold mix it with a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> stir in eight ounces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> just warmed, and add as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will make the batter thick enough; fry in as little <ingredient>lard</ingredient> or <ingredient>dripping</ingredient> as possible.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 152. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Fritters.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Make them of any of the batters directed for pancakes by dropping a small quantity into the pan, or to make the plainer sort put pared <ingredient>apples</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> sliced, or <ingredient>currants</ingredient> into the <ingredient>batter,</ingredient> any <ingredient>sweetmeats</ingredient> or ripe <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> may be made into fritters.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" ethnicgroup="spanish">
<p>No 153. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Spanish Fritters.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Cut <ingredient>biscuits</ingredient> into lengths as thick as your finger, in what shape you please, soak in some <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> pounded <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and one <ingredient>egg;</ingredient> when well soaked, fry of a brown and served with butter wine and sugar sauce.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 154. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Baked Custard Pie.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil one pint of <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and a half pint of
<pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=44"/>
<ingredient>milk</ingredient> with <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> a little of each; when cold mix three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> sweeten, and fill your cups or <ingredient>paste</ingredient> nearly full.</p>
<p>N. B. Custard pies require a hot oven, but custards in cups are best when put in after the bread is drawn, and receive a slow baking.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 155. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Floating Islands.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Scald any sharp <ingredient>apples</ingredient> before they are ripe, pulp them through a sieve, beat the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a spoonful of <ingredient>orange flower water,</ingredient> mix it by degrees with the pulp and beat all together, serve it on a <ingredient>raspberry cream,</ingredient> or you may colour the froth with <ingredient>beet root,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberry,</ingredient> or <ingredient>currant jelly,</ingredient> and set it on a <ingredient>white cream,</ingredient> having given it the flavour of <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> or put the froth on a custard.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 156. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Ice Cream.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Mix the <ingredient>juice of the fruits</ingredient> with as much <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> as will be wanted before you add <ingredient>cream</ingredient> which should be of a middling richness.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="accompaniments">
<p>No 157. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Icing for Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>For a large one, beat and sift half a pound of <ingredient>fine sugar</ingredient> with four spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>whites of two eggs</ingredient> beaten and strained, whisk it well, and when the cake is almost cold, dip a feather in the icing and cover the cake well; set it in the oven to harden, but do not let it stay long enough to get <alt synonym1="discolored;">discolourd;</alt> set the cake in a dry place.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="accompaniments">
<p>No 158. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Jelly.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Prepare twenty <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> boil them in a pint and a half of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till quite tender, then strain the liquor through a <implement>colander;</implement> to every pint
<pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=45"/>
put a pound of <ingredient>fine sugar,</ingredient> add grated <ingredient>orange</ingredient> or <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> then boil to a jelly.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 159. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Raspberry Jam.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Rub fresh gathered <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> through a sieve, to every pint of the pulp put one pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> broken small, put it into a <implement>preserving pan</implement> over a brisk fire, when it begins to boil skim it well, stir it twenty minutes, put it into small pots, cut white paper to the size of the top of the pot dip them in brandy, put them over the jam when cold, with double paper tied over the pot.</p>
<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="Strawberry">Strawpberry</alt> jam</purpose>

is made the same way.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 160. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Quince Sweetmeats.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to one <alt synonym1="of">af</alt> <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and clarify it with an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> then put in your <ingredient>quinces</ingredient> and boil till tender, then take out your <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> put them into pots, boil the sirup to a jelly, on a slow fire, try it occasionally with a spoon.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 161. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Heart Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of fine <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound and a quarter <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> and half a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated, to be baked in small tins in the shape of hearts or otherwise.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 162. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Queen's Drops.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one pound of sifted <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> quater of a pouud of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> any agreeable <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> put drops on a tin about as large as a dollar, sift on <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> to be baked quickly.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="44" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=46"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 163. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Danbury Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Set a <ingredient>sponge</ingredient> with two spoonfuls of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> and a pound of <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> when it is worked a little, mix with it half a pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and other <ingredient>spices</ingredient> pounded fine, prepare <ingredient>paste</ingredient> by rolling it out in small rounds, lay on some of this mixture, cover it with <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> pinch it together and bake it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 164. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Plain Buns.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a <measurement>gill</measurement> of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with enough of the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to make it the thickness of cream, let it stand two hours to rise, then melt one pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> stir it into the other ingredients to make it a soft paste, let it lie an hour, mould it into buns about as large as an egg, lay them in rows three inches apart on tins, set them to rise until their size is doubled, then bake them a good colour. <variation>By adding <ingredient>seed</ingredient> they are called <purpose>seed buns,</purpose>

</variation> <variation>or <ingredient>plums,</ingredient> <purpose>plum buns.</purpose>

</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 165. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Derby, or Short Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Rub one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into two pounds of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> put one pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> mix all together with half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> one <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> two tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> roll it out thin, cut it in round cakes and bake them.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 166, <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Jackson Jumbles.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One cup of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> three of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> tea spoonful of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> five cups of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> to be dropped on a tin with a spoon to <alt synonym1="bake.">bake,</alt></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 167. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cream Cake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound
<pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=47"/>
of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 168. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Jumbles.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> to be dropped on tins to bake.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 169. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Crackers.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a piece of <ingredient>bread dough</ingredient> as large as a pint bowl; after it has risen, take one tea cup of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and work in with <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as hard as you can make it, roll and cut it out and bake it in an oven not very hot; then take them out, cool, then put them in a pan and set back into the oven to dry over night.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 170. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Beets, Carrots &#38;c.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil good brittle <ingredient>beets</ingredient> or <ingredient>carrots,</ingredient> cut and put them in good <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and then partly dry them, make a sirup, pound for pound, and preserve them as other sweetmeats.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 171. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Jelly.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Pare and boil your <ingredient>apples</ingredient> to a pulp, strain, to a pint put a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 172. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Buckwheat Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Stir up your <ingredient><alt synonym1="buckwheat">buckweat</alt></ingredient> about as thick as cream, put good <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> to it, let it rise, then add a little <ingredient>wheat flour,</ingredient> dissolve a little <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and stir it up, add <ingredient>salt</ingredient> then it is ready to fry.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 173. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Rice Snow Balls.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put half a pound of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in a saucepan, boil it ten minutes, drain it on a sieve dry, pare six <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> divide the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> into six parts, spread
<pb n="46" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=48"/>
it on six different cloths, put one <ingredient>apple</ingredient> in each, tie it up loose, boil it one hour, serve it with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> or <ingredient>wine sauce.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 174. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Federal Pancake.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take one quart of <ingredient>bolted rye flour,</ingredient> one quart of <ingredient>bolted Indian meal,</ingredient> mix it well, and stir it with a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> into three pints of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> to the proper consistency of pancakes; fry in <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> and serve up warm.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 175. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Tea Cakes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half pound <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> two pounds <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one <measurement>gill</measurement> <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>orange peel;</ingredient> bake fifteen minutes.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 176. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Tea Biscuit.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> two spoonfuls of <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> mix them together adding one quarter of a pound melted <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> to make it into a stiff paste; bake it in a quick oven, in any shape you please.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 177. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Butter Biscuit.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pint each <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>emptins,</ingredient> laid into <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> in sponge; next morning add one pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> melted, not hot, and knead into as much <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as will, with another pint of <ingredient>warmed milk,</ingredient> be of sufficient consistency to make it soft--some melt the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 178. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Soft Cakes in little pans.</purpose>

</p>
<p>One pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rubbed into two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add one glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> one of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> eight <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and half a <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 179. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A butter Drop.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> two
<pb n="47" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=49"/>
spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> baked in tin pans.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 180. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Bread with grown flour.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take eight quarts of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> one pint of the best of <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> (this article must be good,) three tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> dissolved in half a pint of <ingredient>warm milk,</ingredient> add this to the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and after working the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and work up the whole with <ingredient>milk</ingredient> into stiff bread, more so than of other flour: the oven must be heat with light dry wood, but not hotter than for other bread.--This method, particularly attended to, will demonstrate that good bread may be made with grown flour.</p>
</recipe>
<p>N. B. In all cases where spices are named, it is supposed that they be pounded fine and sifted; sugar must be dried and rolled fine; flour dried in an oven; eggs well beaten or whipped into a raging foam.</p>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" ethnicgroup="american">
<p>No 181. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">American Citron Preserves.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take the <ingredient>rind of a large water mellon,</ingredient> cut it in small pieces, allow <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> pound for pound, make a sirup of the sugar, boil two hours slowly, put into pots for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 182. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For preserving Quinces.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a peck of <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> pare them, take out the core with a sharp knife, if you wish to have them whole; boil parings and cores with two pounds of <ingredient>frost grapes,</ingredient> in three quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil the liquor an hour and a half, or till it is thick, strain it through a coarse <implement>hair sieve,</implement> add a pound and a quarter of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to every pound of <ingredient>quince,</ingredient> put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into the sirup, scald and skim it till it is clear, put the <ingredient>quinces</ingredient>
<pb n="48" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=50"/>
into the sirup, cut up two <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> and mix with the <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> hang them over a gentle fire five hours, then put them in a stone pot for use, set them in a cool dry place.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 183. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For preserving Quinces in loaf sugar.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a peck of <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> put them into a kettle of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> hanging them over the fire, boil them till they are soft, then take them out with a fork when cold, pare them, quarter or halve them if you like; take their weight of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> put it into a <implement>bell metal kettle</implement> or saucepan, with one quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> scald and skim it till it is very clear, then put in your <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> let them boil in the sirup for half an hour, add <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> as before if you like, then put them in stone pots for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 184. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For preserving Strawberries.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take two quarts of <ingredient>strawberries,</ingredient> squeeze them through a cloth, add half a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and two pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> put it into a saucepan scald and skim it, take two pounds of <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> with stems on, set your saucepan on a <implement>chafing dish,</implement> put as many <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> into the dish as you can with the stem up without bruising them, let them boil for about ten minutes, then take them out gently with a fork, and put them into a stone pot for use; when you have done the whole, turn the sirup into the pot, when hot; set them in a cool place for use.</p>
<p><variation><purpose rend="italic"><alt synonym1="currant preserves" synonym2="cherry preserves">Currants and Cherries</alt></purpose>

may be done in the same way, by adding a little more <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="breadsweets">
<p>No 185. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To keep white bullace, pears, plums, or damsons, &#38;c. for tarts or pies.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Gather them when full grown, and just as 
<pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=51"/>
they begin to turn, pick all the largest out, save about two thirds of the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> to the other third put as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as you think will cover them, boil and skim them; when the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is boiled very soft, strain it through a coarse hair sieve; and to every quart of this liquor put a pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> boil it, and skim it very well; then throw in your <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> just give them a scald; take them off the fire, and when cold, put them into bottles with wide mouths, pour your sirup over them, cover with a piece of white paper.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 186. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Marmalade.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To two pounds of <ingredient>quinces</ingredient> put one and a half pounds of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and a pint of <ingredient>spring water;</ingredient> put them over the fire, and boil them till they are tender; take them up and bruise them; put them into the liquor, let it boil three quarters of an hour, and then put it into your pots or saucers.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 187. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Gooseberries, Damsons or Plums.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Gather them when dry, full grown, and not ripe; pick them one by one, put them into glass bottles, that are very clean and dry, and cork them close with new corks; then put a kettle of water on the fire, and put in the bottles with care; wet not the corks; but let the water come up to the necks; make a gentle fire till they are a little <process>codled</process> and turn white; do not take them up till cold, then pitch the corks all over, or wax them close and thick; then set them in a cold dry cellar.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 188. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Peaches.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put your <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> just give them a scald, but don't let them boil, take them
<pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=52"/>
out and put them in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then dry them in a sieve, and put them in long wide mouthed bottles; to half a dozen <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> take a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> clarify it, pour it over your <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> and fill the bottles with <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> stop them close and keep them in a close place.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 189. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Cherries.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take two pounds of <ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> one pound and a half of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>fair water,</ingredient> melt some <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in it; when it is melted, put in your other <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and your <ingredient>cherries;</ingredient> then boil them softly till all the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> be melted; then boil them fast, and skim them: take them off two or three times and shake them, put them on again, and let them boil fast; and when they are of a good colour, and the sirup will stand, they are boiled enough.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 190. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Raspberries.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Choose <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> that are not too ripe, and take the weight of them in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> wet your <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and put in your berries, and let them boil softly; take heed of breaking them; when they are clear, take them up, and boil the sirup till it be thick enough, then put them in again; and when they are cold put them up in glasses.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 191. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Currants.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take the weight of the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> pick out the <ingredient>seeds;</ingredient> take to a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let it melt; then put in your <ingredient>currants</ingredient> and let them do very leisurely, skim them and take them up, let the sirup boil; then put them on again; and when they are clear, and the sirup thick enough, take them off: and when they are cold, put them up in glasses.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=53"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 192. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Plums.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take your <ingredient>plums</ingredient> before they have stones in them, which you may know by puttlng a pin through them, then <process>codle</process> them in many waters till they are as green as grass, peel and <process>codle</process> them again; you must take the weight of them in <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> then put them in, set them on the fire, to boil slowly till they be clear, skimming them often, and they will be very green; put them up in glasses and keep them for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 193. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Strawberry preserve.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take three pounds large fair <ingredient>strawberries,</ingredient> free from stems or hulls, four pounds <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> place these in an earthen pot, first a sprinkling of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> then a laying of <ingredient>strawberries,</ingredient> another of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> and so alternatenly till the whole are placed in the pot, set it away in a cool place; if the weather should be warm, frequently sprinkle <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> upon them, by which they will be preserved fresh and good.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 194. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple Preserve.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take half a peck of large <ingredient>russet sweetings,</ingredient> otherwise a fair sweet <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> pare and core them; take two quarts of <ingredient>frost grapes,</ingredient> boil them in one pint <ingredient>water</ingredient> till soft, squeeze out the juice, add to this the <ingredient>juice of one quart currants</ingredient> well squeezed; to this add three pounds of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> also four <ingredient>whites of eggs</ingredient> and the shells, beat fine, scald and scum clean, then add one pint <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> strain it through a piece of flannel, then add the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and one fresh <ingredient>orange</ingredient> cut fine; boil gently half an hour over a moderate fire, put them in a stone or earthen jar, set in a cool palce, and keep for use.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=54"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 195. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Damson Preserve.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take four pounds <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and one quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil and scum clean, then run through a <implement>jelly bag,</implement> to which add one fresh <ingredient>orange</ingredient> cut fine, and half pint <ingredient>brandy;</ingredient> to this sirup put the <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> let them do over a gentle fire fifteen minutes; put away for use.</p>
<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="cherry preserves" synonym2="grape preserves">Cherris and Grapes</alt></purpose>

may be preserved in the same way.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 196. <hd rend="italic" align="center">A new method of keeping apples fresh and good, through the winter and into summer.</hd></p>
<p>Take a <alt synonym1="quantity">quatity</alt> of pippins, or other good winter apples: take them from the trees carefully when ripe, and before frost, make a hole thro' each one with a goose quill from stem to eye, fill this with sugar, lay in this position two weeks, till they are a little wilted, then put them in a tight <implement>cask,</implement> and keep them from freezing.</p>
</section>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 197. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To <alt synonym1="preserve">preseve</alt> bush beans fresh and good until winter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take half a bushel of <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> of a suitable size and age for eating green, string and break them, then put them into a cask, first sprinkling in <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then a layer of <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> and so alternately till the cask is full, then add a weak <ingredient>brine</ingredient> so as to cover them; take out for use, and freshen twenty four hours in water, often changing it; boil three hours in fresh water.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 198. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Cucumbers.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take large <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> lay them in <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> that will bear an egg, three days, set them on the fire with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> and a small lump of <ingredient>alum;</ingredient> boil them a few minutes, make
<pb n="53" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=55"/>
a thin sirup with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and turn on them, stand two days, then make a rich sirup, lay them in a jar and turn it on them; put it into the kettle again, simmer five or ten minutes, set it by until the next day, then boil again, put it in glasses, and set away for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 199. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Parsley fresh and green, to garnish viands in the winter</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put any quantity of green <ingredient>parsley</ingredient> into a strong pickle of <ingredient>salt and water</ingredient> boiling hot, and keep for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 200. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To keep damsons.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take <ingredient>damsons</ingredient> when they are first ripe, pick them off carefully, wipe them clean, put them into <implement>snuff bottles,</implement> stop them up tight so that no air can get to them, nor water; put nothing into the bottles but <ingredient>plums;</ingredient> but put the bottles into cold water, hang them over the fire, let them heat <alt synonym1="slowly,">sloly,</alt> let the water boil slowly, for half an hour, when the water is cold take out the bottles and set them in a cold place, they will keep twelve months if the bottles are stopped tight so as no air nor water can get to them. They will not keep long after the bottles are opened; the <ingredient>plums</ingredient> must be hard.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 201. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Currant Jelly.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Having stripped the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> from the stalks, put them in a stone jar, stop it close, set it in a kettle of boiling water, half way the jar, let it boil half an hour, take it out and strain the juice through a coarse hair sieve, to a pint of juice put a pound of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> set it over a quick fire in a <implement>preserving pan</implement> or <implement>bell metal skillet,</implement> keep stirring it all the time till the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> be melted, when skim the scum off as fast as it 
<pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=56"/>
rises. When the jelly is very clear and fine, pour it into earthen or china cups, when cold cut white papers just the bigness of the pot and lay on the jelly, dip those papers in brandy, then cover the top of the pot and prick it full of holes, set it in a dry place: you may put some into glasses for present use.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 202. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Plums and Cherries, six months or a year, retaining all that bloom and agreeable flavour, during the whole of that period, of which they are possessed when taken from the tree.</hd></p>
<p>Take any quantity of plums or cherries a little before they are fully ripe with the stems on; take them directly from the tree, when perfectly dry, and with the greatest care, so that they are not in the least bruised--put them with great care into a large stone jug, which must be dry, fill it full, and immediately make it proof against air and water, then sink it in a living spring of water, there let it remain for a year if you like, and when opened they will exhibit every beauty and charm, both as to the appearance and taste, as when taken from the tree.</p>
</section>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 203. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Peach Preserve.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take half a peck of <ingredient>clingstone <alt synonym1="peaches,">peachs,</alt></ingredient> wipe them with a flannel cloth, put them into an earthen pot sufficient to contain them, fill it up with <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> let them stand two days covered, then pour off the brandy, to which add half a pint of the same liquor and four pounds <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> cut two <ingredient>oranges</ingredient> very fine, which add to the sirup, and when boiling hot pour over the <ingredient>peaches;</ingredient> the next day set them in a hot oven, let
<pb n="55" id="notm057.jpg "/>
them stand half an hour, then set them away in a cool place. If the weather should be warm, the sirup must be scalded again in six or eight days, adding thereto another half pint of brandy and one pound <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> pouring it boiling hot upon the <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> then set them again in a cool place. This method of procedure will give them a more fresh and agreeable flavour than any mode yet discovered.</p>
<p><variation><purpose><alt synonym1="pear preserves">Pears,</alt></purpose>

taking out the seeds, may be preserved in the same manner.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 204. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To dry Peaches.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take the fairest and ripest <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> pare them into <ingredient>fair water;</ingredient> take their weight in <ingredient>double refined sugar;</ingredient> of one half make a very thin sirup; then put in your <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> boiling them till they look clear, then split and stone them, boil them till they are very tender, lay them a draining, take the other half of the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and boil it almost to a candy; then put in your <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> and let them lay all night, then lay them on a glass, and set them in a stove till they are dry; if they are sugared too much, wipe them with a wet cloth a little; let the first sirup be very thin, a quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">
<p>No 205. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For brewing Spruce Beer.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take four ounces of <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> boil half an hour, in one gallon <ingredient>water,</ingredient> strain it, then add sixteen gallons <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> two gallons of <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> eight ounces <ingredient>essence of spruce</ingredient> dissolved in one quart <ingredient>water,</ingredient> put it in a clean cask, shake it well together, add half pint <ingredient>emptins,</ingredient> let it stand and work one week, if very warm weather less time will do; when drawn off, add one spoonful <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> to each bottle.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="56" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=58"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" id="no206">
<p>No 206. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Eggs from May until May again.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a piece of <ingredient>unslacked lime</ingredient> as large as a pint bowl, slack it by degrees, when well slacked put ten quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to it and add <ingredient>salt</ingredient> till your <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> will rise, then put them in with care that none get cracked, and lay a cloth on the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> that will keep them wet on the top.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 207. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Souse.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil the <ingredient>souse</ingredient> until it will come from the bone with ease, cut it in slices, lay it in a jar, pour on <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> and tie your <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> in a cloth and throw it in; it is then ready to fry when you wish, and will keep all winter.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p>No 208. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Coffee.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A large spoonful of <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> for each person is sufficient when you make for as many as eight, if less, more. To make good <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> twenty minutes is sufficient to boil, and less will do; the <ingredient>yelk of an egg</ingredient> beat and stirred in before <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> is turned to it, will enrich the <ingredient>coffee;</ingredient> put in <ingredient>codfish skin</ingredient> as large as to clear it; let it stand five minutes after taking from the coals.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 209. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A good substitute for Cream to put in Coffee.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and let it cool, beat the <ingredient>yelks of three eggs</ingredient> and stir in, it will make the coffee much richer.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p>No 210. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To burn Coffee.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Burn your <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> slowly when you commence, but let the burning increase, burn it a good brown, put it away in a close vessel for future use.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="57" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=59"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 211. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To try Lard.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In a <implement>pailful pot</implement> put a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a large handful of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put your <ingredient>lard</ingredient> in and try it fast until the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is boiled out, then let there be a slow and steady fire until the scraps are of a light brown, then strain the <ingredient>lard</ingredient> and set it away, it will be white as snow, and never hurt.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 212. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To keep clear of Bedbugs.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take the <ingredient>white of four eggs,</ingredient> ten cents worth of <ingredient>quicksilver,</ingredient> put them into a bowl, beat them until a perfect froth, take a feather and dip in and apply it to every part of your bedstead where bugs ever conceal themselves, do this early in the spring, and but once a year, and you will never see a bedbug in your house.--Never wet your bedsteads.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 213. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make Yeast Cakes for Yeast.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a quart of <ingredient>distiller's yeast</ingredient> if you can get it, if not the best you can get, add a quart of strong <ingredient>hop water,</ingredient> warm, but not scald your <ingredient>yeast;</ingredient> put as much <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> into it as you can conveniently mix, let it stand half an hour, make it into little flat cakes and lay them on a clean board, set them in the sun and dry until perfectly dry, put them in a dry place. When you wish to use yeast, take one cake and put it into a quart of <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> and dissolve it, stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and make it as thick as thick cream, let it stand by a warm fire over night, it is then ready to make your bread in the morning.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 214. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To keep Cheese in the winter.</hd></p>
<p>Take a clean dry barrel, put a little hay at the bottom, and then a cheese and put hay between each cheese and around it, and keep it covered tight, and in the driest part of the cellar, or in an upper room not subject to frost.</p>
</section>
<pb n="58" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=60"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 215. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Butter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put your <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in stone jars, first sprinkle a little <ingredient>fine salt</ingredient> at the bottom, have it free from buttermilk, then put a layer of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> as thick as you wish to cut a slice, and continue to sprinkle a little <ingredient>salt</ingredient> between each layer, this will enable you to cut it smooth and not have it adhere to the under layer, cover it tight.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 216. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Soapgrease.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Make your cask clean, when you throw in fresh <ingredient>rinds</ingredient> or any thing of the kind, sprinkle on <ingredient>salt</ingredient> enough to preserve it, the same when you put down hog's inwards, and be as careful to keep it tight as any other meat, and you will have no disagreeable smell nor waste of grease by vermin.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 217. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make boiled Soap.</purpose>

</p>
<p>For a barrel take thirty-five pounds of <ingredient>scraps</ingredient> or other <ingredient>grease</ingredient> that is made daily in a family, put half the quantity into a <implement>five pail kettle,</implement> a pailful of <ingredient>strong lie,</ingredient> boil it thoroughly with a moderate fire or it will run over, then keep adding <ingredient>strong lie</ingredient> until full, put it it in a barrel and add <ingredient>weak lie.</ingredient> Then take the other half of the <ingredient>grease</ingredient> and proceed as before.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 218. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cold Soap.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Twenty-five pounds of <ingredient>clear grease,</ingredient> heat it, turn it into the barrel, heat <ingredient>strong lie</ingredient> and turn in, let it stand through the summer. <ingredient>Strong lie</ingredient> and good <ingredient>grease</ingredient> will insure you good soap, cold or hot.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 219. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To put up a Leach, say a large tierce.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Lay sticks across the bottom, then a covering of <ingredient>straw,</ingredient> one peck of <ingredient>lime</ingredient> should come
<pb n="59" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=61"/>
next, after which the <ingredient>ashes,</ingredient> these to be well beaten down several times in the course of filling up, pouring in a pail of <ingredient>water</ingredient> each time after pounding. If you are in no hurry for your lie, <ingredient>water</ingredient> your <alt synonym1="leach">leech</alt> occasionally until it shows a disposition to run at the bottom, then stop until you are ready to commence making soap. It will make two barrels.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 220. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Barley Water.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Upon one ounce of <ingredient>pearl barley,</ingredient> after it has been well washed in cold water, pour half a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and then boil it a few minutes; the <ingredient>water</ingredient> must then be strained off and thrown away; afterwards a quart of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> must be poured over the <ingredient>barley,</ingredient> and which should then be boiled down to one pint and a quarter, and strained off. <variation>The barley water thus made is clear and mucilaginous; and when mixed with an equal quantity of good <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and a small portion of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> is an excellent <purpose>substitute for a mother's milk,</purpose>

when infants are, unfortunately, to be brought up by hand.</variation> Without milk, it is one of the best beverages for all acute diseases, and may have <ingredient>lemon juice,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberry vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>apple tea,</ingredient> <ingredient>infusion of tamarinds,</ingredient> or any other acidulous substance that is agreeable to the palate of the patient, mixed with it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 221. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Gruel.</purpose>

</p>
<p>This farinaceous nutriment may be made either with <ingredient>grits,</ingredient> <ingredient>oatmeal</ingredient> or <ingredient>Indian meal.</ingredient> When <ingredient>grits</ingredient> are used, three ounces of them, after being very well washed, should be put into two quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> and boiled very slowly, until the <ingredient>water</ingredient> be reduced to one half of the original quantity. During the boiling it should be
<pb n="60" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=62"/>
stirred frequently; and, when finished, it should be strained though a hair sieve. <variation>For <purpose>oatmeal gruel,</purpose>

three ounces of meal must be put into a basin, and bruised with the back of the spoon; small quantities of <ingredient>water</ingredient> being successively mixed with it, and each quantity poured off into another basin, before more be mixed; and this must be continued until about a quart of <ingredient>water</ingredient> be mixed with the <ingredient>oatmeal.</ingredient> The remains of the <ingredient>oatmeal</ingredient> should then be thrown away, and the <ingredient>water</ingredient> in which it was bruised is to be boiled for twenty minutes, stirring it the whole of the time.</variation> <variation>Sifted <ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> may be used like oatmeal, only that it needs not so much ceremony. Simply mixing and cooking for a few minutes over the fire does the business.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 222. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Prepared Arrow Root for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p><ingredient>Arrow root</ingredient> forms an excellent nutritive mucilage. Put two tea spoonsful of the powder into a half pint basin; mix them smooth with a few tea spoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and then pour <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> over the mixture while you continue to stir it, until it forms a kind of starchy looking substance. <variation><ingredient>Sago</ingredient> and <ingredient>Tapioca</ingredient> form a similar mucilaginous substance, and are equally useful for children or as articles of diet for a sick person. As they are both hard, they require considerable boiling before they are completely dissolved. The person who makes a decoction of either must determine by trial if it be too thick or too thin.</variation> For a convalescent sick person they may be sweetened and seasoned with a little <ingredient>wine;</ingredient> for a child sweetened only.</p>
<p><ingredient>Arrow root,</ingredient> thus prepared, may be used in the same manner as gruel. It is well adapted
<pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=63"/>
for the food of infants, because it is less liable to ferment than either gruel or barley water; and for the same reason, it is the best fluid nourishment for those who are afflicted with diseases of indigestion. As it is very insipid, it requires either <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> or <ingredient>acids,</ingredient> to be mixed with it whichever may suit the taste and state of habit of the person for whom it is intended. It forms an excellent pudding, when prepared like rice, for children who are a little beyond the age of infancy.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth" alcoholic="yes">
<p>No 223. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">White Wine Whey.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To make this whey, put half a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> diluted with a <measurement>gill</measurement> of <ingredient>water</ingredient> into a saucepan, which must be placed on the fire uncovered.--Watch the moment when the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> boils, which may be known by the frothing and rising up of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> to the top of the pan; pour into it, at that instant, two glasses of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> and a tea spoonful of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> which should previously be mixed with the wine. The curd will immediately form; and, after boiling the mixture for a few minutes, may be separated from the whey, either by letting it settle at the bottom, and then pouring off the whey clear from it, or by straining it through a fine sieve. White wine whey, when drank warm, promotes perspiration; but as it is a stimulant, it cannot be given in inflammatory complaints. When cold, it is a very agreeable beverage in low fevers, and in convalescence, when stimulants are admissible.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 224. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Balm, Mint, and other Teas.</purpose>

</p>
<p>These are simple infusions, the strength of which can only be regulated by the taste.---
<pb n="62" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=64"/>
They are made by putting either the fresh or the dried plants into <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> in a covered vessel which should be placed near the fire for an hour. The young shoots both of <ingredient>balm</ingredient> and of <ingredient>mint</ingredient> are to be preferred, on account of their stronger aromatick qualities. These infusions may be drunk freely in feverish and in various other complaints, in which diluents are recommended. Mint tea, made with the fresh leaves, is useful in allaying nausea and vomiting.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 225. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Beef Tea,</purpose>

</p>
<p>Is too frequently prepared, by simply boiling a piece of <ingredient>beef</ingredient> in a given quantity of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> but by this method it generally resembles gravy soup more than beef tea, and is then unfit for the use of the sick. To make it properly, cut half a pound of good lean <ingredient>beef</ingredient> into very thin slices; spread the slices in a hollow dish, and having poured over them a pint and a half of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> cover up the dish, and place it near the fire for half an hour, and then boil it over a quick fire for about eight minutes. The tea, after having the skum taken off, should stand for ten minutes, after which it is to be poured off clean, and seasoned with a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>
<p>Beef tea thus made is a light and pleasant diluent, and very useful when the bowels and stomach are in a weak and irritable state.--when used as food for infants, it should always be prepared in this manner; and nothing answers better as a breakfast, for those who are habitually sick in a morning, either from a redundance of bile, intemperance, or other causes.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="63" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=65"/>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 226. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Veal Tea,</purpose>

</p>
<p>Is prepared in the same manner as beef tea; and may be used under similar cirumstances.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 227. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Chicken Tea,</purpose>

</p>
<p>Is prepared by cutting, in small pieces, a <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> from which the skin and fat have been removed; and then boiling the pieces, for twenty minutes, in a quart of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with the addition of a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> The tea should be poured from the meat before it is quite cold. It is useful in the same cases as beef and veal tea.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 228. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Toast and Water,</purpose>

</p>
<p>May be made by pouring over <ingredient>toasted bread</ingredient> either a pint of cold or boiling <ingredient><alt synonym1="water.">water</alt></ingredient> In the latter mode it should be made some hours before it is wanted, that it may have time to become perfectly cool.</p>
<p><variation>In some cases of extreme debility, <ingredient>ising-glass</ingredient> is sometimes ordered to be taken in small quantities. An ounce, when dissolved in a pint of <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> forms, when cold, a light jelly, a tea spoonful of which may be mixed with <ingredient>tea,</ingredient> or <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>water.</ingredient></variation> <variation>A very pleasant beverage may, also, be made of <ingredient>orange juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> with the addition of the <ingredient>ising-glass</ingredient> <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 229. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Grapes and other delicate fruits.</hd></p>
<p>Bunches of grapes may be preserved for some time in jars; but each bunch should be wrapped up in soft paper, and every layer of these bunches in the jar covered with well dried bran. The mouth of the jar should be covered
<pb n="64" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=66"/>
with a bladder, or the lid be cemented on with a cement composed of two parts of the curd of skimmed milk and one of lime. But the best method of preserving grapes, is to gather the bunches on the branch to which they are attached, which should be cut about six inches from the bunch, and have both ends of it sealed with common sealingwax. These should then be hung across lines in the fruit-room, taking care, occasionally, to examine them, and clip out, with a pair of scissors, any berries that appear mouldy. If grapes that are not over-ripe be preserved in this manner, they will keep until February. Other and more delicate fruits may also be preserved by wiping them dry to clear away the moisture which they yield after gathering, and then placing them in earthern jars, and covering them with layers of dry sand about an inch in thickness. Each jar should be well filled, closed with cement, and placed in the fruit-room or a cool place, but where it cannot be affected by the frost.</p>
</section>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans" id="no230">
<p>No 230. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Proper place for preserving Roots and Fruit.</hd></p>
<p>The cellar or room where roots and fruits are to be kept should be a dry one if possible, and not subject to freezing. Small double or treble sash windows, and a double door, prevent materially the ingress of frost from these places. A plentiful supply of shelves, and hooks overhead to attach lines are desirable. Shelves fixed up in common cellars will do.</p>
</section>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 231. <hd rend="italic">To keep Onions and other Bulbous roots.</hd></p>
<p>Spread them thinly on the shelves of such
<pb n="65" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=67"/>
a room as is recommended in receipt <ref target="no230">No 230.</ref> Potatoes should be kept high and dry from the bottom of the cellar or they will rot, especially as the weather moderates towards spring.</p>
</section>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 232. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Cabbages, Lettuce, and other similar Plants.</hd></p>
<p>These plants may be preserved throughout the winter, in a state fit for use, if they be taken out of the ground with their main roots entire in perfectly dry weather, at the end of the season, and partially immersed in dry sand. If these and the potatoes be not put into the fruit-cellar, which might be inconvenient, they should be kept in a close dry cellar, of a cold, but not freezing temperature. See No 230.</p>
</section>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 233. <hd rend="italic" align="center">For preserving Fruit.</hd></p>
<p>There are various methods of preserving fruit. Pears and apples, the most useful fruit in a family, are best preserved in glazed, cylindrical, earthen vessels, large enough to hold a gallon, and closely fitted with covers. One kind of apple or of pear only should be put into the same jar, which should be labelled, to prevent the necessity of opening it to ascertain the kind of fruit it contains. Each apple or pear should be wiped dry, then rolled in soft spongy paper, and placed carefully in the jar, on which when it is full, the cover should be cemented, by means of a cement composed of two parts of the curd of skimmed milk and one of lime. These jars may be kept either in the cellar or the room, but the former is the preferable situation. Pears thus preserved, will keep until February or March; but they should be taken from the jars about ten days before
<pb n="66" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=68"/>
they are wanted for the table, and placed on the shelves of the fruit-room, and ultimately removed into a warmer room for the last three days.</p>
<p>Baking apples after they have been gathered a few days, and have, as the gardener would say, perspired, should be wiped and laid on a dry floor or shelf, and covered over with a linnen cloth, which secures them from damp and frost. A woollen cloth will not answer the same purpose; and straw, which is commonly placed over them, gives them a musty and disagreeable taste. Baking pears may be kept in the same manner; but when they are of a large kind, with a strong stalk, they keep much better if they are tied to a string across the ceiling. Apples and pears for baking may also be preserved in hampers or baskets lined with thick paper; and when this method is adopted, the fruit should not be allowed to perspire, but carried directly from the tree, and packed, carefully avoiding all sorts of bruising, and rejecting every bruised fruit. One sort of fruit only should be put into each hamper, which should be labelled.</p>
<p>Apples are preserved in barrels, and kept in rooms where they will not freeze.</p>
</section>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 234. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To take grease spots out of clothes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Rub on <ingredient>spirits turpentine,</ingredient> then take <ingredient>alcohol,</ingredient> rub with a sponge, it will leave the cloth unsoiled.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 235. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Drying and preserving Flowers and Plants.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Provide yourself with a few sheets of <implement>blotting paper,</implement> the number to be regulated by the
<pb n="67" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=69"/>
juiciness of the plants; having stretched one half the paper on a table, arrange the parts of the flower or plant to be dried in a manner you think it will afterwards look the best; lay the other half of the paper over the flower or plant as harmlessly as possible; then with a <implement>smoothing iron,</implement> well heated, you may easily extract all the moisture. Keep moving the paper as often as it becomes wet; continue the operation until no moisture comes. The advantage of this method is, that the flowers so prepared, retain the original colour. If you intend the specimen for a malange, moisten one side of the flower with a strong <ingredient>mucilage of gum,</ingredient> when it will readily adhere to paper. If you wish to preserve it still farther, wash the whole repeatedly with a solution of <ingredient>ising-glass,</ingredient> preparatory to its receiving a wash of <ingredient>copal varnish.</ingredient> In this way the plant may be preserved in full colour to an indefinite period. Sea-weeds preserved in the same way, look exceedingly beautiful, as their variety is endless.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="accompaniments">
<p>No 236. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Preserving Potatoes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Wash them, cut them in pieces, steep them forty-eight hours in <ingredient>lime water,</ingredient> then forty-eight hours in <ingredient>fresh water;</ingredient> dry them in an oven. One hundred parts of fresh <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> will give thirty so prepared and dried. <variation>In this state they may be kept for years, or ground at once into <purpose><alt synonym1="potato flour">flour.</alt></purpose>

This <ingredient>flour</ingredient> mixed with a third part of that of rye, is said to make an excellent bread.</variation> <variation>It is likewise proposed to moisten <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> dried as above, with <ingredient>olive oil,</ingredient> and then to grind them, and use them as <purpose>coffee.</purpose>

</variation></p>
</recipe>
<pb n="68" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=70"/>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 237. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Preservative against Insects and Blight.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A correspondent in a German Agricultural Journal, says, "bore a hole in the branch attacked, drop therein two drops of <ingredient>quicksilver,</ingredient> and at the end of two days, all the insects will be found dead."</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 238. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Extracting Grease.</purpose>

</p>
<p>If a silk or cotton dress have been stained with grease a very excellent method of removing the spots, without taking out the colour, is to grate raw <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> to a pulp, in clean <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and pass the liquid through a coarse sieve, into another vessel of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> let the mixture stand till the fine white particles of the <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> have fallen to the bottom; then pour the liquor off clear and bottle it for use. Dip a sponge in the liquor and apply it to the spot till it disappear; then wash it in <ingredient>clean water</ingredient> several times. Two middle sized <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> will be enough for a pint of <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Be very careful not to wet more of a dress than is necessary, as some delicate colours will look slightly marked even with clean water.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="beverages">
<p>No 239. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Preparing Coffee.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In order to roast <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> properly, the uses of roasting must not be lost sight of, namely, to destroy the hornlike tenacity of the green bean, and to develope its fine scent. Too much heat would destroy the chemical elements which ought to be preserved, and would substitute in their place others which are entirely different in quality. That fine scent which pleases so greatly the admirer of good <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> is succeeded, when the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> is over-
<pb n="69" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=71"/>
roasted, by a bitter taste and burnt smell, which is far from pleasant, and even disagreeable.--If on the other hand, the roasting process is under-done, and the heat to which the <ingredient>beans</ingredient> have been exposed, has not been sufficient, then the raw smell of the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> remains, and of course diminishes the aroma, which requires a certain heat to devlope it. There is of course a just medium to be observed. Well roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> ought to have a pale chocolate colour equally spread over it, which is well known to those who are in the use of performing this operation; but it is never necessary to look at the roasted <ingredient>beans,</ingredient> the scent is sufficient; for when the true aroma is developed, and fills the surrounding atmosphere with its delicious scent, then is the time to stop the roasting. After this period, the oil acquires a burnt flavour, a scent somewhat resembling that exhaled by smokers of tobacco is perceived, and instead of good roasted <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> there is obtained a bad kind of charcoal.</p>
<p>Good raw <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> loses from sixteen to twenty per cent of its weight by roasting; if it loses more it is certainly over-roasted. Many different modes are used, and each has its admirers; but there is in fact only a single rule to be observed, namely, to use the proper degree of heat, and keep it up at the same point until the roasting is finished. Whether the roasting is performed in close or open vessels; whether the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> is left to cool in the <implement>roaster,</implement> or is turned out, or even laid between cloths, appears indifferent. If, indeed, the roasting is carried by accident too far, the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> should be immediately spread out thin on the floor, to 
<pb n="70" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=72"/>
cool as soon as possible. In all cases, when cold, the roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> should be put up into tin-plate boxes, and kept from any moisture.</p>
<p>It being well known that the chemical action of solvents is hastened, in general by reducing the solvent to powder; it is necessary to grind the roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> more or less fine, as it is intended to use the <ingredient>water</ingredient> less or more heated. To reduce <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> to too fine a powder, although <alt synonym1="it">it it</alt> would require only slightly <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> to extract its soluble parts, yet it would be inconvenient in other respects, for the powder would pass through the strainers of the <implement>coffee pot,</implement> and by also remaining suspended in the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> would render the clearing of the drink difficult. At all events, roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> should never be ground but the moment before it is used, as otherwise it loses much of its fine scent.</p>
<p>It now remains only to say a few words respecting the making of the ground roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> into drink--and here the grand points are, not to lose the fine aroma, and not to extract the bitter, acrid, resinous element of the coffee.--To avoid both these inconveniencies, it is necessary that the coffee drink should not be made with too much heat; as this would dissipate the aroma in vapours, and cause the <ingredient>water</ingredient> to dissolve the resin. The <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> therefore, must not be boiled in the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and still less is it proper to boil the grounds over again with fresh <ingredient>water,</ingredient> as is done by some persons. Coffee drink made from the grounds, when it is added to that made from fresh ground <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> gives it indeed a fine deep colour, but the taste of the drink is very bad.</p>
<pb n="71" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=73"/>
<p>It is not even necessary to pour boiling or even warm water on the ground <ingredient>coffee;</ingredient> <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> if sufficient time is allowed, makes equally good coffee drink, for the elements to be extracted from the roasted <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> are extremely soluble in <ingredient>water.</ingredient> But if the coffee drink is required to be prepared in haste, <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> must be used.</p>
<p>It is uiversally agreed on by the French amateurs of <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> that coffee drink is never so good as when, after being made with <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> or with <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> and cooled, it is heated over again, carefully avoiding a boiling heat. This heating over again is supposed to cause the various elements which produce the fine flavour of this drink, to unite more intimately; and this may be the real fact. The excellence of the <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> sold at Paris is well known; and this is always made one day and heated over again the next day, when wanted. A further advantage attends this knowledge, of consequence to single persons who, in summer time, do not keep a fire in their chambers, that by merely pouring <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> on the ground <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> over night, and straining it in the morning, the strained liquor may while they are dressing, be heated sufficiently for drinking, over a lamp; and this gives <ingredient>coffee</ingredient> a superiority over tea for the breakfast of such persons; as tea requires the <ingredient>water</ingredient> to be boiling hot, in order to extract its virtues; and of course <alt synonym1="requires">reqnires</alt> a fire to be lighted.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="household">
<p>No 240. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Washing Cottons and Linen.</hd></p>
<p>Never wash muslins, or any kind of white cotton goods, with linen; for the latter deposits
<pb n="72" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=74"/>
or discharges a gum and colouring matter every time it is washed, which discolours and dies the cotton. Wash them by themselves.</p>
</section>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 241. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">New method of making Jelly.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Press the juice from the <ingredient>fruit;</ingredient> add the proper proportion of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and stir the juice and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is completely melted; put it into jars, and, in twenty-four hours, it will become of a proper consistence. By this means, the trouble of boiling is avoided, and the jelly retains more completely the flavour of the <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient> Care should be taken to stir the mixture until the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is completely melted, and <ingredient>fine sugar</ingredient> should be used.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 242. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Yeast.</purpose>

</p>
<p>To ten pounds of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> add two gallons of <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> stir it well into a paste; let this mixture stand for seven hours, and then add about a quart of <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> In about six or eight hours this mixture, if kept in a warm place, ferments, and produces as much yeast as will bake an hundred and twenty quartern loaves.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets">
<p>No 243. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A good Bread.</purpose>

</p>
<p>A mixture of two parts <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and one <ingredient>potatoe,</ingredient> makes an agreeable bread, which cannot be distinguished from wheaten bread. It is said not less than three hundred tons of <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> are consumed for this purpose in London every week.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">
<p>No 244. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cottage Beer.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a peck of good sweet <ingredient>wheat bran,</ingredient> and put it into ten gallons of <ingredient>water</ingredient> with three handfuls of good <ingredient>hops.</ingredient> Boil the whole together in an iron, brass, or copper kettle, until
<pb n="73" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=75"/>
the <ingredient>bran</ingredient> and <ingredient>hops</ingredient> sink to the bottom. Then strain it through a hair sieve or a thin sheet, into a <implement>cooler,</implement> and when it is about lukewarm, add two quarts of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient> As soon as the <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> is melted, pour the whole into a nine or ten gallon cask, with two table spoonfuls of <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> When the fermentation has subsided, bung up the cask, and in four days it will be fit for use.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="generalnonfood">
<p>No 245. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Foul air in Wells.</purpose>

</p>
<p>The following simple, but certain preservative, is recommended to all persons who follow subterraneous occupations. When a well, vault or drain has been enclosed a considerable time, in order to disperse and rectify the suffocating air, at first opening throw down six or more pails of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and after waiting a quarter of an hour, any one may venture down; the like method should be observed in sinking new wells, especially if the works have been discontinued any length of time.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 246. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To wash printed Calicoes.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Use as little <ingredient>soap</ingredient> as possible, and not with hot <ingredient>water;</ingredient> put in a little <ingredient>pot-ashes,</ingredient> <ingredient>lie</ingredient> or <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> and gently swill them, taking care not to rub the cloth too much; wring it out in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and dry it in the open air. By this means many colours are improved--all indeed but such as are mere water colours, and of this kind good cloths are seldom printed.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 247. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To prevent Moths.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In the month of April beat your fur garments well with a small cane or elastick stick, then lap them up in a linen without pressing the fur too hard, and put between the folds some
<pb n="74" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=76"/>
<ingredient>camphor</ingredient> in small lumps; then put your furs in this state in boxes well closed.</p>
<p>When the furs are wanted for use, beat them well as before, and expose them for twenty-four hours to the air, which will take away the smell of the camphor.</p>
<p>If the fur has long hair, as bear or fox, add to the <ingredient>camphor</ingredient> an equal quantity of <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> in the powder.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 248. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To prevent bad smells in sinks, &#38;c.</purpose>

</p>
<p>There is generally a close conductor attached to the spout of a sink. In this conductor let a well fitted trap door, or damper, made of tin, sheet iron or wood be inserted, having the arbours or bearings so far on one side of the centre as to cause it to shut of itself after letting the liquid pass through. Checks should be placed under the heavy end of the trap so as to keep it horizontal to the pitch of the conductor when in a quiescent state. Any common house joiner or similar mechanick would sufficiently understand from this description how to put one in.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 249. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make sticking paste.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Every good housewife should know how to make paste, but few do, however. Take <ingredient>wheat</ingredient> or <ingredient>rye flour</ingredient> and stir into <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> until a middling thick batter, having all the lumps broken fine; pour on at once as much <ingredient>boiling hot water</ingredient> as to thin it up to the right consistency. Stir it well, set the kettle over just fire enough to keep up the heat produced by the <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and a few moments swell the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> so as to produce good paste.--N. B. A small quantity can be made in a spoon over a lamp or candle almost instantaneously.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="75" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=77"/>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 250. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To transplant Trees.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Let the trees be taken up with as little injury to the roots, and retaining as much of the earth as possible. Saw off the main trunk at such height as you please, also all the limbs, some close to the trunk, others three or four inches from it. Cover where sawed off with <ingredient>tallow,</ingredient> <ingredient>tar</ingredient> and <ingredient>rosin,</ingredient> melted and partly cold. Do not be afraid of this operation; the top will again grow out, in handsome shape too, as soon as the roots will bear one.</p>
<p>In setting out the tree, if any thing more than a mere shrub, let a circular hole as much as four feet across and one and a half feet deep be dug, throwing the <ingredient>turf</ingredient> and <ingredient>top soil</ingredient> in one place and the <ingredient>hardpan</ingredient> in another; throw into the centre a little mound composed of the turf and top soil until high enough to bring your tree up to where you wish it, let it be held upright whilst the roots are carefully laid in their natural position and more of the top soil dashed in around with a shovel. Finish filling up with your hardpan dirt mixed with <ingredient>old foul grass</ingredient> or <ingredient>straw from horse manure</ingredient> with the manure partly shaken out beforehand. After having nearly filled up, tread down the earth, observing to keep the tree perpendicular. The earth thrown into this excavation operates as a sponge upon the adjacent ground, drawing sufficient moisture let the summer be ever so dry.</p>
<p>N. B. All shrubbery thrives infinitely better by having the excavation made very large.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 251. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To clean and renew the appearance of painted Wood-Work.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Dissolve <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> until it becomes slippery; with a sponge or cloth try it on the 
<pb n="76" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=78"/>
paint to see if it pretty readily removes fly specks &#38;c., if you judge it too weak add more <ingredient>pearlash</ingredient> till right. Then as with <ingredient>water</ingredient> freely wash your paint, but immediately, say in three or four minutes, follow with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> wiping dry as you can, and end the process by rubbing the parts entirely dry with a dry woollen cloth.</p>
<p>N. B. Be careful not to scatter the <ingredient>pearlash water</ingredient> where it will lay any considerable length of time for it will dissolve or cut thro' the paint to the wood.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 252. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To kill grass that springs up in seams of flagging or gravel walks.</purpose>

</p>
<p><ingredient>Meat brine,</ingredient> or strong <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> poured into the seams of flagging or sprinkled freely on gravel walks, for a few times, with three or four days' interval, will completely kill the roots of grass or weeds. Some people employ a man for a whole day, say twice in the summer to cut out with a <implement>case knife,</implement> what <ingredient>brine</ingredient> would destroy with a fiftieth part of the trouble.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 253. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To make a white wash that will preserve its whiteness and not rub off.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Bruise or scrape raw <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> and wash the same until you have procured potatoe starch enough for your purpose, (or take <ingredient>common starch,</ingredient>) make it up as common starch for starching clothes and add it to <ingredient>whiting</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> made of the right consistence for white-wash, and mix the whole well together. Let the <ingredient>water</ingredient> be a little warm that the <ingredient>starch</ingredient> may more readily mix with the wash.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="household">
<pb n="77" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=79"/>
<p>No 254. <hd rend="italic" align="center">The only sure way to stop the blaze of a female's dress when accidentally caught on fire.</hd></p>
<p>If children or adults, let them prostrate themselves on the floor as soon as the clothes are discovered to be on fire and commence rolling in such a manner as to smother the flames, and let blankets, water, or any thing else at hand, be applied as soon as assistance comes. Many fatal accidents might be prevented by observing the above. To stand upright or run is sure destruction.</p>
</section>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 255. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To remove spots or stains from linen or cotton.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Put a small quantity of <ingredient>brimstone</ingredient> into a skillet or some such iron vessel and drop in a <ingredient>live coal</ingredient> of fire; having first wet the stained spot with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> lay the cloth over the vessel so as to let the fumes have full access to the stained spot; it will soon disappear or become loose so as to wash out.</p>
<p><variation>N. B. As <purpose>iron rust spots</purpose>

are pretty obstinate the better way to serve these, is to take, say one part <ingredient>muriatick acid,</ingredient> three parts <ingredient>water,</ingredient> wet the spot and lay the same over a teapot containing boiling water; repeat the operation if necessary.</variation></p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 256. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To remove glass stopples when fast.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a cloth dipped in <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> (if in cold weather see that the frost is out of your bottle,) wrap around the neck several folds and let it stand a short time, trying the stopple occasionally until it comes out.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=80"/>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 257. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To prevent wooden ware from cracking.</purpose>

</p>
<p>After washing wooden bowls, trays &#38;c. lean them up against something in the pantry, or any where in the shade to dry, and they seldom crack. The fire or sun inevitably ruins them.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 258. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To sweeten musty tubs or casks.</purpose>

</p>
<p>After scalding and otherwise washing the cask clean, capsize it over a <implement>portable furnace</implement> or kettle, containing <ingredient>charcoal</ingredient> newly set on fire, and let it stand eight or ten minutes, or until partially dried. Let the cask be raised a little so as not to smother the fire. If several casks are to be rectified, throw some small bits of <ingredient>coal</ingredient> on to the furnace each time.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 259. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Parsnips, Carrots and Beets, all the winter.</hd></p>
<p>A little before the frost sets in, draw your beets or parsnips out of the ground, and lay them in the house, burying their roots in sand to the neck of the plant, and ranging them one by another in a shelving position; then another bed of sand, and another of beets, and continue this order to the last. By pursuing this method, they will keep very fresh. When they are wanted for use, draw them as they stand, not out of the middle or sides.</p>
</section>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 260. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To take mildew out of linen.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take <ingredient>soap,</ingredient> and rub it well; then scrape some fine <ingredient>chalk,</ingredient> and rub that also in the linen; lay it on the grass; as it dries, wet it a little, and it will come out at twice doing.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="farmgarden">
<pb n="79" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=81"/>
<p>No 261. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Necessity of taking off superfluous suckers from shrubs.</hd></p>
<p>Many flowering shrubs put out strong suckers from the root, such as lilacks, syringa, and some of the kinds of roses, which take greatly from the strength of the mother plant; and which, if not wanted for the purpose of planting the next season, should be twisted off, or otherwise destroyed.</p>
</section>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 262. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Eggs, to keep.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Lest some may think the receipt <ref target="no206">No 206</ref> page 56, not particular enough we give what may be considered the father of it, which a Mr. Jayne, of Sheffield, England, obtained a patent for in 1791. His receipt is on a large scale to be sure, but a rule below it, to reduce in the same ratio, accommodates it to family use.</p>
<p>"Put into a tub or vessel one bushel of <ingredient>unslacked lime,</ingredient> thirty-two ounces of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> and mix the same together with as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as will reduce the composition, or mixture, to that consistence, that it will cause an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> put into it to swim with its top just above the liquid: then put, and keep the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> therein, which will preserve them perfectly sound for the space of two years at the least."</p>
<p>It will be seen that <emph rend="italic">one ounce</emph> of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and a <emph rend="italic">quarter ounce</emph> of <ingredient>cream of <alt synonym1="tartar,">tarter,</alt></ingredient> to every quart of <ingredient>lime</ingredient> before slackened, are the proportions. The quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> is well enough described above. For more particulars see <ref target="no206">No. 206.</ref></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 263. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Another manner of preserving Eggs perfectly fresh, for twelve months.</purpose>

</p>
<p>An easy way of preserving <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> is to rub
<pb n="80" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=82"/>
the out side of the shell as soon as gathered from the nest, with a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or any other <ingredient>grease</ingredient> that is not fetid. By filling up the pores of the shell, the evaporation of the liquid part of the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> is prevented; and either by that means, or by excluding the external air, the milkiness, which most people are fond of in new laid <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> will be preserved for months, as perfect as when the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> was taken from the nest.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 264. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To wash Woollens so as not to shrink or full.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Never rub soap on to woollen, but previously make your <ingredient>suds,</ingredient> wash, throw them into another tub and pour on clean <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and let them lie until cool enough to wring out.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 265. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Yeasts.</hd></p>
<p>Many people are not aware of the difference between brewer's and other yeasts, such as distiller's. A wedding day was set; to make a wedding cake the cookery book said, "take one pint of yeast," when unluckily brewer's was used; the cake was spoiled and the wedding postponed.</p>
<p>Half a teacupful of brewer's yeast is as much in effect as a pint or even a quart of distiller's. For the manner of using both see <ref target="no103">No 103.</ref>--Distiller's yeast is always meant if not contradicted.</p>
</section>
<formula class="medhealth">
<p>No 266. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To expel nameless intruders from children's heads.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Steep <ingredient>larkspur seed</ingredient> in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> rub the liquor a few times into the child's hair, and the business of destruction is done. This is an effectual remedy. Does it not make your head itch?</p>
</formula>
<pb n="81" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=83"/>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 267. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To wash white Marino Shawls.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Wash the shawl in fair <ingredient>suds</ingredient> made before hand; rub no soap on to the shawl, rinse in fair <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> with two changes if you please; then take a solution of <ingredient>gum Arabick</ingredient> and add to <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> till you think it will produce a little stiffness like starch when dry. Press with a moderately hot iron, before quite dry, laying a clean cotton or linen cloth between the iron and the shawl.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 268. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To manage Feather Beds.</purpose>

</p>
<p>As often as a bed is thought to need airing, lay it exposed to the out door air, high and dry from the ground, and in the shade. Do not lay out until the sun has been up long enough to drive away the morning moisture, and take in before evening.</p>
<p>It is an erroneous notion that beds should be exposed to the sun. The warmth extracts the oily matter in the quill end of the feathers and makes them rancid. By being always aired in the shade, this oily substance in time becomes concrete and inodorous.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 269. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To clean Brass.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take a rag wet with <ingredient>spirits turpentine,</ingredient> and dabble in <ingredient>rotten stone</ingredient> and rub your ornaments; after which finish with a dry rag and <ingredient>rotten stone.</ingredient></p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 270. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Furs from Moths.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Sprinkle in <ingredient>Scotch snuff</ingredient> plentifully to the roots of the furs, tie in a pillow case and hang up or lay away where they will not be likely to have other things thrown on them. When wanted, let them lie one day in the sun, whipping them first, and they are ready for use.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="meatfishgame">
<pb n="82" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=84"/>
<p>No 271. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Dried Beef.</hd></p>
<p>Beef is always corned and dried in the course of the winter months; the method of pickling which, has already been spoken of in No's <ref target="no1">1,</ref> <ref target="no2">2,</ref> <ref target="no3">3,</ref> and the <emph rend="italic">caution</emph> under <ref target="no4">No 4.</ref>--Before fly time in the spring, make flannel bags into which put and tie up closely your dried beef and hang up in a dry cool place.</p>
</section>
<section class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 272. <hd rend="italic" align="center">To keep Hams in the summer.</hd></p>
<p>There are various methods, but the most sure is, before fly time, to roll each ham in a cloth or wrap faithfully in swingle tow, and lay down in a barrel packed in charcoal some broken, so as to pack close, or common house ashes. Let them be completely covered and enclosed on all sides, to guard against the ingress of flies, and you have nothing else to fear.</p>
<p>There is another way which we have known to succeed for several years in succession, and the philosophy of the process is good: Before fly time in the spring make a bag for each ham out of good thick factory cloth, dip it in strong salt and water and dry, alternately, for three or four times. The cloth by this means becomes saturated with salt, which on drying, chrystalizes, and forms an impervious barrier to flies and is quite air tight. Put in your hams, tie close, and hang up in a dry cool place.</p>
</section>
<section class1="breadsweets" class2="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 273. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Observations on Puddings and Pies.</hd></p>
<p>The quality of the various articles employed in the composition of puddings and pies varies so much, that two puddings, made exactly according
<pb n="83" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=85"/>
to the same receipt, will be so different one would hardly suppose they were made by the same person, and certainly not with precisely the same quantities of the (appparently) same ingredients. Flour fresh ground, pure new milk, fresh laid eggs, fresh butter, fresh suet, &#38;c. will make a very different composition, than when kept till each article is half spoiled.</p>
<p>Plum puddings, when boiled, if hung up in a cool place in the cloth they are boiled in, will keep good some months; when wanted, take them out of the cloth, and put them into a clean cloth, and as soon as warmed through, they are ready.</p>
<p>MEM.--In composing these receipts, the quantities of eggs, butter, &#38;c. are considerably less than are ordered in other cookery books; but quite sufficient for the purpose of making the puddings light and wholesome;--we have diminished the expense, without impoverishing the preparations; and the rational epicure will be as well pleased with them as the rational economist.</p>
<p>Milk, in its genuine state, varies considerably in the quantity of cream it will throw up, depending on the material with which the cow is fed. The cow that gives the most milk does not always produce the most cream, which varies fifteen or twenty per cent.</p>
<p>Break eggs one by one into a basin, and not all into a bowl together; because then, if you meet with a bad one, that will spoil all the rest: strain them through a sieve to take out the treddles.</p>
<pb n="84" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=86"/>
<p>Flour varies in quality as much as anything.</p>
<p>Butter also varies much in quality. Salt butter may be washed from the salt, and then it will make very good pastry.</p>
<p>Lard varies extremely from the time it is kept, &#38;c. When you purchase it, ascertain that it be sweet and good.</p>
<p>Suet. Beef is the best, then mutton and veal; when this is used in very hot weather, while you chop it, dredge or sprinkle it lightly with a little flour.</p>
<p>Beef-marrow is excellent for most of the purposes for which suet is employed.</p>
<p>Drippings, especially from beef, when very clean and nice, are frequently used for everyday crusts and pies, and for such purposes are a satisfactory substitute for butter, lard, &#38;c.</p>
<p>Currants, previous to putting them into the pudding, should be swelled or plumped: this is done by pouring some boiling water upon them: wash them well, and lay them on a sieve or cloth before the fire, pick them clean from the stones;--this not only makes them look better, but cleanses them from all dirt.</p>
<p>Raisins, figs, dried cherries, candified orange and lemon peel, citron, and preserves of all kinds, fresh fruits, gooseberries, currants, plums, damsons, &#38;c. are added to batter and suet puddings, or enclosed in the crust intended for apple dumplings, and make all the various puddings called by those names.</p>
<p>Batter puddings must be quite smooth and free from lumps; to ensure this, first mix the flour with a little milk, add the remainder by degrees and then the other ingredients.</p>
<pb n="85" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=87"/>
<p>If it is a plain pudding, put it through a <implement>hair sieve;</implement> this will take out all lumps effectually.</p>
<p>Batter puddings should be tied up tight; if boiled in a mould, butter it first; if baked, also butter the pan.</p>
<p>Be sure the water boils before you put in the pudding, and keep it steadily boiling all the time;--if your pot or vessel sets in contact with the coals the pudding often burns.</p>
<p>Be scrupulously careful that your <implement>pudding cloth</implement> is perfectly sweet and clean; wash it without any soap, unless very greasy; then rinse it thoroughly in clean water after. Immediately before you use it, dip it in boiling water; squeeze it dry, and dredge it with flour.</p>
<p>If your fire is very fierce, mind and stir the puddings every now and then to keep them from sticking to the bottom of the saucepan; if in a mould, this care is not so much required, but keep plenty of water in the saucepean.</p>
<p>When puddings are boiled in a cloth, it should be just dipped in a basin of cold water before you untie the <implement>pudding cloth,</implement> as that will prevent it from sticking; but when boiled in a mould, if it is well buttered, they will turn out without. Custard or bread puddings require to stand five minutes before they are turned out. They should always be boiled in a mould or cups.</p>
<p>Keep your <implement>paste board,</implement> rolling pin, cutters, and tins very clean: the least dust on the tins and cutters, or the least hard paste on the rolling pin, will spoil the whole of your labour.</p>
<pb n="86" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=88"/>
<p>Things used for pastry or cakes should not be used for any other purpose; be very careful that your flour is dried at the fire before you use it, for puff pastes or cakes; if damp it will make them heavy.</p>
<p>In using butter for puff paste, you should take the greatest care to previously work it well on the <implement>paste board</implement> or slab, to get out all the water and buttermilk, which very often remains in; when you have worked it well with a clean knife, dab it over with a soft cloth, and it is then ready to lay on your paste; do not make your paste over stiff before you put in your butter.</p>
<p>For those who do not understand making puff paste, it is by far the best way to work the butter in at two separate times, divide it in half and break the half in little bits, and cover your paste all over: dredge it lightly with flour, then fold it over each side and ends, roll it out quite thin, and then put in the rest of the butter, fold it, and roll it again. Remember almays to roll puff paste from you.--The best made paste, if not properly baked, will not do the cook any credit.</p>
<p>Those who use iron ovens do not alway succeed in baking puff paste, fruit pies, &#38;c. Puff paste is often spoiled by baking it after fruit pies in an iron oven. This may be easily avoided, by putting two or three bricks that are quite even into the oven before it is first set to get hot. This will not only prevent the sirup from boiling out of the pies, but also prevent a very disagreeable smell in the kitchen and house, and almost answers the same purpose as a <implement>brick oven.</implement></p>
</section>
<pb n="87" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=89"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 274. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">An excellent Ketchup which will keep good more than twenty years.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take two gallons of <ingredient>stale strong beer,</ingredient> or <ingredient>ale,</ingredient> the stronger and staler the better; one pound of <ingredient>anchovies,</ingredient> cleansed from the intestines and washed, half an ounce each of <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> one quarter ounce of <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> six large roots of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>eschalots,</ingredient> and two quarts or more of <ingredient>flap mushrooms,</ingredient> well rubbed and picked. Boil these ingredients over a slow fire for one hour; then strain the liquor through a flannel bag, and let it stand till quite cold, when it must be bottled and stopped very close with cork and bladder, or leather. One spoonful of this ketchup to a pint of melted butter, gives an admirable taste and colour, as a fish sauce, and is by many preferred to the best Indian soy.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 275. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="blue dye">To die Cotton Yarn of a deep blue.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Take one pound of <ingredient>logwood</ingredient> chipped fine or pounded, boil it in sufficient quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> until the whole colouring matter is extracted; then take about one half gallon of this liquor, and dissolve in it one ounce of <ingredient>verdigris</ingredient> and about the like quantity of <ingredient>alum;</ingredient> boil your yarn meantime in the logwood water for one hour, stirring it well and keeping it loose.</p>
<p>Take out your yarn, and mix the half gallon containing the <ingredient>verdigris</ingredient> and <ingredient>alum</ingredient> with the <unclear>other; then</unclear> put your yarn into the mixture and boil it four hours; stirring it, and keeping it loose all the time, and taking it out once every hour, to give it air, after which dry it, then boil it in <ingredient>soap</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and it is done.</p>
<pb n="88" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=90"/>
<p>The foregoing preparation will die six pounds of cotton yarn an elegant deep blue. After which put as much yarn into the same liquor and boil it for three hours, stirring it as before, and you will have a good pale blue, <variation>or if you wish for an <purpose><alt synonym1="green dye">elegant green,</alt></purpose>

boil <ingredient>hickory bark</ingredient> in the liquor and it will produce it.</variation></p>
<p>This receipt has been proved satisfactorily from experience, and it is a cheap mode of obtaining the above mentioned colours.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="dutch">
<p>No 276. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Dutch Beef.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take the lean part of a <ingredient>round of beef,</ingredient> rub it well, all over with <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> and let it remain so five or six hours, turning it as many times in the pan or tray where it is placed; then, salting it well with common <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>saltpetre,</ingredient> let it remain a fortnight, only turning it once a day. At the end of that time, roll it up very tightly in a coarse cloth, set it in a <implement>cheese or other press</implement> for a day and a night, and hang it to dry in the smoke of a chimney where a wood fire is kept. It should be boiled in a cloth; and when cold, is to be cut off in thin slices for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 277. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A cheap and excellent Custard.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil in a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>lemon peel,</ingredient> a small stick of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and a couple of <ingredient>peach-leaves,</ingredient> sweeten it with a few lumps of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and rubbing down smoothly two tablespoonfuls of <ingredient>rice flour</ingredient> in a small basin of <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> mix it with the beaten <ingredient>yelk of a single egg,</ingredient> then take a basin of the <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> and well mixing it with the contents of the other basin, pour the whole into the remainder of the <ingredient>boiling milk,</ingredient> and keep stirring it all one way, till it begins to thicken, and is about to
<pb n="89" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=91"/>
boil; it must then instantly be taken off and put into a pan, stirred a little together, and it may be served up either together in a dish, or in <implement>custard-cups,</implement> to be eaten hot or cold.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 278. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Curious and simple manner of keeping Apricots, Peaches, Plums, &#38;c. fresh all the year.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Beat well up together equal quantities of <ingredient>honey</ingredient> and <ingredient>spring water;</ingredient> pour it into an earthen vessel, put in the <ingredient>fruits</ingredient> all freshly gathered and cover them up quite close. When any of the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is taken out, wash it in cold water, and it is fit for immediate use.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 279. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="tan stain for leather">Art of Dying or staining leather Gloves, to resemble the beautiful York Tan, Limerick die, &#38;c.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>These different hues of yellow brown, or tan colour, are readily given to leather gloves by the following simple process. Steep <ingredient>saffron</ingredient> in <ingredient>boiling hot soft water</ingredient> for about twelve hours; then, having slightly sewed up the tops of the gloves, to prevent the die from staining the insides, wet them over with a sponge or soft brush, dipped into the liquid.--The quantity of <ingredient>saffron,</ingredient> as well as of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> will of course depend on how much die may be wanted; and their relative proportions, on the depth of colour required. A common tea cup will contain a sufficient quantity for a single pair of gloves.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 280. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="blue color">Cheap and excellent Blue for Ceilings, &#38;c.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil slowly, for three hours, a pound of <ingredient>blue vitriol,</ingredient> and half a pound of the best <ingredient>whiting,</ingredient> in about three quarts of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> stir it frequently
<pb n="90" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=92"/>
while boiling, and also on taking it off the fire. When it has stood till quite cold, pour off the blue liquor; then mix the cake of colour with good size, and use it with a <implement>plasterer's brush</implement> in the same manner as whitewash, either for walls or ceilings.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 281. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Ready mode of mending cracks in Stoves, Pipes, and Iron Ovens.</purpose>

</p>
<p>When a crack is discovered in a stove, through which the fire or smoke penetrates, the aperture may be completely closed in a moment with a composition consisting of <ingredient>wood ashes</ingredient> and <ingredient>common salt,</ingredient> made up into a paste with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and plastered over the crack. The good effect is equally certain, whether the stove, &#38;c. be cold or hot.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<p>No 282. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Dairy secret for increasing the quantity of Cream.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Have ready two pans in <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> and on the new milk's coming, take out the hot pans, put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> into one of them, and cover it over with the other. This will occasion, in the usual time, a great augmentation of the thickness and quantity of the cream.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="medhealth">
<p>No 283. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Tincture for the Teeth and Gums.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Mix six ounces of the <ingredient>Peruvian bark</ingredient> with half an ounce of <ingredient>sal ammoniac.</ingredient> Shake them well a few minutes every time before the <ingredient>tincture</ingredient> is used. The method of using it is, to take a tea spoonful and hold it near the teeth; then with a finger dipped in it rub the teeth and gums, which are afterwards to be washed with warm water. This tincture not only allays the toothache, but preserves both the teeth and gums, and makes them adhere to each other.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="91" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=93"/>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 284. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">An admirable beverage for a weak constitution.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil as much <ingredient>pearl, or Scotch barley,</ingredient> in pure <ingredient>water,</ingredient> as will make about three pints, then straining it off, and, having in the meantime dissolved an ounce of <ingredient>gum Arabick</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mix them, and just boil the whole up together. The barley water need not be thick, as the gum will give it sufficient consistence. It must be used milk warm, and substituted as a common drink in place of beer, &#38;c. at <alt synonym1="meals.">meals</alt></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 285. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">French method of purifying rancid or tainted Butter.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Let the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> be melted and scummed as for clarifying, then put into it a piece of <ingredient>bread</ingredient> well toasted all over. In a minute or two the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> will lose its offensive taste and smell, but the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> will become perfectly fetid.</p>
</recipe>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 286. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Permanent Red Ink for marking Linen.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take half an ounce of <ingredient>vermillion,</ingredient> and a <measurement>drachm</measurement> of <ingredient>salt of steel,</ingredient> or <ingredient>copperas,</ingredient> let them be finely levigated with <ingredient>linseed oil,</ingredient> to the degree of limpidity required for the occasion. This ink, it is said, will perfectly resist the effects of acids, as well as of all alkaline lies. It may be made of other colours, by substituting the proper articles instead of vermillion, and may be used with either type, a <implement>hair pencil,</implement> or even a pen, but in the latter case it will be necessary to thin it still more than it can be done by oil, by the addition of <ingredient>spirits of turpentine,</ingredient> so as to enable it to flow.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="92" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=94"/>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 287. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Mode of whitening Straw for Bonnets.</purpose>

</p>
<p>In 1806 a new method of whitening straw was discovered in Germany. This consists of steeping it in <ingredient>muriatick acid</ingredient> saturated with <ingredient>potash.</ingredient> The straw thus prepared never turns yellow, is of a shining white, and acquires great flexibility.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="medhealth">
<p>No 288. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">For the cure of Corns, Callous Heels, &#38;c.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Melt any quantity of common <ingredient>soap,</ingredient> by putting it in small pieces into any vessel, placed in a saucepan of <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> over the fire.--When melted, add to it an equal quantity of <ingredient>coarse sea sand,</ingredient> sifted, however, from the very coarsest particles, still keeping it over the fire, until the sand becomes equally hot with the <ingredient>soap.</ingredient> Then pour it into a cup or glass, to serve as a mould, keeping the mould hot by means of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> or otherwise, until the mixture is completely pressed into a solid mass. When it becomes hard, this washball, rubbed occasionally with warm water, against corns, or callous heels, will render them quite soft and easy.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 289. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Preserved Apples.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Make a sirup of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> into which put a stick of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and some <ingredient>orange peel,</ingredient> clarify it with the <ingredient>white of an egg,</ingredient> boil it and strain it, then put in the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> whole, pared or otherwise, as you like, and stew them over a moderate fire till they look clear.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 290. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="dried pumpkin">An excellent way to preserve Pumpions.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil and strain them through a sieve fit for
<pb n="93" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=95"/>
pies, put them into dishes and dry them in the oven or sun till hard and dry--lay them up for use and they will keep for years. When to be used, dissolve it in milk and it is as good as when first boiled.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 291. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Arrow root jelly for sickness,</purpose>

</p>
<p>If genuine, is very nourishing, especially for weak bowels. Put into a saucepan half a pint of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> a glass of <ingredient>sherry,</ingredient> or a spoonful of <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> grated <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and fine <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> boil once up, then mix it by degrees into a <measurement>desert spoonful</measurement> of <ingredient>arrow root,</ingredient> previously rubbed smooth with two spoonfuls of <ingredient>cold water;</ingredient> then return the whole into the saucepan; stir and boil it three minutes.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 292. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Eggs for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>An <ingredient>egg</ingredient> divided, and the yelk and white beaten separately, then mixed with a glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> will afford two very wholesome draughts, and prove lighter than when taken together.</p>
<p><variation><ingredient>Eggs</ingredient> very little boiled or poached, taken in small quantity, convey much nourishment; the <ingredient>yelk</ingredient> only, when dressed, should be eaten by invalids.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 293. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Caudle for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Into a pint of <ingredient>fine gruel,</ingredient> not thick, put, while it is boiling hot, the <ingredient>yelk of an egg</ingredient> beaten with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and mixed with a large spoonful of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> a glass of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Mix by degrees. It is very agreeable and nourishing. Some like gruel, with a glass of <ingredient>table beer,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> &#38;c. with or without a teaspoonful of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 294. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A flour Caudle for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Into five large spoonfuls of the purest <ingredient>water,</ingredient> rub smooth one <measurement>desert spoonful</measurement> of <ingredient>fine
<pb n="94" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=96"/>
flour.</ingredient> Set over the fire five spoonfuls of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> and put two bits of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into it: the moment it boils, pour into it the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>water;</ingredient> and stir it over a slow fire twenty minutes. It is a nourishing and gently astringent food. This is an excellent food for babies who have weak bowels.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes">
<p>No 295. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To mull Wine.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil some <ingredient>spice</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> till the flavour is gained, then add an equal quantity of <ingredient>port,</ingredient> <ingredient><alt synonym1="Madeira,">Maderia,</alt></ingredient> or <ingredient>sherry,</ingredient> some <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg;</ingredient> boil together, and serve with <ingredient>toast.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 296. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Coffee milk for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Boil a <measurement>desert spoonful</measurement> of ground <ingredient>coffee,</ingredient> in nearly a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> a quarter of an hour; then put into it a shaving or two of <ingredient>isinglass,</ingredient> and clear it; let it boil a few minutes, and set it on the side of the fire to grow fine.</p>
<p>This is a very fine breakfast; it should be sweetened with <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> of a good quality.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" class2="medhealth">
<p>No 297. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Apple water for sickness.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Cut two large <ingredient>apples</ingredient> in slices, and pour a quart of <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> on them; or on <ingredient>roasted apples;</ingredient> strain in two or three hours, and sweeten lightly.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" ethnicgroup="moorish" region="ethnic" subregion="mediterranean">
<p>No 298. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">A Moorish method of cooking beef, as described by Captain Riley, the shipwrecked mariner.</purpose>

</p>
<p>"Mr. Willshire's cook had by this time prepared a repast, which consisted of <ingredient>beef</ingredient> cut into square pieces, just large enough for a mouthful before it was cooked; these were then rolled in <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> cut up fine, and mixed with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper;</ingredient> they were in the next place put on iron skewers and laid horizontally across a 
<pb n="95" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=97"/>
pot of burning charcoal, and turned over occasionally, until perfectly roasted:" [<emph rend="italic">Query.</emph>--Does he mean that the skewers be run through the pieces of meat? we think he must, as it would be difficult to make such small pieces lie <emph rend="italic">on the skewers,</emph> without falling through into the fire; especially when the meat came to be turned.] "This dish," continues Captain Riley, "is called <emph rend="italic">cubbub,</emph> and in my opinion far surpasses in flavour the so much admired beef steak; as it is eaten hot from the skewers, and is indeed an excellent mode of cooking beef."</p>
<p><emph rend="italic">Remark.</emph>--How would it do to cut up flakes here and there on our common steak pieces, and put under pieces of raw <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and fasten the flap down by means of little wooden pins or pegs, to be pulled out after cooking?</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 299. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To pickle Peppers.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take out the insides, put them into a brass kettle of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> let them scald, but not boil, for four days in succession, afterwards put them into <ingredient>cold vinegar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans">
<p>No 300. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Cucumbers, to preserve for Pickles.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Have a cask or tub to be called a pickle tub, never to be used for any other purpose. Cut your <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> from the vines with a sharp knife, leaving a short piece of the stem attached to each <ingredient>cucumber.</ingredient> Pour <ingredient>water</ingredient> on them and handle very carefully in the <ingredient>water</ingredient> for a few minutes, and then it may be turned off. Cover the bottom of your tub with <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> then put in a layer of <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> then <ingredient>salt</ingredient> again, and so alternately <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> until you
<pb n="96" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=98"/>
have finished picking. The juice of the <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> added to the dissolving <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> will generally give brine enough to keep the pickles covered; but if not, a very little <ingredient>water</ingredient> may be added. A cloth should always be laid in contact with the pickles so as to keep the top ones wet, thus preventing them getting soft and disposed to rot. Remember to use <ingredient>salt</ingredient> freely--you cannot get in too much. <ingredient>Cucumbers</ingredient> put down in this manner will keep for years.</p>
<p>When you wish to add <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> to your <ingredient>cucumbers,</ingredient> take up such number as you please from the salt pickle above described, freshen them and put on <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> The following course is recommended: The <ingredient>water</ingredient> in which they are put to freshen should be changed every day; and if it be in the winter time let the vessel stand in the cellar where the <ingredient>water</ingredient> will not freeze. A week or ten days are required to freshen--tasting will determine when fresh enough. In one or two of the last changes, <ingredient>hot water</ingredient> may be used; this will make the <ingredient>cucumbers</ingredient> green, and more effectually remove any remains of saltish taste.</p>
<p>Prepare your <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> by putting in <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and if you please add <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> boil it, and pour on hot; the next day you have pickles.</p>
<p>N. B. Save your old brine until <ingredient>cucumber</ingredient> time again, scald and scum, in a brass kettle, and when cold it is ready to receive <ingredient>cucumbers.</ingredient> After your tub is filled add <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> This old brine is said to be better than new, and the repetition can be continued from year to year.</p>
</recipe>
<pb n="97" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=99"/>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 301. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To give meat a red colour, and impregnate it with agreeable vegetable flavours.</purpose>

</p>
<p>If you wish it red, or if you want to keep it a long time, rub it first with <ingredient>salt petre</ingredient> and <ingredient>moist sugar;</ingredient> the <ingredient>salt petre</ingredient> must be pounded fine, and the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> mixed with it, and the mixture made warm before the fire; mix one ounce of this mixture with one pound of <ingredient>common salt,</ingredient> rub this well into the meat as before directed.</p>
<p><variation>You can if you wish, impregnate the meat with a very agreeable vegetable flavour, by pounding some <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> and an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> with the salts, and if you choose, you can add a quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>black pepper</ingredient> and some <ingredient><alt synonym1="allspice">alspice</alt></ingredient> with the <ingredient>sweet herbs</ingredient> and salts; incorporate these ingredients by pounding them together in a mortar, then rub the meat well with the above mixture, turning it and rubbing it every day for a fortnight. This you will find will keep any length of time.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 302. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve fish by sugar.</purpose>

</p>
<p><ingredient>Fish</ingredient> may be preserved in a dried state, and perfectly fresh, by means of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> alone, and even with a very small quantity of it.</p>
<p>Fresh <ingredient>fish</ingredient> may be kept in that state for some days, so as to be as good when boiled, as if just caught. If dried and kept free from mouldiness, there seems no limit to their preservation; and they are much better in this way than when salted. The <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> gives no disagreeable taste.</p>
<p><variation>This process is particularly valuable in making what is called <purpose>kippered salmon;</purpose>

</variation> and the fish preserved in this manner are far superior
<pb n="98" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=100"/>
in quality and flavour, to those which are salted or smoked. If desired, as much <ingredient>salt</ingredient> may be used as to give the taste required; but this substance does not conduce to their preservation.</p>
<p>In the preparation, it is barely necessary to open the fish, and to apply the sugar to the muscular parts, placing it in a horizontal position for two or three days, that this substance may penetrate. After this it may be dried; and it is only further necessary to wipe and ventilate it occasionally, to prevent mouldiness.</p>
<p>A table spoonful of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> is sufficient in this manner, for a <ingredient>salmon</ingredient> of five or six pounds weight, and if <ingredient>salt</ingredient> is desired, a teaspoonful or more may be added; <ingredient>salt petre</ingredient> may be used instead, in the same proportion, if it is desired to make the kipper hard.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="meatfishgame">
<p>No 303. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Easy method of preserving animal food sweet for several days, in the height of summer.</hd></p>
<p>Veal, mutton, beef, or venison, may be kept for nine or ten days, perfectly sweet and good, in the heat of summer, by lightly covering the same with bran, and hanging it up in a high and windy room; therefore, a cupboard full of small holes, or a wire safe, so as the wind may have a passage through, is recommended to be placed in such a room, to keep away the flies.</p>
</section>
<section class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 304. <hd rend="italic" align="center">How to use Nutmegs.</hd></p>
<p>In grating a nutmeg, if you begin at the end next to the stem, it will generally be hollow all the way through, and will be apt to 
<pb n="99" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=101"/>
break. If you begin at the other end, it will be solid all the way through.</p>
</section>
<formula class="medhealth">
<p>No 305. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Castor oil made palatable.</purpose>

</p>
<p>The papers say, boil <ingredient>castor oil</ingredient> a few minutes in an equal quantity of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and sweeten it. When cool, stir it well, and the taste of it is remarkably pleasant.</p>
<p>Whether this preparation impairs the quality or efficacy of the oil, is not mentioned.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 306. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">The Peach Tree, how to guard against insects.</purpose>

</p>
<p>It is generally known that worms, near the surface of the earth, destroy them by eating the bark; the object is therefore to find a preventive, in order that the trees may become aged in a healthy state.</p>
<p>It is evident that these worms pass through the common change, and assume the form of <emph rend="italic">millers,</emph> early in the summer, and deposite their eggs in the bark as low as they can find access to it; and that the worms proceeding from them, begin to operate in the latter part of the summer, when they have been found the size of a common pin. If suffered to remain they grow to the thickness of a rye straw; each of them girdles the tree about an inch, and the wood from the wound to the heart dies. Hence it is, that a single wound impairs the vigor of the tree, and a number of them kill it. The point to be gained, is to protect the tree from the millers, and by a simple method, we have succeeded for several years, which is recommended with full confidence.</p>
<p>About the first of May remove the <ingredient>earth</ingredient> from the body of the tree, and shirt it to the
<pb n="100" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=102"/>
height of 15 or 16 inches, in such manner as to exclude the millers, burying the lower part of it in the earth. We have used <ingredient>straw</ingredient> cut to the length and about half an inch in thickness, bound on with twine. This should be removed about the first of September, as we have sometimes found the young worms in the upper part of the straw, being then readily discovered on the surface of the bark, covered by a little gum. The process should be commenced when the tree is young--they have been found in a rapid growth the first fall after it sprouted. Thus a few minutes in a year devoted to a tree, will protect it against this cause of decay--a very trifling expense compared with the value of this healthy and delicious fruit.</p>
</formula>
<section class1="generalnonfood">
<p>No 307. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Useful remarks on Heat, &#38;c.</hd></p>
<p>All who know any thing of a thermometer, must have learned that it is an instrument for measuring heat. The point at which thermometers are graduated is called <emph rend="italic">zero,</emph> that is, a cipher, 0, or nothing; it is a point at which mercury stands when immersed in a mixture of snow and common salt A glass tube containing mercury or quicksilver is placed against a scale having lines to note the rise and fall of the mercury as it swells or shrinks by greater or less degrees of heat. These lines are called degrees, beginning at 0, <emph rend="italic">(zero,)</emph> and counting each way. No one ever saw a thing so cold, as it is called, but that there was heat in it. Farenheit's thermometer runs no farther than 40 degrees below <emph rend="italic">zero,</emph> (where mercury freezes,) and which is a greater intensity of cold than was ever known in the atmosphere,
<pb n="101" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=103"/>
still it is supposed that 1500 degrees below would only be about the degree to indicate the total absence of heat. This is <emph rend="italic">latent</emph> or <emph rend="italic">hidden</emph> heat in contradistinction to that brought about by artificial means, as by fire, &#38;c. At 32 degrees above <emph rend="italic">zero</emph> it is called the freezing point, 55 temperate, 76 summer heat, 98 blood heat, 102 fever heat, 176 spirits boil, 212 water boils. This is as far as it is useful to understand the scale of a thermometer in common concerns. Now with regard to water; at 212 degrees it boils, and it can be made no hotter let there be ever so much fire added. If the fire is made larger, the water will <emph rend="italic">boil away faster;</emph> but remains just so hot till it flies away in steam and turns to air.--This should furnish a useful hint to economists in fuel. A very small fire keeps water boiling after brought to a boiling heat, and unless evaporating the water at a great rate be an object, it is an utter waste of wood beyond what is sufficient to keep the water at this temperature. From the freezing point, 32 degrees, up to 40, and then from 40 to48 degrees, the expansion of water is just alike; that is, 39 and 41 degrees would fill similar spaces, and so on down to 32and up to 48; but beyond these points there is not this similarity. Expansion continues to a certain extent either from heat or cold; care should be taken therefore in filling kettles too full to heat, or in leaving water in vessels exposed to a very great degree of cold. Heat would overrun, cold would burst.</p>
</section>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>No 308, <purpose rend="italic" align="center">To preserve Plants from the effects of Frost.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Before the plant has been exposed to the
<pb n="102" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=104"/>
sun, or thawed, after a night's frost, sprinkle it well with <ingredient>spring water,</ingredient> in which <ingredient>sal-ammoniack</ingredient> or <ingredient>common salt</ingredient> has been infused.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="medhealth">
<p>No 309. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Remedy for a cough.</purpose>

</p>
<p>The following medicine for a cough has performed such extraordinary cures in private practice, that the possessor is induced to publish it for the benefit of society--Take six ounces of <ingredient>Italian or roll liquorice</ingredient> cut into small pieces, and put into an earthen jar with about one <measurement>gill</measurement> of the best <ingredient>vinegar;</ingredient> simmer together until the <ingredient>liquorice</ingredient> is dissolved; then add two ounces of the <ingredient>oil of almonds,</ingredient> and half an ounce of the <ingredient>tincture of opium,</ingredient> stir the whole well together, and it is fit for use.--Take two tea spoonfuls when going to bed, and the same quantity whenever the cough is troublesome in the day time.</p>
</formula>
<recipe class1="accompaniments">
<p>No 310. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">How to prepare Molasses for preserving fruits, &#38;c.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Take eight pounds <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> of good quality, eight pounds pure <ingredient>water,</ingredient> one pound <ingredient>coarsely powdered charcoal.</ingredient> Boil them together for twenty minutes, then strain the mixture through fine flannel double; put it again in the kettle with the <ingredient>white of an egg,</ingredient> boil it gently till it forms a sirup of proper consistence, then strain it again.</p>
</recipe>
<section class1="household">
<hd align="center" rend="bold"><alt synonym1="DYEING.">DYING.</alt></hd>
<p>N. B. The few following receipts are taken in full or in substance from "The Family Directory in the Art of Dying, by J &#38; R. Bronson," printed at Utica, 1826 a valuable and cheap work which every curious house-wife
<pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=105"/>
should have. It is for sale generally by the booksellers.</p>
<p>Let it be observed that brass, copper, or well tinned vessels should always be used in dying; iron would destroy most colours.</p>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 311 <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="red dye for wollens">To die a Scarlet Red or Woollen Cloth, Yarn, Shawls, Fringe, or any kind of Woollen articles.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>Before the directions are given to die this beautiful colour, it will not be improper to state that a strict attention to neatness, and a careful observance of the rules laid down will be necessary; which, if followed, there will not be the least difficulty to accomplish the dying of this colour in families.</p>
<p>To die one pound of woollen, it will require the following articles, which, when procured at the druggist's, each kind should be written upon to prevent any mistake in using them. Two ounces of <ingredient>spirits of nitre,</ingredient> half a drachm of <ingredient>salt petre,</ingredient> pounded, two drachms of <ingredient>salammonack,</ingredient> pounded, one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>grained tin,</ingredient> also, one ounce of <ingredient>cochineal,</ingredient> pounded fine, half a ounce of <ingredient>starch,</ingredient> four drachms of <ingredient>tumerick,</ingredient> pounded.</p>
<p>Use the same proportions to die any number of pounds.</p>
<p>In the first place, prepare the compound of <ingredient>aqua <unclear>fortis,</unclear></ingredient> which should be made at least two days before you colour the scarlet. It is prepared in the following manner, and the quantity of which is calculated to die one pound of woollen.</p>
<p>Take a clean glass bottle of a suitable size, put in two ounces of <ingredient>spirits of nitre,</ingredient> add to it as much clean <ingredient>rain water,</ingredient> also two <measurement>drachms</measurement> of
<pb n="104" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=106"/>
<ingredient>salammoniack,</ingredient> which is pounded fine, and half a <measurement>drachm</measurement> of fine <ingredient>salt petre.</ingredient> Shake them together until they are dissolved; then add one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>grained tin;</ingredient> these small pieces of tin are to be put in one at a time, letting it dissolve before putting in any more; so proceed until the whole is dissolved. After the compound is made, then stop the bottle close with a wax or glass stopper. In using it be careful to take the clear liquor only.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center">Directions to grain the tin.</purpose>

</p>
<p>Melt <ingredient>block tin</ingredient> over a fire, then pour it from a distance above of four or five feet slowly into a basin of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> By this process, the tin will be cast into thin and loose parts, and is then fit to be dissolved as before mentioned. Tin is sometimes procured at the druggists already grained; in that case, it is ready to be dissolved in the spirits of nitre or aqua <unclear>fortis.</unclear></p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="red dye">Dying the Scarlet.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>1. Prepare a tin, brass, or copper kettle with about five gallons of clean <ingredient>soft water;</ingredient> bring it nearly to a scalding heat, then add one ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> one third of an ounce of <ingredient>cochineal</ingredient> which is finely pounded and sifted through gauze, and four <measurement>drachms</measurement> of pounded <ingredient>turmeric.</ingredient> Make a quick fire, and when the liquor almost boils add nearly half of the clear compound already prepared, and mix it well with the die.</p>
<p>2. The liquor is now brought to a boil.--The cloth, yarn, or woollen articles being before well cleansed, wet and drained, is now to be entered: dip it while boiling for one hour and a half. If it is yarn or garments, they
<pb n="105" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=107"/>
are to be continually moved or stirred with a stick, and if cloth, where it is a sufficient quantity, it is to be run briskly on the reel.</p>
<p>3. The woollen is now to be taken out, drained, cooled, and rinsed in <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient>--Empty out the die, and add as much clean <ingredient>soft water</ingredient> as before; then dissolve half an ounce of <ingredient>starch</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and add to the <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the kettle.</p>
<p>4. Bring the <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a scalding heat and skim it; then add two thirds of an ounce of <ingredient>cochineal,</ingredient> being the remainder, also add a little before it boils the remainder of the prepared tin composition, of which you must be careful to use only the clear part, and when put in the die, it is to be well mixed.</p>
<p>5. The die is now brought to a boil, and the woollen entered, which is to be stirred about as before. Boil it about an hour and a half; it is then to be taken out and aired, then rinsed and dried.</p>
<p>N. B. Fulled cloth must be napped and sheared before it is died scarlet. After it is died and rinsed, then tenter it, and lay the nap with a clean brush. Press it in clean papers, not very hot, as that would tarnish the colour.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 312. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="red dye for woollens">To die a Crimson Colour on Woollen Cloth, Yarn, Flannel, Shawls, Network, Fringe, &#38;c.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>For one pound of woollen it will require the following articles, viz: one ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>cochineal,</ingredient> two <measurement>drachms</measurement> of <ingredient>salammoniack,</ingredient> one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> six ounces of <ingredient>wheat bran.</ingredient></p>
<pb n="106" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=108"/>
<p>Use the same proportions to die any number of pounds.</p>
<p>1. Prepare a brass or copper kettle with about four gallons of <ingredient>rain water</ingredient> or <ingredient>soft spring water;</ingredient> bring it to a scalding heat, then add one ounce of fine <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> pounded fine. The liquor is now brought to a boil, and the woollen entered and stirred about in the die, while boiling, for one hour and a half.</p>
<p>2. In the next place, take out the woollen and air it; then rinse it slightly in clean <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Empty away the liquor, and add as much clean <ingredient>soft water</ingredient> as before. When the <ingredient>water</ingredient> has become blood warm, add about six ounces of <ingredient>wheat bran,</ingredient> tied up in a bag.</p>
<p>3. Now bring the liquor to a moderate heat, and take off the scum as it rises to the top; then take out the bag and add one ounce <ingredient>cochineal</ingredient> that is pounded fine and sifted. The die is now brought to a boil, and the woollen put in and stirred or turned round while boiling for one hour, then take it out and rinse it in clear <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></p>
<p>4. The die is now to be emptied away, and as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> added as before. When the liquor is as warm as the hand can be endured in it, dissolve therein two <measurement>drachms</measurement> of <ingredient>salammoniack</ingredient> which is pounded fine: then enter the woollen, and move it about hastily for five minutes; it is then to be taken out and drained.</p>
<p>5. Now add one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> or about two spoonfuls; mix it well with the liquor, and when the die is almost scalding hot put in the woollen and move it
<pb n="107" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=109"/>
round for about ten minutes; it is then to be taken out, aired and rinsed; which completes a crimson that is permanent and beautiful.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 313. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="pink dye for woollens">For a Rose Colour, or Pink on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>For one pound of woollen. Two ounces of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> one ounce of <ingredient>tin composition,</ingredient> one third of an ounce of <ingredient>cochineal.</ingredient></p>
<p>Take two ounces of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> pounded, and one ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> dissolve these in a small quantity of <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> then add to this about one ounce of <ingredient>tin composition,</ingredient> and stir it <alt synonym1="well.">well</alt></p>
<p>Next put a suitable quantity of soft, clean <ingredient>water</ingredient> into a very clean brass kettle, bring it to a scalding heat, then add one third of an ounce of best bright <ingredient>cochineal,</ingredient> pounded fine, and sifted through a piece of gauze. Boil fifteen minutes, stir it and add the alum liquor and stir again; now enter the woollen, and work it one hour and a half at a gentle boil. For a very full pink it will require half an ounce of <ingredient>cochineal,</ingredient> per pound of woollen: dry in the shade.</p>
<p>N. B. The woollen must be equally moist when put in the die.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 314. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="green dye for woollens">Green on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>To die one pound of cloth, yarn, flannel, or any kind of woollen articles, it will require the following ingredients:</p>
<p>One ounce and a quarter of <ingredient>oil of vitriol,</ingredient> one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>indigo,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> eight ounces of <ingredient>fustic.</ingredient></p>
<p>In the first place prepare the chymic or
<pb n="108" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=110"/>
compound of <ingredient>oil of vitriol</ingredient> and <ingredient>indigo,</ingredient> which is made in the following manner.</p>
<p>Take a glazed earthen cup or pot of a suitable size, and put in one ounce and a quarter of <ingredient>oil of vitriol,</ingredient> then add to it one quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>Spanish flote</ingredient> or best <ingredient>Bengal indigo,</ingredient> which is to be pounded fine and sifted; then stir the mixture hastily with a stick, which is necessary in order to mix it well and produce a regular fermentation; this should be done until it has done working; then add half a table spoonful of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and mix it together and it will be fit for use in one day.</p>
<p>Should the compound not work or ferment after stirring it, you may conclude the <ingredient>oil of vitriol</ingredient> is not good, and had better not be used.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p><purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="green dye">Dying the Green.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>1. Prepare either an iron, brass or copper kettle, with three gallons of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> which is sufficient for one pound of Woollen. When the <ingredient>water</ingredient> is scalding hot, add one ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>alum;</ingredient> then bring it to a boil and put in the woollen; boil it about one hour and a half, stirring it in the liquor occasionally during that time. It is then to be taken out, drained and aired.</p>
<p>2. You will now add some <ingredient>water</ingredient> to the kettle to make up the deficiency caused by boiling; then add to the liquor two thirds of the compound of <ingredient>oil of vitriol</ingredient> and <ingredient>indigo;</ingredient> mix it well with the liquor, then put in the woollen, keeping the liquor at only a scalding heat, and often moving it about in the die. When the woollen has been in the die half an hour, it is to be taken out, aired and rinsed.</p>
<p>3. In the next place add eight ounces of <ingredient>fustick
<pb n="109" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=111"/>
chips</ingredient> to the liquor, which are to be put loosely in a thin coarse bag, and boiled about an hour and a half. The bag is then to be taken out, and the woollen put in and boild gently little more than an hour, airing the woollen once in that time. It is then to be taken out and aired.</p>
<p>4. You will find at this time you have produced a green. Should it be found to bear too much on the yellow, then add a little more of the compound to the die, and put in the woollen again; or if it is too much on the blue shade, boil up a little more <ingredient>fustick</ingredient> in the liquor. In this way you may vary the shade according to your fancy. If you want a light green, use the less <ingredient>fustick</ingredient> and compound. After it is died, air and rinse it.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 315. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="black dye for woollens">To die a common Black on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>For twenty yards, or sixteen pounds of cloth or yarn, it will require two pounds and a half of <ingredient>copperas,</ingredient> two ounces of <ingredient>blue vitriol,</ingredient> eight pounds of <ingredient>logwood,</ingredient> two pounds of <ingredient>fustick.</ingredient></p>
<p>Use the same proportions to die any number of pounds.</p>
<p>1. Prepare a kettle with a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to admit your woollen to be worked in the die without being crowded; bring the <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a scalding heat, then put in the cloth or yarn for a few minutes. When it is wet thoroughly, take it out and drain it.</p>
<p>2. In the next place put in two ounces of <ingredient>blue vitriol.</ingredient> When both are entirely dissolved, bring the liquor to a gentle boil, stir up the die and put in the cloth or yarn. (In dying woollen yarn, observe that it should often be stirred about in the die with a stick: the same
<pb n="110" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=112"/>
way also should be practiced in dying small quantities of flannel cloth; but it will be found necessary to use a reel to die cloth in large quantities;) run the cloth for one hour, and air it once in that time; it is then to be taken out, aired, and rinsed well.</p>
<p>3. The <ingredient>copperas</ingredient> liquor is now to be emptied away and the kettle rinsed and filled nearly full of <ingredient>water;</ingredient> then add eight pounds of <ingredient>logwood chips</ingredient> and two pounds of <ingredient>fustick chips,</ingredient> which are to be boiled about two hours, then add some <ingredient>water</ingredient> and take out the chips.</p>
<p>4. The cloth is now to be put in and run while boiling for half an hour; then take it out and air it. Add half a pound of <ingredient>copperas</ingredient> to the die, and when it is dissolved, enter the woollen and run it for half an hour longer; then air; rinse and scour it well.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 316. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="red dye for woollens">To die Madder Red on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>To die one pound of goods, take three ounces <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> eight ounces <ingredient>madder,</ingredient> half an ounce of <ingredient>stone lime,</ingredient> (and the same proportions for a larger quantity.)--There are three processes to obtain this colour. The</p>
<p>1st. Is to communicate the <emph rend="italic">mordant</emph> or <emph rend="italic">set</emph> to the goods, as follows: Take the three ounces <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> break fine, and the one ounce <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> put the same into five gallons of <ingredient>soft water,</ingredient> in a brass or copper kettle, and after bringing up to a boil, put in the goods and boil two hours, when they are taken out, aired and rinsed and the liquor thrown away.</p>
<p>2ndly. Take the eight ounces of (good) <ingredient>madder,</ingredient> break fine, put into same kind of kettle and same quantity of <ingredient>water</ingredient> as aforesaid, bring
<pb n="111" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=113"/>
the die up to a scalding heat, but not to boil, put in the goods and let them remain in one hour at the same heat; stir about the goods well whilst in the die, take them out, air and rinse as before.</p>
<p>3dly. Add to the die just described half a pint clean lime water made by slacking the half ounce of <ingredient>stone lime,</ingredient> and after settling pour off the clean part into the die. The die being again at the scalding heat put in the goods for about ten minutes take out and rinse immediately.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 317. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="yellow dye for woollens">Yellow on woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>To die one pound; three ounces <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> one pound of <ingredient>fustick;</ingredient>--proceed exactly as with madder red, except as varied, see below, by</p>
<p>1stly. Using the <ingredient>alum</ingredient> and <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> four gallons <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil an hour and a half.</p>
<p>2ndly. Tie the <ingredient>fustick chips</ingredient> in a coarse cloth bag, and put to four gallons <ingredient>water,</ingredient> boil two hours, when the goods are to go in for one hour, boiling the while.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 318.<purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="red dye for woollens">Nicaragua Red on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>To die one pound, three ounces <ingredient>alum,</ingredient> one ounce <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> eight ounces <ingredient>nicaragua;</ingredient> proceed as with madder red, except as follows, by</p>
<p>1stly. Two pails <ingredient>water,</ingredient> scalding heat, add <ingredient>alum</ingredient> pounded, <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> boil, put in goods, boil one hour and a half.</p>
<p>2ndly. Two pails <ingredient>water,</ingredient> <ingredient>nicaragua chips</ingredient> in a coarse bag, boil one and a half hours, take out the chips put in the goods, boil gently one hour, keep stirring, take out &#38;c.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="112" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=114"/>
<formula class="household">
<p>No 319. <purpose rend="italic" align="center"><alt synonym1="orange dye for woollens">Orange colour on Woollen.</alt></purpose>

</p>
<p>To die one pound of goods, one ounce <ingredient>annatto</ingredient> or <ingredient>otter,</ingredient> two ounces <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> proceed exactly as with <ingredient>madder red,</ingredient> except as varied, see below, by</p>
<p>1stly. Proper kettle, two and a half gallons <ingredient>water,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>annatto</ingredient> cut fine, tied in a thin cloth bag, add the <ingredient>pearlash,</ingredient> boil one hour.</p>
<p>2dly. Take out the annatto bag, and put in your goods, stir around, scalding heat, one hour, take out rinse, &#38;c.</p>
</formula>
</section>
<section class1="farmgarden">
<p>No 320. <purpose rend="italic" align="center">Some of the most probable methods of preventing damage to trees &#38;c. by sundry insects.</purpose></p>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>Some vegetables are offensive to all insects; such as the <ingredient>elder,</ingredient> especially the dwarf kind, the <ingredient>onion,</ingredient> <ingredient>tansy,</ingredient> and <ingredient>tobacco,</ingredient> except to the worm that preys upon that plant. The juice of these may therefore be applied, with effect in <purpose>repelling insects;</purpose>

and sometimes the plants themselves, while green, or when reduced to powder, particularly the latter when made into snuff.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>Set an <ingredient>onion</ingredient> in the centre of a <purpose>hill of cucumbers, squashes, melons, &#38;c. and it will effectually keep off the yellow striped bug, that preys upon those plants while young.</purpose>

<variation>Perhaps to sow a few <ingredient>tobacco or onion seeds</ingredient> in the hill, when planting, would have the same effect; and the growing plants from these seeds could be taken away, when no longer wanted as protectors.</variation></p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>Of other substances, <ingredient>sulpher</ingredient> is perhaps the most effectual, as every kind of <purpose><alt synonym1="repelling insects">insect</alt></purpose>

has an utter aversion to it.</p>
</formula>
<pb n="113" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=115"/>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p><ingredient>Powdered quicklime</ingredient> is <purpose><alt synonym1="repelling insects">deadly to many insects, and perhaps offensive to all.</alt></purpose>

</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p><ingredient>Whitewash,</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>sulpher</ingredient> added; <variation><ingredient>urine</ingredient> kept until quite offensive added to <ingredient>soap suds</ingredient> and <ingredient>cowdung;</ingredient></variation> <variation>a strip of <ingredient>sheepskin</ingredient> with the wool outwards, combed loose, bound tight;</variation> <variation>a ring of <ingredient>tar</ingredient> and <ingredient>oil;</ingredient></variation> <variation>a strip of <ingredient>oiled paper</ingredient> with the lower edge standing out like the rim of a hat, well greased with soft <ingredient>grease</ingredient> or <ingredient>oil;</ingredient></variation> all are said to be good <purpose><alt synonym1="repelling insects from trees">preventives by forming rings or bandages around the bodies of trees,</alt></purpose>

from three to four inches wide.</p>
<p><variation>A strong decoction of <ingredient>tobacco,</ingredient> or <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> <ingredient>old urine,</ingredient> <ingredient>soapsuds,</ingredient> either of these applied boiling hot to the roots of trees, after first taking the earth away so as to give free access to the parts where the insect lies which is to come up and do the mischief, is said to be effectual. All to be done early in the spring.</variation></p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>It is said that <purpose>caterpillars</purpose>

will take shelter under woollen rags, when put on trees where they resort; from which they can be easily taken and destroyed.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p><purpose>Gardens that are infested year after year with worms and vermin of every kind</purpose>

are much benefitted by sowing over with <ingredient>salt</ingredient> at the time they are spaded in the spring, some days before seeds are put in.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p>QUERY.--How would a solution of <ingredient>Gum Arabick</ingredient> answer, made pretty slippery, with <ingredient>sulpher</ingredient> enough added to give colour, applied with a feather to plants? Let the composition be applied to the under sides of the leaves as well as all other parts above ground, and even close down into the dirt. The gum would
<pb n="114" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=116"/>
tend to keep the sulpher where it was put; and the night air and evaporation would keep the gum soft enough not to injure the plant by stopping the pores. The hint might be carried farther, by putting any thing that is said to be most offensive to <purpose><alt synonym1="repelling insects from plants">insects</alt></purpose>

with gum, and apply as aforesaid; dissolve the gum in <ingredient>old urine</ingredient>--mix <ingredient>soot</ingredient>--<ingredient>powdered quicklime</ingredient>--a dose of <ingredient>calomel,</ingredient> one or all of these.</p>
</formula>
<formula class="farmgarden">
<p><purpose>CANKERWORM.</purpose>

--The female of this insect comes out of the ground very early in the spring, and ascends the tree to deposit her eggs, which she does in suitable places in the bark; where they are brought forth, and the young brood live on the leaves of the tree.</p>
<p>The only effectual remedy is, to prevent the insect from ascending the tree; and this may be done in various ways; but the easiest perhaps, is as follows:</p>
<p>First scape off the shaggy bark round the body of the tree, to the width of two or three inches; then make up a mixture of <ingredient>lamp, tanner's, or blubber oil,</ingredient> with suitable proportions of <ingredient>sulpher</ingredient> and <ingredient>scotch snuff;</ingredient> and with a brush lay this on the scraped part forming a ring round the tree an inch or two wide; and no insect will ever attempt to pass this barrier, as long as the composition has any considerable moisture left in it.</p>
<p>Let it be repeated when it inclines to harden; though perhaps this is not necessary.--Let it be done early in the spring before the insect comes from the ground.</p>
</formula>
</section>
</chapter>
</body>
<back>
<div type="glossary">
<pb n="115" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=117"/>
<p>No 321. <hd rend="italic" align="center">Explanation of Terms</hd></p>
<list><item><term>ALAMODE,</term> <definition>according to the fashion or prevailing mode.</definition></item>
<item><term>CATSUP, or KETCHUP,</term> <definition>a liquor extracted from mushrooms, used as a sauce.</definition></item>
<item><term>CHAFING-DISH,</term> <definition>a dish or vessel to hold coals for heating any thing set on it; any portable grate for coals.</definition></item>
<item><term>CODLE,</term> <definition>to parboil, or soften by the heat of water; as by placing one vessel containing fruit into another containing water to communicate heat.</definition></item>
<item><term>FARINACEOUS,</term> <definition>consisting or made of meal or flour; as a FARINACEOUS diet, which consists of the meal or flour of the various species of corn or grain.</definition></item>
<item><term>FORCEMEAT,</term> <definition>a kind of stuffing, probably any sort of stuffing may be called forcemeat.</definition></item>
<item><term>FRUIT,</term> <definition>in cookery signifies, raisins, currants, prunes, figs, or any similar things cured by being dried with or without sugar. Green fruit is usually spoken of by its species, as apples, &#38;c.</definition></item>
<item><term>GRAVY,</term> <definition>the fat and other liquid matter that drips from flesh in roasting, or when roasted or baked, or a mixture of that juice with flour.</definition></item>
<item><term>GRITS,</term> <definition>the coarse part of any meal.</definition></item>
<item><term>TO POT,</term> <definition>to preserve seasoned meats in pots, as potted fowl, fish or fruit.</definition></item>
<item><term>SWEET-HERBS,</term> <definition>such herbs as are aromatick, (not spicy,) summer savory, sweet marjoram, thyme, parsley &#38;c. are sweet herbs.</definition></item>
<item><term>SWEET-MEATS,</term> <definition>any fruit preserved in sugar.</definition></item>
<item><term>SAUCE,</term> <definition>(is not Gravy, see GRAVY,) a composition to be eaten with food, for relish.</definition></item>
</list>
</div>
<div type="contents">
<pb n="table of contents" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=118"/>
<hd align="center" rend="bold">CONTENTS.</hd>
<list><item>ARROW ROOT, prepared for sickness, <ref target="notm062.jpg">60</ref></item>
<item>BEEF, to corn, <ref target="notm009.jpg">7,</ref> to pickle 100 pounds to keep a year, <ref target="notm009.jpg">7,</ref> to roast, <ref target="notm010.jpg">8,</ref> alamode, <ref target="notm011.jpg">9,</ref> steak to broil, <ref target="notm017.jpg">15,</ref> dried, <ref target="notm084.jpg">82,</ref> Dutch, <ref target="notm090.jpg">88,</ref> Moorish method to cook, <ref target="notm096.jpg">94</ref></item>
<item>BUTTER, clarified, <ref target="notm018.jpg">16,</ref> to purify, <ref target="notm093.jpg">91,</ref> burnt, <ref target="notm018.jpg">16,</ref> to preserve, <ref target="notm060.jpg">58</ref></item>
<item>BASS, to dress, and many other kinds of fish, <ref target="notm021.jpg">19</ref></item>
<item>BREAD, good rye and Indian, or wheat and Indian, <ref target="notm033.jpg">31,</ref> to make common wheat, <ref target="notm034.jpg">32,</ref> to make with grown flour, <ref target="notm049.jpg">47,</ref> a good bread <ref target="notm074.jpg">72</ref></item>
<item>BISCUIT, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> tea, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46,</ref> butter, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46</ref></item>
<item>BUNS, plain, <ref target="notm046.jpg">44</ref></item>
<item>BEER, for brewing spruce, <ref target="notm058.jpg">55,</ref> cottage, <ref target="notm074.jpg">72</ref></item>
<item>BEDBUGS, to keep clear of, <ref target="notm059.jpg">57</ref></item>
<item>BARLEY WATER, for sickness, <ref target="notm061.jpg">59</ref></item>
<item>BRASS, to clean, <ref target="notm083.jpg">81</ref></item>
<item>CAKES, thanksgiving, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> pearlash, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> cream, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> mineral, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> an excellent, <ref target="notm042.jpg">40,</ref> Tunbridge, <ref target="notm042.jpg">40,</ref> route drop, <ref target="notm042.jpg">40,</ref> clove, <ref target="notm042.jpg">40,</ref> common pancake, <ref target="notm043.jpg">41,</ref> rice pancake, <ref target="notm043.jpg">41,</ref> fritters, <ref target="notm043.jpg">41,</ref> Spanish fritters, <ref target="notm043.jpg">41,</ref> heart, <ref target="notm045.jpg">43,</ref> queen's drops, <ref target="notm045.jpg">43,</ref> Danbury, <ref target="notm046.jpg">44,</ref> Derby, or short, <ref target="notm046.jpg">44,</ref> Jackson's jumbles, <ref target="notm046.jpg">44,</ref> cream, <ref target="notm046.jpg">44,</ref> buckwheat, <ref target="notm047.jpg">45,</ref> rice snow balls, <ref target="notm047.jpg">45,</ref> federal pancake, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46,</ref> tea, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46,</ref> soft, in little pans, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46,</ref> a butter drop, <ref target="notm048.jpg">46,</ref> johnny, or hoe, <ref target="notm035.jpg">33,</ref> Indian slapjacks <ref target="notm036.jpg">34,</ref> loaf, <ref target="notm036.jpg">34,</ref> fruit, <ref target="notm036.jpg">34,</ref> <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> soft wafers, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> hard wafers, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> cup, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> Washington, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> jumbles, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> <ref target="notm047.jpg">45,</ref> wedding, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> rusk, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> crullers, miracles or wonders, <ref target="notm037.jpg">35,</ref> doughnuts, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> dough cake, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> good common, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> cake, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> muffins, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> sponge, <ref target="notm039.jpg">37,</ref> composition, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> whigs, or wigs, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> queen's, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> another queen's, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> Shrewsbury, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> federal, <ref target="notm040.jpg">38,</ref> pound, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39,</ref> minute, <ref target="notm041.jpg">39</ref></item>
<item>CHICKENS, to broil, <ref target="notm014.jpg">12</ref></item>
<item>CALF'S HEAD, to dress turtle fashion, <ref target="notm015.jpg">13,</ref> another way, <ref target="notm015.jpg">13</ref></item>
<item>CUTLETS, veal, <ref target="notm017.jpg">15</ref></item>
<pb n="117" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=119"/>
<item>CODFISH, for dressing, <ref target="notm022.jpg">20,</ref> a good way to cook, <ref target="notm025.jpg">23,</ref> another way to cook, <ref target="notm025.jpg">23</ref></item>
<item><alt synonym1="CHOWDER,">CHOUDER,</alt> <ref target="notm022.jpg">20</ref></item>
<item>CUSTARDS, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> boiled, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> rice, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> common baked, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> a sickbed, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> an excellent, <ref target="notm090.jpg">88</ref></item>
<item>CORNS, cure for, <ref target="notm094.jpg">92</ref></item>
<item>COOKIES, nice, that will keep good three months, <ref target="notm034.jpg">32,</ref></item>
<item>COFFEE, to make <ref target="notm058.jpg">56,</ref> to prepare, <ref target="notm070.jpg">68,</ref> a good substitute for cream to put in, <ref target="notm058.jpg">56,</ref> to burn, <ref target="notm058.jpg">56</ref></item>
<item>CHEESE, to keep in the winter, <ref target="notm059.jpg">57</ref></item>
<item>CABBAGE, lettuce, and other similar plants, to preserve, <ref target="notm067.jpg">65</ref></item>
<item>CRACKERS, to make, <ref target="notm047.jpg">45</ref></item>
<item>CASTOR OIL, to make palatable, <ref target="notm101.jpg">99</ref></item>
<item>COUGH, remedy for, <ref target="notm104.jpg">102</ref></item>
<item>CRACKS, to mend in stoves, pipes, and iron ovens, <ref target="notm092.jpg">90</ref></item>
<item>DRIPPINGS, to clarify, <ref target="notm016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item>DUMPLIN, an apple pudding, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> pear or plum, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28</ref></item>
<item>DYING, receipts for blue, <ref target="notm089.jpg">87,</ref> scarlet, <ref target="notm105.jpg">103,</ref> crimson, <ref target="notm107.jpg">105,</ref> rose or pink colour, <ref target="notm109.jpg">107,</ref> green, <ref target="notm110.jpg">108,</ref> black, <ref target="notm111.jpg">109,</ref> madder red, <ref target="notm112.jpg">110,</ref> yellow, <ref target="notm113.jpg">111,</ref> nicaragua red, <ref target="notm113.jpg">111,</ref> orange, <ref target="notm114.jpg">112</ref></item>
<item>DAIRY, secret for producing cream, <ref target="notm092.jpg">90</ref></item>
<item>EXPLANATION OF TERMS, <ref target="notm117.jpg">115</ref></item>
<item>FLOATING-ISLANDS, to make <ref target="notm044.jpg">42</ref></item>
<item>FROST, to preserve plants from, <ref target="notm103.jpg">101</ref></item>
<item>FOUL AIR, in wells, <ref target="notm075.jpg">73</ref></item>
<item>FEMALES'-DRESS, to put out when on fire, <ref target="notm079.jpg">77</ref></item>
<item>FEATHER-BEDS, to take care of, <ref target="notm083.jpg">81</ref></item>
<item>GRAVIES, gravy for a stuffed pig, <ref target="notm013.jpg">11,</ref> for stuffed and roasted chickens, <ref target="notm014.jpg">12</ref></item>
<item>GENERAL-RULES, to be observed in boiling meats, &#38;c. <ref target="notm020.jpg">18,</ref> for putting butter and sugar into pastes, <ref target="notm036.jpg">34</ref></item>
<item>GINGERBREAD, soft, <ref target="notm038.jpg">36,</ref> soft, with fruit, <ref target="notm039.jpg">37,</ref> sugar, <ref target="notm039.jpg">37,</ref> hard, <ref target="notm039.jpg">37,</ref> orange, <ref target="notm039.jpg">37</ref></item>
<item>GRUEL, of grits, oatmeal, or Indian meal, <ref target="notm061.jpg">59</ref></item>
<item>GREASE-SPOTS, to take out of clothes, <ref target="notm068.jpg">66,</ref> <ref target="notm070.jpg">68</ref></item>
<item>GRASS, to kill in the seams of flagging, <ref target="notm078.jpg">76</ref></item>
<item>GLOVES, to die or stain, <ref target="notm091.jpg">89</ref></item>
<item>HAMS, a good pickle for, <ref target="notm009.jpg">7,</ref> to boil, <ref target="notm021.jpg">19,</ref> to keep thro' the summer, <ref target="notm084.jpg">82</ref></item>
<item>HEAT, remarks on, <ref target="notm102.jpg">100</ref></item>
<item>ICE-CREAM, <ref target="notm044.jpg">42</ref></item>
<item>ICING, for cakes, <ref target="notm044.jpg">42</ref></item>
<pb n="118" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=120"/>
<item>INSECTS, best methods for destroying, <ref target="notm070.jpg">68</ref></item>
<item>INK, red, for marking linen, <ref target="notm093.jpg">91</ref></item>
<item>JELLY, apple, <ref target="notm044.jpg">42,</ref> <ref target="notm047.jpg">45,</ref> currant, <ref target="notm057.jpg">55,</ref> new method, to make, <ref target="notm074.jpg">72</ref></item>
<item>JAM, raspberry, <ref target="notm045.jpg">43</ref></item>
<item>KETCHUP, excellent, keep a long time, <ref target="notm089.jpg">87</ref></item>
<item>LEACH, to put up, <ref target="notm060.jpg">58</ref></item>
<item>LARD, to try, <ref target="notm059.jpg">57</ref></item>
<item>MINCE-MEAT, <ref target="notm024.jpg">22</ref></item>
<item>MEAT, red, and vegetable flavours, <ref target="notm099.jpg">97</ref></item>
<item>MOLASSES, how to prepare for preserving fruits, <ref target="notm104.jpg">102</ref></item>
<item>MOTHS, to prevent, <ref target="notm075.jpg">73,</ref> furs to preserve from, <ref target="notm083.jpg">81</ref></item>
<item>MILDEW, to take out of linen, <ref target="notm080.jpg">78</ref></item>
<item>NUTMEGS, how to use, <ref target="notm100.jpg">98</ref></item>
<item>OYSTERS, to smother a fowl in, <ref target="notm014.jpg">12,</ref> to stew, <ref target="notm017.jpg">15,</ref> to fry, <ref target="notm018.jpg">16</ref></item>
<item>ONIONS, and other bulbous roots to keep, <ref target="notm066.jpg">64</ref></item>
<item>PORK, to salt, <ref target="notm010.jpg">8</ref></item>
<item>PAINTED WOOD-WORK, to clean, <ref target="notm077.jpg">75</ref></item>
<item>PEACH TREE, to guard against insects, <ref target="notm101.jpg">99</ref></item>
<item>PIES, beef steak pie, <ref target="notm023.jpg">21,</ref> lamb, <ref target="notm023.jpg">21,</ref> stew, <ref target="notm023.jpg">21,</ref> sea, <ref target="notm023.jpg">21,</ref> chicken, <ref target="notm024.jpg">22,</ref> save all, <ref target="notm024.jpg">22,</ref> tongue, <ref target="notm025.jpg">23,</ref> minced, <ref target="notm025.jpg">23,</ref> apple, <ref target="notm026.jpg">24,</ref> dried apple, <ref target="notm026.jpg">24,</ref> buttered apple, <ref target="notm026.jpg">24,</ref> currant, <ref target="notm026.jpg">24,</ref> potatoe, <ref target="notm027.jpg">25,</ref> pompion, <ref target="notm042.jpg">40,</ref> custard, <ref target="notm043.jpg">41,</ref> observations on, <ref target="notm084.jpg">82</ref></item>
<item>PUDDINGS, boiled rice pudding with fruit, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> baked rice, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> cheap rice, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> tasty Indian, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> another, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> another, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27,</ref> Sunderland, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> whitpot, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> bread, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> flour, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> boiled flour, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> cottage potatoe, <ref target="notm030.jpg">28,</ref> apple, <ref target="notm031.jpg">29,</ref> carrot, <ref target="notm031.jpg">29,</ref> winter squash, <ref target="notm031.jpg">29,</ref> pumpion, two ways, <ref target="notm031.jpg">29,</ref> orange, <ref target="notm032.jpg">30,</ref> lemon, <ref target="notm032.jpg">30,</ref> Marlborough, <ref target="notm032.jpg">30,</ref> a boiled plum, <ref target="notm032.jpg">30,</ref> sago, for sickness, <ref target="notm032.jpg">30,</ref> quince, <ref target="notm033.jpg">31,</ref> Eve's, <ref target="notm033.jpg">31,</ref> batter, <ref target="notm033.jpg">31,</ref> Nottingham, <ref target="notm033.jpg">31,</ref> observations on, <ref target="notm084.jpg">82</ref></item>
<item>PASTES, puff, for tarts and sweetmeats, nine in number, pages <ref target="notm034.jpg">32 and 33,</ref> referred to by number in other receipts. Puff to make rich, <ref target="notm036.jpg">34,</ref> sticking paste, <ref target="notm076.jpg">74</ref></item>
<item>PICKLES, peppers, <ref target="notm097.jpg">95,</ref> cucumbers, <ref target="notm097.jpg">95</ref></item>
<item>PRESERVES, (SWEETMEATS,) beets, carrots, &#38;c. <ref target="notm047.jpg">45,</ref> quince, <ref target="notm045.jpg">43,</ref> quince in loaf sugar, <ref target="notm050.jpg">48,</ref> American citron, <ref target="notm049.jpg">47,</ref> strawberry, <ref target="notm050.jpg">48,</ref> and <ref target="notm053.jpg">51,</ref> white bullace, (wild sour plums,) pears, plums, or damsons, for
<pb n="119" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=not&#38;PageNum=121"/>
tarts, <ref target="notm050.jpg">48,</ref> marmalade, <ref target="notm051.jpg">49,</ref> gooseberries, damsons, or plums, <ref target="notm051.jpg">49,</ref> peaches, <ref target="notm051.jpg">49</ref> and <ref target="notm056.jpg">54,</ref> cherries, <ref target="notm052.jpg">50,</ref> raspberries, <ref target="notm052.jpg">50,</ref> currants, <ref target="notm052.jpg">50,</ref> plums, <ref target="notm053.jpg">51,</ref> apple, <ref target="notm053.jpg">51</ref> and <ref target="notm094.jpg">92,</ref> damsons, cherries, or grapes, <ref target="notm054.jpg">52,</ref> cucumbers, <ref target="notm054.jpg">52</ref></item>
<item>To PRESERVE, (NOT SWEETMEATS,) apples, fresh and good till the next summer, <ref target="notm054.jpg">52,</ref> green bush beens till winter, <ref target="notm054.jpg">52,</ref> parsley, <ref target="notm055.jpg">53,</ref> damsons, <ref target="notm055.jpg">53,</ref> plums and cherries, <ref target="notm056.jpg">54,</ref> peaches, <ref target="notm057.jpg">55,</ref> eggs from May to May, <ref target="notm058.jpg">56,</ref> <ref target="notm081.jpg">79, 79,</ref> grapes and other delicate fruits, <ref target="notm065.jpg">63,</ref> proper place to preserve roots and fruit, <ref target="notm066.jpg">64,</ref> preserving various fruits, <ref target="notm067.jpg">65,</ref> flowers and plants, <ref target="notm068.jpg">66,</ref> potatoes, <ref target="notm069.jpg">67,</ref> green peas till winter, <ref target="notm022.jpg">20,</ref> pumpions for pies, <ref target="notm094.jpg">92,</ref> parsnips, carrots, and beets, all winter, <ref target="notm080.jpg">78,</ref> apricots, peaches, plums, &#38;c. all the year, <ref target="notm091.jpg">89,</ref> fish by sugar, <ref target="notm099.jpg">97,</ref> animal food in warm weather, <ref target="notm100.jpg">98</ref></item>
<item>To ROAST, beef, <ref target="notm010.jpg">8,</ref> mutton, <ref target="notm010.jpg">8,</ref> veal, <ref target="notm011.jpg">9,</ref> lamb, <ref target="notm011.jpg">9</ref></item>
<item>To STUFF, and roast, or bake, a leg of veal, <ref target="notm012.jpg">10,</ref> a pig, <ref target="notm012.jpg">10,</ref> leg of pork, <ref target="notm012.jpg">10,</ref> a turkey, <ref target="notm013.jpg">11,</ref> a turkey or fowl, <ref target="notm013.jpg">11,</ref> a gosling, <ref target="notm013.jpg">11,</ref> four chickens, <ref target="notm014.jpg">12</ref></item>
<item>SUET, to clarify, to fry with, <ref target="notm016.jpg">14</ref></item>
<item>SAUCES, egg sauce, <ref target="notm019.jpg">17,</ref> lemon, <ref target="notm019.jpg">17,</ref> sage and onion or goose stuffing sauce, <ref target="notm019.jpg">17,</ref> parsley and butter, <ref target="notm018.jpg">16</ref></item>
<item>SHAD, to broil, <ref target="notm017.jpg">15</ref></item>
<item>SOUPS, beef's hock, <ref target="notm020.jpg">18,</ref> veal, <ref target="notm020.jpg">18,</ref> lamb's head and pluck, <ref target="notm020.jpg">18</ref></item>
<item>STURGEON, to dress, <ref target="notm022.jpg">20</ref></item>
<item>SOUSE, to make, <ref target="notm058.jpg">56</ref></item>
<item>SOAP, boiled, <ref target="notm060.jpg">58,</ref> cold, <ref target="notm060.jpg">58</ref></item>
<item>SOAP-GREASE, to keep, <ref target="notm060.jpg">58</ref></item>
<item>SICKNESS, caudles, jellies, milks, &#38;c. for, <ref target="notm093.jpg">91,</ref> <ref target="notm094.jpg">92,</ref> <ref target="notm096.jpg">94,</ref> <ref target="notm103.jpg">101</ref></item>
<item>STRAW, to whiten, <ref target="notm094.jpg">92</ref></item>
<item>SINKS, to prevent bad odours from, <ref target="notm076.jpg">74</ref></item>
<item>SPOTS AND STAINS, to remove from cotton and linen, <ref target="notm079.jpg">77</ref></item>
<item>STOPPLES, glass, to remove when tight, <ref target="notm079.jpg">77</ref></item>
<item>SHRUBS, to take care of, <ref target="notm081.jpg">79</ref></item>
<item>SHAWLS, Marino, to wash, <ref target="notm083.jpg">81</ref></item>
<item>TURKEY, fowl or goose, to boil, <ref target="notm021.jpg">19</ref></item>
<item>TARTS, apple, <ref target="notm028.jpg">26, 26,</ref> raspberry, with cream, <ref target="notm028.jpg">26</ref> currant and raspberry, <ref target="notm028.jpg">26,</ref> cranberry, <ref target="notm028.jpg">26,</ref> gooseberry, <ref target="notm028.jpg">26,</ref> grape, <ref target="notm029.jpg">27</ref></item>
<item>TEAS, balm, mint, and other, <ref target="notm063.jpg">61,</ref> beef, <ref target="notm064.jpg">62,</ref> veal <ref target="notm065.jpg">63,</ref> chicken, <ref target="notm065.jpg">63,</ref> toast and water, <ref target="notm065.jpg">63</ref></item>
<item>TINCTURE, for the teeth and gums, <ref target="notm092.jpg">90</ref></item>
<pb n="120" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=122"/>
<item>TREES, to transplant, <ref target="notm077.jpg">75,</ref> to preserve from insects, <ref target="notm114.jpg">112</ref></item>
<item>TUBS, &#38;c. to purify, <ref target="notm080.jpg">78</ref></item>
<item>To EXPEL, &#38;C. (see <ref target="notm082.jpg">page 80</ref>)</item>
<item>WHEY, white wine, <ref target="notm063.jpg">61</ref></item>
<item>WASHING, cottons and linen, <ref target="notm073.jpg">71,</ref> and <ref target="notm075.jpg">73,</ref> woollens not to shrink, <ref target="notm082.jpg">80</ref></item>
<item>WHITEWASH, excellent, <ref target="notm078.jpg">76</ref></item>
<item>WOODEN-WARE, to prevent cracking, <ref target="notm080.jpg">78</ref></item>
<item>WASH, blue, for ceilings, <ref target="notm091.jpg">89</ref></item>
<item>YEAST, cakes for yeast, to make, <ref target="notm059.jpg">57,</ref> to make, <ref target="notm074.jpg">72,</ref> the difference between kinds, <ref target="notm082.jpg">80</ref></item>
</list>
<p align="center">FINIS.</p>
</div>
<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=123"/>
</div>
<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=124"/>
<p align="center">Georgina McKelvey<lb/>Book..<lb/><unclear>Mooretown</unclear><lb/>County of <unclear>Lambton</unclear><lb/>C. W.</p>
<gap extent="half a page"/> 
<ednote>Handwritten inscription.</ednote>
</div>
<div type="other">
<pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=125"/>
</div>
<div type="backcover">
<pb n="back cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=notm&#38;PageNum=126"/>
</div>
</back>
</cookbook>