<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../cookbooks.xsl"?>
<cookbook type="general" class1="generalfood" region="general" bookID="1832sevf">
<meta><dcTitle>Seventy-Five Receipts for Pastry, Cakes, and Sweetmeats</dcTitle><dcCreator>Leslie, Eliza</dcCreator><dcSubject>Cookery, American.</dcSubject><dcDescription></dcDescription><dcPublisher>Boston, Mass. : Munroe and Francis</dcPublisher><dcContributor>Electronic edition created by Digital &#38; Multimedia Center, Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003.</dcContributor><dcContributor>Supplementary material by Jan Longone, Anne-Marie Rachman, Peter Berg, Yvonne Lockwood, and Val Berryman</dcContributor><dcDate>1832</dcDate><dcType>Text</dcType><dcFormat>xml-external-parsed-entity</dcFormat><dcFormat>jpeg</dcFormat><dcFormat>quicktime</dcFormat><dcIdentifier>http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/seventyfivereceipts/sevf.xml</dcIdentifier><dcSource>OCLC 5700552</dcSource><dcLanguage>en</dcLanguage><dcRelation>Digitized as part of "Feeding America: The Historic American Cookbook Project." Michigan State University Libraries, East Lansing, Michigan, 2002-2003. http://digital.lib.msu.edu/cookbooks/</dcRelation><dcCoverage>United States</dcCoverage><dcCoverage>Nineteenth century</dcCoverage><dcRights>The book digitized here was published in the United States before 1923 and is in the public domain according to U.S. copyright law. The digital version and supplementary materials are made available for all educational uses.</dcRights>
</meta>
<front>
<div type="frontcover"> <pb n="front cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=1"/></div>
<div type="other"> <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=2"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=3"/> <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=4"/></div>
<div type="titlepage"> <pb n="title page" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=5"/><p rend="ornate" size="smaller">Fourth Edition, 
<unclear>Empr</unclear></p><doctitle align="center">SEVENTY-FIVE<lb/><emph rend="bold" size="larger">RECEIPTS</emph><lb/>FOR<lb/>PASTRY, CAKES, AND SWEETMEATS</doctitle><docauthor align="center" size="smaller">BY MISS LESLIE, OF PHILADELPHIA.</docauthor><p align="center" size="smaller">FOURTH EDITION.</p><docimprint align="center" size="smaller">BOSTON:<lb/>MUNROE AND FRANCIS, NO. 128 WASHINGTON-STREET;<lb/>C.S. FRANCIS, NEW-YORK.<lb/>1832.</docimprint></div>
<div type="copyrightstmt"> <pb n="copyright statement" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=6"/><hd align="center" rend="bold"><gap extent="two words"/><unclear>ILY</unclear> BOOKS.</hd><p><gap extent="several words"/>the publishers of this work may be found the<gap extent="several words"/> books for families.</p><p><gap extent="one word"/><unclear>OOK'S</unclear> OWN BOOK: a complete Culinary Encyclopedia; 
<unclear>mprehending</unclear> all the receipts for cooking meats, fish, and fowl, and for composing every eminent kind of soup, pastry, preserves, and essences, that have been published or invented during the last twenty years; particularly those in the "Cook's Oracle," "Cook's Dictionary," and other systems of domestic economy: with numerous original receipts, directions for carving, &#38;c. &#38;c. By an AMERICAN HOUSEKEEPER. The whole alphabetically arranged. To which is added, A Complete System of Confectionary with receipts alphabetically arranged.</p><p>The PRACTICE OF COOKERY, adapted to the business of Every-Day Life. By Mrs. DALGAIRNS. Containing 1419 of the most useful receipts.</p><p>The HOUSE-SERVANTS DIRECTORY, or a Monitor for Private Families; comprising hints on the arrangement and performance of Servants' Work, with general rules for setting out Tables and Sideboards in first order. The art of Waiting in all its branches; and likewise how to conduct Large and Small Parties with order; with general directions for placing on Tables all kinds of Joints, Fish, Fowl, &#38;c.; with full instructions for cleaning Plate, Brass, Steel, Glass, Mahogany; and likewise, all kinds of Patent and Common Lamps; Observations on Servants' Behaviour to their Employers; and upwards of 100 various and useful Receipts, chiefly compiled for the use of House Servants, and identically made to suit the Manners and Customs of Families in the United States. With friendly Advice to Cooks and heads of families. By 
<emph rend="italic">Robert Roberts.</emph> With particular directions for burning LEHIGH, SCHUYLKILL, PEACH ORCHARD and other Anthracite Coal. A new Edition.</p><p>At the same place may be had all the recent publications on Cookery and family economy--among these are the COOK'S ORACLE, The FRUGAL HOUSEWIFE, &#38;c. &#38;c.</p><hd align="center">DISTRICT OF MASSACHUSETTS, TO WIT:</hd><p><emph rend="italic" align="right">District Clerk's Office.</emph></p><p>BE IT REMEMBERED, that on the ninth day of March, A.D. 1827", in the fifty-first year of the Independence of the 
<emph rend="italic">United States of America,</emph> Munroe and Francis, of the said District, have deposited in this Office the title of a book, the right whereof they claim as proprietors, in the words following, 
<emph rend="italic">to wit:</emph></p><p>"Seventy-Five Receipts for Pastry, Cakes, and Sweetmeats. By a Lady of Philadelphia."</p><p>In conformity to the act of the Congress of the United States, entitled, "An act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of maps, charts and books, to the authors and proprietors of such copies, during the times therein mentioned:" and also to an act, entitled. "An act supplementary to an act, entitled an act for the encouragement of learning, by securing the copies of maps, charts, and books to the authors and proprietors of such copies during the times therein mentioned; and extending the benefits thereof to the arts of designing, engraving, and etching historical and other prints."</p><p align="right">JOHN W. DAVIS, 
<emph rend="italic">Clerk of the District of Massachusetts.</emph></p></div>
<div type="preface"> <pb n="preface" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=7"/><hd rend="bold" align="center">PREFACE.</hd><p>The following Receipts for Pastry, Cakes, and Sweetmeats, are original, and have been used by the author and many of her friends with uniform success. They are drawn up in a style so plain and minute, as to be perfectly intelligible to servants, and persons of the most moderate capacity. All the ingredients, with their proper quantities, are enumerated in a list at the head of each receipt, a plan which will greatly facilitate the business of procuring and preparing the requisite articles.</p><p>There is frequently much difficulty in following directions in English and French Cookery Books, not only from their want of explicitness, but from the difference in the fuel, fire-places, and cooking utensils, generally used in Europe and America; and many of the European receipts are so complicated and laborious, that our female cooks are afraid to undertake the arduous task of making any thing from them.</p> <pb n="iv" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=8"/><p>The receipts in this little book are, in every sense of the word, American; but the writer flatters herself that (if exactly followed) the articles produced from them will not be found inferior to any of a similar description made in the European manner. Experience has proved, that pastry, cakes, &#38;c. prepared 
<emph rend="italic">precisely</emph> according to these directions will not fail to be excellent: but where economy is expedient, a portion of the seasoning, that is, the spice, wine, brandy, rosewater, essence of lemon, &#38;c. may be omitted without any essential deviation of flavour, or difference of appearance; retaining, however, the given proportions of eggs, butter, sugar, and flour.</p><p>But if done at home, and by a person that can be trusted, it will be proved, on trial, that any of these articles may be made in the best and most liberal manner at 
<emph rend="italic">one half</emph> of the cost of the same articles supplied by a confectioner. And they will be found particularly useful to families that live in the country or in small towns, where nothing of the kind is to be purchased.</p></div>
<div type="contents"> <pb n="table of contents" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=9"/><hd rend="bold" align="center">CONTENTS.</hd><list><hd align="center">PART THE FIRST</hd><item>Preliminary Remarks - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf015.jpg">7</ref></item><item>puff paste - - - - - _ 
<ref target="sevf017.jpg">9</ref></item><item>Common Paste - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf020.jpg">12</ref></item><item>Mince Pies - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf021.jpg">13</ref></item><item>Plum Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf022.jpg">14</ref></item><item>Lemon Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf023.jpg">15</ref></item><item>Orange Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf025.jpg">17</ref></item><item>Cocoa Nut Pudding - - - - 
<ref target="sevf025.jpg">18</ref></item><item>Almond Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf026.jpg">18</ref></item><item>A Cheesecake - - - - 
<ref target="sevf027.jpg">19</ref></item><item>Sweet Potato Pudding - - - - 
<ref target="sevf029.jpg">21</ref></item><item>Pumpkin Pudding - - - - 
<ref target="sevf029.jpg">21</ref></item><item>Gooseberry Pudding - - - - 
<ref target="sevf030.jpg">22</ref></item><item>Baked Apple Pudding - - - - 
<ref target="sevf031.jpg">23</ref></item><item>Fruit Pies - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf031.jpg">23</ref></item><item>Oyster Pie - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf033.jpg">25</ref></item><item>Beef Steak Pie - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf034.jpg">26</ref></item><item>Indian Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf035.jpg">27</ref></item><item>Batter Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf036.jpg">28</ref></item><item>Bread Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf037.jpg">29</ref></item><item>Rice Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf037.jpg">29</ref></item> <pb n="vi" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=10"/><item>Boston Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf038.jpg">30</ref></item><item>Fritters - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf039.jpg">31</ref></item><item>Fine Custards - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf039.jpg">31</ref></item><item>Plain Custards - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf040.jpg">32</ref></item><item>Rice Custard - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf041.jpg">33</ref></item><item>Cold Custards - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf042.jpg">34</ref></item><item>Curds and Whey - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf042.jpg">34</ref></item><item>A Trifle - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf043.jpg">35</ref></item><item>Whipt Cream - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf044.jpg">36</ref></item><item>Floating Island - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf045.jpg">37</ref></item><item>Ice Cream - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf045.jpg">37</ref></item><item>Calf's-feet Jelly - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf047.jpg">38</ref></item><item>Blanc-mange - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf049.jpg">40</ref></item><hd align="center">PART THE SECOND.</hd><item>General directions - - - - 
<ref target="sevf053.jpg">45</ref></item><item>Queen Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf055.jpg">47</ref></item><item>Pound Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf056.jpg">48</ref></item><item>Black Cake, or Plum Cake - - - 
<ref target="sevf058.jpg">50</ref></item><item>Sponge Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf059.jpg">51</ref></item><item>Almond Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf061.jpg">52</ref></item><item>French Almond Cake - - - - 
<ref target="sevf062.jpg">54</ref></item><item>Maccaroons - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf063.jpg">55</ref></item><item>Apees - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf064.jpg">56</ref></item><item>Jumbles - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf065.jpg">57</ref></item><item>Kisses - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf066.jpg">58</ref></item><item>Spanish Buns - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf066.jpg">58</ref></item><item>Rusk - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf068.jpg">60</ref></item><item>Indian Pound Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf069.jpg">61</ref></item><item>Cup Cake - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf069.jpg">61</ref></item><item>Loaf Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf070.jpg">62</ref></item><item>Sugar Biscuits - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf070.jpg">62</ref></item><item>Milk Biscuits - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf071.jpg">63</ref></item><item>Butter Biscuits - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf072.jpg">64</ref></item><item>Gingerbread Nuts - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf073.jpg">65</ref></item><item>Common Gingerbread - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf074.jpg">66</ref></item><item>La Fayette Gingerbread - - - - 
<ref target="sevf075.jpg">67</ref></item> <pb n="vii" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=11"/><item>A Dover Cake - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf076.jpg">68</ref></item><item>Crullers - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf077.jpg">69</ref></item><item>Dough Nuts - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf078.jpg">70</ref></item><item>Waffles - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf078.jpg">70</ref></item><item>Soft Muffins - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf079.jpg">71</ref></item><item>Indian Batter Cakes - - - - 
<ref target="sevf080.jpg">72</ref></item><item>Flannel Cakes - - - - 
<ref target="sevf081.jpg">73</ref></item><item>Rolls - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf081.jpg">73</ref></item><hd align="center">PART THE THIRD</hd><item>General directions - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf085.jpg">77</ref></item><item>Apple Jelly - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf086.jpg">78</ref></item><item>Red Currant Jelly - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf086.jpg">78</ref></item><item>Black Currant Jelly - - - - 
<ref target="sevf087.jpg">79</ref></item><item>Gooseberry Jelly - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf088.jpg">80</ref></item><item>Grape Jelly - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf088.jpg">80</ref></item><item>Peach Jelly - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf089.jpg">81</ref></item><item>Preserved Quinces - - - - 
<ref target="sevf089.jpg">81</ref></item><item>Preserved Pippins - - - - 
<ref target="sevf090.jpg">82</ref></item><item>Preserved Peaches - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf091.jpg">83</ref></item><item>Preserved Crab-Apples - - - - 
<ref target="sevf092.jpg">84</ref></item><item>Preserved Plums - - - - 
<ref target="sevf092.jpg">84</ref></item><item>Preserved Strawberries - - - - 
<ref target="sevf093.jpg">85</ref></item><item>Preserved Cranberries - - - - 
<ref target="sevf094.jpg">85</ref></item><item>Preserved Pumpkin - - - - 
<ref target="sevf095.jpg">87</ref></item><item>Preserved Pine-Apple - - - - 
<ref target="sevf096.jpg">88</ref></item><item>Raspberry Jam - - - - 
<ref target="sevf096.jpg">88</ref></item><hd align="center">APPENDIX</hd><item>Miscellaneous Receipts - - - - 
<ref target="sevf097.jpg">89</ref></item></list></div>
<div type="other"> <pb n="NONE OF THE ABOVE" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=12"/><p>As all families are not provided with scales and weights, referring to the ingredients generally used in cakes and pastry, we subjoin a list of weights and measures.</p><p rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">WEIGHT AND MEASURE.</p><list><item>Wheat flour - - one pound is - - one quart.</item><item>Indian meal - - one pound, two ounces, is one quart.</item><item>Butter--when soft - one pound is one quart.</item><item>Loaf-sugar, broken one pound is one quart.</item><item>White sugar, powdered one pound, one ounce, is one quart.</item><item>Best brown sugar - one pound, two ounces, is one quart.</item><item>Eggs - - - ten eggs are - - one pound.</item></list><p rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">LIQUID MEASURE.</p><list><item>Sixteen large table-spoonfuls are - - - half a pint.</item><item>Eight large table-spoonfuls are - - - one gill.</item><item>Four large table-spoonfuls are - - - - half a gill.</item><item>A common-sized tumbler holds - - - half a pint.</item><item>A common-sized wine-glass - - - - half a gill.</item></list><p>Allowing for accidental differences in the quality, freshness, dryness, and moisture of the articles, we believe this comparison, between weight and measure, to be as nearly correct as possible.</p></div>
</front>
<body>
<chapter class1="generalfood"> <pb n="NONE OF THE ABOVE" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=13"/><hd align="center">PART THE FIRST.</hd> <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=14"/><pb n="7" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=15"/><hd align="center" size="larger" rend="bold">PASTRY</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p align="center" rend="bold">PRELIMINARY REMARKS.</p><p>IN <purpose>making pastry or cakes,</purpose> it is best to begin by weighing out the ingredients, sifting the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> pounding and sifting the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> washing the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and preparing the <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p><p><ingredient>Sugar</ingredient> can be powdered by pounding it in a large mortar, or by rolling it on a <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board with a rolling-pin. It should be made very fine and always sifted.</p><p>All sorts of <ingredient>spice</ingredient> should be pounded in a mortar, except <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> which it is better to grate. If <ingredient>spice</ingredient> is wanted in large quantities, it may be ground in a mill.</p><p>The <ingredient>butter</ingredient> should always be fresh and very good. Wash it in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> before you use it, and then make it up with your hands into <ingredient>hard</ingredient> lumps, squeezing the <ingredient>water</ingredient> well out.</p><p>It the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> are to be stirred together, always do that before the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> are beaten, as (unless they are kept too warm) the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> will not be injured by standing awhile. For stirring them, nothing is so convenient as a <ingredient>round hickory</ingredient> stick about a <ingredient>foot</ingredient> and a half long, and somewhat flattened at one end.</p><pb n="8" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=16"/><p>The <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> should not be beaten till after all the other ingredients are ready, as they will fall very soon. If the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> are to be beaten separately, do the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> first, as they will stand longer.</p><p><ingredient>Eggs</ingredient> should be beaten in a broad shallow pan, spreading wide at the top. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> should be stirred in a deep pan with straight sides.</p><p>Break every <ingredient>egg</ingredient> by itself, in a saucer, before you put it into the pan, that in case there should be any bad ones, they may not spoil the others.</p><p><ingredient>Eggs</ingredient> are beaten most expeditiously with rods. A small quantity of <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> may be beaten with a knife, or a three-pronged fork.</p><p>There can be no positive rules as to the exact time of baking each article. Skill in baking is the result of practice, attention, and experience. Much, of course, depends on the state of the fire, and on the size of the things to be baked, and something on the thickness of the pans or dishes.</p><p>If you bake in a stove, put some bricks in the oven part to set the pans or plates on, and to temper the heat at the bottom. Large sheets of iron, without sides, will be found very useful for small cakes, and to put under the pans or plates.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="9" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=17"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose placement="heading" align="center" rend="bold"><ingredient>puff paste.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound and two ounces of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of the best fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--washed.</item><item>A little <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></item></list><emph rend="italic" size="smaller">This will make puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> for two Puddings, or for one soup-plate Pie, or for four small Shells.</emph></p><p>Weigh half a pound and two ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and sift it through a hair-sieve into a large deep dish. Take out about one fourth of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and lay it aside on one corner of your pasteboard, to roll and sprinkle with.</p><p>Wash, in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> half a pound of the best fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Squeeze it <ingredient>hard</ingredient> with your hands, and make it up into a round lump. Divide it in four equal parts; lay them on one side of your pasteboard, and have ready a glass of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></p><p>Cut one of the four pieces of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the pan of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Cut it as small as possible. Wet it gradually with a very little <ingredient>water</ingredient> (too much <ingredient>water</ingredient> will make it tough) and mix it well with the point of a large case-knife. Do not touch it with your hands. When the dough gets into a lump, sprinkle on the middle of the board some of the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> that you laid aside, and lay the dough upon it, turning it out of the pan with the knife.</p><p>Rub the rolling-pin with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and sprinkle a little on the lump of <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> Roll it out thin, quickly, and evenly, pressing on the rolling-pin very lightly. Then take the second of the four pieces of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and, with the point of your knife, stick it in little bits at equal distances all over the sheet of <ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p> <pb n="10" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=18"/><p>Sprinkle on some <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and fold up the dough. <ingredient>Flour</ingredient> the <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board and rolling-pin again; throw a little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> and roll it out a second time. Stick the third piece of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> all over it in little bits. Throw on some <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> fold up the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> sprinkle a little more <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on the dough, and on the rolling-pin, and roll it out a third time, always pressing on it lightly. Stick it over with the fourth and last piece of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Throw on a little more <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> fold up the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> and then roll it out in a large round sheet. Cut off the sides, so as to make the sheet of a square form, and lay the slips of dough upon the square sheet. Fold it up with the small pieces of trimmings, in the inside. Score or notch it a little with the knife; lay it on a plate and set it away in a cool place, but not where it can freeze, as that will make it heavy.</p><p>Having made the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> prepare and mix your pudding or pie. When the mixture is finished, bring out your <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> the board and rolling-pin, and roll it out with a short quick stroke, and pressing the rolling-pin rather harder than while you were putting the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in. If the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> rises in blisters, it will be light, unless spoiled in baking.</p><p>Then cut the sheet in half, fold up each piece and roll them out once more, separately, in round sheets the size of your plate. Press on rather harder, but not too <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Roll the sheets thinnest in the middle and thickest at the edges. If intended for puddings, lay them in buttered soup-plates, and trim them evenly round the edges. If the edges do not appear thick enough, you may take the trimmings, put them all together, roll them out, and having cut them in slips the breadth of the rim of the plate, lay them all round to make the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> thicker at the edges, joining them nicely and evenly,<pb n="11" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=19"/> as every patch or crack will appear distinctly when baked. Notch the rim handsomely with a very sharp knife. Fill the dish with the mixture of the pudding, and bake it in a moderate oven. The <ingredient>paste</ingredient> should be of a light brown colour. If the oven is too slow, it will be soft and clammy; if too quick, it will not have time to rise as high as it ought to do.</p><p>In making the best puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> try to avoid using more <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to sprinkle and roll with, than the small portion which you have laid aside for that purpose at the beginning. If you make the dough too soft at first, by using too much <ingredient>water,</ingredient> it will be sticky, and require more <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and will eventually be tough when baked. Do not put your hands to it, as their warmth will injure it. Use the knife instead. Always roll from you rather than to you, and press lightly on the rolling-pin, except at the last.</p><p>It is difficult to make puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> in the summer, unless in a cellar, or very cool room, and on a marble table. The <ingredient>butter</ingredient> should, if possible, be washed the night before, and kept covered with ice till you use it next day. The <ingredient>water</ingredient> should have ice in it, and the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> should be iced as it sets on the <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board. After the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> is mixed, it should be put in a covered dish, and set in <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> till you are ready to give it the last rolling.</p><p>With all these precautions to prevent its being heavy, it will not rise as well, or be in any respect as good as in cold weather.</p><p>The handsomest way of ornamenting the edge of a pie or pudding is to cut the rim in large square notches, and then fold over triangularly one corner of every notch.</p>
</recipe><pb n="12" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=20"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">COMMON <ingredient>PASTE</ingredient> FOR PIES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pound and a half of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>Three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--washed.</item></list><emph rend="italic" size="smaller" align="center">This will make one large pie or two small ones.</emph></p><p>Sift the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a pan. Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into two equal parts. Cut one half of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and cut it up as small as possible. Mix it well with the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> wetting it gradually with a little <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></p><p>Spread some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take the lump of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> out of the pan, <ingredient>flour</ingredient> your rolling-pin, and roll out the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> into a large sheet. Then stick it over with the remaining half of the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in small pieces, and laid at equal distances. Throw on a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> fold up the sheet of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it slightly, and roll it out again. Then fold it up, and cut it in half or in four, according to the size of your pies. Roll it out into round sheets the size of your pie-plates, pressing rather harder on the rolling-pin.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> your pie-plates, lay on your under crust, and trim the edge. Fill the dish with the ingredients of which the pie is composed, and lay on the lid, in which you must prick some holes, or cut a small slit in the top. Crimp the edges with a sharp knife.</p><p>Heap up the ingredients so that the pie will be highest in the middle.</p><p>Some think it makes common <ingredient>paste</ingredient> more crisp and light, to beat it <ingredient>hard</ingredient> on both sides with the <pb n="13" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=21"/> rolling-pin, after you give it the first rolling, when all the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is in.</p><p>If the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is very fresh, you may mix with the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> a <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">MINCE PIES.</purpose><list size="larger" align="indent1"><item>One pound and a half of boiled <ingredient>beef</ingredient>'s <ingredient>heart,</ingredient> or fresh <ingredient>tongue</ingredient>--chopped when cold.</item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> chopped fine.</item><item>Four pounds of <ingredient>pippin apples,</ingredient> chopped.</item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> stoned and chopped.</item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> picked, washed, and dried.</item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>One quart of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient></item><item>One quart of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>One <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>Two grated <ingredient>nutmegs.</ingredient></item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> &#32; &#32; }</item><item>A quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>cloves</ingredient> &#32; } powdered</item><item>A quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>mace</ingredient> &#32; }</item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>Two large <ingredient>oranges.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> cut in slips.</item></list>Parboil a <ingredient>beef</ingredient>'s <ingredient>heart,</ingredient> or a fresh <ingredient>tongue.</ingredient> After you have taken off the <ingredient>skin</ingredient> and <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> weigh a pound and a half. When it is cold, chop it very fine. Take the inside of the <ingredient>suet;</ingredient> weigh two pounds, and chop it as fine as possible. Mix the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet</ingredient> together, adding the <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Pare, core, and chop the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and then stone and chop the <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient> Having prepared the <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> add them to the other <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and mix the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> with the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet.</ingredient> Put in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and the grated peel and <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of the <ingredient>oranges.</ingredient> Wet the whole with the <ingredient>rose water</ingredient> and liquor, and mix all well together.</p><pb n="14" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=22"/><p>Make the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> allowing for each pie, half a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and three quarters of a pound of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Make it in the same manner as puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> but it will not be quite so rich. Lay a sheet of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> all over a soup-plate. Fill it with mince-<ingredient>meat,</ingredient> laying slips of <ingredient>citron</ingredient> on the top. Roll out a sheet of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> for the lid of the pie. Put it on, and crimp the edges with a knife. Prick holes in the lid.</p><p>Bake the pies half an hour in a brisk oven.</p><p>Keep your mince <ingredient>meat</ingredient> in a jar tightly covered. Set it in a dry, cool place, and occasionally add more <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> to it.</p><p>Instead of the <ingredient>heart</ingredient> or <ingredient>tongue,</ingredient> you may, if you choose, use part of a round of fresh <ingredient>beef.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>PLUM</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list size="smaller" align="indent1"><item>One pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> stoned and cut in half.</item><item>One pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> picked, washed and dried.</item><item>One pound of <ingredient>beef suet</ingredient> chopped fine.</item><item>One pound of grated <ingredient>stale bread,</ingredient> or, half a pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and half a pound of <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></item><item>Eight <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A glass of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A glass of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item></list>You must prepare all your ingredients the day before (except beating the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient>) that in the morning you may have nothing to do but to mix them, as the pudding will require six hours to boil.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, then put to them half the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and beat both together. Stir in gradually the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>bread.</ingredient> Next add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> by degrees. Then the <ingredient>suet</ingredient> and <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> alternately. <pb n="15" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=23"/> The <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> must be well sprinkled with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> lest it sink to the bottom. Stir very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Then add the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor, and lastly the remainder of the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Stir the whole mixture very well together. If it is not thick enough, add a little more grated <ingredient>bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> If there is too much <ingredient>bread</ingredient> or <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> the pudding will be <ingredient>hard</ingredient> and heavy.</p><p>Dip your pudding-cloth, in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> shake it out and sprinkle it slightly with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Lay it in a pan and pour the mixture into the cloth. Tie it up carefully, allowing room for the pudding to swell.</p><p>Boil it six hours, and turn it carefully out of the cloth.</p><p>Before you send it to table, have ready some blanched <ingredient>sweet almonds</ingredient> cut in slips, or some slips of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> or both. Stick them all over the outside of the pudding.</p><p>Eat it with <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> or with a <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> made of <ingredient>drawn butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p><p>The pudding will be improved if you add to the other ingredients, the grated <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of a large <ingredient>lemon or orange.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy">
<ednote>handwritten inscription</ednote><p>Lemon Pudding</p><p>1/2 lb butter &#38; Sugar 5 Eggs &#38; 2 Lemons</p><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">LEMON PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One small lemon, with a smooth thin rind.</item><item>Three eggs.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered white sugar.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of fresh butter--washed.</item><item>A table-spoonful of white wine and brandy, mixed.</item><item>A tea-spoonful of rose-water.</item><item>Five ounces of sifted flour, and a quarter of a pound of fresh butter for the paste.</item></list>Grate the yellow part of the rind of a small fresh lemon. Then cut the lemon in half, and squeeze the juice into the plate that contains the <pb n="16" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=24"/> grated rind, carefully taking out all the seeds. Mix the juice and rind together.</p>
<ednote>The following handwritten inscription appears on the bottom of page 15 in the original text.</ednote><p>6 Lemons will make 8 Puddings</p><p>Put a quarter of a pound of powdered white sugar into a deep earthen pan, and cut up in it a quarter of a pound of the best fresh butter. If the weather is very cold, set the pan near the fire, for a few minutes, to soften the butter, but do not allow it to melt or it will be heavy. Stir the butter and sugar together, with a stick or wooden spoon, till it is perfectly light and of the consistence of cream.</p><p>Put the eggs in a shallow broad pan, and beat them with an egg-beater or rods, till they are quite smooth, and as thick as a boiled custard. Then stir the eggs, gradually, into the pan of butter and sugar. Add the liquor and rose water by degrees, and then stir in, gradually, the juice and grated rind of the lemon. Stir the whole very hard, after all the ingredients are in.</p><p>Have ready a puff-paste made of five ounces of sifted flour, and a quarter of a pound of fresh butter. The paste must be made with as little water as possible. Roll it out in a circular sheet, thin in the centre, and thicker towards the edges, and just large enough to cover the bottom, sides, and edges of a soup-plate. Butter the soup-plate very well, and lay the paste in it, making it neat and even round the broad edge of the plate. With a sharp knife, trim off the superfluous dough, and notch the edges. Put in the mixture with a spoon, and bake the pudding about half an hour, in a moderate oven. It should be baked of a very light brown. If the oven is too hot, the paste will not have time to rise well. If too cold, it will be clammy. When the pudding is cool, grate loaf-sugar over it.</p><p>Before using lemons for any purpose, always roll them awhile with your hand on a table. This will cause them to yield a larger quantity of juice.</p>
</recipe><pb n="17" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=25"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>ORANGE</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One large <ingredient>orange,</ingredient> of a deep colour, and smooth thin <ingredient>rind.</ingredient></item><item>One <ingredient>lime.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of mixed <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Grate the yellow <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of the <ingredient>orange</ingredient> and <ingredient>lime,</ingredient> and squeeze the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> into a saucer or soup-plate, taking out all the <ingredient>seeds.</ingredient></p><p>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> as light as possible, and then stir them by degrees into the pan of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add, gradually, the liquor and <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and then by degrees, the <ingredient>orange</ingredient> and <ingredient>lime.</ingredient> Stir all well together.</p><p>Have ready a sheet of puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> made of five ounces of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Lay the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> in a buttered soup-plate. Trim and notch the edges, and then put in the mixture. Bake it about half an hour, in a moderate oven. Grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over it, before you send it to table.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COCOA-<ingredient>NUT</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list size="larger" align="indent1"><item>A quarter of a pound of cocoa-<ingredient>nut,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Three ounces and a half of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>whites</ingredient> only of six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>Half a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Break up a cocoa-<ingredient>nut,</ingredient> and take the thin brown <ingredient>skin</ingredient> carefully off, with a knife. Wash all the <pb n="18" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=26"/> pieces in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and then wipe them dry, with a clean towel. Weigh a quarter of a pound of cocoa-<ingredient>nut,</ingredient> and grate it very fine, into a soup-plate.</p><p>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and add the liquor and <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> gradually to them.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> only, of six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> till they stand alone on the rods; and then stir the beaten <ingredient>white of egg,</ingredient> gradually, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Afterwards, sprinkle in, by degrees, the grated cocoa-<ingredient>nut,</ingredient> stirring <ingredient>hard</ingredient> all the time. Then stir all very well at the last.</p><p>Have ready a puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> sufficient to cover the bottom, sides, and edges of a soup-plate. Put in the mixture, and bake it in a moderate oven, about half an hour.</p><p>Grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over it, when cool.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">ALMOND PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>sweet almonds,</ingredient> which will be reduced to a quarter of a pound, when shelled and blanched.</item><item>An ounce of blanched <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels.</item><item>The <ingredient>whites</ingredient> only, of six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of mixed <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Shell half a pound of <ingredient>sweet almonds,</ingredient> and pour scalding <ingredient>water</ingredient> over them, which will make the <ingredient>skins</ingredient> peel off. As they get cool, pour more <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> till the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> are all blanched. Blanch also the <ingredient>bitter almonds.</ingredient> As you blanch the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> throw them into a bowl of <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Then take them out, one by one, wipe them <pb n="19" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=27"/> dry in a clean towel, and lay them on a plate. Pound them one at a time to a fine <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> in a marble mortar, adding, as you pound them, a few drops of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> to prevent their oiling. Pound the bitter and <ingredient>sweet almonds</ingredient> alternately, that they may be well mixed. They must be made perfectly fine and smooth, and are the better for being prepared the day before they are wanted for the pudding.</p><p>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and add to it, gradually, the liquor.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>whites of six eggs</ingredient> till they stand alone. Stir the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> and <ingredient>white of eggs,</ingredient> alternately, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> and then stir the whole well together.</p><p>Have ready a puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> sufficient for a soup-plate. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> the plate, lay on the <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> trim and notch it. Then put in the mixture.</p><p>Bake it about half an hour in a moderate oven.</p><p>Grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">A CHEESECAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A gill of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of grated <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of mixed <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></item></list>Pick the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> very clean. Wash them through a colander, wipe them in a towel, and then dry them on a dish before the fire.</p><p>When dry take out a few to scatter over the <pb n="20" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=28"/>top of the cheesecake, lay them aside, and sprinkle the remainder of the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> with the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p><p>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Grate the <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and prepare the <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light.</p><p>Boil the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> When it comes to a boil, add to it half the beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and boil both together till it becomes a curd, stirring it frequently with a knife. Then throw the grated <ingredient>bread</ingredient> on the curd, and stir all together. Then take the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread</ingredient> off the fire, and stir it, gradually, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Next, stir in the remaining half of the <ingredient>egg.</ingredient></p><p>Add, by degrees, the liquor and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient></p><p>Lastly, stir in, gradually, the <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></p><p>Have ready a puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> which should be made before you prepare the cheesecake, as the mixture will become heavy by standing. Before you put it into the oven, scatter the remainder of the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> over the top.</p><p>Bake it half an hour in rather a quick oven.</p><p>Do not <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> the top.</p><p>You may bake it either in a soup-plate, or in two small tin patty-pans, which, for cheesecakes, should be of a square shape. If baked in square patty-pans leave at each side a flap of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> in the shape of a half-circle. Cut long slits in these flaps and turn them over, so that they will rest on the top of the mixture.</p><p>You can, if you choose, add to the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> a few <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> stoned, and cut in half.</p>
</recipe><pb n="21" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=29"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>SWEET POTATO</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quarter of a pound of boiled <ingredient>sweet potato.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A glass of mixed <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>A half-glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Pound the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> allowing a smaller proportion of <ingredient>mace</ingredient> than of <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></p><p>Boil and peal some <ingredient>sweet potatoes,</ingredient> and when they are cold, weigh a quarter of a pound. Mash the <ingredient>sweet potato</ingredient> very smooth, and rub it through a sieve. Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> alternately with the <ingredient>sweet potato.</ingredient> Add by degrees the liquor, <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Stir all very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> together.</p><p>Spread puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> on a soup-plate. Put in the mixture, and bake it about half an hour in a moderate oven.</p><p>Grate <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>PUMPKIN</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of stewed <ingredient>pumpkin.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> or a pint of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Stew some <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> with as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible. Drain it in a colander, and press it till dry. When cold, weigh half a pound, and pass it <pb n="22" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=30"/> through a sieve. Prepare the <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Stir together the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> to <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> till they are perfectly light. Add to them, gradually, the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor.</p><p>Beat three <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> alternately with the <ingredient>pumpkin.</ingredient></p><p>Cover a soup-plate with puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and put in the mixture. Bake it in a moderate oven about half an hour.</p><p>Grate <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over it when cool.</p><p><variation>Instead of the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> you may boil a pint of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and when cold, stir into it in turn the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and <ingredient>pumpkin.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>GOOSEBERRY</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list><item>A pint of stewed <ingredient>gooseberries,</ingredient> with all their <ingredient>juice.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of grated <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item></list>Stew the <ingredient>gooseberries</ingredient> till quite soft. When they are cold, mash them fine with the back of a spoon, and stir into them two ounces of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Take two ounces more of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and stir it to a <ingredient>cream</ingredient> with two ounces of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></p><p>Grate very fine as much <ingredient>stale bread</ingredient> as will weigh two ounces.</p><p>Beat three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> in turn with the <ingredient>gooseberries</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></p> <pb n="23" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=31"/><p>Lay puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> in a soup plate. Put in the mixture, and bake it half an hour.</p><p>Do not grate <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">BAKED <ingredient>APPLE</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pint of stewed <ingredient>apples.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> or two ounces of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A table spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of grated <ingredient>lemon-peel.</ingredient></item></list>Stew your <ingredient>apple</ingredient> in as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible, and not long enough for the pieces to break and lose their shape. Put them in a colander to drain, and mash them with the back of a spoon. If stewed, too long, and in too much <ingredient>water,</ingredient> they will lose their flavour. When cold, mix with them the <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and two ounces of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Stir the other two ounces of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> with the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and then mix it gradually with the <ingredient>apple.</ingredient></p><p>Bake it in puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> in a soup-dish, about half an hour in a moderate oven.</p><p>Do not <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> the top.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>FRUIT</ingredient> PIES.</purpose> <ingredient>Fruit</ingredient> pies for family use, are generally made with common <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> allowing three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a pound and a half of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p><p><ingredient>Peaches</ingredient> and <ingredient>plums</ingredient> for pies, should be cut in half, and the stones taken out. <ingredient>Cherries</ingredient> also <pb n="24" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=32"/> should be stoned, and <ingredient>red cherries</ingredient> only should be used for pies.</p><p><ingredient>Apples</ingredient> should be cut into very thin slices, and are much improved by a little <ingredient>lemon peel.</ingredient> Sweet <ingredient>apples</ingredient> are not good for pies, as they are very insipid when baked, and seldom get thoroughly done. If <ingredient>green apples</ingredient> are used, they should first be stewed in as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible, and made very sweet.</p><p><ingredient>Apples,</ingredient> stewed previous to baking, should not be done till they break, but only till they are tender. They should then be drained in a colander, and chopped fine with a knife or the edge of a spoon.</p><p>In making pies of juicy <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> it is a good way to set a small tea-cup on the bottom crust, and lay the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> all round it. The <ingredient>juice</ingredient> will collect under the cup, and not run out at the edges or top of the pie. The <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> should be mixed with a sufficient quantity of <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and piled up in the middle, so as to make the pie highest in the centre. The upper crust should be pricked with a fork, or have a slit cut in the middle. The edges should be nicely crimped with a knife.</p><p><ingredient>Dried peaches,</ingredient> <ingredient>dried apples,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cranberries</ingredient> should be stewed with a very little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and allowed to get quite cold before they are put into the pie. If stewed <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> is put in warm, it will make the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> heavy.</p><p>If your pies are made in the form of shells, or without lids, the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> should always be stewed first, or it will not be sufficiently done, as the shells (which should be of <ingredient>puff paste</ingredient>) must not bake so long as covered pies.</p><p>Shells intended for <ingredient>sweetmeats,</ingredient> must be baked empty, and the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> put into them before they go to table.</p> <pb n="25" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=33"/><p><ingredient>Fruit</ingredient> pies with lids, should have <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> grated over them. If they have been baked the day before, they should be warmed in the stove, or near the fire, before they are sent to table, to soften the crust, and make them taste fresh.</p><p><ingredient>Raspberry</ingredient> and <ingredient>apple</ingredient>-pies are much improved by taking off the lid, and pouring in a little <ingredient>cream</ingredient> just before they go to table. Replace the lid very carefully.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>OYSTER</ingredient> PIE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A hundred large fresh <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> or more if small.</item><item>The <ingredient>yolks of six eggs</ingredient> boiled <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></item><item>A large slice of stale-<ingredient>bread,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Take a large round dish, <ingredient>butter</ingredient> it and spread a <ingredient>rich paste</ingredient> over the sides, and round the edge, but not at the bottom.</p><p><ingredient>Salt oysters</ingredient> will not do for pies. They should be fresh, and as large and fine as possible.</p><p>Drain off part of the liquor from the <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> Put them into a pan, and season them with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Stir them well with the <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient> Have ready the <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> chopped fine, and the grated <ingredient>bread.</ingredient> Pour the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> (with as much of their liquor as you please) into the dish that has the <ingredient>paste</ingredient> in it. Strew over them the chopped <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></p><p>Roll out the lid of the pie, and put it on, crimping the edges handsomely.</p><p>Take a small sheet of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> cut it into a square<pb n="26" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=34"/> and roll it up. Cut it with a sharp knife into the form of a double tulip.</p><p>Make a slit in the centre of the upper crust, and stick the tulip in it.</p><p>Cut out eight large leaves of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and lay them on the lid.</p><p>Bake the pie in a quick oven.</p><p>If you think the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> will be too much done by baking them in the crust, you can substitute for them pieces of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> to keep up the lid of the pie.</p><p>Put the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> with their liquor and the <ingredient>seasoning,</ingredient> chopped <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> &#38;c. into a pan. Cover them closely, and let them just come to a boil, taking them off the fire, and stirring them frequently.</p><p>When the crust is baked, take the lid neatly off (loosening it round the edge with a knife) take out the pieces of <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and put in the <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> Lay the lid on again very carefully.</p><p>For <ingredient>oyster</ingredient> patties, the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are prepared in the same manner.</p><p>They may be chopped if you choose. They must be put in small shells of puff-<ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>BEEF-STEAK</ingredient> PIE.</purpose> <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a deep dish, and spread a sheet of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> all over the bottom, sides, and edge.</p><p>Cut away from your <ingredient>beef-steak</ingredient> all the <ingredient>bone,</ingredient> <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> gristle, and <ingredient>skin.</ingredient> Cut the lean in small thin pieces, about as large, generally, as the palm of your hand. Beat the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> well with the rolling-pin, <pb n="27" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=35"/> to make it juicy and tender. If you put in the <ingredient>fat,</ingredient> it will make the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> too greasy and strong, as it cannot be skimmed.</p><p>Put a layer of <ingredient>meat</ingredient> over the bottom-crust of your dish, and season it to your taste, with <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and, if you choose, a little <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> A small quantity of <ingredient>mushroom ketchup</ingredient> is an improvement; so, also, is a little minced <ingredient>onion.</ingredient></p><p>Have ready some cold boiled <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient> sliced thin. Spread over the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> a layer of <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient>, and a small piece of <ingredient>butter;</ingredient> then another layer of <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> seasoned, and then a layer of <ingredient>potatoes</ingredient>, and so on till the dish is full and heaped up in the middle, having a layer of <ingredient>meat</ingredient> on the top. Pour in a little <ingredient>water.</ingredient></p><p>Cover the pie with a sheet of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and trim the edges. Notch it handsomely with a knife; and, if you choose, make a tulip of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and stick it in the middle of the lid, and lay leaves of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> round it.</p><p>Fresh <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> will greatly improve a <ingredient>beef-steak</ingredient> pie. So also will <ingredient>mushrooms.</ingredient></p><p>Any <ingredient>meat</ingredient> pie may be made in a similar manner.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>INDIAN</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pound of <ingredient>beef-suet,</ingredient> chopped very fine.</item><item>A pint of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A large tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A little grated or chipped <ingredient>lemon-peel.</ingredient></item><item><ingredient>Indian meal</ingredient> sufficient to make a thick batter.</item></list> Warm the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and stir them together. Beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and stir them gradually into the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> in turn with the <ingredient>suet</ingredient> <pb n="28" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=36"/> and <ingredient>indian meal.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> and stir all very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> together. Take care not to put too much <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> or the pudding will be heavy and solid.</p><p>Dip the cloth in <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Shake it out, and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it slightly. Pour the mixture into it, and tie it up, leaving room for the pudding to swell.</p><p>Boil it three hours. Serve it up hot, and eat it with <ingredient>sauce</ingredient> made of <ingredient>drawn butter,</ingredient> <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p><p>When cold, it is good cut in slices and fried.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold">BATTER PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Eight table-spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>One quart of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item></list>Stir the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> gradually, into the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> carefully dissolving all the lumps. Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and add them by degrees to the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Put in the <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and stir the whole well together.</p><p>Take a very thick pudding-cloth. Dip it in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> it. Pour into it the mixture and tie it up, leaving room for it to swell. Boil it <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> one hour, and keep it in the pot, till it is time to send it to table. Serve it up with <ingredient>wine-sauce.</ingredient></p><p>A square cloth, which when tied up will make the pudding of a round form, is better than a bag.</p><p><ingredient>Apple</ingredient> Batter Pudding is made by pouring the batter over a dish of <ingredient>pippins,</ingredient> pared, cored, and sweetened, either whole or cut in pieces. Bake it, and eat it with <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p>
</recipe> <pb n="29" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=37"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>BREAD</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quarter of a pound of grated <ingredient>stale bread.</ingredient></item><item>A quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> boiled with two or three sticks of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> slightly broken.</item><item>Eight <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A little grated <ingredient>lemon-peel.</ingredient></item></list>Boil the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> strain it, and set it away till quite cold.</p><p>Grate as much <ingredient>crumb of stale bread</ingredient> as will weigh a quarter of a pound. Beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and when the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> is cold, stir them into it in turn with the <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and if you choose, a table spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p><p>Bake it in a buttered dish, and grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over it when done. Do not send it to table hot. Baked puddings should never be eaten till they have become cold, or at least cool.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>RICE</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>rice.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A pint and a half of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>Six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A half <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Wash the <ingredient>rice.</ingredient> Boil it till very soft. Drain it, and set it away to get cold. Put the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together in a pan, and stir them till very light. Add to them the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them, gradually, into the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Then stir the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk</ingredient> into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> alternately with the <ingredient>rice.</ingredient></p>
</recipe> <pb n="30" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=38"/><p>Bake it and grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over the top.</p><p><ingredient>Currants</ingredient> or <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed, and stirred in at the last, will greatly improve it.</p><p>It should be eaten cold, or quite cool.</p>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold">BOSTON PUDDING.</purpose> Make a good common <ingredient>paste</ingredient> with a pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient><ref target="r1">*</ref> When you roll it out the last time, cut off the edges, till you get the sheet of <ingredient>paste</ingredient> of an even square shape.</p><p>Have ready some <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> sweetened to your taste. If <ingredient>cranberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>gooseberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>dried peaches,</ingredient> or <ingredient>damsons,</ingredient> they should be stewed, and made very sweet. If <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> they should be stewed in a very little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> drained, and seasoned with <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient> If <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberries,</ingredient> or <ingredient>blackberries,</ingredient> they should be mashed with <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and put into the pudding raw.</p><p>Spread the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> very thick, all over the sheet of <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> (which must not be rolled out too thin.) When it is covered all over with the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> roll it up, and close the dough at both ends, and down the last side. Tie the pudding in a cloth and boil it.</p><p>Eat it with <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> It must not be taken out of the pot till just before it is brought to table.</p><p id="r1" size="smaller">* Or three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>beef suet,</ingredient> chopped very fine. Mix the <ingredient>suet</ingredient> at once with the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> knead it with <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> into a stiff dough, and then roll it out into a large thin sheet. Fold it up and roll it again.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="31" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=39"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold">FRITTERS.</purpose><list align="right" size="smaller"><item>Seven <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>Sufficient <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to make a thick batter.</item></list>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well and stir them gradually into the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and stir in <ingredient>flour</ingredient> enough to make a thick batter.</p><p>Fry them in <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> and serve them up hot.</p><p>Eat them with <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p><p>They are improved by stirring in a table-spoonful of <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></p><p>These are excellent with the addition of cold stewed <ingredient>apple,</ingredient> stirred into the mixture, in which case use less <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold">FINE CUSTARDS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> only, of sixteen <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Six ounces of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> broken in small pieces.</item><item>A large handful of <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves or half an ounce of <ingredient>peach kernels</ingredient> or <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> broken in pieces.</item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item></list>Boil in the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves, or <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels. When it has boiled, set it away to get cold. As soon as it is cold, strain it through a sieve, to clear it from the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves, &#38;c. and stir into it gradually, the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p><p>Beat the <ingredient>yolks of sixteen eggs</ingredient> very light, and <pb n="32" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=40"/>stir them by degrees into the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> which must be quite cold or the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> will make it curdle. Put the custards into cups, and set them in a baking pan, half filled with <ingredient>water.</ingredient> When baked, grate some <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over each and ice them. Make the icing of the <ingredient>whites of eight eggs,</ingredient> a large tea-spoonful of <ingredient>powdered loaf sugar,</ingredient> and six drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> beaten all together till it stands alone. Pile up some of the icing on the top of each custard, heaping it high. Put a spot of red nonpareils on the middle of the pile of icing.</p><p>If the weather be damp, or the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> not new-laid, more than eight <ingredient>whites</ingredient> will be required for the icing.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold">PLAIN CUSTARDS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item>Eight <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A handful of <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves, or half an ounce of <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels, broken in pieces.</item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item></list>Boil the <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves or kernels in the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and set it away to cool. When cold, strain out the leaves or kernels, and stir in the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them gradually into the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> when it is quite cold. Bake it in cups, or in a large <ingredient>white</ingredient> dish.</p><p>When cool, grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over the top.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="33" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=41"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose align="center" placement="heading" rend="bold"><ingredient>RICE</ingredient> CUSTARDS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>rice.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></item><item>Eight <ingredient>yolks of eggs</ingredient> or six whole <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Six ounces of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A quart of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item>A handful of <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves, or half an ounce of <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels, broken in pieces.</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> broken in pieces.</item></list>Boil the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> with the <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> which must first be <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> some cups or a mould, and when the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> is quite soft, drain it, and put it into them. Set it away to get cold.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well. Boil the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with the <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-leaves, or kernels. As soon as it has come to a boil, take it off and strain it through a sieve. Then set it again on the fire, stir into it alternately, the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> taking it off frequently and stirring it <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> lest it become a curd. Take care not to boil it too long, or it will be lumpy and lose its flavour. When done, set it away to cool. Turn out the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> from the cups or mould, into a deep dish. Pour some of the <ingredient>boiled custard</ingredient> over it, and send up the remainder of the custard in a <ingredient>sauce</ingredient>-boat.</p><p>You may, if you choose, ornament the lumps of <ingredient>rice,</ingredient> (after the custard is poured round them) by making a stiff froth of <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> (beaten till it stands alone) and a few drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> with a very little powdered <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Heap the froth on the top of each lump of <ingredient>rice.</ingredient></p>
</recipe> <pb n="34" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=42"/>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">COLD CUSTARDS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> and a half a pint of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A large glass of <ingredient>white wine,</ingredient> in which an inch of washed rennet has been soaked.</item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item></list>Mix together the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>wine</ingredient> into it, and pour the mixture into your custard-cups. Set them in a warm place near the fire, till they become a firm curd. Then set them on ice, or in a very cold place. Grate <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over them.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">CURDS AND <ingredient>WHEY.</ingredient></purpose> Take a small piece of rennet about two inches square. Wash it very clean in <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> to get all the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> off, and wipe it dry. Put it in a tea-cup, and pour on it just enough of <ingredient>lukewarm water</ingredient> to cover it.Let it set all night, or for several hours. Then take out the rennet, and stir the <ingredient>water</ingredient> in which it was soaked, into a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> which should be in a broad dish.</p><p>Set the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> in a warm place, till it becomes a firm curd. As soon as the curd is completely made, set it in a cool place, or on ice (if in summer) for two or three hours before you want to use it.</p><p>Eat it with <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></p><p><variation>The <ingredient>whey,</ingredient> drained from the curd, is an excellent drink for invalids.</variation></p>
</recipe> <pb n="35" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=43"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center">A TRIFLE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> powdered.</item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>white wine</ingredient> }</item><item>Half a gill of <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> } mixed.</item><item>Eight maccaroons, or more if you choose.</item><item>Four small sponge-cakes or <ingredient>Naples biscuit.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of blanched <ingredient>sweet almonds,</ingredient> pounded in a mortar.</item><item>One ounce of blanched <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels.</item><item>The <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and grated <ingredient>peel of two lemons.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A glass of <ingredient>noyau.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of rich baked custard, made of the <ingredient>yolks of eggs.</ingredient></item></list>Pound the sweet and <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> to a smooth <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> adding a little <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> as you pound them.</p><p>Grate the <ingredient>yellow peels of the lemons,</ingredient> and squeeze the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> into a saucer.</p><p>Break the sponge cake and maccaroons into small pieces, mix them with the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> and lay them in the bottom of a large glass bowl. Grate a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> over them, and the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>peel of the lemons.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and let the mixture remain untouched, till the cakes are dissolved in the liquor. Then stir it a little.</p><p>Mix the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> with a glass of <ingredient>noyau,</ingredient> and beat it with a whisk or rods, till it stands alone.</p><p>As the froth rises, take it off with a spoon, and lay it on a sieve (with a large dish under it) to drain. The <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> that drains into the dish, must be poured back into the pan with the rest, and beaten over again. When the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is finished, set it in a cool place.</p><p>When the custard is cold, pour it into the glass bowl upon the dissolved cakes, &#38;c. and when the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is ready, fill up the bowl with it, heaping<pb n="36" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=44"/> it high in the middle. You may ornament it with nonpareils.</p><p>If you choose, you can put in, between the custard and the frothed <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> a layer of <ingredient>fruit jelly,</ingredient> or small <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> preserved.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>WHIPT CREAM.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>whites of four eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Ten drops of strong <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> or two <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> cut in thin slices, or the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of a large <ingredient>lemon.</ingredient></item></list>Mix together, in a broad pan, all the ingredients, unless you use slices of <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and then they must be laid at intervals among the froth, as you heap it in the bowl.</p><p>With a whisk or rods, beat the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> to a strong froth. Have beside your pan a sieve (bottom upwards) with a large dish under it. As the froth rises, take it lightly off with a spoon, and lay it on the sieve to drain. When the top of the sieve is full, transfer the froth to a large glass or china bowl. Continue to do this till the bowl is full.</p><p>The <ingredient>cream</ingredient> which has dropped through the sieve into the dish, must be poured into the pan, and beaten over again. When all the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is converted into froth, pile it up in the bowl, making it highest in the middle.</p><p>If you choose, you may ornament it with red and green nonpareils.</p><p>If you put it in glasses, lay a little <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> in the bottom of each glass, and pile the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> on it.</p><p>Keep it in a cool place till you want to use it.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="37" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=45"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">FLOATING ISLAND.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Six <ingredient>whites of eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Six large table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item></list>Put the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> and <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> into a pan, and beat it together with a whisk, till it becomes a stiff froth and stands alone.</p><p>Have ready the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> in a broad shallow dish. Just before you send it to table, pile up the froth in the centre of the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">ICE <ingredient>CREAM.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of <ingredient>rich cream.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>powdered loaf sugar.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of two large <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> or a pint of <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> or <ingredient>raspberries.</ingredient></item></list>Put the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> into a broad pan. Then stir in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> by degrees, and when all is well mixed, strain it through a sieve.</p><p>Put it into a tin that has a close cover, and set it in a tub. Fill the tub with ice broken into very small pieces, and strew among the ice a large quantity of <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> taking care that none of the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> gets into the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Scrape the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> down with a spoon as it freezes round the edges of the tin. While the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is freezing, stir in gradually the <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> or the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> of a pint of mashed <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> or <ingredient>raspberries.</ingredient> When it is all frozen, dip the tin in <ingredient>lukewarm water;</ingredient> take out the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and fill your glasses; but not till a few minutes before you want to use it, as it will very soon melt.</p><p>You may heighten the colour of the <ingredient>red fruit,</ingredient> by a little <ingredient>cochineal.</ingredient></p><pb n="38" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=46"/><p>If you wish to have it in moulds, put the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> into them as soon as it has frozen in the tin. Set the moulds in a tub of ice and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Just before you want to use the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> take the moulds out of the tub, wipe or wash the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> carefully from the outside, dip the moulds in <ingredient>lukewarm water,</ingredient> and turn out the <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p><p>You may flavour a quart of ice-cream with two ounces of <ingredient>sweet almonds</ingredient> and one ounce of <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> blanched and beaten in a mortar with a little <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> to a smooth <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> Stir in the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> gradually while the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is freezing.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">ANOTHER KIND OF ICE-CREAM.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pint and a half of <ingredient>rich cream.</ingredient></item><item>A quart and a half-pint of morning's <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One table-spoonful of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>lemons.</ingredient></item><item>Or half a <ingredient>Vanilla bean,</ingredient> split into small pieces.</item><item>Or two ounces of <ingredient>sweet almonds</ingredient> and one ounce of <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> blanched and split into pieces.</item></list> Take half of the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and put in the ingredient that is to flavour it, either the <ingredient>vanilla,</ingredient> the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> or the grated <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of the <ingredient>lemons.</ingredient> Boil it, stirring in gradually the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p><p>Having beaten the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well, add to them two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>cold milk,</ingredient> and pour them into the boiling <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Let them simmer two or three minutes, stirring them all the time. Then take the mixture off the fire and strain it through book-muslin into a pan. Add the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> and the remainder of the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and put the whole into the tin freezer, which must be set in a tub filled with ice, among which must be scattered a great deal of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></p><pb n="39" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=47"/><p>Squeeze the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> from the two <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> and stir it into the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> by degrees, while it is freezing.</p><p>When it is all frozen, turn it out, first dipping the tin for a moment in <ingredient>warm water.</ingredient></p><p>If you wish to flavour it with <ingredient>strawberry</ingredient> or <ingredient>raspberry juice,</ingredient> that, like the <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> must be stirred gradually in while the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is freezing.</p><p>In places where <ingredient>cream</ingredient> is not abundant, this receipt (though inferior in richness) will be found more economical than the preceding one. It is, however, less easy and expeditious.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>CALF</ingredient>'S-<ingredient>FEET JELLY.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Eight <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s <ingredient>feet.</ingredient></item><item>Three quarts of <ingredient>water.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>lemons.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>whites of six eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> broken into lumps.</item></list>Endeavour to procure <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s-<ingredient>feet,</ingredient> that have been nicely singed, but not skinned, as the <ingredient>skin</ingredient> being left on, makes the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> much firmer.</p><p>The day before you want to use the <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> boil the eight <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s-<ingredient>feet</ingredient> in three quarts of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> till the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> drops from the <ingredient>bone.</ingredient> When sufficiently done, put it into a cullender or sieve, and let the liquid drain from the <ingredient>meat,</ingredient> into a broad pan or dish. Skim off the <ingredient>fat.</ingredient> Let the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> stand till next day, and then carefully scrape off the sediment from the bottom. It will be a firm <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> if too much <ingredient>water</ingredient> has not been used, and if it has bolted long enough. If it is not firm at first, it will not become so afterwards when boiled with the other ingredients. There should on no account be more than three quarts of <ingredient>water.</ingredient></p><p>Early next morning, put the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> into a tin kettle, or covered tin pan; set it on the fire, and melt <pb n="40" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=48"/> it a little. Take it off, and season it with the <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> slightly broken, a pint of <ingredient>madeira wine,</ingredient> three <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> cut in thin slices, and a half a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> broken up.</p><p>If you wish it high-coloured, add two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>French brandy.</ingredient> Mix all well together. Beat, slightly, the <ingredient>whites of six eggs</ingredient> (saving the <ingredient>egg</ingredient>-shell) and stir the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> into the <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient> Break up the <ingredient>egg</ingredient>-shells into very small pieces, and throw them in also. Stir the whole very well together.</p><p>Set it on the fire, and boil it <ingredient>hard</ingredient> five minutes, but do not stir it, as that will prevent its clearing. Have ready a large <ingredient>white</ingredient> flannel bag, the top wide, and the bottom tapering to a point.</p><p>Tie the bag to the backs of two chairs, or to the <ingredient>legs</ingredient> of a table, and set a <ingredient>white</ingredient> dish or a mould under it.</p><p>After the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> has boiled five minutes, pour it hot into the bag, and let it drip through into the dish. Do not squeeze the bag, as that will make the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> dull and cloudy.</p><p>If it is not clear the first time it passes through the bag, empty out all the ingredients, wash the bag, suspend it again, put another <ingredient>white</ingredient> dish under it, pour the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> back into the bag, and let it drip through again. Repeat this six or eight times, or till it is clear, putting a clean dish under it every time. If it does not drip freely, move the bag into a warmer place.</p><p>When the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> has all dripped through the bag, and is clear, set it in a cool place to congeal. It will sometimes congeal immediately, and sometimes not for several hours, particularly if the weather is warm and damp. If the weather is very cold you must take care not to let it freeze. When it is quite firm, which perhaps it will not be till evening, <pb n="41" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=49"/> fill your glasses with it, piling it up very high. If you make it in a mould, you must either set the mould under the bag while it is dripping, or pour it from the dish into the mould while it is liquid. When it is perfectly congealed, dip the mould for an instant in <ingredient>boiling water</ingredient> to loosen the <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient> Turn it out on a glass dish.</p><p>This quantity of ingredients will make a quart of <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> when finished. In cool weather it may be made a day or two before it is wanted.</p><p>You may increase the <ingredient>seasoning,</ingredient> (that is, the <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient>) according to your taste, but less than the above proportion will not be sufficient to flavour the <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient></p><p>Ice <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> is made in the same manner, only not so stiff. Four <ingredient>calves-feet</ingredient> will be sufficient. Freeze it as you would ice-cream, and serve it up in glasses.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">BLANCMANGE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Four <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s-<ingredient>feet</ingredient></item><item>A pint and a half of thick <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> broken up.</item><item>A glass of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> beaten and sifted.</item></list>Get four <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s-<ingredient>feet;</ingredient> if possible some that have been singed, and not skinned. Scrape, and clean them well, and boil them in three quarts of <ingredient>water</ingredient> till all the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> drops off the <ingredient>bone.</ingredient> Drain the liquid through a colander or sieve, and skim it well. Let it stand till next morning to congeal. Then clean it well from the sediment, and put it into a tin or bell-metal kettle. Stir into it, the <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Boil it <ingredient>hard</ingredient> for five minutes, stirring it several times. Then strain it through a linen cloth or napkin into a large bowl, and add the <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p><p>Set it in a cool place for three or four hours, <pb n="42" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=50"/> stirring it very frequently with a spoon, to prevent the <ingredient>cream</ingredient> from separating from the <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient> The more it is stirred the better. Stir it till it is cool.</p><p>Wash your moulds, wipe them dry, and then wet them with <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> When the blancmange becomes very thick, (that is, in three or four hours, if the weather is not too damp) put it into your moulds.</p><p>When it has set in them till it is quite firm, loosen it carefully all round with a knife, and turn it out on glass or china plates.</p><p>If you wish to make it with <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> take an ounce of blanched <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> and two ounces of sweet. Beat them in a mortar to a fine <ingredient>paste,</ingredient> pouring in occasionally a little <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> When the mixture is ready to boil, add the <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> to it gradually, stirring them well in. Or you may stir them in, while it is cooling in the bowl.</p><p>If it inclines to stick to the moulds, set them an instant in <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> It will then turn out easily.</p><p>If you choose to make it without <ingredient>calf</ingredient>'s <ingredient>feet,</ingredient> you can substitute an ounce of the best and clearest <ingredient>isinglass</ingredient> (or, if in summer, an ounce and a quarter) boiled with the other ingredients. If made with <ingredient>isinglass,</ingredient> you must use two ounces of sweet, and an ounce of <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> with the addition of the grated <ingredient>rind</ingredient> of a large <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> and a large stick of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> broken up, a glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> These ingredients must be all mixed together, with a quart of <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and boiled <ingredient>hard</ingredient> for five minutes. The mixture must then be strained through a napkin, into a large bowl. Set it in a cool place, and stir it frequently till nearly cold. It must then be put into the moulds.</p><p>You may substitute for the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> half a gill of <ingredient>noyau,</ingredient> in which case, omit the <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="breadsweets"> <pb n="43" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=51"/><p><hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">PART THE SECOND.</hd></p><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=52"/> <pb n="45" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=53"/><hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">CAKES.</hd>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p align="center" rend="bold" placement="heading">GENERAL DIRECTIONS.</p><p>In <purpose>making cakes</purpose> it is particularly necessary that the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> should be well beaten. They are not sufficiently light till the surface looks smooth and level, and till they get so thick as to be of the consistence of <ingredient>boiled custard.</ingredient></p><p><ingredient>White of egg</ingredient> should always be beaten till it becomes a heap of stiff froth, without any liquid at the bottom; and till it hangs from the rods or fork without dropping.</p><p><ingredient>Eggs</ingredient> become light soonest when new-laid, and when beaten near the fire or in warm dry weather.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> should be stirred till it looks like thick <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and till it stands up in the pan.</p><p>It should be kept cool. If too warm, it will make the cakes heavy.</p><p>Large cakes should be baked in tin or earthen pans, with straight sides, that are as nearly perpendicular as possible. They cut into handsomer slices, and if they are to be iced, it will be found very inconvenient to put on the icing, if the cake slopes in towards the bottom.</p><p>Before you ice a cake dredge it all over with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and then wipe the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> off. This will enable you to spread on the icing more evenly.</p><pb n="46" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=54"/><p>Before you cut an ice cake, cut the icing by itself with a small sharp penknife. The large knife with which you divide the cake, will crack and break the icing.</p><p>Large Gingerbread, as it burns very easily, may be baked in an earthen pan. So also may Black Cake or <ingredient>Pound Cake.</ingredient> Tin pans or moulds, with a hollow tube in the middle, are best for cakes.</p><p>If large cakes are baked in tin pans, the bottom and sides should be covered with sheets of <ingredient>paper,</ingredient> before the mixture is put in. The <ingredient>paper</ingredient> must be well buttered.</p><p>Sponge cakes, and Almond cakes should be baked in pans that are as thin as possible.</p><p>If the cakes should get burnt, scrape them with a knife or grater, as soon as they are cool.</p><p>Always be careful to <ingredient>butter</ingredient> your pans well. Should the cakes stick, they cannot be got out without breaking.</p><p>For queen-cakes, &#38;c. the small tins of a round or oval shape are most convenient. Fill them but little more than half.</p><p>After the mixture is completed, set it in a cool place till all the cakes are baked.</p><p>In rolling out cakes made of dough, use as little <ingredient>flour</ingredient> as possible. When you lay them in the pans, do not place them too close together, lest they run into each other.</p><p>When you are cutting them out, dip the cutter frequently in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> to prevent its sticking.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="47" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=55"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center">QUEEN CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient>--washed.</item><item>Fourteen ounces of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>Ten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or twelve drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></item><item>One tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>One <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> beaten or grated.</item></list>Pound the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> to a fine powder, in a marble mortar, and sift it well.</p><p>Put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into a deep earthen pan, and cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into it. Stir them together, till very light.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> in a broad shallow pan, till they are perfectly smooth and thick.</p><p>Stir into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> a little of the beaten <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and then a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and so on alternately, a little <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> till the whole is in; continuing all the time to beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and stirring the mixture very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Add by degrees, the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and then the liquor, a little at a time. Finally, put in the <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient><ref target="r2">*</ref> Stir the whole very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> at the last.</p><p>Take about two dozen little tins, or more, if you have room for them in the oven. Rub them very well with fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> With a spoon, put some of the mixture in each tin, but do not fill them to the top as the cakes will rise high in baking. Bake them in a quick oven, about a quarter of an hour. When they are done, they will shrink a little from the sides of the tins.</p><p>Before you fill your tins again, scrape them well with a knife, and wash or wipe them clean.</p><p>If the cakes are scorched by too hot a fire, do not scrape off the burnt parts till they have grown cold.</p><p id="r2" size="smaller">* In buting essence or <ingredient>oil of lemon,</ingredient> endeavour to get that which is <ingredient>white,</ingredient> it being much the strongest and best. When it looks greenish, it is generally very weak, so that when used, a double or treble quantity is necessary.</p> <pb n="48" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=56"/><p>Make an icing with the <ingredient>whites of three eggs,</ingredient> beaten till it stands alone, and twenty-four tea-spoonfuls of the best <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> powdered, and beaten gradually into the <ingredient>white of egg.</ingredient> Flavour it with a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> or eight drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> stirred in at the last. Spread it evenly with a broad knife, over the top of each queen-cake, ornamenting them, (while the icing is quite wet) with red and green nonpareils, or fine <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>-sand, dropped on, carefully, with the thumb and finger.</p><p>When the cakes are iced, set them in a warm place to dry; but not too near the fire, as that will cause the icing to crack.<ref target="r2">*</ref></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>POUND CAKE.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>One pound of <ingredient>white sugar,</ingredient> powdered and sifted.</item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Ten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> }</item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> } Mixed</item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> }</item><item>Twelve drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> powdered.</item></list>Pound the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and sift it. There should be twice as much <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> as <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Mix the <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> together.</p><p>Sift the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> in a broad pan, or wooden bowl. Sift the <ingredient>powdered sugar</ingredient> into a large deep pan, and cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into it, in small pieces. If the weather<pb n="49" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=57"/> is very cold, and the <ingredient>butter hard,</ingredient> set the pan near the fire for a few minutes; but if the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is too warm, the cake will be heavy. Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together, with a wooden stick, till they are very light, and <ingredient>white,</ingredient> and look like <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> in a broad shallow pan with a wood <ingredient>egg</ingredient>-beater or whisk. They must be beaten till they are thick and smooth, and of the consistence of <ingredient>boiled custard.</ingredient></p><p>Pour the liquor and <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> gradually, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> stirring all the time. Add, by degrees, the <ingredient>essence of lemon</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient></p><p>Stir the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> alternately into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a handful of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and about two spoonfuls of the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> (which you must continue to beat all the time,) and when all is in, stir the whole mixture very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> for near ten minutes.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a large tin pan, or a cake mould with an open tube rising from the middle. Put the mixture into it as evenly as possible. Bake it in a moderate oven, for two, or three, or four hours, in proportion to its thickness, and to the heat of the fire.</p><p>When you think it is nearly done, thrust a twig or wooden skewer into it, down to the bottom. If the stick come out clean and dry, the cake is almost baked. When quite done, it will shrink from the sides of the pan, and cease making a noise. Then withdraw the <ingredient>coals</ingredient> (if baked in a dutch oven), take off the lid, and let the cake remain in the oven to cool gradually.</p><p>You may ice it either warm or cold. Before you put the icing on a large cake, dredge the cake all over with <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and then wipe the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> off; this will make the icing stick on better--If you have <pb n="50" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=58"/>sufficient time, the appearance of the cake will be much improved by icing it twice. Put on the first icing soon after the cake is taken out of the oven, and the second the next day when the first is perfectly dry. While the last icing is wet, ornament it with coloured <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>-sand or nonpareils.</p>
<ednote>The following footnote appears on the bottom of page 48 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r3" size="smaller">*You may colour icing of a fine pink, by mixing with it a few drops of liquid cochineal; which is prepared by boiling very slowly in an earthen or china vessel twenty grains of cochineal powder, twenty grains of cream of tartar, and twenty grains of powdered alum, all dissolved in a gill of soft water, and boiled till reduced to one half. Strain it and cork it up in a small phial. Pink icing should be ornamented with white nonpareils.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">BLACK CAKE, OR <ingredient>PLUM</ingredient> CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Twelve <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Two pounds of the best <ingredient>raisins.</ingredient></item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>nutmegs</ingredient> powdered.</item><item>A large glass of <ingredient>wine</ingredient> }</item><item>A large glass of <ingredient>brandy</ingredient> } mixed together</item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> }</item><item>A pound of <ingredient>citron.</ingredient></item></list>Pick the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> very clean, and wash them, draining them through a colendar. Wipe them in a towel. Spread them out on a large dish, and set them near the fire, or in the hot sun, to dry, placing the dish in a slanting position. Having stoned the <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> cut them in half, and, when all are done, sprinkle them well with sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> to prevent their sinking to the bottom of the cake. When the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> are dry, sprinkle them also with <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p><p>Pound the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> allowing twice as much <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> as <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Sift it, and mix the <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> together. Mix also the liquor and <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> in a tumbler or cup. Cut the <ingredient>citron</ingredient> in slips. Sift the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a broad dish. Sift the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into a deep earthen pan, and cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into<pb n="51" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=59"/> it. Warm it near the fire, if the weather is too cold for it to mix easily. Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient></p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> as light as possible. Stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> alternately with the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Add gradually the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor. Stir the <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> and <ingredient>currants</ingredient> alternately into the mixture, taking care that they are well <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed. Stir the whole as <ingredient>hard</ingredient> as possible, for ten minutes after the ingredients are in.</p><p>Cover the bottom and sides of a large tin or earthen pan, with sheets of <ingredient>white paper</ingredient> well buttered, and put into it some of the mixture. Then spread on it some of the <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> which must not be cut too small. Next put a layer of the mixture, and then a layer of <ingredient>citron,</ingredient> and so on till it is all in, having a layer of the mixture at the top.</p><p>This cake is always best baked in a baker's oven, and will require four or five hours, in proportion to its thickness.<ref target="r4">*</ref></p><p>Ice it next day.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">SPONGE CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Twelve <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Ten ounces of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> dried near the fire.</item><item>A pound of <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> powdered and sifted.</item><item>Twelve drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></item><item>A grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> mixed.</item></list>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> as light as possible. <ingredient>Eggs</ingredient> for sponge or almond cakes require more beating than for any other purpose. Beat the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> by degrees, <pb n="52" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=60"/> into the <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Beat very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> and continue to beat some time after the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is all in.</p><p>No sort of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> but loaf will make light sponge-cake. Stir in, gradually, the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient> Then, by degrees, put in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> a little at a time, stirring round the mixture very slowly with a knife. If the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is stirred in too <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> the cake will be tough. It must be done lightly and gently, so that the top of the mixture will be covered with bubbles. As soon as the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> is all in, begin to bake it, as setting will injure it.</p><p>Put it in small tins, well buttered, or in one large tin pan. The thinner the pans, the better for sponge-cake. Fill the small tins about half full. Grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over the top of each, before you set them in the oven.</p><p>Sponge-cake requires a very quick oven, particularly at the bottom. It should be baked as fast as possible, or it will be tough and heavy, however light it may have been before it went into the oven. It is of all cakes the most liable to be spoiled in baking. When taken out of the tins, the cakes should be spread on a sieve to cool. If baked in one large cake, it should be iced.</p><p>A large cake of twelve <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> should be baked at least an hour in a quick oven.</p><p>For small cakes, ten minutes is generally sufficient. If they get very much out of shape in baking, it is a sign that the oven is too slow.</p><p>Some think that sponge-cakes and almond cakes are lighter, when the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> are beaten in separate pans, and mixed gently together before the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is beaten into them.</p><p>If done separately from the <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> should be beaten till they stand alone.</p>
<ednote>The following footnote appear at the bottom of page 51 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r4" size="smaller">*After this cake is done, it will be the better for withdrawing the fire (if baked in an iron oven) and letting it stay in the oven all night, or till it gets quite cold.</p> 
</recipe><pb n="53" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=61"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">ALMOND CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two ounces of blanched <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> pounded very fine.</item><item>Seven ounces of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted and dried.</item><item>Ten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> powdered and sifted.</item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Take two ounces of shelled <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels. Scald them in <ingredient>hot water,</ingredient> and as you peel them, throw them into a bowl of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> then wipe them dry, and pound them one by one in a mortar, till they are quite fine and smooth.</p><p>Break ten <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> putting the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> in one pan and the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> in another. Beat them separately as light as possible, the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> first, and then the <ingredient>yolks.</ingredient></p><p>Add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> gradually, to the <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> beating it in very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Then by degrees, beat in the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> and then add the <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p><p>Stir half the <ingredient>whites of the eggs</ingredient> into the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Divide the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into two equal parts, and stir in one half, slowly and lightly, till it bubbles on the top. Then the other half of the <ingredient>white of egg,</ingredient> and then the remainder of the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> very lightly.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a large square tin pan, or one made of <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board which will be better. Put in the mixture, and set immediately in a quick oven, which must be rather hotter at the bottom than at the top. Bake it according to the thickness. If you allow the oven to get slack, the cake will be spoiled.</p><p>Make an icing with the <ingredient>whites of three eggs,</ingredient> twenty-four tea-spoonfuls of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> and eight drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></p><p>When the cake is cool, mark it in small squares with a knife. Cover it with icing, and ornament it while wet, with nonpareils dropped on in borders, round each square of the cake. When the icing is dry, cut the cake in squares, cutting through the <pb n="54" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=62"/> icing very carefully with a penknife. Or you may cut it in squares first, and then ice and ornament each square separately.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">FRENCH ALMOND CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Six ounces of shelled <ingredient>sweet almonds.</ingredient></item><item>Three ounces of shelled <ingredient>bitter almonds,</ingredient> or <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels.</item><item>Three ounces of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> dried near the fire.</item><item>Fourteen <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of powdered <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Twelve drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></item></list>Blanch the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> by scalding them in <ingredient>hot water.</ingredient> Put them in a bowl of <ingredient>cold water,</ingredient> and wipe them dry, when you take them out. Pound them, one at a time, in a mortar, till they are perfectly smooth. Mix the sweet and <ingredient>bitter almonds</ingredient> together. Prepare them, if possible the day before the cake is made.<ref target="r5">*</ref></p><p>Put the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> and <ingredient>yolks of the eggs,</ingredient> into separate pans. Beat the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> till they stand alone, and then the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> till they are very thick.</p><p>Put the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> gradually, to the <ingredient>yolks,</ingredient> beating it in very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Add, by degrees, the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> still beating very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Then put in the <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient> Next, beat in, gradually, the <ingredient>whites of the eggs,</ingredient> continuing to beat for some time after they are all in. Lastly, stir in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> as slowly and lightly, as possible.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a large tin mould or pan. Put the cake in and bake it in a very quick oven, an hour or more according to its thickness.</p><p>The oven must on no account be hotter at the top, than at the bottom.</p><p>When done, set it on a sieve to cool.</p><p id="r5" size="smaller">*While pounding the <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> pour in occasionally a little <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> It makes them much lighter.</p> <pb n="55" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=63"/><p>Ice it, and ornament it with nonpareils.</p><p>These almond cakes are generally baked in a turban-shaped mould, and the nonpareils put on, in spots or sprigs.</p><p>A pound of <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> in the shells (if the shells are soft and thin,) will generally yield half a pound when shelled. <ingredient>Hard,</ingredient> thick-shelled <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> seldom yield much more than a quarter of a pound, and should therefore never be bought for cakes or puddings.</p><p><ingredient>Bitter almonds</ingredient> and <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels can always be purchased with the shells off.</p><p>Families should always save their <ingredient>peach</ingredient>-kernels, as they can be used in cakes, puddings and custards.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="indent1" placement="heading">MACCAROONS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of shelled <ingredient>sweet almonds.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of shelled <ingredient>bitter almonds.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>whites of three eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Twenty-four large tea-spoonfuls of powdered <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A large tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Blanch and pound your <ingredient>almonds,</ingredient> beat them very smooth, and mix the sweet and bitter together; do them, if you can, the day before you make the maccaroons. Pound and sift your <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>whites of three eggs</ingredient> till they stand alone; add to them, very gradually, the <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> a spoonful at a time, beat it in very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> and put in, by degrees, the <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Then stir in, gradually, the <ingredient>almonds.</ingredient> The mixture must be like a soft dough; if too thick, it will be heavy; if too thin, it will run out of shape. If you find your <ingredient>almonds</ingredient> not sufficient, prepare a few more, and stir them in. When it is all well mixed and stirred, put some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> in the palm of your hand, and taking <pb n="56" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=64"/> up a lump of the mixture with a knife, roll it on your hand with the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a small round ball; have ready an iron or tin pan, buttered, and lay the maccaroons in it, as you make them up. Place them about two inches apart, in case of their spreading. Bake them about eight or ten minutes in a moderate oven; they should be baked of a pale brown colour. If too much baked, they will lose their flavour; if too little, they will be heavy. They should rise high in the middle, and crack on the surface. You may, if you choose, put a larger proportion of <ingredient>spice.</ingredient><ref target="r6">*</ref></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">APEES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> and a table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> mixed.</item><item>Half a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A tea-spoonful of beaten <ingredient>cinnamon</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace.</ingredient></item><item>Three table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>carraway seeds.</ingredient></item></list>Sift the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a broad pan, and cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in it. Add the <ingredient>carraways,</ingredient> <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and pour in the liquor by degrees, mixing it well with a knife; add enough of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> to make it a stiff dough. Spread some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take out the dough, and knead it very well with your hands. Cut it into small pieces, and knead each separately, then put them all together, and knead the whole in one lump. Roll it out in a sheet about a quarter of an inch thick. Cut it out in round cakes, with the edge of a tumbler, or a tin of that size. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> an iron pan, and lay the cakes<pb n="57" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=65"/> in it, not too close together. Bake them a few minutes in a moderate oven, till they are very slightly coloured, but not brown. If too much baked, they will entirely lose their flavour. Do not roll them out too thin.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">JUMBLES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Three <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of powdered <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> grated.</item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light. Throw them, all at once, into the pan of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Put in, at once, the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and then add the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> If you have no <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> substitute six or seven drops of strong <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> or more if the essence is weak. Stir the whole very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> with a knife.</p><p>Spread some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> your hands well. Take up with your knife, a portion of the dough, and lay it on the board. Roll it lightly with your hands, into long thin rolls, which must be cut into equal lengths, curled up into rings, and laid gently into an iron or tin pan, buttered, not too close to each other, as they spread in baking. Bake them in a quick oven about five minutes, and grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over them when cool.</p>
<ednote>The following footnote appears at the bottom of page 56 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r6" size="smaller">*Cocoa-nut cakes may be made in a similar manner, substituting for the pounded almonds half a pound of finely-grated cocoa-nut. They must be made into small round balls with a little flour laid on the palm of the hand, and baked a few minutes. They are very fine.</p>
</recipe><pb n="58" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=66"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">KISSES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>One pound of the best <ingredient>loaf sugar,</ingredient> powdered and sifted.</item><item>The <ingredient>whites of four eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Twelve drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-cup of <ingredient>currant jelly.</ingredient></item></list>Beat the <ingredient>whites of four eggs</ingredient> till they stand alone. Then beat in, gradually, the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful at a time. Add the <ingredient>essence of lemon,</ingredient> and beat the whole very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p><p>Lay a wet sheet of <ingredient>paper</ingredient> on the bottom of a square tin pan. Drop on it, at equal distances, a small tea-spoonful of stiff <ingredient>currant jelly.</ingredient><ref target="r7">*</ref> With a large spoon, pile some of the beaten <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> on each lump of <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> so as to cover it entirely. Drop on the mixture as evenly as possible, so as to make the kisses of a round smooth shape.</p><p>Set them in a cool oven, and as soon as they are coloured, they are done. Then take them out and place them two bottoms together. Lay them lightly on a sieve, and dry them in a cool oven, till the two bottoms stick fast together, so as to form one ball or oval.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">SPANISH <ingredient>BUNS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses and a half of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item>Six ounces of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass and a half of the best <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item><item>A large tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Sift half a pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a broad pan, and sift a quarter of a pound, separately, into a deep<pb n="59" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=67"/> plate, and set it aside. Put the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> into a soup-plate, cut up the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and set it on the stove or near the fire to warm, but do not let it get too hot. When the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is very soft, stir it all through the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> with a knife, and set it away to cool. Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and mix the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> with them, all at once; then pour all into the pan of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Put in the <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or if you prefer it, eight drops of <ingredient>essence of lemon.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> of which an increased quantity will be necessary, if it is not very strong and fresh. Stir the whole very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> with a knife. Add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> gradually. If the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> is not stirred in slowly, a little at a time, the <ingredient>buns</ingredient> will be heavy. Then, by degrees, sprinkle in the remaining quarter of a pound of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir all well together; <ingredient>butter</ingredient> a square iron pan, and put in the mixture. Cover it with a cloth, and set it near the fire to rise. It will probably not be light in less than five hours. When it is risen very high, and is covered with bubbles, bake it in a moderate oven, about a quarter of an hour or more in proportion to its thickness.</p><p>When it is quite cool, cut it in squares, and grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over them. This quantity will make twelve or fifteen <ingredient>buns.</ingredient></p><p>They are best the day they are baked.</p><p>You may, if you choose, bake them separately, in small square tins, adding to the batter half a pound of <ingredient>currants</ingredient> or chopped <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> well <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed, and stirred in at the last.</p><p>In making <ingredient>buns,</ingredient> stir the <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> well before you put it in, having first poured off the <ingredient>beer</ingredient> or thin part from the top. If your <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> is not good, do<pb n="60" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=68"/> not attempt to make <ingredient>buns</ingredient> with it, as they will never be light.</p><p><variation><ingredient>Buns</ingredient> may be made in a plainer way, with the following ingredients, mixed in the above manner.</variation></p>
</recipe><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted into a pan.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted in a plate, and set aside to sprinkle in at the last.</item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> well beaten.</item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass and a half of the best <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A large tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> cut up, and warmed in the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item></list>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">RUSK.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>One <ingredient>egg.</ingredient></item><item>Three <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass and a half of the best <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Sift your <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a pan. Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and warm them a little, so as to soften the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> but not to melt it entirely. Beat your <ingredient>egg;</ingredient> pour the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into your pan of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> then the <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> then the <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and lastly the <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> Stir all well together with a knife.</p><p>Spread some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board: lay the dough on it, and knead it well. Then divide it into small pieces of an equal size, and knead each piece into a little thick round cake. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> an iron pan, lay the cakes in it, and set them in a warm place to rise. Prick the tops with a fork. When they are quite light, bake them in a moderate oven.</p>
<ednote>The following notes appears at the bottom of page 58 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r7" size="smaller">*It is better to put a little of the beaten white of egg and sugar at first under the currant-jelly.</p>
</recipe><pb n="61" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=69"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>INDIAN POUND CAKE.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Eight <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One pint of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>One pint of <ingredient>Indian meal,</ingredient> sifted, and half a pint of <ingredient>wheat-flour.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> grated,--and a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of mixed <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item></list>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light. Stir the meal and <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> alternately, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor. Stir all well. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a tin pan, put in the mixture, and bake it in a moderate oven.</p><p>This cake should be eaten while fresh.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">CUP CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Five <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Two large tea-cups full of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></item><item>The same of <ingredient>brown sugar</ingredient> rolled fine.</item><item>The same of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One cup of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item>Five cups of <ingredient>flour</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a cup of powdered <ingredient>allspice</ingredient> and <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient></item><item>Half a cup of <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient></item></list>Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and warm them slightly. Warm also the <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and stir it into the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient>: then stir in, gradually, the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and set it away to get cool.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the mixture alternately with the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and other <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and stir the whole very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> small tins, nearly fill them with the mixture, and bake the cakes in a moderate oven.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="62" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=70"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">LOAF CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two pounds of sifted <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> setting aside half a pound to sprinkle in at the last.</item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> stoned, and cut in half.</item><item>One pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> washed and dried.</item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>wine.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>mixed spice,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of the best <ingredient>brewer's yeast;</ingredient> or more, if the <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> is not very strong.</item></list>Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and warm it till the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> is quite soft; then stir it together, and set it away to cool. It must not be made too warm. After you have beaten the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> mix them with the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir the whole into the pan of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor, and stir in the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> gradually. Having poured off the thin part from the top, stir the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and pour it into the mixture. Then sprinkle in the remainder of the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p><p>Have ready the <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> which must be well <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed, stir it gradually into the mixture. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a large tin pan, and put the cake into it. Cover it, and set in a warm place for five or six hours to rise. When quite light, bake it in a moderate oven.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>SUGAR BISCUITS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="larger"><item>Three pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>One pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A pound and a half of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>A small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> dissolved in <ingredient>water.</ingredient></item><item>Four table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>carraway seeds.</ingredient></item></list>Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>carraway seeds.</ingredient> Pour in the <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and <pb n="63" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=71"/> then the <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Lastly, put in the <ingredient>pearl-ash.</ingredient> Stir all well with a knife, and mix it thoroughly, till it becomes a lump of dough.</p><p><ingredient>Flour</ingredient> your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, and lay the dough on it. Knead it very well. Divide it into eight or ten pieces, and knead each piece separately. Then put them all together, and knead them very well in one lump.</p><p>Cut the dough in half, and roll it out into sheets, about half an inch thick. Beat the sheets of dough very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> on both sides, with the rolling-pin. Cut them out into round cakes with the edge of a tumbler. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> iron pans, and lay the cakes in them. Bake them of a very pale brown. If done too much, they will lose their taste.</p><p>These cakes kept in a stone jar, closely covered from the air, will continue perfectly good for several months.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>MILK BISCUITS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Six <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses of the best <ingredient>brewer's yeast,</ingredient> or three of good home-made <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item></list> Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and warm it slightly on the top of the stove, or near the fire. Sift the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> into a pan, and pour the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into it. Beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and pour them in also. Lastly the <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> Mix all well together with a knife.</p><p><ingredient>Flour</ingredient> your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, put the lump of dough on it, and knead it very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> Then cut the dough <pb n="64" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=72"/> in small pieces, and knead them into round balls. Stick the tops of them with a fork.</p><p>Lay them in buttered pans and set them to rise. They will probably be light in an hour. When they are quite light, put them in a moderate oven and bake them.</p><p>They are best when quite fresh.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>BUTTER BISCUITS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> or <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>salt</ingredient>-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item></list>Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and put the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to it. Wet it to a stiff dough with the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> or <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Mix it well with a knife.</p><p>Throw some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on the <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take the dough out of the pan, and knead it very well.</p><p>Roll it out into a large thick sheet, and beat it very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> on both sides with the rolling-pin. Beat it a long time.</p><p>Cut it out with a tin, or cup, into small round thick cakes. Beat each cake on both sides, with the rolling-pin. Prick them with a fork. Put them in buttered pans, and bake them of a light brown in a slow oven.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="65" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=73"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">GINGERBREAD <ingredient>NUTS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>One quart of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>-house <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> or more, if it is not very strong.</item><item>Twelve dozen grains of <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> }</item><item>Six dozen <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> } powdered and sifted.</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> }</item><item>A half tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> or sal aeratus, dissolved in a little <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></item></list>Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and mix it with the <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and other <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Wet the whole with the <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> and stir all well together with a knife. Then add the dissolved <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> or sal-aeratus.</p><p>Throw some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take the dough (a large handful at a time) and knead it in separate cakes. Then put all together, and knead it very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> for a long time, in one large lump. Cut the lump in half, roll it out in two even sheets, about half an inch thick, and cut it out in little cakes, with a very small tin, about the size of a cent. Lay them in buttered pans, and bake them in a moderate oven, taking care they do not scorch, as gingerbread is more liable to burn than any other cake.</p><p>You may, if you choose, shape the gingerbread <ingredient>nuts,</ingredient> by putting <ingredient>flour</ingredient> in your hand, taking a very small piece of the dough, and rolling it into a little round ball.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="66" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=74"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">COMMON GINGERBREAD.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A pint of <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Two pounds and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>A pint of of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient></item><item>A small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash,</ingredient> or less if it is strong.</item><item>A tea-cup full of <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient></item></list>Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient></p><p>Having dissolved the <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> in a little <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> stir it with the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>molasses</ingredient> alternately into the other ingredients. Stir it very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> for a long time, till it is quite light.</p><p>Put some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take out small portions of the dough, and make it with your hand into long rolls. Then curl up the rolls into round cakes, or twist two rolls together, or lay them in straight lengths or sticks side by side, and touching each other. Put them carefully in buttered pans, and bake them in a moderate oven, not hot enough to burn them. If they should get scorched, scrape off with a knife, or grater, all the burnt parts, before you put the cakes away.</p><p>You can, if you choose, cut out the dough with tins, in the shape of <ingredient>hearts,</ingredient> circles, ovals, &#38;c. or you may bake it all in one, and cut it in squares when cold.</p><p>If the mixture appears to be too thin, add, gradually, a little more sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></p>
</recipe> <pb n="67" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=75"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">LAFAYETTE GINGERBREAD.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Five <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>brown sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>-house <ingredient>molasses.</ingredient></item><item>A pound and a half of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>Four table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient></item><item>Two large sticks of <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> }</item><item>Three dozen grains of <ingredient>allspice,</ingredient> } powdered and sifted.</item><item>Three dozen of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> }</item><item>The <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and grated peel of two large <ingredient>lemons.</ingredient></item><item>A little <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> or sal-&#230;ratus.</item></list>Stir the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very well. Pour the <ingredient>molasses,</ingredient> at once, into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>ginger</ingredient> and other <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and stir all well together.</p><p>Put in the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> alternately, stirring all the time. Stir the whole very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> and put in the <ingredient>lemon</ingredient> at the last. When the whole is mixed, stir it till very light.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> an earthen pan, or a thick tin or iron one, and put the gingerbread in it. Bake it in a moderate oven, an hour or more, according to its thickness. Take care that it do not burn.</p><p>Or you may bake it in small cakes, or little tins.</p><p>Its lightness will be much improved by a small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> dissolved in a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> and stirred lightly in at the last.<ref target="r8">*</ref> Too much <ingredient>pearl-ash,</ingredient> will give it an unpleasant taste.</p><p>If you use <ingredient>pearl-ash,</ingredient> you must omit the <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> as its taste will be entirely destroyed by the <ingredient>pearl-ash.</ingredient> You may substitute for the <ingredient>lemon,</ingredient> some <ingredient>raisins</ingredient> and <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> well <ingredient>flour</ingredient>ed to prevent their sinking.</p><p id="r8" size="smaller">*If the <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> is strong, half a tea-spoonful will be sufficient, or less even will do. It is better to stir the <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> in, a little at a time, and you can tell by the taste of the mixture, when there is enough.</p> <pb n="68" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=76"/><p>This is the finest of all gingerbread, but should not be kept long, as in a few days it becomes very <ingredient>hard</ingredient> and stale.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">A DOVER CAKE.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A half tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash,</ingredient> dissolved in a little <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One glass of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient></item><item>Half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item><item>One grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Dissolve the <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> in <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> to a <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> and add to it gradually, the <ingredient>spice</ingredient> and liquor. Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> alternately, with the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add, gradually, the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir the whole very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a large tin pan, and put in the mixture. Bake it two hours or more, in a moderate oven. If not thick, an hour or an hour and a half will be sufficient.</p><p>Wrap it in a thick cloth, and keep it from the air, and it will continue moist and fresh for two weeks. The <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> will give it a dark colour.</p><p>It will be much improved by a pound of <ingredient>raisins,</ingredient> stoned and cut in half, and a pound of <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> well washed and dried.</p><p><ingredient>Flour</ingredient> the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> well, and stir it in at the last.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="69" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=77"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">CRULLERS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Three quarters of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> or seven if they are small.</item><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>A grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Cut the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> into the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> add the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and mix them well together.</p><p>Beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and pour them into the pan of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> &#38;c. Add the <ingredient>rose water,</ingredient> and mix the whole into a dough. If the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water</ingredient> are not found sufficient to wet it, add a very little <ingredient>cold water.</ingredient> Mix the dough very well with a knife.</p><p>Spread some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> on your <ingredient>paste</ingredient>-board, take the dough out of the pan, and knead it very well. Cut it into small pieces, and knead each separately. Put all the pieces together, and knead the whole in one lump. Roll it out into a large square sheet, about half an inch thick. Take a jagging-iron, or, if you have not one, a sharp knife; run it along the sheet, and cut the dough into long narrow slips. Twist them up in various forms. Have ready an iron pan with melted <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> Lay the crullers lightly in it, and fry them of a light brown, turning them with a knife and fork, so as not to break them, and taking care that both sides are equally done.</p><p>When sufficiently fried, spread them on a large dish to cool, and grate <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> over them.</p><p>Crullers may be made in a plainer way, with the best <ingredient>brown sugar,</ingredient> (rolled very fine,) and without <ingredient>spice</ingredient> or <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></p> <pb n="70" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=78"/><p>They can be fried, or rather boiled, in a deep iron pot. They should be done in a large quantity of <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> and taken out with a skimmer that has holes in it, and held on the skimmer till the <ingredient>lard</ingredient> drains from them. If for family use, they can be made an inch thick.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">DOUGH-<ingredient>NUTS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Three pounds of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>A pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient></item><item>Three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a large tea-cup full of best <ingredient>brewer's yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A pint and a half of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item><item>A grated <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient></item></list>Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> and <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and pour them into the mixture. Add the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> (half a tea-cup or two <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glasses full,) and then stir in the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> by degrees, so as to make it a soft dough. Cover it, and set it to rise.</p><p>When quite light, cut it in diamonds with a jagging-iron or a sharp knife, and fry them in <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> Grate <ingredient>loaf sugar</ingredient> over them when done.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">WAFFLES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Six <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A quarter of a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient></item><item>A pound and a half of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>A tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></item></list>Warm the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> slightly. Cut up the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in it and stir it a little. Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well, and pour <pb n="71" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=79"/> them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Sprinkle in half the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> gradually. Stir in the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> by degrees, and add the <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Stir in, gradually, the remainder of the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> so that it becomes a thick batter.</p><p>Heat your waffle-iron; then <ingredient>grease</ingredient> it well, and pour in some of the batter. Shut the iron tight, and bake the waffle on both sides, by turning the iron.</p><p>As the waffles are baked, spread them out separately on a clean napkin. When enough are done for a plate-full, lay them on a plate in two piles, buttering them, and sprinkling each with beaten <ingredient>cinnamon.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">SOFT MUFFINS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Five <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A quart of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item><item>Two ounces of <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>Two large table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>brewer's yeast</ingredient> or four of home-made <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>Enough of sifted <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to make a stiff batter.</item></list>Warm the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter</ingredient> together, and add to them the <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light and stir them into the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> and <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Then stir in the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and lastly, sufficient <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to make a thick batter.</p><p>Cover the mixture, and set it to rise, in a warm place, about three hours.</p><p>When it is quite light, <ingredient>grease</ingredient> your baking-iron, and your muffin rings. Set the rings on the iron, and pour the batter into them. Bake them a light brown. When you split them to put on the <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> do not cut them with a knife, but pull them open with your hands. Cutting them while hot will make them heavy.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="72" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=80"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>INDIAN</ingredient> BATTER CAKES.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A quart of sifted <ingredient>indian meal,</ingredient> }</item><item>A handful of <ingredient>wheat flour</ingredient> sifted, } mixed</item><item>Three <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> well beaten, }</item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of fresh <ingredient>brewer's yeast,</ingredient> or four of home-made <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>A quart of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item></list>Make the <ingredient>milk</ingredient> quite warm, and then put into it the <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> stirring them well. Beat the <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and stir them into the mixture. Then, gradually stir in the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> and <ingredient>indian meal.</ingredient></p><p>Cover the batter, and set it to rise four or five hours. Or if the weather is cold, and you want the cakes for breakfast, you may mix the batter late the night before.</p><p>Should you find it sour in the morning, dissolve a small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash</ingredient> in as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> as will cover it, and stir it into the batter, letting it set afterwards at least half an hour. This will take off the acid.</p><p><ingredient>Grease</ingredient> your baking-iron, and pour on it a ladle-full of the batter. When brown on one side, turn the cake on the other.</p><p id="r9" size="smaller">*<ingredient>Indian</ingredient> batter cakes may be made in a plain and expeditious way, by putting three pints of <ingredient>cold water</ingredient> or <ingredient>cold milk</ingredient> into a pan, and gradually sifting into it (stirring all the time) a quart of <ingredient>indian meal</ingredient> mixed with half a pint of <ingredient>wheat-flour,</ingredient> and a small spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Stir it very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> and it may be baked immediately, as it is not necessary to set it to rise.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="73" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=81"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="indent1" placement="heading">FLANNEL CAKES OR CRUMPETS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two pounds of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Three table-spoonfuls of the best <ingredient>brewer's yeast,</ingredient> or four and a half of home-made <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></item></list>Mix a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> with the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and set the pan before the fire. Then warm the <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and stir into it the <ingredient>flour</ingredient> so as to make a stiff batter. Beat the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> Add the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> and <ingredient>yeast</ingredient> to the batter, and beat all well together. If it is too stiff, add a little more warm <ingredient>milk.</ingredient></p><p>Cover the pan closely and set it to rise near the fire. Bake it, when quite light.</p><p>Have your baking-iron hot. <ingredient>Grease</ingredient> it, and pour on a ladle-full of batter. Let it bake slowly, and when done on one side, turn it on the other.</p><p><ingredient>Butter</ingredient> the cakes, cut them across, and send them to table hot.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">ROLLS.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Three pints of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> sifted.</item><item>Two tea-spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>Four table-spoonfuls of the best <ingredient>brewer's yeast,</ingredient> or six of home-made <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of luke-<ingredient>warm water.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint more of <ingredient>warm water,</ingredient> and a little more <ingredient>flour</ingredient> to mix in before the kneading.</item></list>Mix the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> with the <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and make a deep hole in the middle. Stir the <ingredient>warm water</ingredient> into the <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> and pour it into the hole in the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir it with <pb n="74" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=82"/>a spoon just enough to make a thin batter, and sprinkle some <ingredient>flour</ingredient> over the top. Cover the pan, and set it in a warm place for several hours.</p><p>When it is light, add half a pint more of luke-<ingredient>warm water;</ingredient> and make it, with a little more <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> into a dough. Knead it very well for ten minutes. Then divide it into small pieces, and knead each separately. Make them into round cakes or rolls. Cover them, and set them to rise about an hour and a half.</p><p>Bake them, and when done, let them remain in the oven, without the lid, for about ten minutes.</p>
</recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="generalfood"> <pb n="NONE OF THE ABOVE" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=83"/><hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">PART THE THIRD.</hd><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=84"/> <pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=85"/><hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">SWEETMEATS.</hd>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose align="center" rend="bold">GENERAL DIRECTIONS.</purpose> In preparing <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> for <ingredient>sweetmeats,</ingredient> let it be entirely dissolved, before you put it on the fire. If you dissolve it in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> allow about half a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient></p><p>If you boil the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> before you add the <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> to it, it will be improved in clearness by passing it through a flannel bag. Skim off the brown scum, all the time it is boiling.</p><p>If <ingredient>sweetmeats</ingredient> are boiled too long, they lose their flavour and become of a dark colour.</p><p>If boiled too short a time, they will not keep well.</p><p>You may ascertain when <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> is done, by dropping a small spoonful into a glass of <ingredient>water.</ingredient></p><p>If it spreads and mixes with the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> it requires more boiling. If it sinks in a lump to the bottom, it is sufficiently done. This trial must be made after the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> is cold.</p><p><ingredient>Raspberry jelly</ingredient> requires more boiling than any other sort. <ingredient>Black currant jelly</ingredient> less.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="78" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=86"/>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>APPLE JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Take the best <ingredient>pippin,</ingredient> or bell-flower <ingredient>apples.</ingredient> No others will make good <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient> Pare, core, and quarter them. Lay them in a preserving kettle, and put to them as much <ingredient>water</ingredient> only, as will cover them, and as much <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> as you choose. Boil them till they are soft, but not till they break. Drain off the <ingredient>water</ingredient> through a colander, and mash the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> with the back of a spoon. Put them into a <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> bag, set a deep dish or pan under it, and squeeze out the <ingredient>juice.</ingredient></p><p>To every pint of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> broken up, and the juice of two <ingredient>lemons.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>apple</ingredient>-juice, the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> into the preserving kettle. Boil it twenty minutes, skimming it well. Take it immediately from the kettle, and pour it warm into your glasses, but not so hot as to break them. When cold, cover each glass with <ingredient>white paper</ingredient> dipped in <ingredient>brandy,</ingredient> and tie it down tight with another <ingredient>paper.</ingredient> Keep them in a cool place.</p><p><variation><alt synonym1="Quince Jelly"> Quince Jelly</alt> is made in the same manner, but do not pare the <ingredient>quinces.</ingredient> Quarter them only.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>RED CURRANT JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Wash your <ingredient>currants,</ingredient> drain them, and pick them from the stalks. Mash them with the back of a spoon. Put them in a jelly-bag, and squeeze it till all the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> is pressed out.</p> <pb n="79" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=87"/><p>To every pint of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> allow a pound of the best <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into your kettle, and boil them twenty minutes, skimming all the while. Pour it warm into your glasses, and when cold, tie it up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient> <ingredient>Jellies</ingredient> should never be allowed to get cold in the kettle. If boiled too long, they will lose their flavour, and become of a dark colour.</p><p><variation><alt synonym1="Strawberry jelly, raspberry jelly, blackberry jelly, grape jelly"> Strawberry, raspberry, blackberry, and  grape jelly </alt> may be made in the same manner, and with the same proportion of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient></variation></p>
<p><variation><alt synonym1="Red currant jelly"> Red currant jelly</alt> may also be made in a very simple manner, by putting the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> whole into the kettle, with the <ingredient>sugar;</ingredient> allowing a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>currants.</ingredient> Boil them together twenty minutes, skimming carefully. Then pour them into a sieve, with a pan under it. Let them drain through the sieve into the pan, pressing them down with the back of a spoon.</variation></p><p>Take the <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> while warm, out of the pan, and put it into your glasses. Tie it up with <ingredient>brandy paper</ingredient> when cold.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>BLACK CURRANT JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Pick the <ingredient>currants</ingredient> from the stalks, wash and drain them. Mash them soft with a spoon, put them in a bag, and squeeze out the <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> To each pint of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> allow three quarters of a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into a preserving kettle, and boil them about ten minutes, skimming them<pb n="80" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=88"/> well. Take it immediately out of the kettle. Put it warm into your glasses. Tie it up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p>The <ingredient>juice of black currants</ingredient> is so very thick, that it requires less <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and less boiling than any other <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>GOOSEBERRY JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Cut the <ingredient>gooseberries</ingredient> in half, (they must be green) and put them in a jar closely covered. Set the jar in an oven, or pot filled with <ingredient>boiling water.</ingredient> Keep the <ingredient>water</ingredient> boiling round the jar till the <ingredient>gooseberries</ingredient> are soft, take them out, mash them with a spoon, and put them into a <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> bag to drain. When all the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> is squeezed out, measure it, and to a pint of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into the preserving kettle, and boil them twenty minutes, skimming carefully. Put the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> warm into your glasses. Tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p><variation><alt synonym1="Cranberry Jelly"> Cranberry jelly</alt> is made in the same manner.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>GRAPE JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Pick the <ingredient>grapes</ingredient> from the stems, wash and drain them. Mash them with a spoon. Put them in the preserving kettle, and cover them closely with a large plate. Boil them ten minutes. Then pour them into your <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> bag, and squeeze out the <ingredient>juice.</ingredient></p> <pb n="81" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=89"/><p>Allow a pint of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>juice</ingredient> into your kettle, and boil them twenty minutes, skimming them well.</p><p>Fill your glasses while the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> is warm, and tie them up with <ingredient>brandy papers.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PEACH JELLY.</ingredient></purpose> Wipe the wool off your <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> (which should be <ingredient>free-stones</ingredient> and not too ripe) and cut them in quarters. Crack the stones, and break the kernels small.</p><p>Put the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> and the kernels into a covered jar, set them in <ingredient>boiling water,</ingredient> and let them boil till they are soft.</p><p>Strain them through a jelly-bag, till all the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> is squeezed out. Allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> to a pint of <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>juice</ingredient> into a preserving kettle, and boil them twenty minutes, skimming carefully.</p><p>Put the <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> warm into your glasses, and when cold, tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p><variation><alt synonym1="Plum Jelly, Green-gage Jelly"> Plum, and green-gage jelly</alt> may be made in the same manner, with the kernels, which greatly improve the flavour.</variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED QUINCES.</ingredient></purpose> Pare and core your <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> carefully taking out the parts that are knotty and defective. Cut them into quarters, or into round slices. Put them into a preserving kettle, and cover them with the parings and a very little <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Lay a large plate <pb n="82" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=90"/> over them to keep in the steam, and boil them till they are tender.</p><p>Take out the <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> and strain the liquor through a bag. To every pint of liquor, allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Boil the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> together, about ten minutes, skimming it well. Then put in the <ingredient>quinces,</ingredient> and boil them gently twenty minutes. When the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> seems to have completely penetrated them, take them out, put them in a glass jar, and pour the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> over them warm. Tie them up, when cold, with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p>In preserving <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> that is boiled first without the <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> it is generally better (after the first boiling) to let it stand till next day before you put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to it.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED PIPPINS.</ingredient></purpose> Pare and core some of the largest and finest <ingredient>pippins.</ingredient> Put them in your preserving kettle,<ref target="r10">*</ref> with some <ingredient>lemon-peel,</ingredient> and all the <ingredient>apple</ingredient>-parings. Add a very little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and cover them closely. Boil them till they are tender, taking care they do not burn. Take out the <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and spread them on a large dish to cool. Pour the liquor into a bag, and strain it well. Put it into your kettle with a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> to each pint of <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> and add <ingredient>lemon juice</ingredient> to your taste. Boil it five minutes, skimming it well. Then put in the whole <ingredient>apples,</ingredient> and boil them slowly half an hour, or till they are quite soft and clear. Put them with the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> into your jars, and when quite cold, tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p id="r10" size="smaller">*The use of brass or bell-metal kettles is now most entirely superseded by the enamelled kettles of iron lined with china, called preserving kettles; brass and bell-metal having always been objectionable on account of the <ingredient>verdigris</ingredient> which collects in them.</p><pb n="83" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=91"/><p><ingredient>Preserved apples</ingredient> are only intended for present use, as they will not keep long.</p><p><ingredient>Pears</ingredient> may be done in the same way, either whole or cut in half. They may be flavoured either with <ingredient>lemon or cinnamon,</ingredient> or both. The <ingredient>pears</ingredient> for preserving should be green.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED PEACHES.</ingredient></purpose> Take the largest and finest <ingredient>free-stone peaches,</ingredient> before they are too ripe. Pare them, and cut them in halves or in quarters. Crack the stones, and take out the kernels, and break them in pieces. Put the <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> with the parings and kernels, into your preserving kettle, with a very little <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Boil them till they are tender. Take out the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> and spread them on a large dish to cool. Strain the liquor through a bag or sieve. Next day, measure the <ingredient>juice,</ingredient> and to each pint allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into the kettle with the <ingredient>peaches,</ingredient> and boil them slowly half an hour, or till they are quite soft, skimming all the time. Take the <ingredient>peaches</ingredient> out, put them into your jars, and pour the warm liquor over them. When cold, tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p>If boiled too long, they will look dull, and be of a dark colour.<ref target="r11">*</ref></p>
<ednote>The notes below appears at the bottom of page 83 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r11" size="smaller">*To preserve peaches whole, pare them and thrust out the stones with a skewer. Then proceed as above, only blanch the kernels and keep them whole. When the peaches are done, stick a kernel into the hole of every peach, before you put them into the jars. Large fruit will keep best in broad shallow stone pots.</p><p>If you do not wish the juice to be very thick, do not put it on to boil with the sugar, but first boil the <pb n="84" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=92"/> sugar alone, with only as much water as will dissolve it, and skim it well. Let the sugar, in all cases, be entirely melted before it goes on the fire. Having boiled the sugar and water, and skimmed it to a clear syrup, then put in your juice and fruit together, and boil them till completely penetrated with the sugar.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">PRESERVED CRAB APPLES.</purpose> Wash your <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient> Cover the bottom of your preserving kettle with <ingredient>grape leaves.</ingredient> Put in the <ingredient>apples.</ingredient> Hang them over the fire, with a very little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and cover them closely. Do not allow them to boil, but let them simmer gently till they are yellow. Take them out, and spread them on a large dish to cool. Pare and core them. Put them again into the kettle, with fresh <ingredient>vine-leaves</ingredient> under and over them, and a very little <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Hang them over the fire till they are green. Do not let them boil.</p><p>Take them out, weigh them, and allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>crab-apples.</ingredient> Put to the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> just <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to dissolve it. When it is all melted, put it on the fire, and boil and skim it. Then put in your <ingredient>fruit,</ingredient> and boil the <ingredient>apples</ingredient> till they are quite clear and soft. Put them in jars, and pour the warm liquor over them. When cold, tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED PLUMS.</ingredient></purpose> Cut your <ingredient>plums</ingredient> in half, (they must not be quite ripe,) and take out the stones. Weigh the <ingredient>plums,</ingredient> <pb n="85" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=93"/> and allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient> Crack the stones, take out the kernels and break them in pieces. Boil the <ingredient>plums</ingredient> and kernels very slowly for about fifteen minutes, in as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as possible. Then spread them on a large dish to cool, and strain the liquor.</p><p>Next day make your <ingredient>syrup.</ingredient> Melt the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in as little <ingredient>water</ingredient> as will suffice to dissolve it, (about half a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>) and boil it a few minutes, skimming it till quite clear. Then put in your <ingredient>plums</ingredient> with the liquor, and boil them fifteen minutes. Put them in jars, pour the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> over them warm, and tie them up, when cold, with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient><ref target="r12">*</ref></p><p><ingredient>Syrups</ingredient> may be improved in clearness, by adding to the dissolved <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>water,</ingredient> some <ingredient>white of egg</ingredient> very well beaten, allowing the <ingredient>white of one egg</ingredient> to each pound of <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Boil it very <ingredient>hard,</ingredient> and skim it well, that it may be quite clear before you put in your <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<ednote>The following notes appears at the bottom of page 85 in the original text.</ednote><p id="r12" size="smaller">*Plums for common use, are very good done in molasses. Put your plums into an earthen vessel that holds a gallon, having first slit each plum with a knife. To three quarts of plums put a pint of molasses. Cover them and set them on hot coals in the chimney corner. Let them stew for twelve hours or more, occasionally stirring them, and renewing the coals. Next day put them up in jars. Done in this manner they will keep till the next spring.</p>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED STRAWBERRIES.</ingredient></purpose> Weigh the <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> after you have picked off the stems. To each pound of <ingredient>fruit</ingredient> allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> which must be powdered. Strew half of the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over the <ingredient>strawberries,</ingredient> and let them stand in a cold place two or three hours. Then put them in a preserving kettle over a slow <pb n="86" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=94"/> fire, and by degrees strew on the rest of the <ingredient>sugar.</ingredient> Boil them fifteen or twenty minutes, and skim them well.</p><p>Put them in wide-mouthed bottles, and when cold, seal the corks.</p><p>If you wish to do them whole, take them carefully out of the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> (one at a time) while boiling. Spread them to cool on large dishes, not letting the <ingredient>strawberries</ingredient> touch each other, and when cool, return them to the <ingredient>syrup,</ingredient> and boil them a little longer. Repeat this several times.</p><p>Keep the bottles in dry sand, in a place that is cool and not damp.</p><p><variation><alt synonym1="Gooseberries Preserved, Currents Preserved, Raspberries Preserved, Cherries Preserved, Grapes Preserved"> Gooseberries, currants, raspberries, cherries and grapes</alt> may be done in the same manner. The stones must be taken from the <ingredient>cherries</ingredient> (which should be morellas, or the largest and best <ingredient>red cherries;</ingredient>) and the <ingredient>seeds</ingredient> should be extracted from the <ingredient>grapes</ingredient> with the sharp point of a penknife. <ingredient>Gooseberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>grapes,</ingredient> and <ingredient>cherries,</ingredient> require longer boiling than <ingredient>strawberries,</ingredient> <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> or <ingredient>currants.</ingredient></variation></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED CRANBERRIES.</ingredient></purpose> Wash your <ingredient>cranberries,</ingredient> weigh them, and to each pound allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Dissolve the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a very little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> (about half a pint of <ingredient>water</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>) and set it on the fire in a preserving kettle. Boil it nearly ten minutes, skimming it well. Then put in your <ingredient>cranberries,</ingredient> and boil them slowly, till they are quite soft, and of a fine colour.</p><p>Put them warm into your jars or glasses, and tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper,</ingredient> when cold.</p> <pb n="87" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=95"/><p>All sorts of <ingredient>sweetmeats</ingredient> keep better in glasses, than in stone or earthen jars. When opened for use, they should be tied up again immediately, as exposure to the air spoils them.</p><p>Common glass tumblers are very convenient for <ingredient>jellies,</ingredient> and preserved small <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient> <ingredient>White</ingredient> jars are better than stone or earthen, for large <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED PUMPKIN.</ingredient></purpose> Cut slices from a fine high-coloured <ingredient>pumpkin,</ingredient> and cut the slices into chips about the thickness of a dollar. The chips should be of an equal size, six inches in length, and an inch broad. Weigh them, and allow to each pound of <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> chips, a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Have ready a sufficient number of fine <ingredient>lemons,</ingredient> pare off the yellow <ingredient>rind,</ingredient> and lay it aside. Cut the <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> in half, and squeeze the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> into a bowl. Allow a gill of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> to each pound of <ingredient>pumpkin.</ingredient></p><p>Put the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> into a broad pan laying the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> among it. Pour the <ingredient>lemon-juice</ingredient> over it. Cover the pan, and let the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> chips, <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> and <ingredient>lemon-juice,</ingredient> set all night.</p><p>Early in the morning put the whole into a preserving pan, and boil all together (skimming it well) till the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> becomes clear and crisp, but not till it breaks. It should have the appearance of lemon-candy. You may if you choose, put some <ingredient>lemon-peel</ingredient> with it, cut in very small pieces.</p><p>Half an hour's boiling (or a little more) is generally sufficient.</p><p>When it is done, take out the <ingredient>pumpkin,</ingredient> spread it on a large dish, and strain the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> through a bag. Put the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> into your jars or glasses, pour the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> over it, and tie it up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><pb n="88" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=96"/><p>If properly done, this is a very fine <ingredient>sweetmeat.</ingredient> The taste of the <ingredient>pumpkin</ingredient> will be lost in that of the <ingredient>lemon and sugar,</ingredient> and the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> is particularly pleasant. It is eaten without <ingredient>cream,</ingredient> like preserved <ingredient>ginger.</ingredient> It may be laid on puff-<ingredient>paste</ingredient> shells, after they are baked.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PRESERVED PINE-APPLE.</ingredient></purpose> Pare your <ingredient>pine-apples,</ingredient> and cut them in thick slices. Weigh the slices and to each pound allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Dissolve the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> in a very small quantity of <ingredient>water,</ingredient> stir it, and set it over the fire in a preserving-kettle. Boil it ten minutes, skimming it well. Then put in it the <ingredient>pine-apple</ingredient> slices, and boil them till they are clear and soft, but not till they break. About half an hour (or perhaps less time) will suffice. Let them cool in a large dish or pan, before you put them into your jars, which you must do carefully, lest they break. Pour the <ingredient>syrup</ingredient> over them. Tie them up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>RASPBERRY JAM.</ingredient></purpose>Allow a pound of <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> to a pound of <ingredient>fruit.</ingredient> Mash the <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> and put them with the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into your preserving kettle. Boil it slowly for an hour, skimming it well. Tie it up with <ingredient>brandy paper.</ingredient></p><p>All jams are made in the same manner.</p>
</recipe>
</chapter>
<chapter class1="generalfood"> 
<section><pb n="89" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=97"/><hd align="center" size="larger" rend="bold">APPENDIX.</hd><pb n="90" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=98"/><hd align="center">CONTENTS.</hd><list><item>A-la-mode Beef - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf099.jpg">91</ref></item><item><ingredient>Chicken</ingredient> Pudding - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf100.jpg">92</ref></item><item>A boned <ingredient>Turkey</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf101.jpg">93</ref></item><item>Collared <ingredient>Pork</ingredient> - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf102.jpg">94</ref></item><item>Spiced <ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf103.jpg">95</ref></item><item>Stewed <ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf104.jpg">96</ref></item><item><ingredient>Oyster</ingredient> Soup - - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf104.jpg">96</ref></item><item>Fried <ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf104.jpg">96</ref></item><item>Baked <ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf105.jpg">97</ref></item><item><ingredient>Oyster</ingredient> Patties - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf105.jpg">97</ref></item><item><ingredient>Oyster Sauce</ingredient> - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf105.jpg">97</ref></item><item>Pickled <ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf106.jpg">98</ref></item><item><ingredient>Chicken</ingredient> Salad - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf106.jpg">98</ref></item><item><ingredient>Lobster</ingredient> Salad - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf107.jpg">99</ref></item><item><ingredient>Stewed Mushrooms</ingredient> - - - - 
<ref target="sevf107.jpg">99</ref></item><item><ingredient>Peach Cordial</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf108.jpg">100</ref></item><item><ingredient>Cherry Bounce</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf108.jpg">100</ref></item><item><ingredient>Raspberry Cordial</ingredient> - - - 
<ref target="sevf108.jpg">100</ref></item><item><ingredient>Blackberry Cordial</ingredient> - - - 
<ref target="sevf109.jpg">101</ref></item><item><ingredient>Ginger Beer</ingredient> - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf109.jpg">101</ref></item><item><ingredient>Jelly</ingredient> Cake - - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf110.jpg">102</ref></item><item><ingredient>Rice</ingredient> Cakes for Breakfast 
<ref target="sevf111.jpg">103</ref></item><item>Ground <ingredient>Rice</ingredient> Pudding - - 
<ref target="sevf111.jpg">103</ref></item><item><ingredient>Tomata Ketchup</ingredient> - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf111.jpg">103</ref></item><item><ingredient>Yeast</ingredient> - - - - - - - - - 
<ref target="sevf112.jpg">104</ref></item></list>
</section><pb n="91" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=99"/><hd rend="bold" align="center" size="larger">MISCELLANEOUS RECEIPTS.</hd>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">A-LA-MODE <ingredient>BEEF.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A round of fresh <ingredient>beef</ingredient> weighing from eighteen to twenty pounds.</item><item>A pound of the <ingredient>fat of bacon</ingredient> or <ingredient>corned pork.</ingredient></item><item>The <ingredient>marrow</ingredient> from the <ingredient>bone</ingredient> of the <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> }</item><item>A quarter of a pound of <ingredient>beef-suet,</ingredient> } chopped together.</item><item>Two bundles of pot <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> small <ingredient>onions,</ingredient> &#38;c. chopped fine.</item><item>Two large bunches of <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> }</item><item>Two bunches of <ingredient>sweet basil,</ingredient> } sufficient when powdered to make four table-spoonfuls of each.</item><item>Two large <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> }</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> } beaten to a powder.</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> }</item><item>One table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>One table-spoonful of <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient></item><item>Two glasses of <ingredient>madeira wine.</ingredient></item></list> If your a-la-mode <ingredient>beef</ingredient> is to be eaten cold, prepare it three days before it is wanted.</p><p>Take out the <ingredient>bone.</ingredient> Fasten up the opening with skewers, and tie the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> all round with tape. Rub it all over on both sides with <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> A large <ingredient>round of beef</ingredient> will be more tender than a small one.</p><p>Chop the <ingredient>marrow</ingredient> and <ingredient>suet</ingredient> together. Pound the <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Chop the pot-<ingredient>herbs</ingredient> very fine. Pick the sweet-<ingredient>marjoram</ingredient> and sweet-<ingredient>basil</ingredient> clean from the stalks, and rub the leaves to a powder. You must have at least four table-spoonfuls of each. Add the <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> and mix well together all the ingredients that compose the <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient></p><p>Cut the <ingredient>fat</ingredient> of the <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> or <ingredient>pork</ingredient> into pieces about a quarter of an inch thick and two inches long. With a sharp knife make deep incisions all over the <ingredient>round of beef</ingredient> and very near each other. Put first a little of the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> into each hole, then a slip of the <ingredient>bacon</ingredient> pressed down <ingredient>hard</ingredient> and covered with more <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient> Pour a little <ingredient>wine</ingredient> into each hole.</p><pb n="92" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=100"/><p>When you have thus stuffed the upper side of the <ingredient>beef,</ingredient> turn it over and stuff in the same manner the under side. If the round is very large, you will require a larger quantity of <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient></p><p>Put it in a deep baking dish, pour over it some <ingredient>wine,</ingredient> cover it, and let it set till next morning. It will be much the better for lying all night in the <ingredient>seasoning.</ingredient></p><p>Next day put a little <ingredient>water</ingredient> in the dish, set it in a covered oven, and bake or stew it gently for twelve hours at least, or more if it is a large round. It will be much improved by stewing it in <ingredient>lard.</ingredient> Let it remain all night in the oven.</p><p>If it is to be eaten hot at dinner, put it in to stew the evening before, and let it cook till dinner-time next day. Stir some <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and a beaten <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient></p><p>If brought to table cold, cover it all over with <ingredient>green parsley,</ingredient> and stick a large bunch of something green in the centre.</p><p>What is left will make an excellent hash the next day.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame" class2="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>CHICKEN</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose> Cut up a pair of young <ingredient>chickens,</ingredient> and season them with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg.</ingredient> Put them into a pot with two large spoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and <ingredient>water</ingredient> enough to cover them. Stew them gently; and when about half cooked, take them out and set them away to cool. Pour off the <ingredient>gravy,</ingredient> and reserve it to be served up separately.</p><p>In the mean time, make a batter as if for a pudding, of eight table-spoonfuls of sifted <ingredient>flour</ingredient> stirred gradually into a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> six <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> well beaten and added by degrees to the mixture, and a very little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put a layer of <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> in the bottom of a deep dish, and pour over it some of the batter; then another <pb n="93" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=101"/> layer of <ingredient>chicken,</ingredient> and then some more batter; and so on till the dish is full, having a cover of batter at the top. Bake it till it is brown. Then break an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> into the <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> which you have set away, give it a boil, and send it to table in a <ingredient>sauce</ingredient>-boat to eat with the pudding.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">A BONED <ingredient>TURKEY.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A large <ingredient>turkey.</ingredient></item><item>Three sixpenny loaves of <ingredient>stale bread.</ingredient></item><item>One pound of fresh <ingredient>butter.</ingredient></item><item>Four <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>One bunch of pot-<ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> <ingredient>parsley,</ingredient> <ingredient>thyme,</ingredient> and little <ingredient>onions.</ingredient></item><item>Two bunches of <ingredient>sweet marjoram.</ingredient></item><item>Two bunches of <ingredient>sweet basil.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> }</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> } pounded fine.</item><item>A quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> }</item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient></item><item>Skewers, tape, needle, and coarse thread will be wanted.</item></list>Grate the <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and put the crusts in <ingredient>water</ingredient> to soften. Then break them up small into the pan of crumbled <ingredient>bread.</ingredient> Cut up a pound of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> in the pan of <ingredient>bread.</ingredient> Rub the <ingredient>herbs</ingredient> to powder, and have two table-spoonfuls of sweet-<ingredient>marjoram</ingredient> and two of <ingredient>sweet basil,</ingredient> or more of each if the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> is very large. Chop the pot-<ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and pound the <ingredient>spice.</ingredient> Then add the <ingredient>salt</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> and mix all the ingredients well together. Beat slightly four <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and mix them with the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> and <ingredient>bread crumbs.</ingredient></p><p>After the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> is drawn, take a sharp knife and, beginning at the <ingredient>wings,</ingredient> carefully separate the flesh from the <ingredient>bone,</ingredient> scraping it down as you go; and avoid tearing or breaking the <ingredient>skin.</ingredient> Next, loosen the flesh from the <ingredient>breast</ingredient> and back, and then from the <ingredient>thighs.</ingredient> It requires great care and patience to do it nicely. When all the flesh is thus loosened, <pb n="94" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=102"/> take the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> by the <ingredient>neck,</ingredient> give it a pull, and the skeleton will come out entire from the flesh, as easily as you draw your hand out of a glove. The flesh will then be a shapeless mass. With a needle and thread mend or sew up any holes that may be found in the <ingredient>skin.</ingredient></p><p>Take up a handful of the <ingredient>seasoning,</ingredient> squeeze it <ingredient>hard</ingredient> and proceed to stuff the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> with it, beginning at the <ingredient>wings,</ingredient> next to the body, and then the <ingredient>thighs.</ingredient></p><p>If you stuff it properly, it will again assume its natural shape. Stuff it very <ingredient>hard.</ingredient> When all the <ingredient>stuffing</ingredient> is in, sew up the <ingredient>breast,</ingredient> and skewer the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> into its proper form, so that it will look as if it had not been boned.</p><p>Tie it round with tape and bake it three hours or more. Make a <ingredient>gravy</ingredient> of the <ingredient>giblets</ingredient> chopped, and enrich it with some <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and an <ingredient>egg.</ingredient></p><p>If the <ingredient>turkey</ingredient> is to be eaten cold, drop spoonfuls of <ingredient>red currant jelly</ingredient> all over it, and in the dish round it.</p><p>A large <ingredient>fowl</ingredient> may be boned and stuffed in the same manner.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">COLLARED <ingredient>PORK.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>A <ingredient>leg</ingredient> of fresh <ingredient>pork,</ingredient> not large.</item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of powdered <ingredient>sage.</ingredient></item><item>Two table spoonfuls of <ingredient>sweet marjoram,</ingredient> }</item><item>One table-spoonful of <ingredient>sweet basil,</ingredient> } powdered.</item><item>A quarter of an ounce of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> }</item><item>Half an ounce of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> } powdered.</item><item>Two <ingredient>nutmegs,</ingredient> }</item><item>A bunch of pot-<ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> chopped small.</item><item>A sixpenny loaf of <ingredient>stale bread,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>Half a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> cut into the <ingredient>bread.</ingredient></item><item>Two <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>A table-spoonful of <ingredient>black pepper.</ingredient></item></list>Grate the <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and having softened the crust in <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mix it with the crumbs. Prepare all the <pb n="95" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=103"/>other ingredients, and mix them well with the grated <ingredient>bread</ingredient> and <ingredient>egg.</ingredient></p><p>Take the <ingredient>bone</ingredient> out of a <ingredient>leg of pork,</ingredient> and rub the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> well on both sides with <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Spread the <ingredient>seasoning</ingredient> thick all over the <ingredient>meat.</ingredient> Then roll it up very tightly and tie it round with tape.</p><p>Put it into a deep dish with a little <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and bake it two hours. If eaten hot, put an <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and some <ingredient>wine</ingredient> into the <ingredient>gravy.</ingredient> When cold, cut it down into round slices.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">SPICED <ingredient>OYSTERS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two hundred large fresh <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient></item><item>Four table-spoonfuls of strong <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></item><item>A <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> grated.</item><item>Three dozen of <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> whole.</item><item>Eight blades of <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> whole.</item><item>Two tea-spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt</ingredient> if the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are fresh.</item><item>Two tea-spoonfuls of whole <ingredient>allspice.</ingredient></item><item>As much <ingredient>cayenne pepper</ingredient> as will lie on the point of a knife.</item></list>Put the <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> with their liquor, into a large earthen pitcher. Add to them the <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> and all the other ingredients. Stir all well together. Set them in the stove, or over a slow fire, keeping them covered. Take them off the fire several times, and stir them to the bottom. As soon as they boil completely they are sufficiently done; if they boil too long they will be <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p><p>Pour them directly out of the pitcher into a pan, and set them away to cool. They must not be eaten till quite cold, or indeed till next day.</p><p>If you wish to keep them a week, put a smaller quantity of <ingredient>spice,</ingredient> or they will taste too much of it by setting so long. Let them be well covered.</p><p><ingredient>Oysters</ingredient> in the shell may be kept all winter by laying them in a heap in the cellar, with the concave side upwards to hold in the liquor. Sprinkle them every day with strong <ingredient>salt and water,</ingredient> and <pb n="96" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=104"/> then with <ingredient>indian meal.</ingredient> Cover them with matting or an old carpet.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">STEWED <ingredient>OYSTERS.</ingredient></purpose> Open the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and strain the liquor. Put to the liquor some grated <ingredient>stale bread,</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> adding a glass of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient> Boil the liquor with these ingredients, and then pour it scalding hot over the dish of raw <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> This will cook them sufficiently.</p><p>Have ready some slices of <ingredient>buttered toast</ingredient> with the crust cut off. When the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are done, dip the <ingredient>toast</ingredient> in the liquor, and lay the pieces round the sides and in the bottom of a deep dish. Pour the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and liquor upon the <ingredient>toast,</ingredient> and send them to table hot.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="soups"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>OYSTER</ingredient> SOUP.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Three pints of large fresh <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient></item><item>Two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour.</ingredient></item><item>A bunch of <ingredient>sweet herbs.</ingredient></item><item>A saucer full of chopped <ingredient>celery.</ingredient></item><item>A quart of <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient></item><item><ingredient>Pepper</ingredient> to your taste.</item></list>Take the liquor of three pints of <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> Strain it, and set it on the fire. Put into it, <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> to your taste, two table-spoonfuls of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> rolled in <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> and a bunch of <ingredient>sweet marjoram</ingredient> and other pot-<ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> with a saucer full of chopped <ingredient>celery.</ingredient> When it boils, add a quart of <ingredient>rich milk</ingredient>--and as soon as it boils again, take out the <ingredient>herbs,</ingredient> and put in the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> just before you send it to table. Boiling them in the soup will shrivel them and destroy their taste.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">FRIED <ingredient>OYSTERS.</ingredient></purpose> For frying, choose the largest and finest <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> Beat some <ingredient>yolks of eggs,</ingredient> and mix with them grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> and a small quantity of beaten <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and a little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Having stirred this<pb n="97" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=105"/> batter well, dip your <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> into it, and fry them in <ingredient>lard,</ingredient> till they are of a light brown colour. Take care not to do them too much. Serve them up hot.</p><p>For grated <ingredient>bread,</ingredient> some substitute <ingredient>crackers</ingredient> pounded to a powder, and mixed with <ingredient>yolk of egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>spice.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">BAKED OR SCOLLOPED <ingredient>OYSTERS.</ingredient></purpose> Grate a small loaf of stale-<ingredient>bread.</ingredient> <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a deep dish well, and cover the sides and bottom with <ingredient>bread crumbs.</ingredient> Put in half the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> with a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>pepper.</ingredient> Cover them with crumbs and small bits of <ingredient>butter</ingredient> strewed over them. Then put in the remainder of the <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient> Season them. Cover them as before with crumbs and <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> If the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are fresh, pour in a little of the liquor. If they are <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> substitute a little <ingredient>water.</ingredient> Bake them a very short time. You may cook them in the small scolloped dishes made for the purpose.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>OYSTER</ingredient> PATTIES.</purpose> Make some rich-puff-<ingredient>paste,</ingredient> and bake it in very small tin patty pans. When cool, turn them out upon a large dish.</p><p>Stew some large fresh <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> with a few <ingredient>cloves,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>mace</ingredient> and <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> some <ingredient>yolk of egg</ingredient> boiled <ingredient>hard</ingredient> and grated, a little <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and as much of the <ingredient>oyster liquor</ingredient> as will cover them. When they have stewed a little while, take them out of the pan, and set them away to cool. When quite cold, lay two or three <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> in each shell of puff-<ingredient>paste.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>OYSTER-SAUCE.</ingredient></purpose> When your <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are opened, take care of all the liquor, and give them one boil in it. Then<pb n="98" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=106"/> take the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> out, and put to the liquor three or four blades of <ingredient>mace.</ingredient> Add to it some melted <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and some thick <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>rich milk.</ingredient> Put in your <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and give them a boil. As soon as they come to a boil, take them off the fire.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">PICKLED <ingredient>OYSTERS.</ingredient></purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Four hundred large fresh <ingredient>oysters.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></item><item>Eight spoonfuls of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>A pint of <ingredient>white wine.</ingredient></item><item>Six table-spoonfuls of whole <ingredient>black pepper.</ingredient></item><item>Eight blades of <ingredient>mace.</ingredient></item></list>Strain the liquor of the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> and boil it. Then pour it hot over the <ingredient>oysters,</ingredient> and let them lie in it about ten minutes. Then take them out, and cover them. Boil the liquor with the <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> <ingredient>pepper,</ingredient> <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar</ingredient> and <ingredient>wine.</ingredient> When cold, put the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> in a close jar, and pour the liquor over them. Cover the jar very tight, and the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> will keep a long time.</p><p>If the <ingredient>oysters</ingredient> are <ingredient>salt,</ingredient> put no <ingredient>salt</ingredient> to the liquor.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>CHICKEN</ingredient> SALAD.</purpose><list align="indent1" size="smaller"><item>Two large <ingredient>cold fowls,</ingredient> either boiled or roasted.</item><item>The <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of nine <ingredient>hard-boiled eggs.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>sweet oil.</ingredient></item><item>Half a pint of <ingredient>vinegar.</ingredient></item><item>A gill of <ingredient>mixed mustard.</ingredient></item><item>A small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>cayenne pepper.</ingredient></item><item>A small tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient></item><item>Two large <ingredient>heads,</ingredient> or four small ones, of fine <ingredient>celery.</ingredient></item></list>Cut the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> of the <ingredient>fowls</ingredient> from the <ingredient>bones,</ingredient> in pieces not exceeding an inch in size.</p><p>Cut the <ingredient>white</ingredient> part of the <ingredient>celery</ingredient> into pieces, about an inch long. Mix the <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> and <ingredient>celery</ingredient> well together. Cover them and set them away.</p><p>With the back of a wooden spoon, mash the <ingredient>yolks of eggs</ingredient> till they are a perfectly smooth <ingredient>paste.</ingredient> <pb n="99" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=107"/> Mix them with the <ingredient>oil,</ingredient> <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Stir them for a long time, till they are thoroughly mixed and quite smooth. The longer they are stirred the better. When this dressing is sufficiently mixed, cover it, and set it away.</p><p>Five minutes before the salad is to be eaten pour the dressing over the <ingredient>chicken</ingredient> and <ingredient>celery,</ingredient> and mix all well together. If the dressing is put on long before it is wanted, the salad will be tough and <ingredient>hard.</ingredient></p><p>This salad is very excellent made of <ingredient>cold turkey</ingredient> instead of <ingredient>chicken.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans" class2="meatfishgame"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>LOBSTER</ingredient> SALAD.</purpose> Take two large boiled <ingredient>lobsters.</ingredient> <ingredient>Extract</ingredient> all the <ingredient>meat</ingredient> from the shell, and cut it up into very small pieces.</p><p>For <ingredient>lobster</ingredient> salad, you must have <ingredient>lettuce</ingredient> instead of <ingredient>celery.</ingredient> Cut up the <ingredient>lettuce</ingredient> as small as possible.</p><p>Make a dressing as for a <ingredient>chicken</ingredient>-salad, with the <ingredient>yolks</ingredient> of nine <ingredient>hard-boiled eggs,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>sweet oil,</ingredient> half a pint of <ingredient>vinegar,</ingredient> a gill of <ingredient>mustard,</ingredient> a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>cayenne,</ingredient> and a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Mix all well together with a wooden spoon.</p><p>A few minutes before it is to be eaten, pour the dressing over the <ingredient>lobster</ingredient> and <ingredient>lettuce,</ingredient> and mix it very well.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="fruitvegbeans"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>STEWED MUSHROOMS.</ingredient></purpose> Take a quart of fresh <ingredient>mushrooms.</ingredient> Peel them and cut off the stems. Season them with <ingredient>pepper</ingredient> and <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Put them in a <ingredient>sauce</ingredient>-pan or skillet, with a lump of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> the size of an <ingredient>egg,</ingredient> and sufficient <ingredient>cream</ingredient> or <ingredient>rich milk</ingredient> to cover them. Put on the lid of the pan, and stew the <ingredient>mushrooms</ingredient> about<pb n="100" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=108"/> a quarter of an hour, keeping them well covered or the flavour will evaporate.</p><p>When you take them off the fire, have ready one or two beaten <ingredient>eggs.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> gradually into the stew, and send it to table in a covered dish.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>PEACH CORDIAL.</ingredient></purpose> Take a peck of <ingredient>cling-stone peaches;</ingredient> such as come late in the season, and are very juicy. Pare them, and cut them from the stones. Crack about half the stones and save the kernels. Leave the remainder of the stones whole, and mix them with the cut <ingredient>peaches;</ingredient> add also the kernels. Put the whole into a wide-mouthed demi-john, and pour on them two gallons of double-rectified <ingredient>whiskey.</ingredient> Add three pounds of rock-<ingredient>sugar</ingredient> candy. Cork it tightly, and set it away for three months: then bottle it, and it will be fit for use. This <ingredient>cordial</ingredient> is as clear as <ingredient>water,</ingredient> and nearly equal to <ingredient>noyau.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>CHERRY BOUNCE.</ingredient></purpose> Take a peck of <ingredient>morella cherries,</ingredient> and a peck of black <ingredient>hearts.</ingredient> Stone the morellas and crack the stones. Put all the <ingredient>cherries</ingredient> and the cracked stones into a demi-john, with three pounds of <ingredient>loaf-sugar</ingredient> slightly pounded or beaten. Pour in two gallons of double-rectified <ingredient>whiskey.</ingredient> Cork the demi-john, and in six months the <ingredient>cherry</ingredient>-bounce will be fit to pour off and bottle for use; but the older it is, the better.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>RASPBERRY CORDIAL.</ingredient></purpose> To each quart of <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> allow a pound of <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Mash the <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> and strew the <pb n="101" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=109"/> <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> over them, having first pounded it slightly, or cracked it with the rolling-pin. Let the <ingredient>raspberries</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> set till next day, keeping them well covered, then put them in a thin linen bag and squeeze out the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> with your hands. To every pint of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> allow a quart of double-rectified <ingredient>whiskey.</ingredient> Cork it well, and set it away for use. It will be ready in a few days.</p><p><ingredient>Raspberry Vinegar</ingredient> (which, mixed with <ingredient>water,</ingredient> is a pleasant and cooling beverage in warm weather) is made exactly in the same manner as the <ingredient>cordial,</ingredient> only substituting the best <ingredient>white vinegar</ingredient> for the <ingredient>whiskey.</ingredient></p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>BLACKBERRY CORDIAL.</ingredient></purpose> Take the ripest <ingredient>blackberries.</ingredient> Mash them, put them in a linen bag and squeeze out the <ingredient>juice.</ingredient> To every quart of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> allow a pound of beaten <ingredient>loaf-sugar.</ingredient> Put the <ingredient>sugar</ingredient> into a large preserving kettle, and pour the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> on it. When it is all melted, set it on the fire, and boil it to a thin <ingredient>jelly.</ingredient> When cold, to every quart of <ingredient>juice</ingredient> allow a quart of <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> Stir them well together, and bottle it for use. It will be ready at once.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="beverages" alcoholic="yes"><p><purpose rend="bold" placement="heading" align="center"><ingredient>GINGER BEER.</ingredient></purpose> Put into a kettle, two ounces of powdered <ingredient>ginger,</ingredient> (or more if it is not very strong,) half an ounce of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> two large <ingredient>lemons</ingredient> cut in slices, two pounds of broken <ingredient>loaf-sugar,</ingredient> and one gallon of <ingredient>soft water.</ingredient> Simmer them over a slow fire for half an hour. When the liquor is nearly cold, stir into it a large table-spoonful of the best <ingredient>yeast.</ingredient> After it has fermented, bottle for use.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="102" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=110"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>JELLY</ingredient> CAKE.</purpose> Stir together till very light, half a pound of fresh <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and half a pound of powdered <ingredient>white sugar.</ingredient> Beat twelve <ingredient>eggs</ingredient> very light, and stir them into the <ingredient>butter</ingredient> and <ingredient>sugar,</ingredient> alternately with a pound of sifted <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Add a beaten <ingredient>nutmeg,</ingredient> and half a <ingredient>wine</ingredient>-glass of <ingredient>rose-water.</ingredient> Have ready a flat circular plate of tin, which must be laid on your griddle, or in the oven of your stove, and well greased with <ingredient>butter.</ingredient> Pour on it a large ladle-full of the batter, and bake it as you would a <ingredient>buck-wheat</ingredient> cake, taking care to have it of a good shape. It will not require turning. Bake as many of these cakes as you want, laying each on a separate plate. Then spread <ingredient>jelly</ingredient> or <ingredient>marmalade</ingredient> all over the top of each cake, and lay another upon it. Spread that also with <ingredient>jelly,</ingredient> and so on till you have a pile of five or six, looking like one large thick cake. Trim the edge nicely with a penknife, and cover the top with <ingredient>powdered sugar.</ingredient> Or you may ice it; putting on the nonpareils or <ingredient>sugar</ingredient>-sand in such a manner as to mark out the cake in triangular divisions. When it is to be eaten, cut it in three-cornered slices as you would a pie.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">COLOURING FOR ICING, &#38;c.</purpose><emph rend="italic">To make a red colouring for icing.</emph> Take twenty grains of <ingredient>cochineal powder,</ingredient> twenty grains of <ingredient>cream of tartar,</ingredient> and twenty grains of powdered <ingredient>alum.</ingredient> Put them into a gill of <ingredient>cold soft water,</ingredient> and boil it very slowly till reduced to one half. Strain it through thin muslin, and cork it up for use. A very small quantity of this mixture will colour icing of a beautiful pink. With pink icing, <ingredient>white</ingredient> nonpareils should be used.</p>
</recipe> <pb n="103" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=111"/>
<recipe class1="breadsweets"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>RICE</ingredient> CAKES FOR BREAKFAST.</purpose> Put half a pound of <ingredient>rice</ingredient> in soak overnight. Early in the morning boil it very soft, drain it from the <ingredient>water,</ingredient> mix with it a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and set it away to cool. When it is cold, stir it into a quart of <ingredient>milk,</ingredient> and add a very little <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> Beat six <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> and sift half a pint of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Stir the <ingredient>egg</ingredient> and <ingredient>flour</ingredient> alternately into the <ingredient>rice</ingredient> and <ingredient>milk.</ingredient> Having beaten the whole very well, bake it on the griddle in cakes about the size of a small dessert-plate. <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> them, and send them to table hot.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="eggscheesedairy"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading">GROUND <ingredient>RICE</ingredient> PUDDING.</purpose> Take five table-spoonfuls of ground <ingredient>rice</ingredient> and boil it in a quart of <ingredient>new milk,</ingredient> with a grated <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> or a tea-spoonful of powdered <ingredient>cinnamon,</ingredient> stirring it all the time. When it has boiled, pour it into a pan and stir in a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>butter,</ingredient> and a quarter of a pound of <ingredient>powdered sugar,</ingredient> a <ingredient>nutmeg</ingredient> and half a pint of <ingredient>cream.</ingredient> Set it away to get cold. Then beat eight <ingredient>eggs,</ingredient> omitting the <ingredient>whites</ingredient> of four. Have ready a pound of <ingredient>dried currants</ingredient> well cleaned, and sprinkled with <ingredient>flour;</ingredient> stir them into the mixture alternately with the beaten <ingredient>egg.</ingredient> Add half a glass of <ingredient>rose-water,</ingredient> or half a glass of mixed <ingredient>wine</ingredient> and <ingredient>brandy.</ingredient> <ingredient>Butter</ingredient> a deep dish, put in the mixture, and bake it of a pale brown. Or you may bake it in saucers.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>TOMATA KETCHUP.</ingredient></purpose> Slice the <ingredient>tomatas.</ingredient> Put them in layers into a deep earthen pan, and sprinkle every layer with <ingredient>salt.</ingredient> <pb n="104" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=112"/> Let them stand in this state for twelve hours. Then put them over the fire in a preserving kettle, and simmer them till they are quite soft. Pour them into a thin linen bag, and squeeze the <ingredient>juice</ingredient> from them. Season the liquor to your taste, with grated horse-<ingredient>radish,</ingredient> a little <ingredient>garlic,</ingredient> some <ingredient>mace,</ingredient> and a few <ingredient>cloves.</ingredient> Boil it well with these ingredients--and, when cold, bottle it for use.</p>
</recipe>
<recipe class1="accompaniments"><p><purpose rend="bold" align="center" placement="heading"><ingredient>YEAST.</ingredient></purpose>Have ready two quarts of <ingredient>boiling water;</ingredient> put into it a large handful of <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> and let them boil twenty minutes. Sift into a pan a pound and a half of <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Strain the liquor from the <ingredient>hops,</ingredient> and pour half of it over the <ingredient>flour.</ingredient> Let the other half of the liquid stand till it is cool, and then pour it gradually into the pan of <ingredient>flour,</ingredient> mixing it well. Stir into it a large tea-cup full of good <ingredient>yeast,</ingredient> (<ingredient>brewer's yeast</ingredient> if you can get it.) Put it immediately into bottles, and cork it tightly. It will be fit for use in an hour. It will be much improved and keep longer, by putting into each bottle a tea-spoonful of <ingredient>pearl-ash.</ingredient></p><p>FINIS.</p>
</recipe>
</chapter>
</body>
<back>
<div type="other"> <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=113"/><pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=114"/> <pb n="blank" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=115"/></div>
<div type="backcover"> <pb n="back cover" id="/projects/cookbooks/coldfusion/display.cfm?ID=sevf&#38;PageNum=116"/></div>
</back>
</cookbook>
